<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkd258</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10684940</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The initiator element of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> &#x003b2;<italic>2 tubulin</italic> gene core promoter contributes to gene expression <italic>in vivo</italic> but is not required for male germ-cell specific expression</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santel</surname><given-names>Ansgar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="N0x98713f8.0x8b4e7e8">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>J&#x000f6;rg</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x98713f8.0x8b4e988">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hyland</surname><given-names>Ruth</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Renkawitz-Pohl</surname><given-names>Renate</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x98713f8.0x8b4e988">Zoologie-Entwicklungsbiologie am Fachbereich Biologie, Philipps-Universit&#x000e4;t Marburg, Karl-von-Frisch-Stra&#x000df;e, D-35032 Marburg, Germany and <label>1</label>Chiron Corporation, Chiron Technologies, 4560 Horton Street, Emeryville, CA 94608, USA</aff><author-notes><fn id="N0x98713f8.0x8b4e7e8"><label>a</label><p>To whom correspondence should be addressed at present address: Department of Developmental Biology, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, CA 94305, USA. Tel: &#x0002b;1 650 725 7625; Fax: &#x0002b;1 650 725 7739; Email: santel&#x00040;cmgm.stanford.edu</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2000</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1439</fpage><lpage>1446</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http:&#x0002f;&#x0002f;www.oup.co.uk&#x0002f;nar&#x0002f;Volume&#x0005f;28&#x0002f;Issue&#x0005f;6&#x0002f;html&#x0002f;gkd258.htm"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>1999</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2000</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2000</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2000 Oxford University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2000</copyright-year><abstract><p>The tissue-specific expression of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> &#x003b2;<italic>2 tubulin</italic> gene (<italic>B2t</italic>) is accomplished by the action of a 14-bp activator element (&#x003b2;2UE1) in combination with certain regulatory elements of the TATA-less, Inr-containing <italic>B2t</italic> core promoter. We performed an <italic>in vivo</italic> analysis of the Inr element function in the <italic>B2t</italic> core promoter using a transgenic approach. Our experiments demonstrate that the Inr element acts as a functional <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory element <italic>in vivo</italic> and quantitatively regulates tissue-specific reporter expression in transgenic animals. However, our mutational analysis of the Inr element demonstrates no essential role of the Inr in mediating tissue specificity of the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter. In addition, a downstream element seems to affect promoter activity in combination with the Inr. In summary, our data show for the first time the functionality of the Inr element in an <italic>in vivo</italic> background situation in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Tissue-specific gene expression in higher eukaryotes can be accomplished by the recruitment of cell type-specific transcription factors (activators) to distinct promoter&#x0002f;enhancer sequences. The binding of specific activators allows for the interaction with the general transcription initiation machinery at the core promoter and leads to transcriptional activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c3">3</xref>). The analysis of core promoter function within transcriptional activation and initiation has led to the identification of relevant <italic>cis</italic>-acting promoter sequences and their <italic>trans</italic>-acting counterparts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c6">6</xref>). The core promoter of genes transcribed by RNA-polymerase II is defined as the minimal sequence surrounding the transcription start site that is capable of initiating accurate basal transcription <italic>in vitro</italic>. The best characterized core promoter elements are the TATA box at the &#x02013;25 region and the initiator (Inr) sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c8">8</xref>) encompassing the transcriptional initiation site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c9">9</xref>). In addition to core promoters containing one or both of these elements, promoters that lack both elements have been identified. Recently, in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, an additional 7-bp core promoter element was found ~30 bp downstream of the transcription start site in TATA-less, but Inr-containing, core promoters, termed the DPE (downstream promoter element; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c11">11</xref>). Functional analysis of these core promoter elements revealed their role in recruiting the TFIID complex for transcriptional start site selection by the binding of different components of the multisubunit TFIID complex to each of these elements. While the TATA box is recognized by the TATA box binding protein (TBP; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c12">12</xref>), the Inr and the DPE serve as binding sites for certain TAFs (TBP associated factors; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c13">13</xref>). In particular, the Inr is thought to function either as a TATA box analog in TATA-less core promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c6">6</xref>) or as an enhancer of TATA box function in TATA box-containing core promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c14">14</xref>). It has also been shown that the Inr element serves as a selective determinant for directing promoter accessibility and usage, resulting in differential gene expression (e.g. temporal versus spatial gene expression; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c18">18</xref>). Additionally, the observation of TAF-mediated direct TFIID recognition of the Inr and sequences located further downstream of the transcription start site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c22">22</xref>) stresses the importance of TFIID recruitment to the core promoter as a crucial step for transcription initiation.</p><p>Activated gene expression is conferred by the core promoter in conjunction with appropriate transcriptional activator element(s). Interestingly, concerning the mechanism of activated gene expression, it has been shown that TFIID (i.e. certain TAFs) plays a fundamental role in mediating activation of transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c24">24</xref>). In addition, efforts to analyze the regulatory activities of core promoter structure <italic>in vivo</italic> have been undertaken (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c28">28</xref>). However, currently less is known about the role of core promoter function in mediating tissue-dependent promoter specificity <italic>in vivo</italic>. While intensive studies address the question of promoter specificity due to different core promoter structures in combination with different activators <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c30">30</xref>), we examined the properties and dependence of a distinct core promoter architecture for controlling tissue-specific gene expression using the <italic>Drosophila</italic> &#x003b2;<italic>2</italic> tubulin gene promoter <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p>The <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><italic>2</italic> tubulin gene (<italic>B2t</italic>) encodes a tissue-specific &#x003b2; tubulin variant that is exclusively used during spermatogenesis. The promoter sequence responsible for tissue-specific gene activation is confined to a region of 80 bp sufficient to drive germline specific expression in the testis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c31">31</xref>). In addition, a 14-bp activator element (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic><italic>2</italic>UE1) is necessary for promoter specificity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c31">31</xref>).</p><p>In this paper, we examine the capability of the <italic>B2t</italic> core promoter, in conjunction with the activator element, to regulate tissue-specific gene expression <italic>in vivo</italic> using a transgenic system. Reporter analysis of testes from transgenic animals haboring different core promoter constructs reveals that an Inr sequence element at the transcription start site contributes to promoter strength <italic>in vivo</italic>. However, functional knockout of the Inr sequence does not affect tissue specificity of the B2t promoter suggesting that the &#x003b2;2UE1 activator element is the only element crucial for directing tissue-specific gene activation, while the core promoter architecture defines the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter strength.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Generation of <italic>B2t</italic> promoter <italic>lacZ</italic> reporter constructs</title><p><italic>B2t</italic> promoter constructs were generated according to the description for the construction of previous <italic>B2t-lacZ</italic> reporter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c31">31</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>P-element mediated germ-line transformation and fly strains</title><p>Highly purified plasmid DNA (0.5 mg&#x0002f;ml), along with the presence of the helper plasmid p&#x003c0;25.7wc (0.25 mg&#x0002f;ml), was injected into the recipient strain <italic>w</italic><italic><sup>1</sup></italic><italic>,sn</italic><italic><sup>w</sup></italic>. A representative &#x003b2;<italic>2UE1-hsp70-lacZ</italic> strain (<italic>hsp70</italic> gene promoter sequence from the chromosomal location 87C contains a TATA-box as well as an Inr-homologous transcription start site followed by an 89-bp untranslated leader region) was compared with a representative <italic>B2t</italic>-lacZ strain (&#x02018;&#x02013;511&#x02019;) containing the entire <italic>B2t</italic> regulatory region. Both strains have been described and established previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c32">32</xref>). For comparative whole mount <italic>in situ</italic> hybridizations to assess &#x003b2;2DE1 activity <italic>in vivo</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f5">5</xref>A and B), the transgenic line <italic>B2t</italic>(&#x02013;<italic>53</italic>&#x0002f;&#x0002b;<italic>70</italic>) (&#x003b2;2DE1-active strain: &#x02018;&#x0002b;&#x003b2;2DE1&#x02019;) and the transgenic strain <italic>B2t</italic>(&#x02013;<italic>53</italic>&#x0002f;&#x0002b;<italic>70</italic>)<italic>URN</italic>, carrying an inverted and therefore inactive &#x003b2;2DE1 (designated &#x02018;&#x02013;&#x003b2;2DE1&#x02019;) were used and have already been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c33">33</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Whole mount <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization</title><p>Whole mount <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization of adult testes was performed with digoxygenin-labeled DNA probes (<italic>lacZ</italic> probe) according to standard protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c34">34</xref>) with minor modifications. Hybridization was carried out overnight at 45&#x000b0;C. Testis samples of the compared strains were processed in parallel under identical conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>Histochemical &#x003b2;-galactosidase staining</title><p>For quantitative or comparative histochemical staining analysis, testes of adult males (aged 2&#x02013;4 days) and larvae from independently transformed reporter lines were stained in side-by-side reactions as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c34">34</xref>). Staining was performed at room temperature, monitored every 5 min and stopped by intensive washing with phosphate buffer. After staining, testes were mounted in 50&#x00025; glycerol and photographed under a Zeiss Axiophot microscope.</p></sec><sec><title>Enzymatic &#x003b2;-galactosidase assay (CPRG assay)</title><p>Quantification of testis-specific &#x003b2;-galactosidase expression was performed essentially as described by Glaser and Lis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c35">35</xref>). Briefly, individual males from lines to be analyzed were outcrossed to the injection stock to generate progeny heterozygous for the P-element. Duplicate sets of five testes from 3&#x02013;5-day-old males from each outcrossed line were dissected and homogenized in homogenization buffer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c35">35</xref>). Testis protein extracts from each transformed line were assayed. The &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity was monitored over a 3-h time period, during which a constant enzyme activity was measured (linear assay). The values for the duplicate samples were averaged. Values are expressed as percentages of the mean level of activity observed for the appropriate control construct. Standard errors of the mean were calculated.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA binding assay</title><p>For gel-shift experiments, crude testis protein extracts were prepared as follows: testes from 2-day-old healthy males were dissected in ice cold Ringer&#x02019;s solution and collected in a test tube on ice. After collection, excess buffer was removed and an equal volume of 2&#x000d7; protein extraction buffer (40 mM HEPES pH 7.9, 200 mM KCl, 2 mM DTT, 40&#x00025; glycerol, 0.2 mM EDTA, 0.2&#x00025; NP-40) was added. The samples were frozen at &#x02013;80&#x000b0;C over night. After thawing on ice the tissue was homogenized and the extract sonicated for 20 min at 4&#x000b0;C in a sonifier bath (Sonorex TK52, Bandelin). Cell debris was spun down by centrifugation for 10 min at 8000 r.p.m. in a centrifuge (Eppendorf Centrifuge 5314 C). The supernatant was frozen in small aliquots at &#x02013;80&#x000b0;C. Protein concentrations were determined with the BioRad assay dye. Binding reactions were carried out in a final volume of 20 &#x000b5;l containing 1&#x000d7; binding buffer (10 mM HEPES pH 7.6; 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>; 50 mM KCl, 0.5 mM DTT, 2.5&#x00025; glycerol), 1 mg poly-dAdT (Boehringer Mannheim), 15&#x02013;20 fmol <sup>32</sup>P end-labeled, double-stranded oligonucleotides as probe (~3000 c.p.m.&#x0002f;fmol), and 10 &#x000b5;g testis protein extract at 18&#x000b0;C for 30 min. For competition experiments, unlabeled oligonucleotides were added to the reaction mixture prior to the addition of probe. Following the binding reaction 5 &#x000b5;l 50&#x00025; glycerol were added to the samples, which were subsequently resolved on a 6&#x00025; native polyacrylamide gel (acrylamide to bisacrylamide ratio of 39:1; running buffer: 50 mM Tris, 400 mM glycine) at 180 V and 18&#x000b0;C for 90 min. The gels were dried after electrophoresis and autoradiographed using Kodak X-Omat XR films.</p><p>The following DNA oligonucleotides were used (sense strand shown):</p><p>B2t(&#x02013;51&#x0002f;&#x02013;38): 5&#x02032;-GGAAATCGTAGTAGCCTAT-3&#x02032;</p><p>B2t(&#x02013;37&#x0002f;&#x0002b;18): 5&#x02032;-GATCTGAACATTCGGTGTAGTAATCCAAGCCAGGATCAGTTCCACCTCAGTATCAG-3&#x02032;</p><p>B2t(&#x0002b;39&#x0002f;&#x0002b;86): 5&#x02032;-CTAGAAAAATCTAAACCTGAAAAATTATACGTTTAAATATTCAGTCTTTTGCCGATTTTC-3&#x02032;</p><p>B2t(&#x02013;55&#x0002f;&#x02013;26): 5&#x02032;-GGAAATCGTAGTAGCCTATTTGTGAACATT-3&#x02032; (&#x0003d;comp2 in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>B)</p><p>unspecific competitor: 5&#x02032;-AGCTGCGACTATCGCGATCCTCAGTCGACGTCTAGACTGAAGATGA-3&#x02032; (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>B)</p><p>unspecific competitor (derived from the <italic>B1</italic>t upstream region; see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>C): 5&#x02032;- GTATGGCCACACTGCGGCCATCG-3&#x02032;.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>The TATA-less testis-specific <italic>B2t</italic> promoter of <italic>Drosophila</italic> contains a conserved initiator sequence (Inr)</title><p><italic>In vivo</italic> transcriptional analysis of the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter region resulted in the identification of the <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements responsible for driving tissue-specific <italic>B2t</italic> gene expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c33">33</xref>). Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f1">1</xref> depicts the overall structure of the <italic>B2</italic>t promoter and its associated regulatory elements. Within the promoter, three major <italic>cis</italic> elements have been identified: the 14-bp activator element, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><italic>2</italic>UE1, which is necessary for cell type-specific gene activation, and two quantitative regulatory elements called <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><italic>2</italic>UE2 at the &#x02013;25 region and &#x003b2;<italic>2</italic>DE1 in the &#x0002b;60 region. The <italic>B2t</italic> core promoter does not contain a TATA box in the &#x02013;25 region. Instead, &#x003b2;<italic>2</italic>UE2(GAACAT), a sequence element that is conserved between <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> and <italic>Drosophila hydei</italic> and exhibits regulatory capability, is located in that region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c31">31</xref>). However, the transcription start site which is also involved in <italic>B2t</italic> gene regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c32">32</xref>), represents a consensus Inr sequence (PyPyCAXPy) observed in many TATA-less promoters (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f1">1</xref>, highlighted in green; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c10">10</xref>). Therefore, we decided to use the testis-specific <italic>B2t</italic> promoter as an experimental model to elucidate the Inr function <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>All three identified regulatory elements in the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter serve as binding sites for DNA binding proteins</title><p>To further characterize the defined <italic>B2t</italic> promoter elements, we performed gel electrophoretic mobility shift experiments to prove the existence of specific DNA&#x02013;protein interactions. Incubation of crude <italic>Drosophila</italic> testis extracts with radiolabeled, double-stranded oligonucleotides representing the three major regulatory elements resulted in the formation of sequence-specific DNA&#x02013;protein complexes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>A&#x02013;C). Using &#x003b2;2UE1 as a probe, a single, sequence-specific DNA protein complex is observed (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>A). The &#x003b2;<italic>2</italic>UE2 element also represents a binding site for testicular DNA binding proteins as demonstrated in competition gel shift assays (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>B). Radiolabeled, double-stranded oligonucleotides representing the core promoter region from &#x02013;37 to &#x0002b;18 are recognized by DNA binding proteins from testes extracts (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>), resulting in the formation of retarding DNA&#x02013;protein complexes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>B). Competition experiments with unlabeled competitor DNA, whose sequence of which overlaps the region of the probe at &#x003b2;2UE2, results in specific competition of the complex.</p><p>Finally, to determine if the downstream region of the <italic>B2t</italic> gene harboring the &#x003b2;2DE1 regulatory element might serve as a protein-binding site, gel-shift analysis was carried out with crude testis protein extracts in the presence of a probe containing the &#x003b2;2DE1 sequence. The experiment revealed the formation of one dominant retarding DNA&#x02013;protein complex (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>C, left panel). Competition experiments with three different competitors (for origin and sequence see Materials and Methods) clearly demonstrate the sequence specificity of the retarding DNA&#x02013;protein complex. We extended the gel shift analysis by using protein extracts derived from adult testes of <italic>D.hydei</italic> and ovaries from <italic>D.melanogaster</italic>, respectively. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f2">2</xref>C shows the result of this band shift experiment. The same probe binds also to testes proteins from <italic>D.hydei</italic>, but fails to generate any DNA&#x02013;protein interactions with proteins from ovaries. Binding assays with a probe comprised solely of the sequence of the &#x003b2;2DE1 (&#x0002b;49 to &#x0002b;72) using testis extracts from <italic>D.melanogaster</italic> confirmed the existence of a DNA-binding protein specific for this sequence element (data not shown). Since the &#x003b2;2DE1 element is conserved in sequence and position in the <italic>B2t</italic> gene of both <italic>Drosophila</italic> species, we presume that the &#x003b2;2DE1 represents a DNA-binding site for a testis-specific DNA-binding protein, which might be involved in transcriptional regulation.</p></sec><sec><title>The combination of a heterologous TATA containing core promoter (<italic>hsp70</italic>) with the &#x003b2;2UE1 activator element decreases promoter strength but has no influence on tissue specificity <italic>in vivo</italic></title><p>In order to investigate the influence of the core promoter on the strength of the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter we substituted the <italic>B2t</italic> core promoter for the <italic>hsp70</italic> core promoter. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f3">3</xref>, reporter gene expression was analyzed qualitatively in larval testes (which contain only transcriptionally active germ cells) derived from transgenic animals carrying either reporter constructs containing the <italic>B2t</italic> core promoter or a reporter construct containing the <italic>hsp70</italic> core promoter, in combination with the &#x003b2;2UE1 activator element. Surprisingly, the &#x003b2;2UE1 activator element does not work efficiently in the context of the <italic>hsp70</italic> core promoter, which carries a TATA-box in the &#x02013;25 region compared to the TATA-less <italic>B2t</italic> core promoter. Therefore, the &#x003b2;2UE1 activator element requires an Inr-containing, but TATA-less, core promoter to achieve its maximal activity. Taken together, these data suggest that certain transcriptional activation depends on a specific core promoter architecture to activate transcription <italic>in vivo</italic>. To address the question whether the Inr is required for activator mediated tissue-specificity, we set out to analyze a non-functional Inr element in this promoter context <italic>in vivo.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>The Inr element is functionally active, but not necessary to confer tissue-specific gene expression</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription analysis of synthetic promoters has revealed the relevant nucleotides within an Inr consensus element that are critical for Inr activity. Replacement of a C by a G at position &#x02013;1, or a T by a G at &#x0002b;3, abolishes any transcriptional activity of Inr containing promoter templates <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c36">36</xref>). Thus, we examined the relevance of these two nucleotides <italic>in vivo</italic> in the context of the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter.</p><p><italic>B2t</italic>-promoter <italic>lacZ</italic> constructs carrying mutations at these nucleotide positions were generated &#x0005b;Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f4">4</xref>A, construct <italic>B2</italic>t(&#x02013;53&#x0002f; &#x0002b;156): wild type; <italic>B2</italic>t(&#x02013;53&#x0002f;&#x0002b;156)&#x0002a;Inr: mutated Inr&#x0005d;, introduced into the <italic>Drosophila</italic> genome by P-element mediated transformation and transgenic fly lines established. As a further positive control, in addition to the <italic>B2t</italic> wild type promoter construct, a construct was generated with 10 bp of the murine TdT (terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase) transcription start site, representing a functional Inr sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c6">6</xref>), in place of the endogenous <italic>B2t</italic> start (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f4">4</xref>A, B2t-TdT). Tissue-specific promoter activity was monitored by histochemical &#x003b2;-galactosidase staining of testes from different transgenic lines (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f4">4</xref>B). The stainings revealed that each tested <italic>B2t</italic> promoter variant is capable of driving reporter gene expression in the male germ line in the <italic>B2t</italic> pattern.</p><p>All constructs show correct temporal and spatial reporter expression. Consequently, &#x003b2;-galactosidase staining is exclusively present in male germ-cells from late spermatocytes onwards. No reporter expression is seen in early germ cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f4">4</xref>B, arrows) or somatic genital tissues like paragonia (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f4">4</xref>B, double arrow). However, differences in the staining intensity were observed between these constructs. While the <italic>B2t</italic>(&#x02013;53&#x0002f; &#x0002b;156)TdT construct shows nearly the same staining intensity as the wild type construct, the construct carrying the mutated Inr sequence clearly exhibits reduced staining intensity. Staining of corresponding larval testes containing solely transcriptionally active cells reflects the same relative reporter expression levels, indicating the influence of changed start sites on transcriptional regulation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f4">4</xref>B, right panels). In order to confirm these qualitative results and to consider effects of chromosomal position of the insertion sites, we attempted to analyze the expression quantitatively in multiple lines. The qualitatively observed differences in the reporter expression are underscored by the quantitative measurement of &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity in testis extracts derived from multiple independent strains (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f4">4</xref>C, the number of strains are indicated).</p><p>Mutation of the Inr element at the <italic>B2t</italic> transcription start site results in a decrease of ~50&#x00025; in &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity relative to the reporter activity for wild type constructs and ~25&#x00025; relative to the observed activity in the constructs with functional TdT&#x02013;Inr. However, the results with the TdT&#x02013;Inr construct are difficult to interpret because of higher variability between the measured strains (see standard deviation, Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f4">4</xref>C). The difference in &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity between wild type and TdT&#x02013;Inr suggests that the additional base pairs surrounding the Inr might participate in promoter function. In summary, this experiment demonstrates that removal of the relevant Inr base pairs within the <italic>B2t</italic> start site has no effect on the tissue-specificity of the promoter but leads to a decrease of promoter strength. The result further implies that the Inr element is functional in determining expression level of the reporter gene <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>The &#x003b2;2DE1 downstream element supports promoter strength, but is not dependent on the presence of the Inr</title><p>Initial investigations of the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter structure reveal the presence of a conserved AT-rich regulatory element, &#x003b2;2DE1, located downstream of the transcription start site in the 5&#x02032;-UTR (&#x0002b;60 region). It has been proposed that this element regulates mRNA levels during post-meiotic stages of spermatogenesis, probably by conferring stability on the <italic>B2t</italic> mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c33">33</xref>). It has become increasingly evident that downstream elements are also involved in transcriptional regulation and significantly contribute to Inr function in TATA-less promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c42">42</xref>). To investigate this with respect to the &#x003b2;2DE1 we first examined the <italic>lacZ</italic> mRNA levels by <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization in adult testes of transgenic animals bearing either a <italic>B2t</italic>-wild type reporter construct containing the &#x003b2;2DE1 element (denoted as &#x0002b;&#x003b2;2DE1; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f5">5</xref>A) or a promoter-<italic>lacZ</italic> construct lacking a functional &#x003b2;2DE1 (&#x02013;&#x003b2;2DE1; construct carries inverted &#x003b2;2DE1 element; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f5">5</xref>B; for fly strains see Materials and Methods). It has been shown previously by a comparative S1 nuclease-quantification assay that deletion of the &#x003b2;2DE1 element gives rise to a 3-fold reduction in the amount of <italic>lacZ</italic> mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c33">33</xref>). Comparison of the relative staining intensities after equivalent hybridization reflects the difference in the <italic>lacZ</italic> mRNA levels measured <italic>in vitro</italic> by the S1 nuclease quantification assay (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f5">5</xref>A and B). The <italic>lacZ</italic> mRNA level seems to be reduced already in primary spermatocytes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f5">5</xref>B). This cell type is characterized by its high transcriptional activity. Thus, we verified the difference in mRNA levels measured <italic>in vitro</italic> by an <italic>in vivo</italic> approach, showing the reduction in <italic>lacZ</italic> mRNA directly on the cellular level. To show the regulatory activity of the &#x003b2;2DE1 region in combination with Inr function <italic>in vivo</italic> we generated transgenic flies carrying truncated <italic>B2t</italic>-promoter constructs (&#x0002b;50 instead of &#x0002b;156: removal of the &#x003b2;2DE1 region) in conjunction with either a TdT&#x02013;Inr or mutated&#x0002f;inactivated <italic>B2t</italic>&#x02013;Inr as described above &#x0005b;constructs <italic>B2t</italic>(&#x02013;53&#x0002f;&#x0002b;50)TdT, <italic>B2t</italic>(&#x02013;53&#x0002f;&#x0002b;50)&#x0002a;Inr&#x0005d;. Analysis of &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity in these strains revealed that each promoter is still capable of directing testis-specific gene expression; however, an additional reduction in reporter gene activity between constructs with or without &#x003b2;2DE1 region becomes evident (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkd258f5">5</xref>C). The expression level between the constructs with mutated Inr elements in comparison to the constructs bearing the TdT&#x02013;Inr in the presence and absence of the &#x003b2;2DE1 differs in the same relative ratio to each other. The presence of a mutated Inr gives rise to an additional 25&#x00025; reduction of &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity in comparison to the constructs carrying the TdT&#x02013;Inr. Hence, the analysis of these constructs supports the described Inr activity. However both elements seem to act independently of each other in quantitatively regulating reporter gene expression.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this report, we show the regulatory capability of an Inr element during tissue-specific gene expression <italic>in vivo</italic> using the well-characterized <italic>Drosophila</italic><italic>&#x003b2;</italic><italic>2 tubulin</italic> gene promoter (<italic>B2t</italic>). This promoter contains an indispensable activator element (&#x003b2;2UE1) and an Inr element, but lacks a TATA box. We tested the regulatory capacity of the Inr sequence <italic>in vivo</italic> by analyzing reporter gene expression from different <italic>B2t</italic> promoter-<italic>lacZ</italic> fusion constructs in testes of transgenic animals. We showed that the activator element, in combination with an Inr-defective core promoter, is still capable of driving testis-specific reporter expression <italic>in vivo</italic>. However, mutation of the nucleotides essential for Inr activity <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c36">36</xref>) results in a decrease of reporter expression, suggesting that the Inr serves as a quantitative regulatory element to maintain high expression levels, but seems not to be required for tissue-specific gene expression of the <italic>B2t</italic> gene. The TdT&#x02013;Inr, when substituted for the <italic>B2t</italic>&#x02013;Inr sequence, is not able to restore promoter activity completely. This finding is consistent with <italic>in vitro</italic> transcriptional analysis of the TdT&#x02013;Inr sequence showing that mutations adjacent to the start site affect expression, but not as severely as mutation of the base pairs crucial for Inr activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c8">8</xref>). In summary, we conclude that the Inr element represents a regulatory element that improves promoter strength during tissue-specific <italic>B2t</italic> gene activation <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p>It has been shown previously that the Inr can functionally replace a TATA box and can improve gene expression in conjunction with a TATA box (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c14">14</xref>). However, the presence of a TATA box cannot replace the <italic>B2t</italic> core promoter function, suggesting an additional function of the Inr other than solely being a TATA analog. Consequently, our data support the idea of a distinct role of the Inr in mediating transcriptional activation, which is specific for certain core promoters. For example, it has been demonstrated that the activation domains of VP16 and Sp1 have different transcriptional effects in combination with distinct core promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c29">29</xref>).</p><p>In addition, our functional <italic>in vivo</italic> analysis of Inr activity revealed that two base pairs (at positions &#x02013;1 and &#x0002b;3) affect normal reporter gene expression levels. However, the effect of these point mutations are not as dramatic as the results reported by Smale and coworkers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c36">36</xref>), which are based on <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription experiments using a large series of Inr mutations. The experiment using the TdT&#x02013;Inr sequence in place of the <italic>B2t</italic> sequence suggests that the sequence in the vicinity of the start site also participates in this process. Interestingly, a more recent report by Chalkley and Verrijzer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c43">43</xref>) demonstrates that it is not just the Inr sequence that is recognized by a TAF<sub>II</sub>250&#x02013;TAF<sub>II</sub>150 complex, but that in addition the DNA structure is essential for the recognition process.</p><p>In summary, analysis of the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter in directing tissue-specific expression has shown that all these <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements are confined to a region of ~80 bp. Within that region, there is a 14-bp activator element, &#x003b2;2UE1, which is required for testis-specific <italic>B2t</italic> gene expression. This element is the only element necessary for tissue-specific initiation of transcription, while the other elements of the core promoter and leader are not critical for tissue-specific initiation. However, these elements are contributing to the level of gene expression. Due to the crucial role of the &#x003b2;2UE1 activator element, we propose a two-step model. In the initial step, a tissue&#x0002f;testis-specific activator opens the structure of the chromatin. In the second step the TFIID complex is recruited to the now accessible core promoter. The overall gene expression level can be modulated by the affinity of TFIID for the core promoter.</p><p>Previous analysis has implicated the downstream located &#x003b2;2DE1 implicated to have a functional role in post-transcriptional regulation, namely mRNA stability. Our additional characterization showed that the &#x003b2;2DE1 element has an influence on the premeiotic mRNA-level in highly transcriptionally active spermatocytes. Thus, we conclude that the &#x003b2;2DE1-downstream element might also contribute to transcriptional regulation in addition to its proposed post-transcriptional function. This conclusion is supported by the observation that the downstream promoter region represents a binding site for testis-specific factors. Interestingly, members of the <italic>Drosophila Mst</italic>(<italic>3</italic>)<italic>CGP</italic> gene family, which like the <italic>B2t</italic> gene are exclusively expressed in male germ-cells, carry a conserved regulatory element (TCE) in the 5&#x02032;-UTR which confers translational control and also has been implicated to function on the transcriptional level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkd258c44">44</xref>). Therefore, the regulatory elements within the 5&#x02032;-UTR of these genes may exhibit a dual function on the transcriptional as well as post-transcriptional level. This aspect is very conceivable, since all testis-specific promoters identified so far have an extremely short regulatory region, which is capable of driving gene expression in the complex developmental context of spermatogenesis.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig id="gkd258f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p> Schematic diagram of the structure of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> testis-specifc <italic>B2t</italic> promoter and showing a potential Inr element. The <italic>B2t</italic> promoter region consists of at least three regulatory elements (&#x003b2;2UE1, blue box; &#x003b2;2UE2, green box; &#x003b2;2DE1, red box with arrowhead) (31&#x02013;33). A sequence comparison with known initiator-containing <italic>Drosophila</italic> core promoters and the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter of <italic>D.hydei</italic> and <italic>D.melanogaster</italic> reveals a highly conserved Inr element overlapping the start site &#x0005b;sequence highlighted in green; adapted from Burke and Kadonaga (10)&#x0005d;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkd25801"/></fig><fig id="gkd258f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p> Gel-shift analysis of the three different functional elements &#x003b2;2UE1, &#x003b2;2UE2 and &#x003b2;2DE1 in the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter. Three different regions of the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter were radiolabeled and incubated with <italic>Drosophila</italic> testis extracts. The specificity of the shifted bands is demonstrated by competition with specific and unspecific competitor sequences as indicated. (<bold>A</bold>) One specific DNA&#x02013;protein complex is observed using the &#x003b2;2UE1 activator element as probe (lane 2, arrow; lane 1, free probe; lanes 3&#x02013;5, unlabeled probe as specific competitor with 5-, 25- and 50-fold molar excess, respectively). (<bold>B</bold>) The &#x003b2;2UE2 serves as a specific binding site for testicular <italic>trans</italic>-acting factors. Gel-shift assays were performed with a radiolabeled double-stranded DNA probe encompassing the promoter region from &#x02013;37 to &#x0002b;18. The binding reaction results in the formation of two prominent DNA&#x02013;protein complexes (arrowhead, arrow). Competition experiments demonstrate the sequence specificity of the DNA&#x02013;protein complexes (lanes 3&#x02013;5, specific competitor &#x02018;comp1&#x02019; with 3-, 11- and 30-fold excess; lanes 6&#x02013;8, unspecific competitor with 26-, 52- and 87-fold excess, respectively). An unlabeled double-stranded oligonucleotide comprising the region from &#x02013;55 to &#x02013;26 (&#x02018;comp2&#x02019;) competes out the formation of DNA&#x02013;protein complex &#x00023;1 (lanes 11, 12; lane 9, free probe; lane 10, without competitor). The sequence of the competitor overlaps with the sequence of the probe at the &#x003b2;2UE2 as shown below, indicating the presence of the formation of protein&#x02013;DNA interactions at the &#x003b2;2UE2 element. (<bold>C</bold>) Testis proteins also interact specifically with the &#x003b2;2DE1 region (arrow). Testes extracts were incubated with a probe comprising the sequence from &#x0002b;39 to &#x0002b;86 (free probe lane 1); lanes 3&#x02013;5 specific competitor, unlabeled probe sequence with a 2-, 7- and 70-fold molar excess, respectively; lanes 6&#x02013;8, unspecific competitor (see Materials and Methods) with same molar excess of competitor as lanes 3&#x02013;5. The major DNA&#x02013;protein complex in the right panel seems to be specific for testis extracts (<italic>D.melanogaster</italic> lane 9, <italic>D.hydei</italic> lane 10) and is absent using ovarian extract (lane 11).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkd25802"/></fig><fig id="gkd258f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p> Substitution of the <italic>B2t</italic> core promoter for the <italic>hsp70</italic> core promoter decreases promoter strength but not tissue specificity <italic>in vivo</italic>. Larval testes (containing only transcriptionally active cells) of representative corresponding transgenic fly strains &#x0005b;see Michiels <italic>et al.</italic> (32)&#x0005d; were analyzed histochemically for &#x003b2;-galactosidase reporter expression. The presence of the TATA-containing <italic>hsp70</italic> core promoter in combination with the &#x003b2;2UE1-activator element results in a decrease of reporter activity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkd25803"/></fig><fig id="gkd258f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><italic>In vivo</italic> analysis of Inr function in tissue-specific <italic>B2t</italic> gene regulation. (<bold>A</bold>) Inr-sequences used in the <italic>B2t</italic> promoter background for reporter expression analysis in the transgenic fly system. (<bold>B</bold>) &#x003b2;-galactosidase reporter expression of corresponding <italic>B2t</italic>&#x02013;Inr constructs. Expression was analyzed by histochemical X-Gal staining of adult testes and monitored after 30 min (left panels) and 240 min (middle panels), respectively. In addition, stainings of corresponding larval testes which contain only premeiotic, transcriptionally active germ cells are shown (right panels). In each case the activator element is able to drive testis-specific reporter expression. However, differences in the staining intensity are evident. The construct carrying the mutated Inr (middle panels) shows a weaker staining in comparison to the wild type (upper panels) and also in comparison to the construct with the TdT&#x02013;Inr region (lower panels), indicating a regulatory effect of the Inr element. (<bold>C</bold>) &#x003b2;-galactosidase enzyme activity assays confirm the quantitative function of the Inr element. Mutation of the relevant Inr base pairs leads to 50&#x00025; reduction in reporter expression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkd25804"/></fig><fig id="gkd258f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p> Regulatory activity of the downstream element, &#x003b2;2DE1. (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) <italic>In situ</italic> hybridization experiments with testes from transgenic flies expressing <italic>B2t-lacZ</italic> reporter genes containing &#x0005b;(A) &#x003b2;2DE1 in sense orientation, black arrowhead&#x0005d; or lacking &#x0005b;(B) &#x003b2;2DE1 in antisense orientation, inverse black arrowhead&#x0005d; a functional downstream element, &#x003b2;2DE1, reveal differences in the premeiotic <italic>lacZ</italic> mRNA reporter expression. The apical tips of adult testes are shown, where transcriptionally active cells are located. Side-by-side staining after <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization with a DIG-labeled <italic>lacZ</italic> probe shows reduced expression in the strain lacking &#x003b2;2DE1 function (B). (<bold>C</bold>) The Inr acts independently in combination with the &#x003b2;2DE1 element. Testis-specific &#x003b2;-galactosidase reporter activity was analyzed from different transgenic strains carrying truncated 5&#x02032;-UTR <italic>B2t</italic> promoters in combination with different Inr start sites. Removal of the &#x003b2;2DE1 downstream element, in combination with an Inr defective <italic>B2t</italic> promoter, results in further reduction of reporter expression. Relative reporter expression levels are shown in &#x00025; &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity (the value of the TdT construct reporter expression was set at 100&#x00025;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkd25805"/></fig></sec><ack><sec><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>Charlene Y. Kon, Matthias K&#x000e4;mpfer and John P. Mills are gratefully acknowledged for discussion and critical reading of the manuscript. This work was supported by a grant from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (Re628&#x0002f;9-1 and Re628&#x0002f;9-2) and the Fond der Chemischen Industrie to R.R.-P.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="gkd258c1"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Tjian</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and Maniatis,T. (1994) <source>Cell</source>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8156597</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c2"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ranish</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name> and Hahn,S. (1996) <source>Curr. Opin. Gen. Dev.</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>158</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c3"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Berk</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name> (1999) <source>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>330</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10395559</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c4"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Orphanides</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, Lagrange,T. and Reinberg,D. (1996) <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>2657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2683</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8946909</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c5"><label>5.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name> (1996) <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>334</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8870495</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c6"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Smale</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name> (1997) <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>, <volume>1351</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9116046</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c7"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Cherbas</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and Cherbas,P. (1993) <source>Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8485519</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c8"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> and Smale,S.T. (1996) <source>Gene</source>, <volume>182</volume>, 1<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c9"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Smale</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name> and Baltimore,D. (1989) <source>Cell</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2467742</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c10"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name> and Kadonaga,J.T. (1996) <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>724</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8598298</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c11"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name> and Kadonaga,J.T. (1997) <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>3020</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3031</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9367984</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c12"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> (1993) <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1308</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8330735</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c13"><label>13.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Tansey</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name> and Herr,W. (1997) <source>Cell</source>, <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>729</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>732</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9118213</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c14"><label>14.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Colgan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and Manley,J.L. (1995) <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>92</volume>, <fpage>1955</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1959</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7892207</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c15"><label>15.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name> and Tjian,R. (1995) <source>Cell</source>, <volume>82</volume>, <fpage>565</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>575</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7664336</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c16"><label>16.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Schwyter</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name>, Huang,J.-D., Dubnicoff,T. and Courey,A.J. (1995) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>3960</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3968</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7791801</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c17"><label>17.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Verrijzer</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name>, Chen,J.-L., Yokomori,K. and Tjian,R. (1995) <source>Cell</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>1115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1125</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7600579</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c18"><label>18.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Verrijzer</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name> and Tjian,R. (1996) <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>342</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8870497</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c19"><label>19.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> and Smale,S.T. (1994) <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>829</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7926770</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c20"><label>20.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, Verrijzer,C.P., Shao,J. and Smale,S.T. (1996) <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>873</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>886</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8846923</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c21"><label>21.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Purnell</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name>, Emanuel,P.A. and Gilmour,D.S. (1994) <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>830</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>842</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7926771</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c22"><label>22.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Sypes</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name> and Gilmour,D.S. (1994) <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>814</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8139922</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c23"><label>23.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Hansen,S.K. and Tjian,R. (1995) <source>Science</source>, <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>1783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1788</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8525367</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c24"><label>24.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Hansen,S.K. and Tjian,R. (1995) <source>Science</source>, <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>1825</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1828</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8525377</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c25"><label>25.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name>, M&#x000fc;ller,S. and Sauer,F. (1999) <source>Mech. Dev.</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10473116</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c26"><label>26.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Shopland</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name>, Hirayoshi,K., Fernandes,M. and Lis,J.T. (1995) <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>2756</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2769</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7590251</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c27"><label>27.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ohtsuki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Levine,M. and Cai,H.N. (1998) <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>556</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9472023</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c28"><label>28.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> and Maniatis,T. (1998) <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1076</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1086</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9463385</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c29"><label>29.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Emami</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name>, Navarre,W.W. and Smale,S.T. (1995) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>5906</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5916</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7565743</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c30"><label>30.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Garraway</surname><given-names>I.P.</given-names></name>, Semple,K. and Smale,S.T. (1996) <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>93</volume>, <fpage>4336</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4341</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8633066</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c31"><label>31.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Gasch,A., Kaltschmidt,B. and Renkawitz-Pohl,R. (1989) <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1565</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2504583</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c32"><label>32.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Wolk,A. and Renkawitz-Pohl,R. (1991) <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>4515</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4521</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1909432</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c33"><label>33.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Buttgereit,D. and Renkawitz-Pohl,R. (1993) <source>Eur. J. Cell Biol.</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>66</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8269980</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c34"><label>34.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Santel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, Winhauer,T., Bl&#x000fc;mer,N. and Renkawitz-Pohl,R. (1997) <source>Mech. Dev.</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9232593</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c35"><label>35.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name> and Lis,J.T. (1990) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2104657</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c36"><label>36.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Javahery</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, Khachi,K., Lo,K., Zenzie-Gregory,B. and Smale,S.T. (1994) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>116</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>127</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8264580</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c37"><label>37.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Jarrell</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name> and Meselson,M. (1991) <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1702540</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c38"><label>38.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Arkhipova</surname><given-names>I.R.</given-names></name> and Ilyin,Y. (1991) <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1708722</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c39"><label>39.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, Bucheton,A. and Finnegan,D.J. (1993) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>1042</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1050</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8380889</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c40"><label>40.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Fridell</surname><given-names>Y.-W.C.</given-names></name> and Searles,L.L. (1992) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>4571</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4577</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1406647</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c41"><label>41.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Minchiotti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, Contursi,C. and Di Nocera,P.P. (1997) <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>267</volume>, <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9096205</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c42"><label>42.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name>, Hatada,E.N., Scholz,G. and Scheidereit,C. (1997) <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>3995</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4003</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9321649</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c43"><label>43.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Chalkley</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name> and Verrijzer,C.P. (1999) <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>4835</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4845</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10469661</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkd258c44"><label>44.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kempe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, Muhs,B. and Sch&#x000e4;fer,M. (1993) <source>Dev. Genet.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>449</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8111973</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 