<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15121519</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association between hemochromatosis genotype and lead exposure among elderly men: the normative aging study.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>Robert O</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>Edwin K</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsaih</surname><given-names>Shring-Wern</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Senter</surname><given-names>Jody</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>Scott T</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aro</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Howard</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Pediatrics, Children's Hospital, Boston, Massachusetts 02115, USA. robert.wright@channing.harvard.edu</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>112</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>750</lpage><abstract><p>Because body iron burden is inversely associated with lead absorption, genes associated with hemochromatosis may modify body lead burden. Our objective was to determine whether the C282Y and/or H63D hemochromatosis gene (HFE) is associated with body lead burden. Patella and tibia lead levels were measured by K X-ray fluorescence in subjects from the Normative Aging Study. DNA samples were genotyped for C282Y and H63D using polymerase chain reaction/restriction fragment length polymorphism (PCR/RFLP). A series of multivariate linear regression models were constructed with bone or blood lead as dependent variables; age, smoking, and education as independent variables; and C282Y or H63D as independent risk factors and/or effect modifiers. Of 730 subjects, 94 (13%) carried the C282Y variant and 183 (25%) carried the H63D variant. In the crude analysis, mean tibia, patella, and blood lead levels were consistently lower in carriers of either HFE variant compared with levels in subjects with wild-type genotypes. In multivariate analyses that adjusted for age, smoking, and education, having an HFE variant allele was an independent predictor of significantly lower patella lead levels (p &#x0003c; 0.05). These data suggest that HFE variants have altered kinetics of lead accumulation after exposure. Among elderly men, subjects with HFE variants had lower patella lead levels. These effects may be mediated by alterations in lead toxicokinetics via iron metabolic pathways regulated by the HFE gene product and body iron stores.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 