<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Pain</journal-id><journal-title>Molecular Pain</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1744-8069</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1744-8069-2-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16503963</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1744-8069-2-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Depression of presynaptic excitation by the activation of vanilloid receptor 1 in the rat spinal dorsal horn revealed by optical imaging</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kusudo</surname><given-names>Kei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kusudo@synapse.his.fukui-u.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Hiroshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ikeda@synapse.his.fukui-u.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>Kazuyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>murase@synapse.his.fukui-u.ac.jp</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>University of Fukui, 3-9-1 Bunkyo, Fukui 910-8507, Japan</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.molecularpain.com/content/2/1/8"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2005</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 Kusudo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2006</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kusudo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author> Kusudo Kei kusudo@synapse.his.fukui-u.ac.jp </dc:author><dc:title> Depression of presynaptic excitation by the activation of vanilloid receptor 1 in the rat spinal dorsal horn revealed by optical imaging </dc:title><dc:date>2006</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Molecular Pain 2(1): 8-. (2006)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1744-8069(2006)2:1&#x0003c;8&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1744-8069</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>In this study, we show that capsaicin (CAP) depresses primary afferent fiber terminal excitability by acting on vanilloid receptor 1 (TRPV1 channels) of primary afferent fibers in adenosine 5'-triphosphate (ATP)- and temperature-dependent manner using two optical imaging methods. First, transverse slices of spinal cord were stained with a voltage-sensitive dye and the net excitation in the spinal dorsal horn was recorded. Prolonged treatment (&#x0003e;20 min) with the TRPV1 channel agonist, CAP, resulted in a long-lasting inhibition of the net excitation evoked by single-pulse stimulation of C fiber-activating strength. A shorter application of CAP inhibited the excitation in a concentration-dependent manner and the inhibition was reversed within several minutes. This inhibition was Ca<sup>++</sup>-dependent, was antagonized by the TRPV1 channel antagonist, capsazepine (CPZ), and the P<sub>2</sub>X and P<sub>2</sub>Y antagonist, suramin, and was facilitated by the P<sub>2</sub>Y agonist, uridine 5'-triphosphate (UTP). The inhibition of excitation was unaffected by bicuculline and strychnine, antagonists of GABA<sub>A </sub>and glycine receptors, respectively. Raising the perfusate temperature to 39&#x000b0;C from 27&#x000b0;C inhibited the excitation (-3%/&#x000b0;C). This depressant effect was antagonized by CPZ and suramin, but not by the P<sub>2</sub>X antagonist, 2', 3'-O-(2,4,6-trinitrophenyl) adenosine 5'-triphosphate (TNP-ATP). Second, in order to record the presynaptic excitation exclusively, we stained the primary afferent fibers anterogradely from the dorsal root. CAP application and a temperature increase from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C depressed the presynaptic excitation, and CPZ antagonized these effects. Thus, this study showed that presynaptic excitability is modulated by CAP, temperature, and ATP under physiological conditions, and explains the reported central actions of CAP. These results may have clinical importance, especially for the control of pain.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Yaksh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] first reported that an intrathecal injection of capsaicin (CAP) depletes substance P from primary sensory neurons and causes a prolonged increase in the thermal and chemical, but not mechanical, pain thresholds. Since then, a number of studies have shown that CAP produces analgesic action at the spinal level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. However, as reported by Nagy et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], the depletion of spinal cord substance P by CAP may not be sufficient to explain the changes induced by CAP.</p><p>Recent studies in peripheral axons revealed that CAP acts on vanilloid receptors 1 (TRPV1 channels) that are present on fine afferent fibers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The receptor channels are activated by painful heat stimuli (&#x0003e;43&#x000b0;C), as well as noxious chemical stimuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. The flow of Ca<sup>++ </sup>and Na<sup>+ </sup>through the channels induces depolarizing receptor potentials at the peripheral terminals, which generate action potentials that transmit pain information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Following such primary excitatory actions, treatment with CAP often produces secondary inhibitory actions. The application of TRPV1 channel agonists at afferent fiber bundles blocks conduction of the action potential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Adenosine triphosphate (ATP) also affects TRPV1 channels indirectly through the activation of G-protein, and sensitizes them so as to be activated at a lower temperature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. In the superficial layers (laminae I-II) of the dorsal horn, TRPV1 channels are abundant, especially at presynaptic elements of unmyelinated C-fiber origins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. However, their roles in afferent signal transmission are unclear.</p><p>We have been recording neuronal excitation in central slices by using an optical method with a voltage-sensitive dye [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], and investigated the neuronal circuitry and plasticity in spinal cord slices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. Recently, we succeeded in staining primary afferent fibers anterogradely from the dorsal root, and optically recorded the presynaptic excitation exclusively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Utilizing these two types of optical imaging methods, the visualization of presynaptic excitation and net excitation of pre- and postsynaptic elements, we investigated the mechanism of CAP action in the spinal cord. In addition, we examined the temperature dependence of CAP activity, because, unlike other brain regions such as the olfactory bulb and the hippocampus, we noticed that the magnitude of optical signal, especially in the superficial dorsal horn, changes depending on the perfusate temperature. Further, we speculated that TRPV1 channels contribute to this temperature dependence. In this study, we report that CAP acts on TRPV1 channels, most likely at presynaptic elements, that are consistently sensitized via P2Y receptors, and, therefore, that CAP can inhibit the afferent signal transmission even at physiological temperature.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>The effects of CAP on net excitation of pre- and postsynaptic elements</title><p>An example of optically recorded neuronal activity elicited by the stimulation is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>. In a transverse slice of the lumbar spinal cord stained with the voltage-sensitive dye, stimulation was applied to one of the dorsal roots attached to the slice, and neuronal activity in the dorsal horn region ipsilateral to the stimulated dorsal root was recorded optically. Single-pulse dorsal-root stimulation of C fiber-activating strength evoked prolonged (&#x0003e; 100 ms) neuronal activity in the superficial dorsal horn (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Stimulation of A-fiber-activating strength elicited no detectable response in the region (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Previously. we concluded that the optical response mostly reflects long-lasting neuronal activities of C-fiber origin, such as a burst of action-potential firings, synaptic bombardment and an increase in membrane excitability, which are known to be present after intense dorsal root stimulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Note that the optical response is composed of both excitation of afferent fibers and terminals and the following postsynaptic excitations.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Depression of afferent-evoked net neuronal excitation by CAP</bold>. <bold>A</bold>) A pseudo-color image sequence of stimulation-induced net optical responses measured from a slice bathed in a control solution (left), a CAP (0.5 &#x003bc;M)-containing solution (center), and the control solution for recovery (right). At left bottom, superimposed time traces obtained at the black square in the schematic drawing are illustrated for the respective images. At right bottom, the spatial distributions along the dorso-ventral lines in the schematic drawings are also illustrated. <bold>B</bold>) Concentration-dependent inhibition of net neuronal excitation by CAP at the period of 0.6&#x02013;1.8 ms in evoked response (circles), and of 4.8&#x02013;6.0 ms (squares). The curves were drawn according to the equation <italic>I </italic>= <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>max</italic></sub>/[<italic>1</italic>+(<italic>IC</italic><sub>50</sub>/[<italic>CAP</italic>])<sup><italic>N</italic></sup>] (IC<sub>50 </sub>= 0.5 &#x003bc;M &#x00026; I<sub>max </sub>= -30% N = 1.0 at 0.6&#x02013;1.8 ms of evoked response, and IC<sub>50 </sub>= 1.7 &#x003bc;M &#x00026; I<sub>max </sub>= -33% N = 0.5 at 4.8&#x02013;6.0 ms of evoked response) <bold>C</bold>) Changes in normalized time courses of the magnitudes of net neuronal excitation by CAP application with two different durations, 10 and 20 min (circles and squares, respectively). The period of CAP application is indicated by the bar. <bold>D</bold>) Pseudo-color image sequence of stimulation-induced net optical responses measured from a slice bathed in a control solution (left), a anandamide (50 &#x003bc;M)-containing solution (center), and the control solution for recovery (right). At left bottom, superimposed time traces obtained at the black square in the schematic drawing are illustrated for the respective images and at A-fiber stimulation. At right bottom, the spatial distributions along the dorso-ventral lines a, b and c in the schematic drawings are also illustrated. Excitation evoked by the dorsal root stimulation of A-fiber-activating strength in the normal condition is illustrated with dotted lines in the time traces and the spatial distributions. No detectable changes were observed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-2-8-1"/></fig><p>First, we investigated the action of CAP on the net neuronal excitation consisting of pre- and postsynaptic components. At a perfusate temperature of 27&#x000b0;C, the bath application of CAP for 10 min inhibited the neuronal excitation most effectively at the superficial regions of the dorsal horn, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>. The inhibitory effect was concentration-dependent (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). The effect was less during the initial several milliseconds of elicited excitation than during the delayed part (IC<sub>50 </sub>= 0.5 &#x003bc;M, Imax = -30%, N = 1.0 for the initial 0.6&#x02013;1.8 ms, v.s. IC<sub>50 </sub>= 1.7 &#x003bc;M, Imax = -33%, N = 0.5 for later 4.8&#x02013;6.0 ms). As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, the excitation in the former period was unchanged in a Ca<sup>++</sup>-free condition, and, thus, reflects predominately the excitation of presynaptic elements, and the latter reflects the following postsynaptic excitation (see also Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref> and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref> for the duration of presynaptic excitation). In the following results pertain to the initial period unless otherwise noted. It is interesting to note that the depressant effect lasted over an hour after a prolonged application of CAP of over 20 min (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). In the following experiments, we used a 10 minutes application of 1 &#x003bc;M CAP, because the effect (-11.8 &#x000b1; 1.4%, n = 3, p = 0.02) was reversible within several minutes. The second application of CAP at one hour after recovery from the first application produced a similar inhibition in two slices, but not in three slices (data not shown). The natural ligand of the TRPV1 channel, anandamide (50 &#x003bc;M, 10 min), also depressed the neuronal excitation in the superficial laminae (-23.3 &#x000b1; 4.43%, n = 3, p = 0.03) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>). Although the 10&#x02013;23% change in excitation may seem small, we believe that it is not marginal since it is caused by the change in the magnitude or in the number of evoked action potentials (see the Discussion for details).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Pharmacology of CAP-induced depression of net neuronal excitation</bold>. <bold>A</bold>) Time traces obtained using various agents. The effect of CAP was antagonized by the vanilloid receptor 1 antagonist, CPZ (20 &#x003bc;M), suramin (100 &#x003bc;M), and a Ca<sup>++</sup>-free medium. It was not affected by BMI (10 &#x003bc;M) and STRY (3 &#x003bc;M), and was potentiated by UTP (30 &#x003bc;M) and at a higher temperature of 33&#x000b0;C. <bold>B</bold>) Concentration dependencies of CAP effect in normal solution at 27&#x000b0;C (circles) and 33&#x000b0;C (squares), and in UTP at 27&#x000b0;C (diamonds). Points were fitted with IC<sub>50 </sub>= 1.7 &#x003bc;M, Imax = -30% and N = 1.0 for 27&#x000b0;C, IC<sub>50 </sub>= 0.3 &#x003bc;M, Imax = -34% and N = 1.2 for 33&#x000b0;C, and IC<sub>50 </sub>= 0.6 &#x003bc;M, Imax = -33% and N = 1.5 for UTP. <bold>C</bold>) Averaged percent control response in various agents in 4&#x02013;6 slices. Statistical significance and insignificance to control change are indicated with signs, * (p &#x0003c; 0.05) and # (p &#x0003e; 0.5), respectively. Although +UTP was not significant, it shifted the dose-response curve reasonably well (diamonds in C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-2-8-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of temperature increase on C-fiber evoked net excitation</bold>. <bold>A</bold>) Pseudo-color image sequence of stimulation-induced optical responses measured in a slice in perfusion solution at 27&#x000b0;C, 33&#x000b0;C, 36&#x000b0;C, and 39&#x000b0;C (from left to right). Superimposed time traces of optical signals obtained at 27&#x000b0;C (thin black), 33&#x000b0;C (thin red), 36&#x000b0;C (bold black), and 39&#x000b0;C (dashed red). These records were obtained by spatial average of the optical signals of 8 &#x000d7; 8 pixels corresponding to the black square area (50 &#x000d7; 50 &#x003bc;m) shown in the schematic drawing of the dorsal horn. Dotted line in the optical signal records indicates the baseline level. <bold>B</bold>) Pseudo-color image sequence of stimulation-induced optical responses measured from slices bathed in 27&#x000b0;C, 33&#x000b0;C, and 27&#x000b0;C (form left to right). Superimposed time traces obtained at 27&#x000b0;C (thin black), 33&#x000b0;C (dashed black), and 27&#x000b0;C (red) are indicated at left below. Spatial distributions of the magnitude of excitation along lines in schematic drawing are illustrated at right below. <bold>C</bold>) Normalized time course of magnitude of optical signals showing the averaged effect induced by a change of temperature from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C (left), and the averaged temperature-dependency of depression (right), in 4 slices.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-2-8-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Pharmacology of temperature effect on net excitation</bold>. <bold>A</bold>) Antagonism by CPZ (20 &#x003bc;M) and a Ca<sup>++</sup>-free medium. Upper inserts show the time traces of optical signals at 27&#x000b0;C (thin) and 33&#x000b0;C (bold). Bottom graph shows the averaged changes in normalized magnitude of optical signal obtained in 4 slices when temperature was altered from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C as indicated by the bar above. Circles, squares and diamonds indicate results obtained in the normal solution (control), in a Ca<sup>++</sup>-free medium, and CPZ-containing solution, respectively. <bold>B</bold>) Antagonism by suramin (100 &#x003bc;M) and potentiation by TNP-ATP (1 &#x003bc;M). Bottom line in the graph indicates the duration of drug application. <bold>C</bold>) No effect of BMI (10 &#x003bc;M) and STRY (3 &#x003bc;M) (squares), and Ni<sup>++ </sup>(diamonds) is observed on temperature effect. <bold>D</bold>) Augmented effect in APV (50 &#x003bc;M) and CNQX (10 &#x003bc;M).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-2-8-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Changes of net excitation induced by temperature increase from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C in various conditions</bold>. Each bar exhibits the averaged results obtained in 4&#x02013;7 slices. Statistical significance to control change is indicated with signs, ** (p &#x0003c; 0.01) and * (p &#x0003c; 0.05), respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-2-8-5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Depression of presynaptic excitation by CAP</bold>. <bold>A</bold>) Pseudo-color image sequence of stimulation-induced presynaptic excitation measured from a slice in the control solution (left) and with CAP (right) at 27&#x000b0;C. Superimposed time traces at the black square in the schematic drawing, as well as spatial distributions along the dorso-ventral lines a, b and c, are illustrated at bottom. <bold>B</bold>) No effect of CAP in a Ca<sup>++</sup>-free condition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-2-8-6"/></fig><p>In slices from rats lacking most of the CAP sensitive afferent fibers by neonatal CAP treatment, the bath application of CAP did not inhibit the neuronal excitation (+4.3 &#x000b1; 5.8%, n = 4). Therefore, the inhibition of neuronal excitation by CAP is likely due to the change in excitability of capsaicin sensitive afferent fibers.</p><p>The pharmacology of the CAP action is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. The inhibition by CAP was not observed in the presence of the TRPV1 channels antagonist, capsazepine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] (CPZ, 20 &#x003bc;M, applied for 40 min from 20 min before CAP application), or in the absence of Ca<sup>++</sup>, which is the major ion carried through TRPV1 channels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The possibility that the depression might be due to the activation of inhibitory interneurons by CAP was excluded, since the CAP action was unaffected by the presence of bicuculline (BMI, 10 &#x003bc;M) and strychnine (STRY, 5 &#x003bc;M), antagonists of GABA<sub>A </sub>and glycine receptors, respectively. However, a possible contribution of interneurons that contain other inhibitory transmitters still remained. In the presence of CPZ, anandamide depressed the neuronal excitation by -10.8 &#x000b1; 1.7% (n = 3, P = 0.017), which is approximately one half of the effect obtained by anandamide alone (-23.3 &#x000b1; 4.4%, n = 3, p = 0.03). This result suggests that TRPV1 and CB1 receptors contributed equally to the anandamide effect.</p><p>Adenosine 5'-triphosphate (ATP) is known to sensitize or potentiate CAP and heat evoked TRPV1 currents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. As shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>, the depression by CAP was blocked by the P<sub>2</sub>X and P<sub>2</sub>Y purinoceptor antagonist, suramin (100 &#x003bc;M). In addition, the depression by CAP was facilitated by the P<sub>2</sub>Y agonist, uridine 5'-triphosphate, in a dose-related manner (UTP, IC<sub>50 </sub>= 0.6 &#x003bc;M, Imax = -33%, N = 1.5) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). We found that the CAP-dependent depression was significantly larger at 33&#x000b0;C, and the dose-response curve was shifted leaving the maximum effect unchanged (IC<sub>50 </sub>= 0.3 &#x003bc;M, Imax = -34%, N = 1.2) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). Thus, we investigated the temperature dependent change of the excitation and its relation with TRPV1 channels.</p></sec><sec><title>Action of temperature increase on net neuronal excitation</title><p>When the perfusate temperature was increased from 27&#x000b0;C to 33, 36 and 39&#x000b0;C, the magnitude of excitation evoked by the dorsal root stimulation was depressed (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). The effect was reversible, and was most significant in the superficial dorsal horn, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>, where the magnitudes of excitation at 27&#x000b0;C and 33&#x000b0;C are plotted along dorso-ventral lines. The optical response recorded at 36&#x000b0;C and 39&#x000b0;C often deteriorated gradually by the loss of slice viability. Therefore, we set the bath temperature at 27&#x000b0;C where stable recording over 5 hours could be achieved consistently, and increased the temperature when necessary. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref> exhibits the magnitudes of the optical response in lamina II when the temperature was increased from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C for a period of 40 min. The effect was significant (-19.7 &#x000b1; 2.65%, n = 3, p = 0.009), and was reversible, although the excitation was somewhat augmented after recovery (5.86 &#x000b1; 4.19%, n = 3, p = 0.5). The percent decrease of excitation was linearly related at -3%/&#x000b0;C for the temperature range of 27&#x000b0;C to 39&#x000b0;C over an average of four slices (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>).</p><p>It is possible that the temperature dependent decrease of neuronal excitation observed in the superficial dorsal horn might be due to a property of the voltage-sensitive dyes used in the experiment. The following results, however, indicate that it is unlikely, and the observation is due to the temperature-dependent activation of TRPV1 channels, possibly by residual or released ligand(s).</p><p>As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>, in the medium containing no Ca<sup>++ </sup>ions, which are the primary ions flowing through TRPV1 channels, the temperature increase from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C did not induce significant change in the magnitude of neuronal excitation evoked by the dorsal root stimulation (-4.73 &#x000b1; 2.49%, n = 3, p = 0.74). Also, in the presence of the TRPV1 channel antagonist, CPZ (20 &#x003bc;M), the temperature increase from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C did not affect the neuronal excitation (-7.13 &#x000b1; 0.57%, n = 3, p = 0.18).</p><p>We further investigated whether ATP modulates the temperature-dependent change of the evoked excitation (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). The P<sub>2</sub>X and P<sub>2</sub>Y antagonist, suramin (100 &#x003bc;M, 15 min), did not affect the neuronal excitation at 27&#x000b0;C (1.43 &#x000b1; 3.31%, n = 4, p = 0.70). In the presence of suramin, the temperature increase from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C produced an insignificant change in excitation (-8.01 &#x000b1; 2.70%, n = 4, p = 0.06). The P<sub>2</sub>X antagonist, 2',3'-O-(2,4,6-Trinitrophenyl) adenosine 5'-triphosphate (TNP-ATP, 1 &#x003bc;M, 15 min), was ineffective on the excitation at 27&#x000b0;C (102.40 &#x000b1; 3.00%, n = 3, p = 0.50). In the presence of TNP-ATP, the excitation was suppressed by the temperature increase from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C (-22.4 &#x000b1; 2.80%, n = 3, p = 0.01).</p><p>GABA-and Glycine-containing inhibitory interneurons did not seem to contribute to the temperature dependency of excitation, because, in the presence of the inhibitory amino acid antagonists, BMI (10 &#x003bc;M) and STRY (3 &#x003bc;M), the excitation was depressed by the temperature increase significantly (-17.7 &#x000b1; 0.43%, n = 3, p = 0.005) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>).</p><p>The voltage-gated Ca<sup>++ </sup>channel blocker, Ni<sup>++</sup>, is known to reduce the synaptic transmission significantly. In the presence of Ni<sup>++</sup>(1 mM), the degrees of depression (-18.1 &#x000b1; 0.97%, n = 4, p = 0.005) were identical to those observed in the control condition without Ni<sup>++ </sup>(-19.7 &#x000b1; 2.65%, n = 3, p = 0.0009) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). The temperature increase also depressed the excitation recorded in the presence of the excitatory amino acid receptor antagonists, D(-)-2-Amino-5-phosphonovaleric acid (D-APV, 50 &#x003bc;M) and 6-Cyano-7-nitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione (CNQX, 10 &#x003bc;M), where presynaptic excitation predominates in the recorded optical response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. These results are consistent with the possibility that the presynaptic excitation is strongly temperature dependent, although the postsynaptic excitation could be also temperature dependent. These pharmacological properties of temperature effect are summarized in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Presynaptic action of capsaicin and temperature</title><p>Since TRPV1 channels are abundant on presynaptic sites rather than on postsynaptic cells in the dorsal horn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], we directly tested the CAP effect on the excitation of presynaptic elements. The presynaptic fibers and terminals were anterogradely stained with the voltage-sensitive dye that was applied by the suction pipette used for dorsal root stimulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Dorsal root stimulation of C fiber-activating strength elicited excitation most intensely in lamina II, as seen in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>. Since the response was altered very little by the perfusion of Ca<sup>++</sup>-free medium (e.g., Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>), we can conclude that only the presynaptic elements were stained and the excitation of presynaptic elements was recorded. A 10 minute application of CAP (1 &#x003bc;M) depressed the presynaptic excitation in lamina II significantly (-20.4 &#x000b1; 6.54%, n = 5, p = 0.02) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). CAP was ineffective in the Ca<sup>++</sup>-free medium (-2.09 &#x000b1; 1.03%, n = 5) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>).</p><p>When the perfusate temperature was increased from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C, the magnitude of presynaptic excitation was depressed (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>). As seen in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7C</xref>, the presynaptic excitation was largest in lamina II, and was depressed by the temperature increase. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7D</xref> exhibits the time course of the change in magnitude in lamina II induced by a temperature increase from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C for a period of 40 min. The effect observed in lamina II was significant (-17.3 &#x000b1; 1.4%, n = 3, p = 0.006), and was reversible (1.2 &#x000b1; 1.2%, n = 3, p = 0.42).</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of temperature increase on presynaptic excitation</bold>. <bold>A</bold>) Pseudo-color image sequence of stimulation-induced optical responses measured in the solution at 27&#x000b0;C, 33&#x000b0;C, and 27&#x000b0;C in a slice (from left to right). <bold>B</bold>) Superimposed time traces of optical signals obtained at 27&#x000b0;C (black), 33&#x000b0;C (dashed black), and 27&#x000b0;C (red). These records were obtained by spatial average of the optical signals of 8 &#x000d7; 8 pixels corresponding to a black square area (50 &#x000d7; 50 &#x003bc;m) shown in the schematic drawing of the dorsal horn. Dotted line in the optical signal records indicates the baseline level. <bold>C</bold>) Spatial distributions of the magnitude of excitation along dorso-ventral lines a, b and c in schematic drawing. <bold>D</bold>) Normalized time course of magnitude of optical signals showing the averaged effect induced by a change of temperature from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1744-8069-2-8-7"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In the present study, we showed that CAP, anandamide and an increase in perfusate temperature inhibited the net excitation of pre and postsynaptic elements and the presynaptic excitation evoked by dorsal root stimulation in the superficial dorsal horn. These inhibitions were Ca<sup>++</sup>-dependent, antagonized by a TRPV1 channel antagonist and a P<sub>2</sub>X and P<sub>2</sub>Y antagonist, and facilitated by a P<sub>2</sub>Y agonist, but not by a P<sub>2</sub>X agonist. In addition, the inhibitions were unaffected by antagonists of GABA<sub>A </sub>and glycine receptors.</p><p>Several studies have shown that an intrathecal injection of CAP induces analgesic action at the spinal level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. In addition, electrophysiological studies have revealed that CAP suppresses C-fiber-evoked synaptic transmission in the spinal dorsal horn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. A bath application of CAP for 1 min produces a large increase in the spontaneous EPSCs frequency using patch clamp recording from spinal dorsal horn neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. However, the mechanism of these effects has not been clarified. In this study, we showed that CAP inhibits neuronal excitation, especially in superficial layers of the spinal dorsal horn. This distribution of inhibited area by CAP agrees with the distribution of TRPV1 channels reported by immunohistochemical studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. It is well known that the activation of TRPV1 channels induces an influx of Ca<sup>++ </sup>and Na<sup>+ </sup>ions via this receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. In this study, we showed that inhibition of the neuronal excitation by CAP was not observed in the presence of CPZ. In addition, the CAP effect was not dependent on the activation of inhibitory amino acid-containing neurons, since this inhibition was unaffected by BMI and STRY. Therefore, it is reasonable to conclude that CAP inhibited the neuronal excitation via TRPV1 channels in superficial layer of the spinal dorsal horn, although a possibility remains that CAP-sensitive interneurons containing other inhibitory transmitter(s) and/or modulator(s) contributed to the CAP effect.</p><p>Next, we investigated the Ca<sup>++ </sup>dependency of the CAP and temperature effects. Calcium ions are the major cation carried through the TRPV1 channel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Both the CAPs- and temperature-dependent inhibitions were blocked in Ca<sup>++</sup>-free condition. Although the TRPV1 channel has a relatively high permeability to Ca<sup>++</sup>, both CAP and heat are known to activate the channels in the absence of external Ca<sup>++ </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], and it seems difficult to explain the complete block of CAP and heat effects in the Ca<sup>++ </sup>free condition. It is possible that TRPV1 channels were activated by CAP and heat in the Ca<sup>++ </sup>free condition, but that the influx of cations other than Ca<sup>++ </sup>via TRPV1 channels, and the following presynaptic depolarization, might not be sufficient to inhibit the neuronal excitation.</p><p>In the periphery, the acute administration of CAP induces burning pain by activating C fibers via TRPV1 channels. It depolarizes the terminals generating action potentials. They are conducted to the spinal cord and induce nociceptive sensation. Larger doses and/or prolonged administration of CAP have analgesic effect due to the desensitization of TRPV1 channels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. We recorded the excitation centrally. The depolarization of afferent terminals and/or fibers branching points would cause reduction of action potential size and even failure of action potential generation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. The central inhibitory action of CAP observed in this study accords well with this presynaptic inhibition mechanism. When CAP was applied for 10 min, the inhibition of neuronal excitation was reversible. However, when CAP was applied for 20 min, it became irreversible. This prolonged irreversible effect of CAP might be due to other mechanisms, such as CB1 activation.</p><p>In this study, the neuronal excitation was also inhibited by anandamide to a larger extent (-23.3%) than by CAP (-11.8%), and the effect of anandamide was partially antagonized by CPZ. It is known that the cannabinoid CB1 receptors are also activated by anandamide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Therefore, it is possible that the inhibition of the neuronal excitation by anandamide is the combination of TRPV1 and CB1 channel activation.</p><p>TRPV1 channels in the periphery are activated by heat, as well as by CAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. However, the temperature dependence of TRPV1 channels in the spinal dorsal horn has not been reported. In this study, we showed that increasing the perfusate temperature inhibited the neuronal excitation in the superficial laminae of the spinal dorsal horn. This inhibition was Ca<sup>++</sup>-dependent, antagonized by CPZ, and was unaffected by BMI and STRY, as well as, by the inhibition by CAP. From these results, the inhibition of neuronal excitation by increasing the perfusate temperature may be induced by the same mechanism as the inhibition induced by CAP. That is, the natural ligand of TRPV1 channels is present in the normal condition, and is continuously activating TRPV1 channels. In fact, in the natural condition, anandamide has been found in the dorsal horn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], and we showed in this study that anandamide depressed the neuronal excitation in a similar manner to CAP.</p><p>Normally, the thermal threshold for activation of TRPV1 channels is more than 43&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. However, in this study, the perfusate temperature increase from 27 to 33&#x000b0;C was sufficient to inhibit the neuronal excitation mediated by TRPV1 channels. Tominaga et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] reported that the temperature threshold for TRPV1 channels activation was reduced from 42 to 35&#x000b0;C in the presence of ATP by measuring the current in HEK293 cells and that this effect was mediated by the P<sub>2</sub>Y receptor. In this study, the effect of CAP was blocked by suramin and was facilitated by UTP, and the effect of increasing the perfusate temperature was blocked by suramin, but not by TNP-ATP. These results indicate that the threshold for activation of TRPV1 channels in the spinal dorsal horn is decreased by the activation of the P<sub>2</sub>Y receptor. ATP has been reported to be a fast synaptic transmitter in the spinal dorsal horn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. ATP release from primary afferent terminals may contribute to the decrease of threshold for TRPV1 channels activation. The presence of ATP in the unstimulated condition is also highly likely. Therefore, TRPV1 channels in the spinal dorsal horn may be activated even at physiological temperatures.</p><p>In this study, the optical signal was recorded by anterograde staining of only primary afferents. Since this optical response was not decreased in a Ca<sup>++</sup>-free medium (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>) or in D-AP5 and CNQX [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], it reflects exclusively the voltage change of presynaptic elements. The inhibition of the presynaptic response by CAP and by the increase in perfusate temperature suggests a decrease in the amplitude or number of presynaptic action potentials in presynaptic elements. TRPV1 channels exist, not only on primary afferent terminals, but also on postsynaptic neurons in the superficial dorsal horn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] though not conclusive at present. Therefore, the decrease of presynaptic excitation may be due to a direct effect on TRPV1 channels in primary afferent terminals, or indirect effects mediated by any factor(s) released from TRPV1 channel-activated postsynaptic neurons. However, the latter possibility is less likely since the effect of CAP was observed in the presence of D-AP5 and CNQX, when most of the fast afferent signal transmission to the postsynaptic sites is blocked, although a possibility remains that the afferent stimulation we used activated CAP-sensitive glutamate-containing interneurons via transmitter(s) other than glutamate. Therefore, the inhibition of the presynaptic response by CAP and the increase in perfusate temperature is likely due to a decrease in the amplitude or number of presynaptic action potentials via the activation of TRPV1 channels.</p><p>In the spinal dorsal horn, the regulation of presynaptic spiking is known in the context of presynaptic inhibition. The depolarization of primary afferent terminals decreases the amplitude of action potentials and, thus, produces the presynaptic inhibition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. In addition, the silent presynaptic afferent terminals may become activated after their liberation from the shunting of the action potentials at primary afferent terminals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. In the superficial laminae of the dorsal horn, TRPV1 channels are abundant, especially at presynaptic elements of unmyelinated C-fiber origin. Therefore, CAP and the increase in perfusate temperature may inhibit neuronal excitation in the spinal dorsal horn via TRPV1 channels at primary afferent terminals.</p><p>TRPV1 channels exist not only at sensory neuron somata and primary afferent terminals, but also on axonal membranes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Furthermore, it is reported that the application of TRPV1 channel agonists at afferent fiber bundles blocks action potential conduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Therefore, another possibility is that the inhibition of neuronal excitation in the spinal dorsal horn by CAP and an increase in perfusate temperature may be caused by <bold>a </bold>conduction block of the action potential in primary afferent fibers. It has been reported that removal of external Ca<sup>++ </sup>does not affect the C fiber conduction block caused by CAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Therefore, the decrease of neuronal excitation by CAP and temperature increase is less likely due to a conduction block. It is difficult to distinguish, however, whether the effect of CAP and an increase in perfusate temperature is caused by a change of action potential at the level of primary afferent fibers or their terminals in the dorsal horn, because the presynaptic response that we measured in this study was the sum of excitations in both afferent fibers and terminals along the slice depth. To elucidate this point, it is necessary to record the action potentials in individual afferent fibers with higher-resolution camera in the future.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The electrically evoked neuronal excitation in the spinal dorsal horn was prevented by CAP and by the increase in perfusate temperature via TRPV1 channels. These inhibitions were caused by the depression of primary afferent fiber terminal excitability, at least in part. Our results showed that these inhibitions were modulated by the P<sub>2</sub>Y receptor subtypes, and it may play a role to enable activation of TRPV1 channels at physiological temperature. This study clarifies the properties of TRPV1 channels in the spinal dorsal horn and the mechanism of analgesic effect by CAP at the spinal level. These findings may have clinical importance, especially for the control of pain.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>The preparation, apparatus, and data processing for the optical imaging were identical to those used in our previous studies [[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]; for detailed descriptions see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]]. A brief summary follows.</p><sec><title>Preparation</title><p>All animal studies were undertaken with protocols approved by the university animal ethics committee. Transverse slices (350&#x02013;450 &#x003bc;m thick) with dorsal roots attached (5&#x02013;10 mm in length) were prepared from lumbosacral enlargements of 12- to 25-day-old Sprague-Dawley rat spinal cords, as described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. A slice, stained with a voltage-sensitive absorption dye, RH-482 (0.1 mg/ml, 20 min), was set in a submersion-type chamber (0.2 ml) on an inverted microscope (IMT, Olympus, Tokyo) equipped with a 150-W halogen lamp. The slice was perfused with Ringer solution at 27&#x000b0;C containing 124 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 1.2 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 1.3 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 2.4 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 26 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 0.2 mM thiourea, 0.2 mM ascorbic acid, and 10 mM glucose (oxygenated with 95% O<sub>2 </sub>and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>).</p><p>The RH-482 (NK-3630) dye was obtained from Nippon Kanko Shikiso (Okayama, Japan); the DL-2-amino-5-phosphonovaleric acid (D-AP5), bicuculline methiodide, strychnine hemisulfate, and nifedipine were from Sigma (St. Louis, MO); and the other chemicals were from Nacalai Tesque (Kyoto, Japan). Each of these chemicals was dissolved in distilled water at high concentration, divided into aliquots, and kept frozen at -40&#x000b0;C until use. The aliquots were dissolved in the bathing solution at known concentrations during the experiments. The perfusion solution of the slice was switched to the drug-containing solution for a fixed period.</p></sec><sec><title>Neonatal capsaicin treatment</title><p>Capsaicin was dissolved in 100% ethanol, and then diluted with Tween80/PBS solution until ethanol concentration became 10%. Rats of postnatal day 2&#x02013;3 were injected the capsaicin solution (50 mg/kg) subcutaneously at the dorsal cervix. Three weeks after the injection, rats were tested on a hot plate (65&#x000b0;C). While normal untreated rats raised and licked the feet within 10 seconds, successfully treated rats did not react over one minute.</p></sec><sec><title>Optical recording</title><p>The light absorption change in a 0.83-mm-square area in the dorsal horn at a wavelength of 700 &#x000b1; 32 nm was recorded by an imaging system (SD1001, Fuji Film Microdevice, Tokyo) with 128 &#x000d7; 128-pixel photo sensors at a frame rate of 0.6 ms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Thirty-two single pulses were given to the dorsal root at a constant interval of 12&#x02013;15 s. Starting at 10 ms before each stimulus, 128 consecutive frames of the light-absorption images were taken by the image sensor with a sampling interval of 0.6 ms. The reference frame, which was taken immediately before each series of 128 frames, was subtracted from each of the subsequent 128 frames. Thirty-two series of such difference images were averaged and stored in the system memory. We determined the initial frame by averaging the first 15 frames of the difference image and then subtracting this from each of the 128 frames of the image data on a pixel-by-pixel basis in order to eliminate the effects of noise contained in the reference frame. The ratio image was then calculated by dividing the image data by the reference frame. In most cases, the ratio image was filtered by a 3-point moving average over time [see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] for detail].</p></sec><sec><title>Dorsal root stimulation</title><p>The dorsal root was stimulated by a glass suction electrode. The types of primary afferent fibers activated by the electrical stimuli were initially identified by the field potentials recorded by a glass microelectrode positioned either in the superficial dorsal horn or at the entry zone of the root, as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>The single current-pulse stimulation of the dorsal root elicits the following optical responses in the dorsal horn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]: (1) a brief (&#x0003c; 3 ms) and small, almost undetectable, response is evoked at the entry zone of the dorsal root and, occasionally, in the deep dorsal horn by a 0.05-mA current pulse of 0.05 ms duration; (2) by increasing the stimulus intensity to 0.1 mA, an optical response of longer duration (&#x0003c; 100 ms) appears in lamina I extending to the outer part of lamina II, and in lamina III and deeper laminae; (3) additional increases in intensity (&#x0003e; 0.3 mA) and/or duration (&#x0003e; 0.5 ms) lead to the generation of an intense, prolonged (&#x0003e; 200 ms) response in the superficial laminae I-III, most prominently in lamina II. The long-lasting response in lamina II is delayed, with the latency corresponding to the slow conduction velocity of C fibers (ca. 1 m/s). The onset of optical responses in lamina I and lamina III or deeper laminae elicited by any of these conditions takes place within one image frame (i.e., the latency is less than 0.6 ms). The conduction velocity of fibers responsible for the induction of the immediate response should be faster than 6 m/s (dorsal root length of 4 mm/0.6 ms), which corresponds to the conduction velocity of A fibers. These spatial and temporal profiles of optical responses agree fairly well with the cytoarchitectonic organization of the dorsal horn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>], giving additional indications of the fiber types activated by the stimuli.</p><p>Therefore, <bold>t</bold>he activation conditions consisted of a 0.05-mA current pulse of 0.05 ms duration for A&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; fibers (A fib<bold>e</bold>r other than A&#x003b4; fibers), a 0.1-mA current pulse of 0.05 ms duration (low-intensity stimulation) for A&#x003b1;/&#x003b2;/&#x003b4; fibers (all types of A fibers), and a 1.5-mA current pulse of 0.5 ms duration (high-intensity stimulation) for A and C fibers. These parameters were similar to those used in other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Temperature control</title><p>The temperature of perfusate in the recording chamber was maintained with a heating coil along the polyethylene tubing (50 cm in length and 1 mm in diameter) between a peristalic pump and the inlet of chamber. Solution in a reservoir that was maintained at a room temperature of 25&#x000b0;C was heated to 27&#x000b0;C while passing through the tubing. The solution temperature in the chamber was continuously monitored with a small sensor positioned near the specimen. Since the room temperature was maintained constant and the solution in the reservoir was equilibrated to the room, the solution temperature in the chamber was usually stable, within &#x000b1; 0.2&#x000b0;C, during the duration of each experiment (1&#x02013;3 hours). Since the capacity of the chamber (0.5 ml) and the volume in the tubing (0.1 ml) were small in respect to the flow (3 ml/min), the temperature of the solution in the chamber could be controlled by the amount of electric current. In control experiments, the temperature measured at the surface of the slice was increased from 27&#x000b0;C to 33&#x000b0;C within 180 seconds by a current increase, and, following the reduction after 20 min at 33&#x000b0;C, the temperature at the surface of the slice was returned to 27&#x000b0;C within 300 seconds.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Results were expressed as the mean &#x000b1; SE. Non-parametric ANOVA (Tukey-Kramer test) was used for statistical difference<bold>s</bold>. Significant differences were calculated using the t-test, and differences were considered significant when p &#x0003c; 0.05 (*) or p &#x0003c; 0.01 (**) and # (p &#x0003e; 0.5).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was <bold>s</bold>upported by Grant-in-Aids from Japanese Society for Promotion of Science, and a grant from Yazaki Memorial Foundation for Science and Technology.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yaksh</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Farb</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Leeman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessell</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrathecal capsaicin depletes substance P in the rat spinal cord and produces prolonged thermal analgesia</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1979</year><volume>206</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">228392</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sipes</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>Burks</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capsaicinoid-induced local and systemic antinociception without substance P depletion</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1982</year><volume>244</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6180803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(82)90921-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Micevych</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaksh</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Szolcsanyi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of intrathecal capsaicin analogues on the immunofluorescence of peptides and serotonin in the dorsal horn in rats</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>1983</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6188075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0306-4522(83)90031-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jhamandas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaksh</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Harty</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Szolcsanyi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Go</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Action of intrathecal capsaicin and its structural analogues on the content and release of spinal substance P: selectivity of action and relationship to analgesia</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1984</year><volume>306</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6205719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(84)90371-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Emson</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Iversen</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A re-evaluation of the neurochemical and antinociceptive effects of intrathecal capsaicin in the rat</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1981</year><volume>211</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6165438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(81)90980-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caterina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Malmberg</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Raumann</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Basbaum</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cloned capsaicin receptor integrates multiple pain-producing stimuli</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1998</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9768840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80564-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Masu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentiation of capsaicin receptor activity by metabotropic ATP receptors as a possible mechanism for ATP-evoked pain and hyperalgesia</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>6951</fpage><lpage>6956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.111025298</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heyman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rang</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depolarizing responses to capsaicin in a subpopulation of rat dorsal root ganglion cells</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>1985</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4011050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-3940(85)90442-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The C-fibre conduction block caused by capsaicin on rat vagus nerve in vitro</article-title><source>Pain</source><year>1989</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2594402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-3959(89)90011-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actions of capsaicin on mouse dorsal root ganglion cells in vitro</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>1993</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8233051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-3940(93)90733-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grosskreutz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Quasthoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grafe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capsaicin blocks tetrodotoxin-resistant sodium potentials and calcium potentials in unmyelinated C fibres of biopsied human sural nerve in vitro</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>1996</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8731172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-3940(96)12536-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valtschanoff</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rustioni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vanilloid receptor VR1 is both presynaptic and postsynaptic in the superficial laminae of the rat dorsal horn</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2001</year><volume>436</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.1063</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanifuji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Horizontal propagation of excitation in rat visual cortical slices revealed by optical imaging</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>266</volume><fpage>1057</fpage><lpage>1059</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7973662</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanifuji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optical responses evoked by single-pulse stimulation to the dorsal root in the rat spinal dorsal horn in slice</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>812</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9813252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(98)00928-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Randic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust suppression of afferent-induced excitation in the rat spinal dorsal horn after conditioning low-frequency stimulation</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>1957</fpage><lpage>1964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10515985</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust changes of afferent-induced excitation in the rat spinal dorsal horn after conditioning high-frequency stimulation</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>2412</fpage><lpage>2420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10758142</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glial nitric oxide-mediated long-term presynaptic facilitation revealed by optical imaging in rat spinal dorsal horn</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>9888</fpage><lpage>9896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15525773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2608-04.2004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The actions of anandamide on rat superficial medullary dorsal horn neurons in vitro</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>548</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12562891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2002.035063</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumamoto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Furue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Action of capsaicin on dorsal root-evoked synaptic transmission to substantia gelatinosa neurons in adult rat spinal cord slices</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>830</volume><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10366683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(99)01408-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baccei</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardoni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of nociceptive synaptic inputs to the neonatal rat dorsal horn: glutamate release by capsaicin and menthol</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>549</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12679376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2003.040451</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakatsuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Furue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of central terminal vanilloid receptor-1 receptors and alpha beta-methylene-ATP-sensitive P2X receptors reveals a converged synaptic activity onto the deep dorsal horn neurons of the spinal cord</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1228</fpage><lpage>1237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11850450</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caterina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Julius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The capsaicin receptor: a heat-activated ion channel in the pain pathway</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>389</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9349801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/39724</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Oortgiesen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capsaicin inhibits activation of voltage-gated sodium currents in capsaicin-sensitive trigeminal ganglion neurons</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11160509</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bardoni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDermott</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ATP P2X receptors mediate fast synaptic transmission in the dorsal horn of the rat spinal cord</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>5297</fpage><lpage>5304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9204914</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Calejesan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ATP P2x receptors and sensory synaptic transmission between primary afferent fibers and spinal dorsal horn neurons in rats</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>3356</fpage><lpage>3360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9862932</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rustioni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of sensory input to the spinal cord by presynaptic ionotropic glutamate receptors</article-title><source>Acta Ital Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacDermott</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Role</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegelbaum</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presynaptic ionotropic receptors and the control of transmitter release</article-title><source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source><year>1999</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10202545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.neuro.22.1.443</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamakura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ataka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Taga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimoji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Propofol enhances GABA(A) receptor-mediated presynaptic inhibition in human spinal cord</article-title><source>Neuroreport</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11930137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001756-200203040-00021</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cattaert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>El Manira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shunting versus inactivation: analysis of presynaptic inhibitory mechanisms in primary afferents of the crayfish</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>6079</fpage><lpage>6089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10407044</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cannabinoid-induced presynaptic inhibition at the primary afferent trigeminal synapse of juvenile rat brainstem slices</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>555</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14673184</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parnas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashkovan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel mechanism for presynaptic inhibition: GABA(A) receptors affect the release machinery</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1240</fpage><lpage>1246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10979998</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cattaert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Libersat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>El Manira</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presynaptic inhibition and antidromic spikes in primary afferents of the crayfish: a computational and experimental analysis</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1007</fpage><lpage>1021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157086</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardoni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelman</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Magherini</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDermott</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional expression of AMPA receptors on central terminals of rat dorsal root ganglion neurons and presynaptic inhibition of glutamate release</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2002</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12123614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(02)00729-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernardini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhuber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeh</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological evidence for functional capsaicin receptor expression and calcitonin gene-related peptide exocytosis in isolated peripheral nerve axons of the mouse</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2004</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15183508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2004.03.017</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanifuji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optical responses recorded after local stimulation in rat neostriatal slice preparations: effects of GABA and glutamate antagonists, and dopamine agonists</article-title><source>Exp Brain Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8566183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00241114</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Randi&#x000e6;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrophysiological properties of rat spinal dorsal horn neurones in vitro: calcium-dependent action potentials</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1983</year><volume>334</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6306228</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ichioka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iijima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ono T, Squire LR, Raichle ME, Perrett DI, Fukuda M</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Real-time optical recording of neuronal activities in the brain</article-title><source>Brain Mechanisms of Perception and Memory</source><year>1993</year><publisher-name>London: Oxford Univ Press</publisher-name><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>648</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fyffe</surname><given-names>REW</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Davidoff RA</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Afferent fibers</article-title><source>Handbook of the Spinal Cord</source><year>1984</year><publisher-name>New York, Dekker</publisher-name><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>136</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wall PD, Melzack R</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The course and termination of primary afferent fibers</article-title><source>Textbook of Pain</source><year>1989</year><publisher-name>Churchill Livingstone, New York</publisher-name><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coggeshall</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><source>Sensory Mechanisms of the Spinal Cord</source><year>1991</year><publisher-name>New York: Plenum</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spinal organization of C-fiber afferents related with nociception or non-nociception</article-title><source>Prog Brain Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9009743</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Perl</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of primary afferent and glutamate excitation of neurons in the mammalian spinal dorsal horn</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1988</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2062</fpage><lpage>2073</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2898513</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessell</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary afferent-evoked synaptic responses and slow potential generation in rat substantia gelatinosa neurons in vitro</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>1989</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2754484</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Randi&#x000e6;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term potentiation and long-term depression of primary afferent neurotransmmission in the rat spinal cord</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1993</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>5228</fpage><lpage>5241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8254370</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandk&#x000fc;hler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of long-term potentiation of C-fiber-evoked potentials in spinal dorsal horn of adult rat: essential role of NK1 and NK2 receptors</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1973</fpage><lpage>1982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9325365</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandk&#x000fc;hler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Randi&#x000e6;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-frequency stimulation of afferent A&#x003b4;-fibers induces long-term depression at primary afferent synapses with substantia gelatinosa neurons in the rat</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>6483</fpage><lpage>6491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9236256</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 