<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8594560</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">5s1004</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>PAH Mutation Analysis Consortium Database: a database for disease-producing and other allelic variation at the human PAH locus.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Byck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prevost</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scriver</surname><given-names>C R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>The DeBelle Laboratory, McGill University-Montreal Children's Hospital Research Institute, Montreal, Quebec, Canada.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><abstract><p>The PAH Mutation Analysis Consortium (81 investigators, 26 countries) is engaged in mutation detection at the human PAH locus. Ascertainment of probands occurs largely through newborn screening for hyperphenylalaninemia. A relational database records allelic variation (disease-producing and polymorphic) at the locus. Information is distributed by Newsletter, diskette (WINPAHDB software stand-alone executable on IBM compatible hardware), and at a 'real' site on the Worldwide Web (http://www.mcgill.ca/pahdb). The database presently records (Sept. 27, 1995) 248 alleles in 798 different associations (with polymorphic haplotype, geographic region and population) along with additional information. The database, as a record of human genetic diversity, at a particular locus, contributes to the study of human evolution and demic expansion; it also has medical relevance.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 