<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8650000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">5e0670</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Examining the contribution of a dA+dT element to the conformation of Escherichia coli integration host factor-DNA complexes.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>L M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gumport</surname><given-names>R I</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>J F</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Microbiology, University of Illinois, Urbana, 61801, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1780</fpage><lpage>1786</lpage><abstract><p>DNA binding proteins that induce structural changes in DNA are common in both prokaryotes and eukaryotes. Integration host factor (IHF) is a multi-functional DNA binding and bending protein of Escherichia coli that can mediate protein-protein and protein-DNA interactions by bending DNA. Previously we have shown that the presence of a dA+dT element 5'-proximal to an IHF consensus sequence can affect the binding of IHF to a particular site. In this study the contribution of various sequence elements to the formation of IHF-DNA complexes was examined. We show that IHF bends DNA more when it binds to a site containing a dA+dT element upstream of its core consensus element than to a site lacking a dA+dT element. We demonstrate that IHF can be specifically crosslinked to DNA with binding sites either containing or lacking this dA+dT element. These results indicate the importance of flanking DNA and a dA+dT element in the binding and bending of a site by IHF.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 