<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8668530</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6c0044</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Target specificity of neuronal RNA-binding protein, Mel-N1: direct binding to the 3' untranslated region of its own mRNA.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, Kobe University, Japan.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2011</fpage><lpage>2016</lpage><abstract><p>We have identified cDNAs encoding Mel-N1, the mouse homologue of a human nervous system-specific RNA-binding protein, Hel-N1. Two major mRNA transcripts of Mel-N1 were detected predominantly in the adult mouse brain by Northern blot analysis. To gain insight into the RNA binding specificity of Mel-N1, we performed iterative in vitro RNA selection. The resulting in vitro selected RNAs were found to contain AU-rich sequences as well as a GAAA motif in the majority of clones. By means of in vitro binding assays we demonstrate that this GAAA sequence appears to significantly affect the Mel-N1 RNA-binding efficiency. Our studies further reveal that Mel-N1 can bind to its own 3' untranslated region (3'UTR) as well as to the c-fos 3'UTR, and is localized predominantly in the cytoplasmic region in cells, suggesting that posttranscriptional autoregulation of Mel-N1 gene expression occurs in vivo.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 