<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8710501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6w0037</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cold shock domain proteins repress transcription from the GM-CSF promoter.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>L S</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Occhiodoro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vadas</surname><given-names>M A</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>M F</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Division of Human Immunology, Hanson Centre for Cancer Research, Institute of Medical and Veterinary Science, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2311</fpage><lpage>2317</lpage><abstract><p>The human granulocyte-macrophage colony stimulating factor (GM-CSF) gene promoter binds a sequence-specific single-strand DNA binding protein termed NF-GMb. We previously demonstrated that the NF-GMb binding sites were required for repression of tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) induction of the proximal GM-CSF promoter sequences in fibroblasts. We now describe the isolation of two different cDNA clones that encode cold shock domain (CSD) proteins with NF-GMb binding characteristics. One is identical to the previously reported CSD protein dbpB and the other is a previously unreported variant of the dbpA CSD factor. This is the first report of CSD factors binding to a cytokine gene. Nuclear NF-GMb and expressed CSD proteins have the same binding specificity for the GM-CSF promoter and other CSD binding sites. We present evidence that CSD factors are components of the nuclear NF-GMb complex. We also demonstrate that overexpression of the CSD proteins leads to complete repression of the proximal GM-CSF promoter containing the NF-GMb/CSD binding sites. Surprisingly, we show that CSD overexpression can also directly repress a region of the promoter which apparently lacks NF-GMb/CSD binding sites. NF-GMb/CSD factors may hence be acting by two different mechanisms. We discuss the potential importance of CSD factors in maintaining strict regulation of the GM-CSF gene.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 