<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8836176</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6w0107</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genes encoding isoforms of transcription elongation factor TFIIS in Xenopus and the use of multiple unusual RNA processing signals.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Plant</surname><given-names>K E</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>G T</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Genetics, University of Nottingham, UK.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>3514</fpage><lpage>3521</lpage><abstract><p>We have identified cDNAs encoding three related forms of transcription elongation factor TFIIS (S-II) in Xenopus laevis ovary. Comparison of Xenopus and mammalian sequences identifies likely diagnostic amino acids that distinguish classes of vertebrate TFIIS. The diversity of TFIIS polypeptides in Xenopus is due partly to the presence of two diverged genes in this tetraploid genome. We isolated genomic clones containing one of the genes, xTFIIS.oA, and, unlike a previously described vertebrate TFIIS gene, found that it contains introns. Alternative splicing at a CAG/CAG motif containing the 3' splice site of intron 4 produces the third form of xTFIIS, which differs from one of the others simply in lacking Ser109. Intron 6 of xTFIIS.oA contains splice and branch site consensus sequences conforming to those of the minor class of AT-AC introns and this was confirmed for the homeologous xTFIIS.oB gene by genomic PCR. Other unusual but functional variants of RNA processing signals were found in xTFIIS genes at the 5' splice site of intron 8 and the polyadenylation hexanucleotides. Utilization of multiple unusual processing signals may make the generation of mature xTFIIS.o mRNAs inefficient and the possible regulatory consequences of this are discussed.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 