<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">8972853</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">6w0157</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fission yeast genes which disrupt mitotic chromosome segregation when overexpressed.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Javerzat</surname><given-names>J P</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cranston</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Allshire</surname><given-names>R C</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>M.R.C. Human Genetics Unit, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, UK. jpaul.javerzat@ibgc.u-bordeaux2.fr</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>1996</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>4676</fpage><lpage>4683</lpage><abstract><p>An interference assay has been devised in Schizosaccharomyces pombe to rapidly identify and clone genes involved in chromosome segregation. Random S.pombe cDNAs were overexpressed from an inducible promoter in a strain carrying an additional, non-essential minichromosome. Overexpression of cDNAs derived from four genes, two known (nda3+and ubc4+, encoding beta-tubulin and a ubiquitin conjugating enzyme, respectively) and two unknown, named mlo2+ and mlo3+ (missegregation &#x00026; lethal when over expressed) caused phenotypes consistent with a failure to segregate chromosomes. Full overexpression of all four cDNAs was lethal. Cells overexpressing nda3+ and ubc4+ cDNAs arrested with condensed unsegregated chromosomes and cells overexpressing mlo2+ displayed an asymmetric distribution of nuclear chromatin. Sublethal levels of overexpression of nda3+, ubc4+ and mlo2+ cDNAs caused elevated rates of minichromosome loss. A third cDNA mlo3+, displayed no increase in the frequency of minichromosome loss at sublethal levels of overexpression but full overexpression caused a complete failure to segregate chromosomes. Our results confirm the assumption that beta-tubulin overexpression is lethal in S.pombe, implicate ubc4+ in the control of metaphase-anaphase transition in fission yeast and finally identify two new genes, mlo2+and mlo3+, likely to play an important role for chromosome transmission fidelity in mitosis.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 