<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9185579</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">gka431</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of the human XIST gene promoter: implications for models of X chromosome inactivation.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hendrich</surname><given-names>B D</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Plenge</surname><given-names>R M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Willard</surname><given-names>H F</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Genetics and Center for Human Genetics, Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine, Cleveland, OH 44106-4955, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>1997</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>2661</fpage><lpage>2671</lpage><abstract><p>The XIST gene in both humans and mice is expressed exclusively from the inactive X chromosome and is required for X chromosome inactivation to occur early in development. In order to understand transcriptional regulation of the XIST gene, we have identified and characterized the human XIST promoter and two repeated DNA elements that modulate promoter activity. As determined by reporter gene constructs, the XIST minimal promoter is constitutively active at high levels in human male and female cell lines and in transgenic mice. We demonstrate that this promoter activity is dependent in vitro upon binding of the common transcription factors SP1, YY1 and TBP. We further identify two cis -acting repeated DNA sequences that influence reporter gene activity. First, DNA fragments containing a set of highly conserved repeats located within the 5'-end of XIST stimulate reporter activity 3-fold in transiently transfected cell lines. Second, a 450 bp alternating purine-pyrimidine repeat located 25 kb upstream of the XIST promoter partially suppresses promoter activity by approximately 70% in transient transfection assays. These results indicate that the XIST promoter is constitutively active and that critical steps in the X inactivation process must involve silencing of XIST on the active X chromosome by factors that interact with and/or recognize sequences located outside the minimal promoter.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 