<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9207021</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">gka453</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The leptin receptor promoter controls expression of a second distinct protein.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bailleul</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akerblom</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Strosberg</surname><given-names>A D</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Institut Cochin de G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique Mol&#x000e9;culaire, Laboratoire d'ImmunoPharmacologie Mol&#x000e9;culaire, CNRS UPR 0415, 22 rue M&#x000e9;chain, 75014 Paris, France. bailleul@icgm.cochin.inserm.fr</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>1997</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2752</fpage><lpage>2758</lpage><abstract><p>The leptin receptor (OB-R) is a single membrane- spanning protein that mediates the weight-regulatory effects of leptin (OB protein). Several mRNA splice variants have been described which either encode OB-R proteins with cytoplasmic domains of different length or the OB-R and B219/OBR variants, which have different 5'-untranslated regions. Here we report evidence for the synthesis of a human mRNA splice variant of the OB-R gene that potentially encodes a novel protein, leptin receptor gene-related protein (OB-RGRP), which displays no sequence similarity to the leptin receptor itself. This OB-RGRP transcript contains the first two OB-R gene 5'-untranslated exons, but then is alternatively spliced to two novel exons which were mapped to a yeast artificial chromosome containing the leptin receptor gene. First identified by analysis of a large human expressed sequence tag database, the OB-RGRP transcript has now also been found in human and mouse tissues by the use of PCR. Preliminary experiments suggest that OB-RGRP and the OB-R variants share similar patterns of expression that are distinct from that of the B219/OBR variant. OB-RGRP is highly homologous to putative open reading frames in both yeast and Caenorhabditis elegans , suggesting a phylogenetically conserved role for this novel protein.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 