<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9611225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">gkb501</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evolutionary conservation of histone macroH2A subtypes and domains.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pehrson</surname><given-names>J R</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fuji</surname><given-names>R N</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>University of Pennsylvania, Department of Animal Biology, School of Veterinary Medicine, Philadelphia, PA 19104-6048, USA. pehrson@vet.upenn.edu</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2837</fpage><lpage>2842</lpage><abstract><p>Histone macroH2A is an unusual core histone that contains a large non-histone region, and a region that resembles a full length H2A. We examined theconservation of this novel structural arrangement by cloning chicken macroH2A cDNAs and comparing them to their rat counterparts. The amino acid sequences of the two known macroH2A subtypes are &#x0003e;95% identical between these species despite evolutionary separation of approximately 300 million years. The H2A region of macroH2A is completely conserved, and thus is even more conserved than conventional H2A in these species. The origin of the non-histone domain was examined by comparing its sequence to proteins found in bacteria and RNA viruses. These comparisons indicate that this domain is derived from a gene that originated prior to the appearance of eukaryotes, and suggest that the non-histone region has retained the basic function of its ancestral gene.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 