<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9592142</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">gkb434</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exonuclease IX of Escherichia coli.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shafritz</surname><given-names>K M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sandigursky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>W A</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Radiology, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1300 Morris Park Avenue, Bronx, NY 10461, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2593</fpage><lpage>2597</lpage><abstract><p>The bacteria Escherichia coli contains several exonucleases acting on both double- and single-stranded DNA and in both a 5'--&#x0003e;3' and 3'--&#x0003e;5' direction. These enzymes are involved in replicative, repair and recombination functions. We have identified a new exonuclease found in E.coli, termed exonuclease IX, that acts preferentially on single-stranded DNA as a 3'--&#x0003e;5' exonuclease and also functions as a 3'-phosphodiesterase on DNA containing 3'-incised apurinic/apyrimidinic (AP) sites to remove the product trans -4-hydroxy-2-pentenal 5-phosphate. The enzyme showed essentially no activity as a deoxyribophosphodiesterase acting on 5'-incised AP sites. The activity was isolated as a glutathione S-transferase fusion protein from a sequence of the E.coli genome that was 60% identical to a 260 bp region of the small fragment of the DNA polymerase I gene. The protein has a molecular weight of 28 kDa and is free of AP endonuclease and phosphatase activities. Exonuclease IX is expressed in E.coli , as demonstrated by reverse transcription-PCR, and it may function in the DNA base excision repair and other pathways.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 