<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9649625</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">gkb561</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Rapid changes of nucleotide excision repair gene expression following UV-irradiation and cisplatin treatment of Dictyostelium discoideum.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S L</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S K</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Division of Biological Sciences, 422 Tucker Hall, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO 65211-7400, USA.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>26</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>3397</fpage><lpage>3403</lpage><abstract><p>Organisms use different mechanisms to detect and repair different types of DNA damage, and different species vary in their sensitivity to DNA damaging agents. The cellular slime mold Dictyostelium discoideum has long been recognized for its unusual resistance to UV and ionizing radiation. We have recently cloned three nucleotide excision repair (NER) genes from Dictyostelium , the rep B, D and E genes (the homologs of the human xeroderma pigmentosum group B, D and E genes, respectively). Each of these genes has a unique pattern of expression during the multicellular development of this organism. We have now examined the response of these genes to DNA damage. The rep B and D DNA helicase genes are rapidly and transiently induced in a dose dependent manner following exposure to both UV-light and the widely used chemotherapeutic agent cisplatin. Interestingly, the rep E mRNA level is repressed by UV but not by cisplatin, implying unique signal transduction pathways for recognizing and repairing different types of damage. Cells from all stages of growth and development display the same pattern of NER gene expression following exposure to UV-light. These results suggest that the response to UV is independent of DNA replication, and that all the factors necessary for rapid transcription of these NER genes are either stable throughout development, or are continuously synthesized. It is significant that the up-regulation of the rep B and D genes in response to UV and chemical damage has not been observed to occur in cells from other species. We suggest that this rapid expression of NER genes is at least in part responsible for the unusual resistance of Dictyostelium to DNA damage.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 