<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.2 20060430//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?origin pubmed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mediators Inflamm</journal-id><journal-title>Mediators of Inflammation</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0962-9351</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">12581497</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0962935021000051520</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">XYMV5LERX2NR6P62</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>H(1)-Receptor activation triggers the endogenous nitric oxide signalling system in the rat submandibular gland.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borda</surname><given-names>Enri</given-names></name><email>enri@farmaco.odon.uba.ar</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stranieri</surname><given-names>Graciela</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sterin-Borda</surname><given-names>Leonor</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Pharmacology Unit, School of Dentistry and Pharmacology Department, School of Medicine, University of Buenos Aires and National Research Council of Argentina (CONICET), Buenos Aires, Argentina.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2002</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><abstract><p>BACKGROUND: Histamine is released from mast cells by immunologic and non-immunologic stimuli during salivary gland inflammation, regulating salivary secretion. The receptor-secretory mechanism has not been studied in detail. AIMS: The studies reported were directed toward elucidating signal transduction/second messenger pathways within the rat submandibular gland associated with 2-thiazolylethylamine (ThEA)-induced H(1)-receptor responses. MATERIALS AND METHODS: To assess the H(1) receptor subtype expression in the rat submandibular gland, a radioligand binding assay was performed. The study also included inositolphosphates and cyclic GMP accumulation, protein kinase C and nitric oxide synthase activities, and amylase release. RESULTS: The histamine H(1) receptor subtype is expressed on the rat submandibular gland with high-affinity binding sites. The ThEA effect was associated with activation of phosphoinositide-specific phospholipase C, translocation of protein kinase C, stimulation of nitric oxide synthase activity and increased production of cyclic GMP. ThEA stimulation of nitric oxide synthase and cyclic GMP was blunted by agents able to interfere with calcium movilization, while a protein kinase C inhibitor was able to stimulate ThEA action. On the other hand, ThEA stimulation evoked amylase release via the H1 receptor but was not followed by the L-arginine/nitric oxide pathway activation. CONCLUSIONS: These results suggest that, apart from the effect of ThEA on amylase release, it also appears to be a vasoactive chemical mediator that triggers vasodilatation, modulating the course of inflammation.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 