<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.2 20060430//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?origin pubmed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mediators Inflamm</journal-id><journal-title>Mediators of Inflammation</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0962-9351</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15223612</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09511920410001713493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">1DVC6EJ3JHXYK7X3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The effects of peritoneal dialysis and hemodialysis on serum tumor necrosis factor-alpha, interleukin-6, interleukin-10 and C-reactive-protein levels.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borazan</surname><given-names>Ali</given-names></name><email>aliborazan@mail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ust&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>Hasan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ustundag</surname><given-names>Yucel</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aydemir</surname><given-names>Selim</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bayraktaroglu</surname><given-names>Taner</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sert</surname><given-names>Mehmet</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>Ahmet</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Zonguldak Karaelmas University, Faculty of Medicine, Zonguldak, Turkey.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><abstract><p>BACKGROUND: Markers of an acute phase reaction, such as C-reactive protein (CRP) or tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) and interleukin (IL)-6, are predictive for cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in normal subjects and in chronic renal failure patients. In this study, we aimed to investigate serum TNF-alpha, IL-6, IL-10 and CRP levels in continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD) and hemodialysis (HD) patients. MATERIALS AND METHODS: Serum levels of TNF-alpha, IL-6, IL-10 and CRP levels were measured in 30 patients who were just diagnosed with end-stage renal failure and treated, with 16 CAPD (nine female, seven male) and 14 HD (eight female, six male) patients, before CAPD or HD treatment and after 3 months from the beginning of CAPD or HD in patients with no clinical signs of infection. The control groups were 20 healthy persons of similar age and sex. Serum levels of TNF-alpha, IL-6, IL-10 and CRP were measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay in stable CAPD and HD patients and in healthy persons. RESULTS: The mean serum levels of TNF-alpha, IL-6, IL-10 and CRP showed no significant differences between the CAPD and HD patients for the beginning values and the third month of treatment. However, serum TNF-alpha, IL-6, IL-10 and CRP levels were higher than the control group in the CAPD and HD patients regarding the beginning values and the third month of treatment (p &#x0003c; 0.001). CONCLUSIONS: CAPD and HD of the renal replacement therapy have no effects on serum CRP and cytokines.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article> 