<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.2 20060430//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">06-PONE-RA-00302R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000211</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subject>Microbiology</subject><subject>Molecular Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Bacterial Toxicity of Potassium Tellurite: Unveiling an Ancient Enigma</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Tellurite Toxicity</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>Jos&#x000e9; M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Calder&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>Iv&#x000e1;n L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>Felipe A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>Derie E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pradenas</surname><given-names>Gonzalo A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>Eugenia L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sandoval</surname><given-names>Juan M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>Miguel E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>El&#x000ed;as</surname><given-names>Alex O.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e1;squez</surname><given-names>Claudio C.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="n101"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Laboratorio de Microbiolog&#x000ed;a Molecular, Facultad de Qu&#x000ed;mica y Biolog&#x000ed;a, Universidad de Santiago de Chile, Santiago, Chile</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Sonenshein</surname><given-names>Abraham</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref rid="edit1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Tufts University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="n101">&#x0002a; To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>cvasquez@usach.cl</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: CV IC JP DF FA. Performed the experiments: IC JP DF FA GP EF JS MC AE. Analyzed the data: CV IC JP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: CV. Wrote the paper: CV.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e211</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date></history><copyright-statement>P&#x000e9;rez et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><abstract><p>Biochemical, genetic, enzymatic and molecular approaches were used to demonstrate, for the first time, that tellurite (TeO<sub>3</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup>) toxicity in <italic>E. coli</italic> involves superoxide formation. This radical is derived, at least in part, from enzymatic TeO<sub>3</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> reduction. This conclusion is supported by the following observations made in K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>-treated <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113: i) induction of the <italic>ibpA</italic> gene encoding for the small heat shock protein IbpA, which has been associated with resistance to superoxide, ii) increase of cytoplasmic reactive oxygen species (ROS) as determined with ROS-specific probe 2&#x02032;7&#x02032;-dichlorodihydrofluorescein diacetate (H<sub>2</sub>DCFDA), iii) increase of carbonyl content in cellular proteins, iv) increase in the generation of thiobarbituric acid-reactive substances (TBARs), v) inactivation of oxidative stress-sensitive &#x0005b;Fe-S&#x0005d; enzymes such as aconitase, vi) increase of superoxide dismutase (SOD) activity, vii) increase of <italic>sodA, sodB</italic> and <italic>soxS</italic> mRNA transcription, and viii) generation of superoxide radical during <italic>in vitro</italic> enzymatic reduction of potassium tellurite.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>To date, it is not known if elements like Ag, As, Cd, Cr, Hg, Pb, Te, or some of their derivatives play a defined biological function and they are mainly associated with toxicity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Silver1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Westenberg1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Oxyanions of tellurium, like tellurite (TeO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;2</sup>), are highly toxic for most microorganisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Taylor1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. However, tellurite-resistant bacteria do exist in nature and they often reduce tellurite to its elemental less toxic form Te&#x000b0; that is accumulated as black deposits inside the cell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Moscoso1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Avazri1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>It has been argued that tellurite toxicity results from its ability to act as a strong oxidizing agent over a variety of cell components <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Summers1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Turner1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. Evidence has accumulated in the last few years suggesting that tellurite could exert its toxicity through intracellular generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS).</p><p>ROS compounds such as hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>), superoxide anion (O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>) and hydroxyl radical (O&#x01e22;) are typical byproducts of the aerobic metabolism that can be formed by exposure of cells to free radical-generating molecules like metals and metalloids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Fridovich1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Recent indirect evidence suggests a relationship between tellurite toxicity and superoxide generation inside the cell. Tantale&#x000e1;n et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Tantalen1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref> showed that resistance of <italic>E. coli</italic> to K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> increases approximately ten-fold when cells are grown under anaerobic conditions, which is presumably due to the cell's inability to produce ROS under oxygen deprivation conditions. The authors also observed that <italic>E. coli</italic> cells lacking superoxide dismutase genes <italic>sodA</italic> and <italic>sodB</italic> exhibited a tellurite hypersensitive phenotype.</p><p>Rojas and V&#x000e1;squez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Rojas1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref> working with <italic>E. coli</italic> wild type and desulfurase mutants found that most of tellurite toxicity takes place in an aerobic environment. Borssetti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Borsetti1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref> reported that <italic>Rhodobacter capsulatus</italic> cells incubated with potassium tellurite exhibit increased superoxide dismutase (SOD) activity and increased resistance to tellurite when exposed to the O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> generator paraquat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Borsetti1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Here we demonstrate that the oxidative damage attributed to potassium tellurite is due at least in part to the intracellular generation of the reactive oxygen species superoxide radical. We report that K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> activates the <italic>ibpA</italic> gene promoter. The <italic>ibpA</italic> gene codes for a small chaperone involved in a heat shock response that has been directly related with O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Kitagawa1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Kitagawa2">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>. In addition, exposure to tellurite generated intracellular reactive oxygen species and increased the cellular content of protein carbonyl groups and thiobarbituric responsive substances (TBARs). Activity of the ROS-sensitive enzyme aconitase decreased upon tellurite exposure, while the activity of superoxide dismutase significantly increased. Moreover, we detected increased levels of <italic>soxS</italic> mRNA after treatment with tellurite. Finally, <italic>soxS, sodA sodB</italic> and <italic>ibpA</italic> mutant strains exhibited a hypersensitive tellurite phenotype when compared to their wild type counterparts.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Tellurite triggers expression of the <italic>ibpA</italic> stress response promoter</title><p>Aiming to investigate potassium tellurite toxicity in <italic>E. coli</italic> we studied induction of <italic>lacZ</italic> fusions to the well-characterized stress response promoters <italic>ibpA, sulA</italic>, p3<italic>RpoH</italic> and <italic>cspA</italic> in cells exposed to tellurite.</p><p>Significant promoter activation by K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> was observed only for the <italic>ibpA</italic> promoter. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g001">Fig. 1</xref> shows that <italic>E. coli</italic> cells treated with tellurite exhibited a 10-fold transcription induction as compared with the untreated controls. This finding is interesting because IbpA protein has been associated with increased resistance to oxidative stress induced by superoxide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Kitagawa1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Kitagawa2">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>. CspA mRNA is highly transcribed in response to cytoplasmic protein stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Goldstein1">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Goldenberg1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. Our results showed a 2-fold increase in the <italic>cspA</italic> promoter transcription in response to tellurite. Promoters <italic>sulA</italic> and p3<italic>RpoH</italic> did not show any detectable activation suggesting that tellurite does not involve DNA damage or periplasmic stress in <italic>E. coli</italic>. The slight increments of &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity seen in controls after 3 h of tellurite treatment may be due to the fact that the cells have reached the stationary growth phase.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Tellurite generates ROS in the cytoplasm of <italic>E. coli</italic></title><p>The fluorescent probe H<sub>2</sub>DCFDA (2&#x02032;, 7&#x02032;- dichlorodihydrofluorescein diacetate) was used to monitor formation of intracellular ROS in tellurite-treated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). Cells treated with different sub lethal concentrations of K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> exhibited significant probe activation. This activation was proportional to tellurite concentration, with the highest ROS levels in cells treated with 0.5&#x02013;1.0 &#x000b5;g/ml K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>. The inset clearly shows that the behaviour of <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 remains the same after 28 min of tellurite exposure. The slight increase in probe activation seen in control experiments is most likely related with the generation of metabolic ROS.</p><p>These results support previous findings that the oxidative effects of tellurite inside the cell are mediated, at least in part, by an increase in intracellular ROS concentration which in turn is most likely a consequence of tellurite reduction in the bacterial cytoplasm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Turner1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Vsquez1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Tellurite increases oxidation of cytoplasmatic proteins</title><p>The generation of carbonyl groups in proteins, produced by the modification of side chains of some amino acids, is a suitable marker to monitor oxidation of the intracellular environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Echave1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. Spectrophotometric determination of derivatized carbonyl groups with 2,4 dinitrophenyl hydrazine (DNPH) showed that crude extracts of K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>-treated <italic>E. coli</italic> exhibited a 4-fold increase in the content of oxidized cytoplasmatic proteins compared with the 2-fold increase observed with peroxide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). Determination of carbonyl groups using specific antibodies against DNPH-derivatized proteins confirmed the oxidative effect of K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> on cytoplasmatic proteins. Although the protein immunoreactive pattern between untreated and treated cells was not significantly different, a few high molecular weight proteins were distinctly observed in tellurite-treated cell extracts (data not shown). Experiments to determine the identity of these proteins are in progress.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Tellurite increases cytoplasmic TBARs</title><p>The level of TBARs has been extensively used to assess the damage of oxidative stress to membrane lipids in many organisms <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-RiceEvans1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>. It has been recently shown that TBARs concentration significantly increases in <italic>E. coli</italic> exposed to hydrogen peroxide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. We also observed an increase of TBARs in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). However, this increase was only approximately 30&#x00025; of that previously observed in <italic>E. coli</italic> KS400 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> treatment also produced an important increase of TBARs in <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113. This increase was about one half of that induced by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, an observation that is consistent with the idea of a secondary toxic effect of tellurite due to superoxide anion generation during tellurite reduction.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Determination of ROS-sensitive and ROS-responsive enzymatic activities</title><p>A number of enzymatic activities that are known to be affected by ROS were determined in cells grown under aerobic conditions with or without K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000211-t001">Table 1</xref>). Aconitase activity, a ROS-sensitive enzyme containing a &#x0005b;Fe-S&#x0005d; cluster <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Echave1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Gardner1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>, decreased approximately 5-fold in K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> treated cells. Malate dehydrogenase, an enzyme reported to be resistant to oxidative stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Echave1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Bergmeyer1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>, showed no differences between tellurite-treated and untreated cells.</p><p>To determine the effect of tellurite on ROS-responsive enzymatic behavior, the activities of catalase (CAT) and superoxide dismutase (SOD) were assayed during the first hour of tellurite treatment. These activities were determined in <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 extracts obtained at 15 min intervals after tellurite exposure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g004">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><p>While catalase activity increased progressively in controls without tellurite, extracts prepared from tellurite-treated <italic>E. coli</italic> cells exhibited a peak of catalase activity during the first 15 min of treatment followed by a 50&#x00025; decrease in activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). This initial rise in activity could be associated with the generation of peroxide produced along the course of superoxide dismutation by the bacterial superoxide dismutase (SOD).</p><p>Crude extracts obtained from tellurite-treated cells showed an important increase in SOD activity as compared to the basal level exhibited by untreated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). The highest rise in SOD activity was observed within the first 15 min and was followed by a lower activity increase. These results show that O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> levels increase as a result of tellurite exposure suggesting that the stress conditions generated by K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> in <italic>E. coli</italic> may be associated, at least in part, with intracellular generation of superoxide.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Tellurite induces <italic>soxS</italic> mRNA synthesis in <italic>E. coli</italic></title><p>To determine whether ROS-response related genes are induced by tellurite exposure, <italic>E. coli sodA, sodB, soxS</italic> and <italic>katG</italic> mRNAs were quantitated by PCR using total RNA of tellurite-treated or untreated cells. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g005">Fig. 5</xref> shows that <italic>E. coli sodA, sodB</italic> and <italic>katG</italic> genes exhibited a rather basal expression in untreated cells. Interestingly, no <italic>soxS</italic> was detected under the same experimental conditions. After 10 min of tellurite exposure a marginal increase was observed for <italic>sodA</italic> and <italic>sodB</italic> mRNAs. Under the same conditions, a strong transcriptional activation was seen for <italic>katG</italic> and particularly for <italic>soxS.</italic> Only the housekeeping <italic>gapA</italic> gene, encoding glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase, showed a transcription decrease in tellurite-exposed cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). These results suggest that tellurite causes induction of genes known to be responsive to increases in ROS levels. Presence of <italic>soxS</italic> mRNA in tellurite-treated cells is also indicative that superoxide radical is being generated.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Absence of <italic>E. coli</italic> superoxide-responsive genes causes tellurite hypersensitivity</title><p>Deletion of genes that are induced upon K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> exposure results in an increase of sensitivity to this toxic salt. Interestingly, <italic>ibpA</italic>-, <italic>sodAsodB</italic>- and <italic>soxS</italic>-deficient strains are the most affected, a result that agrees with observations described above. <italic>katG</italic>, which is highly induced in the presence of tellurite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g005">Fig. 5</xref>) does not seem to be involved in tellurite tolerance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000211-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> superoxide generation</title><p>Results described above suggest that inside the cell K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> behaves as a ROS generator with superoxide radical being the most likely species generated. To test this assumption an <italic>in vitro</italic> tellurite-reduction assay was carried out (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> for details). The rationale for these experiments is based on previous observations indicating that superoxide radical is formed during intracellular selenite reduction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Seko1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Spallholz1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. Because Se and Te share several chemical properties, we reasoned that tellurite reduction may also be associated with superoxide formation.</p><p>As expected, <italic>in vitro</italic> K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3 </sub>reduction resulted in an increase in WST-formazan absorption (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g006">Fig. 6</xref>); this increase was proportional to superoxide concentration (not shown). That superoxide was generated during tellurite reduction was demonstrated by performing the assay in the presence of SOD. This enzyme totally inhibited the increase of OD<sub>438</sub> which did not occur when &#x003b2;-amylase was used. This observation confirms that superoxide radical is formed during tellurite reduction <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Results described in this work represent a step ahead in the understanding of the mechanism underlying potassium tellurite toxicity. We have previously shown that <italic>E. coli</italic> cells overexpressing <italic>G. stearothermophilus</italic> V cysteine metabolism-related genes develop a significant increase (&#x0223c;25 fold) in tellurite resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Tantalen1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Vsquez1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Araya1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>. Expression of <italic>G. stearothermophilus</italic> V <italic>cysK</italic> and <italic>iscS</italic> genes prevented the typical decrease in intracellular RSH content caused by tellurite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Vsquez1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> and unpublished results). Our interpretation was that the cysteine synthase-encoding <italic>cysK</italic> gene indirectly participates in the generation/regeneration of GSH required to maintain the reductive cytoplasmic environment altered by tellurite.</p><p>The IscS desulfurase is probably involved in recovery of tellurite-damaged &#x0005b;Fe-S&#x0005d; clusters that are part of the active site of some ROS-sensitive enzymes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Tantalen1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Rojas1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>. Superoxide radical, the ROS that is most probably involved in the oxidative toxic effect of tellurite, would be generated during tellurite reduction in a process similar to that previously described for selenium oxyanions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Seko1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Spallholz1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. ROS generation by tellurite was suggested by experiments using <italic>sodA sodB</italic> tellurite-hypersensitive <italic>E. coli</italic> mutants and by demonstration that the minimal inhibitory concentration of potassium tellurite increased under anaerobic conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Tantalen1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Rojas1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>. We hypothesized that tellurite reduction by thiols or cellular reductases generates metallic tellurium (Te<sup>o</sup>) and involves ROS generation as well.</p><p>To further study tellurite-mediated toxicity we analyzed activation of stress promoters <italic>ibpA, sulA</italic>, P3<italic>rpoH</italic> and <italic>cspA</italic> in response to K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>. Significant tellurite-mediated transcription activation was only observed for the <italic>ibpA</italic> promoter. The <italic>ibp</italic> operon is a member of the <italic>E. coli</italic> &#x003c3;<sup>32</sup> regulon that encodes the small heat shock proteins IbpA and IbpB. This operon undergoes a high level of transcriptional induction in response to a temperature up shift and participates in events associated with oxidative stress. IbpA over expression generates an important increase in resistance to superoxide anions but does not have any effect in resistance of <italic>E. coli</italic> to hydrogen peroxide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Kitagawa1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Kitagawa2">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>. Results obtained with an <italic>E. coli ibpA</italic> mutant (BW25113 <italic>kan:: ibpA</italic>) showed a &#x0223c;32 fold increase in tellurite sensitivity as compared to the wild type strain suggesting that IbpA plays a role in K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> resistance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000211-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>Our results showed a 2-fold increase in the <italic>cspA</italic> promoter transcription in response to tellurite. CspA mRNA is highly transcribed in response to cytoplasmic protein stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Goldstein1">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Goldenberg1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. This tellurite-mediated activation is in line with the idea that TeO<sub>3</sub><sup>2&#x02212;</sup> has an oxidative effect on cytoplasmatic proteins by replacing Se or reacting with catalytic cysteine residues in key cellular proteins.</p><p>The P3<italic>rpoH</italic> promoter is induced by periplasmic protein misfolding and is transcribed by the E&#x003c3;<sup>E</sup> holoenzyme <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Missiakas1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>. We did not observe tellurite-induced activation of the P3<italic>rpoH</italic> promoter suggesting that tellurite-mediated stress mainly affects cytoplasmic proteins. It is well known that K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> affects proteins and cellular targets by direct interaction and/or its capability to oxidize cellular thiols <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Turner1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Vsquez1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. We hypothesized that ROS produced during Te<sup>o</sup> generation could account for part of tellurite toxicity. Te<sup>&#x0002b;4</sup> reduction takes place in the cytoplasm and it is probably mediated by thiols and/or by cellular reductases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Moscoso1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Avazri1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Chiong1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-OGara1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>. Results of experiments with the P3<italic>rpoH</italic> promoter are consistent with previous findings reporting that a <italic>Rhodobacter capsulatus</italic> mutant in the periplasmic antioxidant gene s<italic>enC</italic> does not exhibit sensitivity to K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>, which has been interpreted as evidence that superoxide radical is not generated in the periplasm of this rod <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Borsetti1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>The <italic>sulA</italic> gene is activated as part of the cellular SOS response induced by compounds that generate DNA damage or affect DNA replication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Schnarr1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>. We showed that the <italic>sulA</italic> gene promoter was not activated in response to tellurite suggesting that the toxic effect of tellurite does not involve DNA damage or activation of the SOS response. These results lead to the speculation that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> or hydroxyl radical, that are the ROS directly involved in DNA damage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Imlay1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>, are not generated during tellurite reduction.</p><p>To discard a Fenton-like reaction as the one described for chromate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Itoh1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref> we performed <italic>in vitro</italic> incubations of plasmid DNA with K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> or with K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> in the presence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. No DNA damage was evidenced as judged by the lack of shift mobility on agarose gels. A similar result was obtained under tellurite reduction conditions confirming that tellurite toxicity does not seem to involve DNA damage (data not shown).</p><p>To further assess that the cellular oxidative stress generated by tellurite lies on the intracellular generation of oxygen reactive species a direct measure of cytoplasmic ROS using the intracellular, specific, probe H<sub>2</sub>DCFDA in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells treated with different sub lethal K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> concentrations was made. Tellurite treatment increased cytoplasmic ROS in a fashion that was proportional to K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> concentration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). These results suggested that in <italic>E. coli</italic> the tellurite-mediated stress can be associated, at least in part, with an increase in the cytoplasmic ROS concentration.</p><p>Protein carbonylation occurs in a number of physiological and pathological processes and it has been suggested that protein carbonylation can be used to determine the ratio between oxidative stress damage and the power of protective systems to avoid it <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Refsgaard1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>. Tellurite generates an important increase of protein carbonylation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>) confirming that part of intracellular toxicity involves protein damage associated to ROS generation. Oxidized proteins from cellular membranes did not show significant differences between treated and untreated cells (data not shown) suggesting that ROS generated by tellurite reduction can be associated with cytoplasmic and membrane proteins and not preferentially with membrane reductases as suggested previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Avazri1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>. Interestingly, tellurite-treated cells exhibited a higher protein carbonylation than peroxide-treated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>). These results may be related to a direct effect of tellurite on the intracellular GSH pool, which then could alter the cell's non-enzymatic antioxidant response. This would hamper the cellular defense against tellurite-induced protein oxidation through the generation of ROS or reactive aldehydes. Carbonyl generation has been associated with aldehyde-mediated protein oxidation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Refsgaard1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>. Aldehydes are generated during lipid peroxidation, a poorly understood process in prokaryotes that may involve interactions with ROS and biological membranes.</p><p>The increase in TBARs content has been widely used to assess oxidative stress damage to lipids in many microorganisms including <italic>E. coli</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-RiceEvans1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Refsgaard1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g003">Fig. 3B</xref> shows that K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>-treated <italic>E. coli</italic> cells exhibit an increase in lipid peroxidation products (determined as TBARs) suggesting that these tellurite-generated compounds are probably a consequence of ROS generation during the reduction of the tellurium oxyanion. TBARs levels were lower in tellurite-treated cells as compared to cells exposed to hydrogen peroxide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g003">Fig. 3A and 3B</xref>). This observation may be related to the multifactor toxic effect of K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> that would affect different cellular processes through the generation of secondary toxic molecules such as O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>, aldehydes and peroxides. Preliminary results from our laboratory indicate that a putative <italic>E. coli</italic> aldehyde reductase can be associated with a protection against tellurite-generated lipid peroxidation products (unpublished results).</p><p>An alternative approach to monitor the generation of ROS upon tellurite exposure is to estimate induction of some specific ROS-sensitive or ROS-responsive enzymatic activities. The activity of aconitase, a superoxide sensitive enzyme, was evaluated in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells treated with potassium tellurite. Aconitases possess &#x0005b;4Fe-4S&#x0005d; clusters highly sensitive to superoxide and represent suitable markers to estimate ROS sensitivity. Cells exposed to tellurite exhibited an important decrease in aconitase activity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000211-t002">Table 2</xref>). Fumarase A, another ROS-sensitive enzyme, also showed a decreased activity under tellurite stress conditions (unpublished observations). These results confirm that tellurite triggers an enzymatic ROS phenotype, presumably via superoxide generation. The activity level of the ROS-resistant metabolic enzyme malate dehydrogenase was determined as control. No differences in malate dehydrogenase activity of <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 cells treated and untreated with tellurite was detected (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000211-t001">Table 1</xref>). These results agree with previous observations indicating that tellurite also causes a rapid reduction of ATP levels that does not involve a decrease in the glycolytic pathway or depletion of glucose in <italic>E. coli</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-LohmeierVogel1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>. This effect is most likely due to a shift to anaerobic metabolism similar to that described for other toxic metals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Wang1">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Activation of oxidative stress enzymatic responsive systems estimated by measuring catalase (CAT) and superoxide dismutase (SOD) activities upon K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> exposure was also analyzed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g004">Fig. 4A and 4B</xref>, respectively). Catalase HPI, encoded by the <italic>katG</italic> gene, is highly induced by an increase in peroxide concentration. Unexpectedly, an increase in CAT activity was observed during the first 10 min of tellurite exposure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). This result may be a consequence of the hydrogen peroxide produced by superoxide dismutation because an increase in CAT activity was associated with the highest increase of SOD activity (15 min) along the K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). The fact that CAT activity does not increase at later times suggests that hydrogen peroxide is not the ROS generated in <italic>E. coli</italic> tellurite-stressed cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). <italic>In situ</italic> catalase activity determinations on native gels showed no correlation between tellurite concentration and catalase activity over 30 min incubation (data not shown). These results also favor the idea that tellurite does not produce peroxide inside <italic>E. coli</italic> as does the hydrogen peroxide-hypersensitive <italic>katG</italic> strain which showed a negligible increase in sensitivity to K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000211-t002">Table 2</xref>). <italic>E. coli</italic> cells over expressing a <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> catalase gene showed a slight increase in tellurite resistance suggesting that the role of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> in tellurite resistance, if any, is not an important feature of K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> toxicity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Caldern1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>It has been shown that SOD activity slightly increases when wt <italic>E. coli</italic> cells are about to enter the second half of the logarithmic growth phase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Gardner2">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>. We observed similar results in <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 cells that were not treated with tellurite. SOD activity was consistently induced throughout the course of the experiment confirming that superoxide dismutases play a role in the cellular response of <italic>E. coli</italic> to potassium tellurite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>).</p><p>The slight increment of <italic>sodA</italic> and <italic>sodB</italic> mRNA synthesis observed after a brief exposure to K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> also suggest that superoxide is produced in response to tellurite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). Induction of <italic>katG</italic> during early stages of tellurite treatment reflects an increase of peroxide concentration that is probably generated by superoxide dismutation as suggested above. High levels of <italic>soxS</italic> mRNA were also detected under tellurite exposure confirming that tellurite-generated O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> activates the most specific and important superoxide response system in <italic>E. coli</italic>.</p><p>An <italic>E. coli soxS</italic> strain (BW25113 <italic>kan::soxS</italic>) showed a tellurite-sensitive phenotype (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0000211-t002">Table 2</xref>), an observation which is consistent with a role of O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>-protection systems in response to tellurite exposure. The lower sensitivity to tellurite observed by this mutant when compared with the <italic>ibpA</italic> and <italic>sodAsodB</italic> strains is presumably due to the fact that the several genes governed by the <italic>soxRS</italic> regulon are also regulated by other global networks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Demple1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>An <italic>in vitro</italic> tellurite reduction assay was used to demonstrate that reduction of Te<sup>&#x0002b;4</sup> to Te<sup>0</sup> indeed generates O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>. Production of O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> was determined by the use of WST-1, a molecule known to be highly specific and sensitive to reduction by superoxide radicals. Enzymatic reduction of tellurite <italic>in vitro</italic> produced a significant increase in light absorption at 438 nm that is indicative of O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> generation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). The superoxide concentration was proportional to tellurite concentration confirming that K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> reduction involves O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> generation (data not shown). The <italic>in vitro</italic> reduction assay performed in the presence of SOD confirmed that superoxide is one of the products of tellurite reduction.</p><p>Altogether, our results strongly indicate that the dramatic toxic effect of potassium tellurite in <italic>E. coli</italic> can be associated with the chemical activity of the tellurium oxyanion at various levels of bacterial metabolic pathways including, among others, inactivation of &#x0005b;Fe-S&#x0005d; center-containing dehydratases, cytoplasmic thiol oxidation, enzyme and protein carbonylation and membrane peroxidation.</p><p>Before the submission of this manuscript Tremaroli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Tremaroli1">&#x0005b;37&#x0005d;</xref> inferred that superoxide radicals are generated as a result of the increased superoxide dismutase activity of <italic>Pseudomonas pseudoalcaligenes</italic> cells in response to tellurite exposure.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p><italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Datsenko1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref> was the parental strain used in all experiments. <italic>E. coli</italic> mutants deficient in the <italic>katG, ibpA</italic> and <italic>soxS</italic> genes were provided by the NARA Institute of Science and Technology, Japan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Baba1">&#x0005b;39&#x0005d;</xref>. Cells were routinely grown in LB medium <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Sambrook1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref> at 37&#x000b0;C with shaking. Antibiotics were added as required. Kan<sup>R</sup> insertions into <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 chromosomal ROS resistance genes were constructed by the method of Datsenko and Wanner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Datsenko1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Enzyme activity assays</title><p>Cells were disrupted by sonication on ice-cooled water and extracts cleared by centrifugation. Aliquots of cell-free extracts were assayed for aconitase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Gardner1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>, malate dehydrogenase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Bergmeyer1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>, catalase and superoxide dismutase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Chen1">&#x0005b;41&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Jakubowski1">&#x0005b;42&#x0005d;</xref>. Protein concentration was determined by the Bradford method.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Stress-promoter activation assays</title><p>Promoter regions of the <italic>ibpA, cspA, rpoH</italic> and <italic>sulA</italic> genes have been routinely used as molecular tools to detect and characterize antibacterial agents that induce stress response in <italic>E. coli</italic> due to their strength and specificity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Bianchi1">&#x0005b;43&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Shapiro1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p><italic>ibpA</italic> gene, encoding for the small bacterial heat shock protein IbpA, undergoes high level of induction following a temperature up shift and has been associated with oxidative stress response in <italic>E. coli</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Kitagawa1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Kitagawa2">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>. CspA is the major <italic>E. coli</italic> cold shock protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Goldstein1">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>. <italic>E. coli</italic> cells dedicate more than 10&#x00025; of their synthetic capability to produce CspA shortly after transfer to 10&#x000b0;C <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Goldenberg1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>While the P3<italic>rpoH</italic> promoter is activated by unfolded proteins generated during periplasmic stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Missiakas1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>, the <italic>sulA</italic> gene is activated during the course of the SOS response by compounds that damage DNA or affect its replication <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Schnarr1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p><italic>E. coli</italic> strains used in the stress-promoter activation assays are ADA100 &#x0005b;AB734 &#x003bb;&#x003a6;(<italic>ibp</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic>)&#x0005d;, ADA310 &#x0005b;AB734&#x003bb;&#x003a6; (<italic>cspA</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic>)&#x0005d;, ADA410 &#x0005b;AB734 &#x003bb;&#x003a6;(p3<italic>RpoH</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic>)&#x0005d; and ADA510 &#x0005b;AB734 &#x003bb;&#x003a6;(<italic>sulA</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic>)&#x0005d; and were kindly provided by Dr. Francois Baneyx <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Bianchi1">&#x0005b;43&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Shapiro1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Flasks (500 ml) containing 100 ml of LB medium were inoculated with 2 ml of overnight cultures and grown at 37&#x000b0;C under aerobic conditions until the optical density at 600 nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) was 0.4. Aliquots of 25 ml were then transferred to preheated 125 ml flasks and the cultures incubated for 3 h in the presence of 0.5 &#x000b5;g/ml K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>. Control cultures contained an equal volume of H<sub>2</sub>O. The fold induction was calculated by comparing &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity after 3 h of tellurite treatment divided by the activity at time 0, as described by the group of Baneyx <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Bianchi1">&#x0005b;43&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Shapiro1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>. All experiments were carried out in triplicate or higher.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>&#x003b2;-galactosidase assay</title><p>Following the incubation with tellurite, samples (2 ml) were withdrawn at defined time intervals and OD<sub>600</sub> determined. Cells were sedimented by centrifugation at 6,500&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 8 min, suspended in an equal volume of 50 mM monobasic potassium phosphate (pH 6.5), and disrupted by sonication. After centrifugation at 10,000&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 10 min to discard cell debris, aliquots of the cleared lysate were assayed for <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-galactosidase activity (triplicate) using the chromogenic substrate <italic>O</italic>-nitrophenyl-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-D-galactopyranoside <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Miller1">&#x0005b;45&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Tellurite sensitivity assay</title><p>Cells were grown overnight and diluted one hundred-fold with fresh LB medium. Ten &#x000b5;l of these dilutions were transferred into tubes containing 1 ml of LB added with specific amounts of antibiotics and potassium tellurite. Cells were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 48 h with shaking and the OD<sub>600</sub> monitored to determine the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC).</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Determination of intracellular oxidation levels</title><p>The oxidant-sensitive probe H<sub>2</sub>DCFDA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Echave1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref> was used to determine the intracellular levels of ROS in cells treated with 3 different tellurite concentrations (0.2, 0.5, and 1 &#x000b5;g/ml). Cells were grown aerobically in tellurite-amended LB medium until OD<sub>600</sub> 0.5, washed with 10 mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 7.0), and incubated for 30 min in the same buffer containing 10 &#x000b5;M H<sub>2</sub>DCFDA dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide. After washing, the cells were suspended in the same buffer and disrupted by sonication. Cell extracts (100 &#x000b5;l) were mixed with 1 ml of phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) and the fluorescence intensity was measured at 2 min intervals over a 30 min period using an Applied Biosystems Citofluor 4000 Fluorescence multi-well plate reader (excitation, 490 nm; emission, 519 nm). The inset of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0000211-g002">Fig. 2</xref> represents the emission obtained for all the treatments at a fixed time (28 min). Emission values were normalized by protein concentration.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Determination of protein carbonyl content</title><p>The carbonyl content in cellular proteins was determined as described by Semchyshyn et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. Crude extracts were prepared from <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 cells treated or untreated with K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> (0.5 &#x000b5;g/ml) or H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (100 &#x000b5;M) for 30 min. Extracts were treated with streptomycin sulfate (2&#x00025;) and incubated on ice for 15 min. Precipitated nucleic acids were discarded by centrifugation at 14,000&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 5 min. After adding four volumes of 10 mM dinitrophenylhydrazine (DNPH, prepared in 2 M HCl) to 100 &#x000b5;l of the nucleic acid-free supernatant, the mixture was incubated for 1 h at room temperature with vortexing every 10&#x02013;15 min. Proteins were precipitated by adding 500 &#x000b5;l of 20&#x00025; trichloroacetic acid (TCA) and then sedimented by centrifugation at 14,000&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 5 min. The pellet was washed at least three times with an ethanol:ethylacetate mixture (1&#x02236;1) to remove any unreacted DNPH and redissolved at 37&#x000b0;C with 450 &#x000b5;l guanidine HCl/dithiothreitol. Carbonyl content was determined spectrophotometrically at 370 nm using a molar absorption coefficient of 22,000 M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Determination of thiobarbituric acid-reactive substances (TBARs)</title><p>TBARs in cell extracts were determined as described by Rice-Evans et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-RiceEvans1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>. Briefly, 1-ml of cell suspensions were precipitated with 1.0 ml of 20&#x00025; TCA (w/v) and centrifuged at 10,000&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 5 min. Supernatants were mixed with 2.0 ml of a saturated solution containing thiobarbituric acid in 0.1 M HCl and 10 mM butylated hydroxytoluene. Samples were then heated for 60 min in a water bath kept at 100&#x000b0;C. Aliquots of 1.5 ml were then removed, chilled, mixed with 1.5 ml of butanol and centrifuged at 4,000&#x000d7; g for 10 min. The organic fraction was recovered and the OD<sub>535</sub> was measured spectrophotometrically. TBARs content was determined using a molar extinction coefficient of 156 mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-RiceEvans1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>RNA purification and RT-PCR experiments</title><p><italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 cells were inoculated in two 200 ml flasks at 1&#x02236;100 dilution and incubated at 200 rpm at 37&#x000b0;C until the OD<sub>600</sub> was 0.6. At that moment one culture was amended with K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> solution (0.5 &#x000b5;g/ml final concentration) and incubated for 10 min, sedimented at 13,000&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> by 3 min and total RNA was isolated using the QIAGEN RNeasy purification kit (Promega) following the vendor recommendations. The ratio OD<sub>260/280</sub> was determined for the purified RNA using an Agilent 8453 UV-visible spectrophotometer. Independent RT-PCR experiments were performed using 2 &#x000b5;g of total RNA as template. The set of primers used to amplify fragments of approximately 300 bp of <italic>E. coli katG, sodA, sodB</italic> and <italic>soxS</italic> genes were skatG3 5&#x02032;-GCTCGCCCAACCTAAACCTTGTTC-3&#x02032;, skatG5 5&#x02032;-GAAAAAGCCTGGCTGACTCACCGT-3&#x02032;, ssodA3 5&#x02032;-TCGATAGCCGCTTTCAGGTCACCC-3&#x02032;, ssodA5 5&#x02032;-CCTGCCATCCCTGCCGTATGCTTA-3&#x02032;, ssodB3 5&#x02032;-TAAACTGCGCTTTGAAATCGGCAA-3&#x02032;, ssodB5 5&#x02032;-AAGATGCTCTGGCACCGCACATTT-3&#x02032;, ssoxS3 5&#x02032;-CGAGCATATTGACCAGCCGCTTAA-3&#x02032;, and ssoxS5 5&#x02032;-TTACAGGCGGTGGCGATAATCGCT-3&#x02032;.</p><p>RT-PCR conditions included a 30 min incubation at 25&#x000b0;C with RNA-free DNAse I (Promega) followed by a DNAse-inactivating step of 10 min at 65&#x000b0;C. Synthesis of cDNA was allowed to proceed for 2 h at 42&#x000b0;C using a commercial enzyme and RT-PCR kit (QIAGEN). PCR conditions included an initial denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min followed by 20 amplification cycles (95&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 45&#x000b0;C for 30 s and 72&#x000b0;C for 1 min). A final incubation of 72&#x000b0;C for 10 min was added to ensure fully extension of the amplified fragments. PCR products were fractionated on agarose gels (1.5&#x00025;) and the DNA content was estimated using the Gel Pro 4.0 program (Media Cybernetics).</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Determination of <italic>in vitro</italic> K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> reduction reaction products</title><p>An <italic>in vitro</italic> K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> enzymatic reduction assay was developed to demonstrate the generation of superoxide along the course of tellurite reduction. Superoxide radical specifically reduces 2-(4-Iodophenyl)-3-(4-nitrophenyl)-5-(2,4-disulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium (WST-1, Cell Technology Lab) to the soluble form WST-formazan that can be easily detected at 438 nm. We have previously established that tellurite can be reduced by different enzymes including catalase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Moscoso1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Chiong1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Caldern1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>. Reduction mix contained 200 &#x000b5;g/ml of purified bovine liver catalase, 1 mM NADPH, 1 mM potassium tellurite and 50 mM Tris-HCl buffer pH 7.0. Generation of WST-formazan was monitored at 438 nm. Assays in which catalase was replaced by either superoxide dismutase or &#x003b2;-amilase were included as negative controls.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0000211-Silver1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Genes for all metals- a bacterial view of the periodic table.</article-title><source>J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9523453</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Westenberg1"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerinot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Regulation of bacterial gene expression by metals.</article-title><source>Adv Genet</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9348656</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Taylor1"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Bacterial tellurite resistance.</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10203839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Moscoso1"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moscoso</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Loyola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e1;squez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichuantes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Biochemical characterization of tellurite-reducing activities of <italic>Bacillus stearothermophilus</italic> V.</article-title><source>Res Microbiol</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9766238</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Avazri1"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avaz&#x000e8;ri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pommier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Tellurite reductase activity of nitrate reductase is responsible for the basal resistance of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to tellurite.</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>143</volume><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>1189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9141681</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Summers1"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacoby</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1977</year><article-title>Plasmid-determined resistance to tellurium compounds.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>129</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">401494</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Turner1"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Tellurite-mediated thiol oxidation in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Microbiology</source><volume>145</volume><fpage>2549</fpage><lpage>2557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10517608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Fridovich1"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fridovich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Superoxide radical and superoxide dismutases.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7574505</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Tantalen1"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tantale&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Araya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>The <italic>Geobacillus stearothermophilus</italic> V <italic>iscS</italic> gene, encoding cysteine desulfurase, confers resistance to potassium tellurite in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>5831</fpage><lpage>5837</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Rojas1"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasquez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Sensitivity to potassium tellurite of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> cells deficient in CSD, CsdB and IscS cysteine desulfurases.</article-title><source>Res Microbiol</source><volume>156</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15862443</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Borsetti1"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borsetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremaroli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Michelacci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Borghese</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Winterstein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Tellurite effects on <italic>Rhodobacter capsulatus</italic> cell viability and superoxide dismutase activity under oxidative stress conditions.</article-title><source>Res Microbiol</source><volume>156</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15946826</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Kitagawa1"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyakawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchido</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> small heat shock proteins, IbpA and IbpB, protect enzymes from inactivation by heat and oxidants.</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><volume>269</volume><fpage>2907</fpage><lpage>2917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12071954</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Kitagawa2"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchido</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Small heat shock proteins, IbpA and IbpB, are involved in resistances to heat and superoxide stresses in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><volume>184</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10713416</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Goldstein1"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Major cold shock protein of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2404279</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Goldenberg1"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Azar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppenheim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Differential mRNA stability of the <italic>cspA</italic> gene in the cold-shock response of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8825770</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Vsquez1"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e1;squez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Loyola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Araya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichuantes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>The product of the <italic>cysK</italic> gene of <italic>Bacillus stearothermophilus</italic> V mediates potassium tellurite resistance in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11685509</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Echave1"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Echave</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamarit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabiscol</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Novel antioxidant role of alcohol dehydrogenase E from <italic>Escherichia coli.</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>30193</fpage><lpage>30198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12783863</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Semchyshyn1"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semchyshyn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagnyukova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lushchak</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Hydrogen peroxide increases the activities of soxRS regulon enzymes and the levels of oxidized proteins and lipids in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Cell Biol Intern</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>898</fpage><lpage>902</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-RiceEvans1"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice-Evans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Diplock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Symins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Buerdon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>van Kniooenberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Methods for TBA-reaction.</article-title><source>Editors, Laboratory techniques in Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><comment>In:</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Gardner1"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridovich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Superoxide sensitivity of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> aconitase.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>266</volume><fpage>19328</fpage><lpage>19333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1655783</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Bergmeyer1"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergmeyer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><year>1974</year><article-title>Meth Enzymatic Anal</article-title><volume>1</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>486</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Seko1"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitahara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Imura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>. Wendel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>198</year><article-title>Active oxygen generation by the reaction of selenite with reduced glutathione <italic>in vitro</italic>.</article-title><source>Selenium in biology and medicine.</source><publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Spallholz1"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spallholz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>On the nature of selenium toxicity and carcinostatic activity.</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7959166</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Araya1"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Swearingen</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Plishker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chasteen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title><italic>Geobacillus stearothermophilus</italic> V <italic>ubiE</italic> gene product is involved in the evolution of dimethyl telluride in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 cultures amended with potassium tellurate but not with potassium tellurite.</article-title><source>J Biol Inorg Chem</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15164269</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Missiakas1"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Missiakas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>The extracytoplasmatic function sigma factors; role and regulation.</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9680198</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Chiong1"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e1;squez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year><article-title>Purification and biochemical characterization of tellurite-reducing activities from <italic>Thermus thermophilus</italic> HB8.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>170</volume><fpage>3269</fpage><lpage>3273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3384810</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-OGara1"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Gara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomelsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Identification and molecular genetic analysis of multiple loci contributing to high-level tellurite resistance in <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic> 2.4.1.</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>4713</fpage><lpage>4720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9406390</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Schnarr1"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnarr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oertel-Buchheit</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazmaier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger-Schnarr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>DNA binding properties of the LexA repressor.</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1911942</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Imlay1"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Pathways of oxidative damage.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527285</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Itoh1"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Horitsu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Mechanism of chromium(VI) toxicity in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: is hydrogen peroxide essential in Cr(VI) toxicity?</article-title><source>J Biochem (Tokyo).</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>780</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7592539</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Refsgaard1"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Refsgaard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadtman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Modifications of proteins by polyunsaturated fatty acid peroxidation products.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10639127</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-LohmeierVogel1"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohmeier-Vogel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>In vivo <sup>31</sup>P nuclear magnetic resonance investigation of tellurite toxicity in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>70</volume><fpage>7342</fpage><lpage>7347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15574934</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Wang1"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Global gene expression responses to cadmium toxicity in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><volume>187</volume><fpage>3259</fpage><lpage>3266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15838054</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Caldern1"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calder&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Araya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Catalases are NAD(P)H-dependent tellurite reductases.</article-title><source>PloS ONE.</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>e70</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183702</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Gardner2"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridovich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Inactivation-reactivation of aconitase in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. A sensitive measure of superoxide radical.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>267</volume><fpage>8757</fpage><lpage>8763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1315737</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Demple1"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demple</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Regulation of bacterial oxidative stress genes.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genet</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1667460</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Tremaroli1"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tremaroli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zannoni</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Evidence for a tellurite-dependent generation of reactive oxygen species and absence of a tellurite-mediated adaptive response to oxidative stress in cells of <italic>Pseudomonas pseudoalcaligenes</italic> KF707.</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><comment> DOI 10.1007/s00203-006-0179-4</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Datsenko1"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Datsenko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>One-step inactivation of chromosomal genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 using PCR products.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>97</volume><fpage>6640</fpage><lpage>6645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10829079</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Baba1"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Okumura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Construction of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 in-frame, single-gene knockout mutants: the Keio collection.</article-title><source>Molecular Systems Biology</source><comment> doi:10.1038/msb4100050</comment></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Sambrook1"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritsch</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><source>Molecular Cloning: a laboratory manual. 2nd Ed.</source><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Chen1"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Patten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schellhorn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Controlled expression of an <italic>rpoS</italic> antisense RNA can inhibit RpoS function in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>3485</fpage><lpage>3493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576106</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Jakubowski1"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jakubowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilinski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartosz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Oxidative stress during aging of stationary cultures of the yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>.</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10754260</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Bianchi1"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baneyx</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Stress responses as a tool to detect and characterize the mode of action of antibacterial agents.</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>5023</fpage><lpage>5027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10543818</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Shapiro1"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Baneyx</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Stress-based identification and classification of antibacterial agents: second-generation <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> reporter strains and optimization of detection.</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>2490</fpage><lpage>2497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12121923</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0000211-Miller1"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year><source>Experiments in molecular genetics.</source><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name></citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig id="pone-0000211-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000211.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Tellurite-induction of &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity in <italic>E. coli</italic> reporter strains.</title><p><italic>E. coli</italic> reporter strains ADA100 &#x0005b;AB734 &#x003bb;&#x003a6;(<italic>ibp</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic>)&#x0005d;, ADA310 &#x0005b;AB734&#x003bb;&#x003a6; (<italic>cspA</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic>)&#x0005d;, ADA410 &#x0005b;AB734 &#x003bb;&#x003a6;(p3<italic>RpoH</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic>)&#x0005d; and ADA510 &#x0005b;AB734 &#x003bb;&#x003a6;(<italic>sulA</italic>::<italic>lacZ</italic>)&#x0005d; containing the stress-responsive promoters <italic>ibpA, cspA, p3RpoH</italic> and <italic>sulA</italic> fused to the <italic>lacZ</italic> gene respectively, were used to study transcription induction in cells treated or untreated with K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> (0.5 &#x000b5;g/ml). &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity was evaluated at time 0 and after 3 h with or without tellurite treatment. The fold induction was calculated dividing the value obtained at 3 h by the value at time 0. Results are the average of at least 4 determinations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0000211.g001"/></fig><fig id="pone-0000211-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000211.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Generation of intracellular ROS by K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>.</title><p>Cytoplasmic ROS content was evaluated measuring the H<sub>2</sub>DCFDA probe activation in <italic>E. coli</italic> cells treated with different sub lethal concentrations of tellurite &#x0005b;0 (&#x025aa;), 0.2 (&#x02022;), 0.5 (&#x025b4;) and 1 &#x000b5;g/ml (&#x025c2;)&#x0005d;. Fluorescence was measured 10 times at 2 min intervals. The inset shows probe activation at 28 min by tellurite at the indicated concentrations. See <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref> for details.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0000211.g002"/></fig><fig id="pone-0000211-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000211.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Tellurite increases the oxidation of cytoplasmic proteins and membrane lipids in <italic>E. coli.</italic></title><p>Effects of K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> (0.5 &#x000b5;g/ml) and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (100 &#x000b5;M) on protein carbonyl (A) and TBARs content (B) of <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 cells exposed to these compounds for 30 min. A, protein oxidation was determined by a chemical protein carbonyl assay by derivatizing total cellular proteins with DNPH and reading specific carbonyls absorbance at 370 nm. B, membrane peroxidation products were determined as thiobarbituric acid-reactive substances present in crude extracts of <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 by the method described by Rice-Evans et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-RiceEvans1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0000211.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone-0000211-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000211.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Effect of potassium tellurite on <italic>E. coli</italic> catalase and superoxide dismutase.</title><p>A, activity of catalases in crude protein extracts of <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 treated (&#x02022;) or untreated (&#x025aa;) with 0.5 &#x000b5;g/ml of K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>. Cells were collected at 15 min intervals and catalase activity (&#x000b5;mol hydrogen peroxide/min/mg protein) was determined. B, activity of superoxide dismutases in crude protein extracts of <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 treated (&#x02022;) and untreated (&#x025aa;) with 0.5 &#x000b5;g/ml K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>. Cells were harvested and SOD activity (U/mg protein) was determined.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0000211.g004"/></fig><fig id="pone-0000211-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000211.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Tellurite induces <italic>katG</italic> and <italic>soxS</italic> mRNA synthesis in <italic>E. coli.</italic></title><p>DNA fragments (300 bp) from <italic>E. coli sodA, sodB, katG, soxS</italic> and <italic>gapA</italic> genes were amplified by RT-PCR and fractionated by electrophoresis on agarose gels (1.5&#x00025;). Total RNA from cells grown with (K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub>) or without (control) 0.5 &#x000b5;g/ml potassium tellurite was used as template for the RT-PCR. The estimated DNA (ng) content determined for each band is shown (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Material and Methods</xref> for details).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0000211.g005"/></fig><fig id="pone-0000211-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000211.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><italic>In vitro</italic> tellurite reduction generates superoxide in <italic>E. coli.</italic></title><p>Superoxide generation was evaluated using an <italic>in vitro</italic> tellurite reduction assay previously developed in our laboratory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0000211-Caldern1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>. The system makes use of the O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> specific reactive compound WST-1. WST-1 reduction was determined in the presence of catalase and NADPH (Cat); catalase, tellurite and NADPH (Cat/Te); catalase, tellurite, NADPH and purified superoxide dismutase (Cat/Te/SOD); catalase, tellurite, NADPH and &#x003b2;-amylase (Cat/Te/amylase).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0000211.g006"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0000211-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000211.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Effect of potassium tellurite on <italic>E. coli</italic> malate dehydrogenase and aconitase<italic>.</italic></title></caption><graphic id="pone-0000211-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0000211.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0000211-t001-1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">STRAIN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC (&#x000b5;g/ml)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wt</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ibpA</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>katG</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sodAsodB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>soxS</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Enzymatic activities were determined in crude extracts obtained from cells treated or untreated with 0.5 &#x000b5;g/ml K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub> for 30 min as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Methods</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0000211-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000211.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Minimal inhibitory concentrations (MIC) of K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3 </sub>for <italic>E. coli</italic> BW25113 strains deficient in ROS-responsive genes.</title></caption><graphic id="pone-0000211-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0000211.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0000211-t002-2"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malate dehydrogenase &#x000b5;g/min/mg prot</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aconitase &#x000b5;mol/min/mg prot</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#x000b1;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.380&#x000b1;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K<sub>2</sub>TeO<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59&#x000b1;0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085&#x000b1;0.02</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>Numbers are the mean of 4 independent determinations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>JMP, DEF and JMS received fellowships from MECESUP and ILC, FAA, MEC received fellowships from CONICYT. This work was supported in part by FONDECYT grant 1060022 to CCV and by Dicyt, Universidad de Santiago de Chile.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article> 