<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Nucleic Acids Research</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl1148</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17264115</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>RNA</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CRD-BP shields c-<italic>myc</italic> and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA from endonucleolytic attack by a mammalian endoribonuclease</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sparanese</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Chow H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Chemistry Program, University of Northern British Columbia, 3333 University Way, Prince George, BC V2N 4Z9, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+250&#x02009;960&#x02009;5413</phone>; Fax: <fax>+250&#x02009;960&#x02009;5170</fax>; Email: <email>leec@unbc.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><!--For NAR: both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1209</fpage><lpage>1221</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date></history><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license><abstract><p>The c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA coding region determinant-binding protein (CRD-BP) has high affinity for the coding region determinant (CRD) of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA. Such affinity is believed to protect c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD from endonucleolytic attack. We have recently purified a mammalian endoribonuclease which can cleave within the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD <italic>in vitro</italic>. The availability of this purified endonuclease has made it possible to directly test the interaction between CRD-BP and the endonuclease in regulating c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA cleavage. In this study, we have identified the coding region of <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA as a new target for CRD-BP. CRD-BP has the same affinity for c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD nts 1705&#x02013;1886 and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA nts 746&#x02013;962 with <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> of 500&#x02009;nM. The concentration-dependent affinity of CRD-BP to these transcripts correlated with the concentration-dependent blocking of endonuclease-mediated cleavage by CRD-BP. In contrast, three other recombinant proteins tested which had no affinity for c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD did not block endonuclease-mediated cleavage. Finally, we have identified RNA sequences required for CRD-BP binding. These results provide the first direct evidence that CRD-BP can indeed protect c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD cleavage initiated by an endoribonuclease, and the framework for further investigation into the interactions between CRD-BP, c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA, <italic>MDR</italic>-1 mRNA and the endoribonuclease in cells.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The c-Myc protein is an important transcription factor. It influences cell proliferation, differentiation and apoptosis via the activation of a multitude of target genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). It has been estimated that c-Myc can influence the expression of &#x0223c;10% of all genes in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). c-Myc is implicated in human cancers, and overexpression of c-Myc at the protein and/or mRNA levels has been observed in virtually all types of cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). These observations highlight the significance of understanding c-<italic>myc</italic> gene regulation.</p><p>c-Myc expression is regulated at multiple levels including the level of mRNA stability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3 B4 B5">3&#x02013;5</xref>). By using a cell-free mRNA decay assay as well as <italic>in vivo</italic> analysis, it has been shown that c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA can be degraded by two different pathways. One pathway involves rapid removal of the poly(A) tail which is then followed by 3&#x02032;&#x02013;5&#x02032; decay accomplished by 3&#x02032;&#x02013;5&#x02032; exoribonuclease(s) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). The second decay pathway involves endonucleolytic cleavage within the coding region of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA, a region termed the coding region determinant (CRD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Several studies have subsequently confirmed that the coding region of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA, including the CRD, is involved in the regulation of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA stability in cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8 B9 B10 B11">8&#x02013;11</xref>).</p><p>A cell-free mRNA decay assay involving polysome extracts and a 180&#x02009;nt&#x02009;RNA sense strand corresponding to the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD was found to induce endonucleolytic cleavage within the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD and destabilized the transcript 8-fold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). The effect was highly specific because competitor RNA corresponding to other regions of the c-<italic>myc</italic> transcript failed to destabilize c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). Based on these observations, Ross and co-workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) postulated the following model: (i) c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA is susceptible to attack by a polysome-associated endoribonuclease; (ii) a protein can interact with and protect the CRD from attack by an endoribonuclease; (iii) the addition of competitor CRD RNAs titrate the protein off c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA, leaving the CRD unprotected and susceptible to endonuclease attack. A protein that binds with high affinity <italic>in vitro</italic> to the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD has been purified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) and cloned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). This protein termed the c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA coding region determinant-binding protein or CRD-BP, was later found to be identical to the IGF-II mRNA-binding protein 1 (IMP-1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>).</p><p>The following observations supported CRD-BP being an oncofetal protein. CRD-BP has been shown to be abundantly expressed in fetal tissues but not in adult tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). CRD-BP-deficient mice exhibited dwarfism, impaired gut development and increased perinatal mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>), providing further support that CRD-BP plays a critical role in developmental processes. <italic>De novo</italic> expression studies on CRD-BP have shown it to be overexpressed in breast cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>), colorectal cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>), brain tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>) and non-small cell lung tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Further evidence to associate CRD-BP with breast cancer are the observations that &#x0223c;30% of human breast cancer cases exhibited amplification of the CRD-BP gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>), and transgenic mice carrying targeted expression of the protein developed mammary tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>To date, CRD-BP and its orthologs have been shown to bind to several RNAs, and depending on the RNA in question, multiple functions for these proteins have been proposed. CRD-BP binds to the 5&#x02032;-untranslated region of <italic>IGF</italic>-II mRNA and influences its subcellular localization and translation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). CRD-BP also binds to <italic>H</italic>19 RNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>) and neuron-specific <italic>tau</italic> mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>) to influence their localization in cells. The zipcode-binding protein binds to &#x003b2;-actin mRNA and localizes it to the leading edge of fibroblast lamellipodia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). The IMP binds to the 3&#x02032;-untranslated region of CD44 mRNA and stabilizes the transcript (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). A recent study has identified CRD-BP as the protein that interacts with the coding region of &#x003b2;TrCP1 mRNA and stabilizes the transcript in response to the &#x003b2;-catenin signaling pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). Finally, as indicated above, CRD-BP has been shown to bind to and is believed to shield the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD from endonucleolytic attack thereby prolonging its cytosolic half-life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>).</p><p>Three observations support the CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD shielding hypothesis. First, overexpression of CRD-BP in colorectal cancer correlates with a modest elevation of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Second, decreased expression of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA subsequent to knockdown of CRD-BP was observed in MCF-7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>) and colorectal cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). Finally, addition of sense RNA corresponding to the CRD resulted in enhanced decay of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA in cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). However, the following two recent observations do not support the CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD shielding hypothesis: (i) transgenic mice over-expressing CRD-BP in mammary tissues did not exhibit elevated levels of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>); and (ii) targeted knockdown of CRD-BP in K562 cells had no effect on c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). Such unexpected results or discrepancies may in part be due to the role of the third party molecule, namely an endoribonuclease that can cleave the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD. The availability of an identified endoribonuclease should permit systematic testing of the CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD shielding hypothesis <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>, and may help clarify some of the contradictory reports.</p><p>We have recently purified a mammalian endoribonuclease from rat liver based on its ability to cleave within the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). Several biochemical properties distinguished the enzyme from previously described vertebrate endonucleases and supported it being a novel mammalian endoribonuclease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The enzyme preferentially cleaves between the dinucleotides UA, CA and UG, and it is capable of cleaving other RNAs including <italic>MDR</italic>-1 and &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). With the availability of purified mammalian endoribonuclease and recombinant CRD-BP, we sought to directly test the CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD-shielding hypothesis. In this study, we show that CRD-BP is able to dose-dependently bind to c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA with <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> of &#x0223c;500&#x02009;nM. This interaction correlates with its ability to dose-dependently inhibit cleavage of c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA by the mammalian endoribonuclease.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Expression and purification of recombinant CRD-BP, Rpp20, Rpp21, Rpp25 and Rpp40</title><p>The plasmid pET28b(+)-CRD-BP which contains mouse CRD-BP cDNA was a generous gift from Dr Jeffrey Ross, University of Wisconsin and was prepared as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). Plasmids pHTT7k-p20, pHTT7k-p21, pHTT7k-p25 and pHTT7k-p40 which contain the Rpp20, Rpp21, Rpp25 and Rpp40 cDNAs were generous gifts from Dr Sidney Altman, Yale University and were prepared as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32 B33 B34">32&#x02013;34</xref>). All His<sub>6</sub>-tagged proteins were purified from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> BL21(DE3) using the QIAexpress Ni-NTA metal affinity spin kit (QIAGEN) under denaturing conditions. Proteins eluted from the column at either pH 5.4 or 4.5 were subjected to a series of dialysis steps (3&#x02009;h at each step) pH 5/6&#x02009;M&#x02009;urea, pH 5.5/4&#x02009;M&#x02009;urea, pH 6/2&#x02009;M&#x02009;urea, pH 6.7/1M&#x02009;urea and pH 7.4/0&#x02009;M&#x02009;urea in a buffer containing 200&#x02009;mM&#x02009;KCl, 1&#x02009;mM&#x02009;EDTA, 10% (v/v) glycerol, 1&#x02009;mM&#x02009;reduced glutathione, 0.1&#x02009;mM&#x02009;oxidized glutathione, 0.01% (v/v) Triton X-100, 20&#x02009;mM&#x02009;triethanolamine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>) and EDTA-free protease inhibitor tablets (Roche). Following dialysis, samples were spun at 13,200&#x02009;rpm for 30&#x02009;min to remove any precipitated proteins. The purified protein solutions were then quantified and analyzed for purity using Coomasie blue-stained 12% SDS-PAGE.</p></sec><sec><title>Purification of the mammalian endoribonuclease</title><p>Purification of the mammalian endoribonuclease from rat livers has been previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). One unit of the purified enzyme from the last step of column chromatography, the heparin-sepharose column, was used in all experiments described in this study.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription and labeling of 5&#x02032; ends of RNA</title><p>To synthesize c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA, plasmids pUC19-CRD<italic>myc</italic>-1705-1792 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>) and pUC19-CRD<italic>myc</italic>-1705-1886 were linearized with EcoRI and transcribed with SP6 RNA polymerase using SP6 Megascript kits (Ambion, TX, USA). To make human &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA corresponding to nts 1&#x02013;145, the plasmid SP&#x003ba;&#x003b2;c (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>) was linearized with FokI and transcribed with SP6&#x02009;RNA polymerase using SP6 Megascript kit. To make human <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA corresponding to nts 746&#x02013;962, the plasmid pGEM7Z-<italic>MDR</italic>-1-V2 was linearized with <italic>Apa</italic>LI and transcribed with T7 RNA polymerase using T7 Megascript kit (Ambion, TX, USA). For 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P-end labeling of RNA, 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of <italic>in-vitro</italic> transcribed RNA was first dephosphorylated with 10 units of calf alkaline phosphatase (GE Healthcare) for 30&#x02009;min at 37&#x000b0;C in a 100-&#x003bc;l reaction according to the manufacturer's instructions. Dephosphorylated RNA was purified by phenol/chloroform extraction and ethanol precipitation. About 2.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of dephosphorylated RNA was incubated in a 25-&#x003bc;l reaction with 30&#x02013;50&#x02009;&#x003bc;Ci of [&#x003b3;-<sup>32</sup>P] ATP at 37&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h with 40&#x02013;50 units of T4 polynucleotide kinase (New England Biolabs). The entire sample was then run on a 6% polyacrylamide/7M&#x02009;urea gel and the band containing 5&#x02032;-labeled <sup>32</sup>P-RNA was excised and eluted with elution buffer (0.5&#x02009;M ammonium acetate, 1&#x02009;mM&#x02009;EDTA, 0.2% SDS) at 37&#x000b0;C for 6&#x02009;h. The purified radiolabeled RNA was then concentrated by ammonium acetate/isopropanol precipitation. Specific activity of the RNA was determined by scintillation counting.</p></sec><sec><title>Electrophoretic mobility shift assays</title><p>Electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA) binding buffers (5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;Tris-Cl pH 7.4, 2.5&#x02009;mM&#x02009;EDTA pH 8.0, 2&#x02009;mM&#x02009;DTT, 5% glycerol, 0.1&#x02009;mg/ml bovine serum albumin, 0.5&#x02009;mg/ml yeast tRNA, 5 units RNasin) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>) were prepared on ice prior to each experiment. In order to facilitate RNA denaturation and renaturation, the [<sup>32</sup>P] RNA sample was heated to 50&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min and cooled to room temperature before being added to the EMSA-binding buffer. EMSA-binding buffer containing radiolabeled RNA was then incubated with purified recombinant protein in a 20-&#x003bc;l reaction volume at 30&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min and transferred to ice for 5&#x02009;min. The reaction was again incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min and transferred to ice for an additional 5&#x02009;min. Heparin (Sigma) was then added to a final concentration of 5&#x02009;mg/ml and the reaction was incubated on ice for a final 5-min period. A total of 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;l&#x02009;EMSA loading dye (250&#x02009;mM&#x02009;Tris-Cl&#x02009;pH 7.4, 0.2% bromophenol blue, 0.2% xylene cyanol, 40% sucrose) was added to each reaction and 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of the EMSA reaction was loaded onto an 8% native polyacrylamide gel and resolved at 25&#x02009;mA for 90&#x02009;min. Following electrophoresis, the gel was dried and subjected to autoradiography using the Cyclone PhosphorImager and Optiquant Software.</p><p>All EMSA saturation-binding experiments were carried out as described above and the dissociation constant (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>) for CRD-BP against <italic>MDR</italic>-1 and c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD was determined by fits to the Hill equation: <disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="gkl1148um1.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/></disp-formula> where <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> is the dissociation constant and [<italic>L</italic>] is the concentration of CRD-BP and <italic>n</italic> is the Hill coefficient. All saturation-binding data was analyzed by densitometry of the autoradiograph using the Cyclone Storage Phosphor-System and Optiquant software. For each reaction the total activity in each lane was determined; this involved summing the total activity in bound complexes with the total activity present in the unbound fraction. It should be noted that in lanes in which both Complex I and Complex II were present, their total activity was added together and therefore represented the total bound fraction. This analysis allowed for the calculation of the percentage of RNA bound to the protein. The percentage of bound RNA and the protein concentration (nM) were inserted into the Hill equation and the results were expressed graphically.</p><p>For EMSA competition assays, 5&#x02032;-[<sup>32</sup>P] radiolabeled c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 and unlabeled <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed competitor RNA were prepared as described above. EMSA-binding buffers and EMSA reaction mixtures were prepared and 350&#x02009;nM of CRD-BP was added to the reactions containing one of the following unlabeled competitors: c-<italic>myc</italic>-CRD-1705-1885, c-<italic>myc</italic>-CRD 1705-1792, <italic>MDR</italic>-1 or &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA. EMSA competition assays involved the pre-incubation between competitor RNA and CRD-BP for 10&#x02009;min at 30&#x000b0;C. Following the pre-incubation, 40&#x02009;nM [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA was added to the reaction. This was followed by the standard EMSA protocol as described above. The concentrations of unlabeled competitor RNA employed were 1-, 2-, 5-, 10- and 50-fold greater than the 40&#x02009;nM [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic>-CRD RNA used.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> endonuclease shielding assay</title><p>The first step of this assay involved the binding between one of the [<sup>32</sup>P] RNA constructs (c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD-1705-1886, <italic>MDR</italic>-1 or &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic>) and one of the purified recombinant proteins (CRD-BP, Rpp20, Rpp21, Rpp25 or Rpp40). Binding was facilitated using the standard EMSA protocol. Immediately following the final EMSA step, one unit of the heparin-sepharose purified mammalian endoribonuclease was added to the binding reaction, mixed and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;min. As a positive control, the dialyzed mammalian endoribonuclease was added to the EMSA buffer in the absence of recombinant protein and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;min. All reactions were terminated by heating at 100&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;min followed by the addition of 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;l&#x02009;phenol and 3&#x02009;&#x000b5;l formamide loading dye (80% formamide, 0.05&#x02009;mg/ml bromophenol blue, 0.05&#x02009;mg/ml xylene cyanol, 0.01&#x02009;M&#x02009;EDTA pH 8.0). Aliquots containing &#x0223c;30&#x02009;000&#x02009;c.p.m. were loaded onto 8% denaturing polyacrylamide gel and resolved at 30&#x02009;mA until the bromophenol blue reached the bottom of the gel plate. Gels were fixed in 10% acetic acid, 10% methanol for 15&#x02009;min and subjected to autoradiography. In some experiments, higher amounts (three units) of the purified endoribonuclease were used. In such cases, similar blocking effects of CRD-BP on endonuclease-mediated cleavage were observed.</p><p>RNase T1 digestion and alkaline hydrolysis of radiolabeled c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA were performed to generate sequencing ladders for cleavage site identification purposes. Alkaline ladders were generated by combining 100&#x02009;000&#x02009;c.p.m. [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD-1705-1886 RNA and 1&#x000d7; alkaline hydrolysis buffer (50&#x02009;mM&#x02009;NaHCO<sub>3</sub>/Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> pH 9.2, 1&#x02009;mM&#x02009;EDTA, 3&#x02009;&#x003bc;g yeast tRNA) in a total reaction volume not exceeding 15&#x02009;&#x000b5;l. The reaction was incubated at 95&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min, transferred to ice and combined with 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of formamide loading dye and stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C until required. RNase T1 digests were generated by incubating 100&#x02009;000&#x02009;c.p.m. [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD-1705-1886 RNA in EMSA-binding buffer with 1 unit of RNase T1 (Ambion). The RNA/EMSA binding buffer mixture was heated to 55&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min and cooled to room temperature prior to the addition of RNase T1. The T1 cleavage reaction was incubated at room temperature for 10&#x02009;min and was terminated by phenol/chloroform extraction. The RNA was extracted using ammonium acetate/isopropanol precipitation and was resuspended in 15&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of formamide loading dye.</p></sec><sec><title>Mapping of CRD-BP-binding sites using hydroxyl radical foot-printing</title><p>The Fe(II)/EDTA cleavage complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) was used to map the CRD-BP-binding sites on c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD-1705-1886. Initially, binding between c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD (&#x0223c;45&#x02009;nM; 100&#x02009;000&#x02009;c.p.m./reaction) and CRD-BP (1500&#x02009;nM) was facilitated using the standard EMSA buffer and reaction conditions as described above. Immediately following the binding reaction, 6&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of Fe(II)/EDTA cleavage reagent (0.4&#x02009;mM&#x02009;Fe(II)(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>, 0.8&#x02009;mM&#x02009;EDTA pH 8.0, 20&#x02009;mM&#x02009;<sc>l</sc>-ascorbic acid sodium salt, 0.35% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) was added to the 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;l binding reaction. The cleavage reaction was incubated at room temperature for 10&#x02009;min and was terminated by the addition of 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;l 0.1&#x02009;M Thiourea (Sigma). The RNA was extracted by ammonium acetate/isopropanol precipitation and the pellet was resuspended in 15&#x02009;&#x000b5;l formamide loading dye. About 5&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of the reaction was run on an 8% denaturing polyacrylamide-sequencing gel.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP binds to the full-length c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA nts 746&#x02013;962</title><p>In an effort towards testing the CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD shielding hypothesis, it was imperative to demonstrate that purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP could bind avidly to the CRD. The plasmid pET28b(+)-CRD-BP was used to generate the recombinant mouse CRD-BP containing a His<sub>6</sub>-tag at the C-terminus of the protein. CRD-BP fractions eluted from the Ni-NTA column contained an enriched band at &#x0223c;68&#x02009;kDa when visualized by SDS-PAGE, (refer to lane 3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) which is consistent with the predicted and reported molecular weight of recombinant mouse CRD-BP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). The recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP of &#x0223c;95% purity was consistently obtained and an example of this is shown in lane 3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. Additional recombinant proteins, Rpp20, Rpp21, Rpp25 and Rpp40, were used as controls in this investigation. Rpp20, Rpp21, Rpp25 and Rpp40 are protein subunits of human RNase P (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32 B33 B34">32&#x02013;34</xref>) and were chosen on the basis of their ability or inability to bind to nucleic acids. The criteria used to determine if these recombinant proteins possessed this binding potential was based on the presence of putative nucleic-acid-binding domains in their sequence and known RNA&#x02013;protein interactions. Purity of the recombinant proteins was assessed by visualization using Coomasie blue-stained SDS-PAGE. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, the purity of all the recombinant proteins was greater than 95% and their observed molecular weights were consistent with their predicted molecular weights (lanes 2, 4, 5, 7). </p><p>EMSA was performed to determine whether the purified and dialyzed recombinant proteins were capable of binding to c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886. About 500&#x02009;nM recombinant CRD-BP was incubated with c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD [<sup>32</sup>P]RNA and RNA&#x02013;protein complexes were visualized following non-denaturing gel electrophoresis. As shown in lane 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, two clear bound complexes were observed. In contrast, no bound complexes were observed when 500&#x02013;750&#x02009;nM&#x02009;Rpp20 (lanes 3&#x02013;5), Rpp21 (lanes 6&#x02013;8) or Rpp40 (lanes 12&#x02013;14) were incubated with c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD [<sup>32</sup>P]RNA. Three low-activity binding complexes were observed when Rpp25 was incubated with c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD [<sup>32</sup>P]RNA (lanes 9&#x02013;11). The ability of Rpp25 to bind to the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD was not surprising given the fact that it possesses an Alba RNA-binding motif (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>) and it is known to bind to several RNA targets including a 71-nt segment of <italic>H</italic>1 RNA, <italic>M</italic>1 RNA and <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA<sup>tyr</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). It should be noted that the intensity of the Rpp25-binding complexes is significantly less than CRD-BP-binding complexes at the same concentration. Further study would be required to determine if Rpp25 has in fact lower affinity than CRD-BP for c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD or yeast tRNA present in the EMSA reaction actually competed with Rpp25 for binding to the transcript. The inability of Rpp40 to bind with the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD was supported by the previous suggestions that this protein in isolation does not play a role in nucleic acid binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). </p><p>To further determine if the recombinant CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD [<sup>32</sup>P] RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 association was specific, we chalenged the interaction with unlabeled competitor RNA. Our EMSA competition assays revealed that up to 50X molar excess of unlabeled &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> competitor RNA was unable to dilute the binding between CRD-BP and [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD (lanes 15&#x02013;18, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A; lanes 7&#x02013;8, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). The inability of unlabeled &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> competitor to dilute the CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD interaction in conjunction with the saturation-binding experiment shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C support the observation that the 145-nt &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA fragment is not a <italic>bona fide</italic> CRD-BP target <italic>in vitro</italic>. The &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> results from this investigation are also supported by the two earlier reports (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). </p><p>Similar to unlabeled c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD nts 1705&#x02013;1886 (compare lane 3 to lane 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A), at 1&#x000d7; molar excess, the <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA nts 746&#x02013;962 was capable of diluting the CRD-BP-[<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD interaction (compare lane 11 to lane 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A) and at 5&#x000d7;, 10&#x000d7; and 50&#x000d7; molar excess it diluted the interaction completely (compare lanes 13&#x02013;14 with lane 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A; compare lanes 9&#x02013;10 with lane 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). Similar results were observed when the unlabeled competitor c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD-1705-1886 RNA was used (compare lanes 5&#x02013;6 with lane 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A; compare lanes 3&#x02013;4 with lane 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). The unlabeled competitor c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD nts 1705&#x02013;1792 was also observed to dilute the interaction when a minimum of 2&#x000d7; molar excess was added (compare lane 8 to lane 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A) and even at 50&#x000d7; molar excess, the CRD-BP-[<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD interaction was still visible (compare lanes 5&#x02013;6 with lane 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). This result is consistent with previous observation that c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD nts 1705&#x02013;1792 has indeed reduced affinity for CRD-BP as compared to the full-length c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD nts 1705&#x02013;1886 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>). It is possible that the secondary structure of the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD-1705-1886 contains the full complement of recognition and binding elements that facilitate high-affinity-binding interactions with CRD-BP.</p></sec><sec><title>Characterizing the binding of CRD-BP to c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA and <italic>MDR</italic>1 RNA</title><p>Although CRD-BP is known to bind to the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>), the binding characteristics between the two components has not been previously determined. With the availability of purified recombinant CRD-BP as well as <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA, we decided to further characterize and compare the nature of the binding interactions. Saturation-binding experiments were carried out using the standard EMSA conditions and employed a wide range of CRD-BP concentrations. The saturation-binding experiments were conducted three times, using three different purified CRD-BP preparations. A representative result for the binding of CRD-BP to c-<italic>myc</italic> [<sup>32</sup>P] CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A. It was determined experimentally that the minimum concentration of CRD-BP required to generate Complex I (binding of one molecule of CRD-BP, see below for discussion) was about 15&#x02009;nM (data not shown). At concentrations above 100&#x02009;nM, the slower migrating Complex II (binding of two molecules of CRD-BP, see below for discussion) was frequently observed (lanes 3&#x02013;20, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). In many instances, at higher concentrations of CRD-BP (e.g. 500&#x02013;750&#x02009;nM), Complex I was absent and it would appear that the bound RNA shifted exclusively to Complex II (compare lanes 8&#x02013;20 to lanes 2&#x02013;7, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). When the saturation-binding data from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A was fit to the Hill equation and expressed graphically, a sigmoidal curve was generated as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> of 500&#x02009;nM). It is important to point out that the concentration of CRD-BP at which formation of Complexes I and II would take place was highly dependent upon the age of the dialyzed protein and the number of freeze&#x02013;thaw cycles subjected to the protein. However, the actual dissociation constant may be lower than 500&#x02009;nM because it cannot be assumed that 100% of the CRD-BP molecules were present in a conformation suitable for binding.</p><p>Keeping in mind the limitation of the EMSA, we also performed saturation-binding experiments to determine if CRD-BP could bind with other radiolabeled RNA substrates. When challenged with [<sup>32</sup>P] &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA, CRD-BP up to 3070&#x02009;nM was unable to form an observable RNA&#x02013;protein complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). However, when CRD-BP was challenged with [<sup>32</sup>P] <italic>MDR</italic>-1, two RNA&#x02013;protein complexes that exhibited a similar profile to that of the CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD interaction were observed; <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> = 500&#x02009;nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). The analysis of the combined binding data from three separate experiments revealed a level of cooperativity was present between the formation of the first and second binding complexes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). The cooperativity observed is also reflected in the Hill coefficient, which for CRD-BP versus c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B) was 2.06, and 2.6 when challenged with <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). The Hill coefficients in both cases suggest that two molecules of CRD-BP bind with one molecule of c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA or with one molecule of <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA at identical or non-identical sites. Evidence to support a two RNA-binding site model is provided by the kinetic analysis of the interactions between IMP-1 and <italic>IGF</italic>-II RNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). In this study, IMP-1 was shown to bind through a cooperative, sequential mechanism via two binding sites within the <italic>IGF</italic>-II transcript (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). Interestingly, dissociation constant of about 2&#x02009;nM was reported for the interaction between IMP-1 and <italic>IGF</italic>-II RNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). The significantly higher dissociation constant determined in this study could reflect the inefficiency of renaturation of CRD-BP and c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA as discussed above, or/and the use of His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP since it has been previously reported that tagged-IMP-1 exhibited poor RNA binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). </p></sec><sec><title>CRD-BP protects the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA from cleavage by the mammalian endoribonuclease</title><p>Having established that recombinant CRD-BP can bind c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA, we then sought to determine if the binding of CRD-BP to RNA could directly protect these transcripts from degradation by an endoribonuclease recently discovered in our lab (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>).</p><p>5&#x02032;-End labeled c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD nts 1705&#x02013;1886 was incubated with one unit of the purified endonuclease in the presence or absence of recombinant CRD-BP. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A, the typical ten distinct cleavage sites at nts 1742, 1747, 1751, 1757, 1768, 1771, 1773, 1775, 1845 and 1855 were generated upon incubation with the purified endonuclease (lanes 3, 8 and 13) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). For ease in quantification and categorization, we have named the separate cleavage sites as Region I (1845, 1855), Region II (1768, 1771, 1773, 1775) and Region III (1742, 1747, 1751, 1757) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). Incubation of the transcript with recombinant CRD-BP at 500&#x02009;nM (lane 2), 750&#x02009;nM (lane 7) and 1500&#x02009;nM (lane 12) alone had no effect, indicating that CRD-BP lacks RNase activity. It was anticipated that c-<italic>myc</italic> cleavage would be reduced using CRD-BP concentrations equal to the measured dissociation constant because 50% of c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD would be bound at 500&#x02009;nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B). This prediction was confirmed by the reduction in cleavage fragments observed in all three regions indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A (compare lanes 4&#x02013;5 with lane 3). At 500&#x02009;nM, CRD-BP was responsible for a 43% reduction in Region I, a 72% reduction in Region II and a 77% reduction in Region III. </p><p>It was predicted that cleavage reductions would increase at concentrations above the measured dissociation constant because at 750 and 1500&#x02009;nM, &#x0223c;75 and 90% of c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD were bound by CRD-BP respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B). At 750&#x02009;nM, (lanes 9&#x02013;10, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A) CRD-BP was responsible for a 45% reduction in Region I, a 75% reduction in Region II and a 80% reduction in Region III. As shown in lanes 14&#x02013;15 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A, at 1500&#x02009;nM, CRD-BP was responsible for the 95% cleavage reductions observed in all three regions.</p><p>To determine if the blocking effect was due to specific binding interactions, we incubated c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA with Rpp20, Rpp21 and Rpp40 which had been shown to have no affinity for the transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B shows that at 1500&#x02009;nM, Rpp20, Rpp21 and Rpp40 were unable to block endonucleolytic cleavage of CRD RNA by the native mammalian endoribonuclease (compare lanes 4, 6 and 8 to lane 2).</p><p>CRD-BP was shown to bind with considerable affinity and specificity to <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>) and we have previously shown that the endonuclease is capable of cleaving <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). It was therefore anticipated that CRD-BP would also be capable of blocking <italic>MDR</italic>-1 cleavage by the mammalian endoribonuclease. As predicted, CRD-BP was observed to shield <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA from endonucleolytic attack in a concentration-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A), and the most significant cleavage reductions were observed at 1500&#x02009;nM (lane 3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A). The consistent reduction observed in all regions suggests that the entire <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA was protected via CRD&#x02013;BP interactions. We have also tested the ability of CRD-BP to block cleavage of &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA by the endonuclease. As expected, CRD-BP that had no affinity for &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C) did not effectively block the endonuclease from cleaving this transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B). </p><p>Taken together, our overall results suggest that CRD-BP was capable of shielding both c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNAs in a dose-dependent manner from the cleavage activities of a mammalian endoribonuclease via specific RNA&#x02013;protein interactions. In addition, the results suggest that CRD-BP binds to a considerable portion of both <italic>MDR</italic>-1 and c-<italic>myc</italic> RNAs and at 1500&#x02009;nM, both RNA transcripts appeared to be entirely protected.</p></sec><sec><title>Mapping the CRD-BP-binding sites on c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA</title><p>To map the CRD-BP-binding sites on c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD, we used the hydroxyl radical foot-printing method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). The chemical cleavage reagent chosen was the Fe(II)/EDTA complex. The Fe(II)/EDTA complex is a negatively charged species and does not interact electrostatically with the RNA molecule thereby limiting its interference with RNA&#x02013;protein interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). The complex is known to generate hydroxyl radicals from the reduction of hydrogen peroxide in a reaction known as the Haber&#x02013;Weiss reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). The hydroxyl radical is thought to cleave the RNA backbone by attacking ribose moieties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Regions of the RNA backbone that are occluded by protein are cleaved with decreased efficiency by the radical and the result is a series of cleavage fragments exhibiting reduced intensity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>A shows a typical CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD foot-printing experiment. Lane 3 depicts the Fe(II)/EDTA cleavage profile characteristic of [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD-1705&#x02013;1886 in the absence of CRD-BP. The alkaline hydrolysis ladder (lane 2) exhibited a uniform cleavage profile with the exception of two enriched fragments located between nts 1794 and 1842; which were also observed in lanes 4&#x02013;9. RNase T1 digest of [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD-1705&#x02013;1886 shown in lane 1 provided mapping for cleavage site identification. The cleavage pattern observed as a result of Fe(II)/EDTA-treatment of c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD was hallmarked by several enriched fragments which have been mapped and are indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>A. When compared to cleavage reactions containing 1500&#x02009;nM CRD-BP (lanes 4&#x02013;7), it is apparent that several regions of cleavage were significantly reduced. The cleavage fragments corresponding to nts 1741 and 1748 (lane 3) were reduced by 75%. An equivalent reduction was also observed at discrete fragments in the nucleotide region spanning 1765&#x02013;1775 (compare lane 3 with lanes 4&#x02013;7). At positions 1787 and 1791, a 50% reduction in cleavage intensity was observed and a 75% reduction was also observed at positions 1843, 1855 and 1864 (compare lane 3 with lanes 4&#x02013;7). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>B shows the identified CRD-BP-binding sites in comparison with the putative CRD-BP-binding sites previously determined using antisense oligonucleotides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Six of the binding sites (1765, 1767, 1771, 1773, 1775, 1787) identified in this study were in good agreement with those identified by Coulis <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Six identified CRD-BP-binding sites (1747, 1767, 1771, 1773, 1855) are within the direct cleavage sites of the mammalian endonuclease and five (1741, 1765, 1787, 1791, 1843) are within one to two nucleotides away from the enzyme cleavage sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>B). Such observation is consistent with the notion that CRD-BP is capable of shielding c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA from attack by the endonuclease. </p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>CRD-BP belongs to the VICKZ family of RNA-binding proteins that influence various aspects of cellular physiology such as cell growth and differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). CRD-BP was initially discovered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>) and eventually purified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) based on its ability to bind to the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD. The working model for CRD-BP function is that it binds to and protects the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD from endonucleolytic cleavage, resulting in enhanced transcript half-life and expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). This hypothesis is supported by evidence from <italic>in vitro</italic> mRNA decay studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>) as well as studies in cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). Although this hypothesis has been proposed for a number of years, it has not been directly tested. That is CRD-BP has not been directly shown to block CRD cleavage by an endoribonuclease. This is in part due to the unavailability of a candidate endoribonuclease that can cleave within the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD. In this study, we show that recombinant CRD-BP can dose-dependently inhibit cleavage of c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA by a mammalian endoribonuclease. This blocking effect correlates with CRD-BP's dose-dependent affinity for c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNAs.</p><p>Specificity of recombinant CRD-BP for the CRD was demonstrated in two ways. First, while three other recombinant proteins, Rpp20, Rpp21 and Rpp40, had no affinity for c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD, CRD-BP was shown to bind strongly to the transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Second, consistent with previous findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>), c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD competitor RNAs were effective in competing with [<sup>32</sup>P]c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD in binding to CRD-BP, with nts 1705&#x02013;1886 being more effective than nts 1705&#x02013;1792 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). On the contrary, at 50&#x000d7; molar excess, &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA could not compete with [<sup>32</sup>P]c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD in binding to CRD-BP. Unexpectedly, we found that the coding region of <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA nts 746&#x02013;962 was as effective as c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD nts 1705&#x02013;1886 in competing for binding to CRD-BP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). This result is consistent with the observed saturating-binding profile upon incubation of excess CRD-BP with [<sup>32</sup>P]<italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>The <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> for the CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic>-1705&#x02013;1886 interaction was significantly lower than that of CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic>-1705&#x02013;1792 interaction. It is apparent that one of the proposed CRD-BP-binding sites (nts 1843&#x02013;1864) is absent from the 1705&#x02013;1792 CRD region, and may attributed to the differences in specificity and stability observed in the RNA&#x02013;protein interactions. The binding profiles exhibited by the CRD-BP-c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD and CRD-BP&#x02013;<italic>MDR</italic>-1 interactions were hallmarked by the presence of two binding complexes. These RNA&#x02013;protein interactions are believed to occur via a sequential, cooperative binding mechanism. The formation of the faster migrating Complex I at low concentrations of CRD-BP, the emergence of the slower migrating Complex II at intermediate concentrations of CRD-BP and the predominance of Complex II at concentrations greater than (or) equal to the calculated <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> are suggestive of a sequential binding mechanism. It is possible that the formation of Complex I may represent an intermediate state in which one molecule of CRD-BP is bound to one RNA molecule. The emergence of Complex II suggests that a second molecule of CRD-BP engages in interactions with a Complex I species in a concentration-dependent manner. We propose that Complex II may function to increase the stability and specificity of the RNA&#x02013;protein interaction. Such interactions have also been observed and proposed for IMP-1-<italic>IGF</italic>-II RNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>) and Vg1RBP-<italic>VLE</italic> 3&#x02032;-UTR RNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>).</p><p>Our data demonstrated that the blocking of endonuclease-mediated c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD cleavage by CRD-BP is concentration dependent and this correlated with concentration-dependent binding of CRD-BP to the transcript. We propose that at 500&#x02009;nM CRD-BP, most c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA molecules are bound by only one molecule of CRD-BP. At 1500&#x02009;nM CRD-BP, c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA is likely to be bound by two molecules of CRD-BP as observed by the formation of Complex II. In this scenario, it is highly likely that the entire transcript is bound and protected by CRD-BP as evidenced by the hydroxyl radical foot-printing experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). Our observations that CRD-BP binds to larger stretches of nucleotides rather than to specific positions is supported by evidence that members of the VICKZ family bind to larger elements rather than to individual nucleotides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). Further evidence to support this came from a study using complementary oligonucleotides to map the CRD-BP-binding sites within the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Our findings of the presence of CRD-BP-binding sites within the regions targeted by the mammalian endoribonuclease support the hypothesis that CRD-BP serves as a stabilizing factor for c-<italic>myc in vitro</italic>. The evidence provided in this study confirms that CRD-BP is in fact capable of blocking a mammalian endoribonuclease from cleaving c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD via specific interactions with RNA sequences.</p><p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to demonstrate the ability of CRD-BP to directly protect c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD cleavage by an endoribonuclease. This is a critical first step towards directly testing the interaction between CRD-BP and endoribonuclease in regulating c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD cleavage in cells. As indicated in the Introduction, four studies indirectly supported this hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). However, two recent observations on the lack of changes in c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA and protein levels upon changes in CRD-BP expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) are inconsistent with this working model. As previously suggested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>), the known multilevel regulation of c-<italic>myc</italic> gene expression could contribute to these observations. Alternatively, the absence of the responsible endoribonuclease may in part explain these unexpected findings. The latter hypothesis can be investigated upon availability of identified endoribonucleases that can cleave within the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD.</p><p>Our finding that CRD-BP has high affinity for <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA was totally unexpected and has important implications. <italic>MDR</italic>-1 is a plasma membrane drug-transporter protein and is associated with multidrug resistance phenotypes in cultured cells as well as in human cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>). Enhanced mRNA stability for <italic>MDR</italic>-1 and c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA has been reported in liver cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>) and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 mRNA decay intermediates corresponding to nts 746&#x02013;962 of <italic>MDR</italic>-1 have been detected in the normal liver but not liver cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). Although CRD-BP expression has not been studied in liver cancer, results to date are consistent with the model that c-<italic>myc</italic> and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 mRNAs are short-lived in normal adult tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>) because CRD-BP is absent or present at low levels. However, in cancerous liver cells, enhanced <italic>MDR</italic>-1 and c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>) are observed because CRD-BP may be overexpressed.</p><p>In conclusion, our data provides direct evidence that CRD-BP can indeed protect c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA from cleavage by an endoribonuclease, and supports its proposed role in regulating mRNA stability in cells. We have also identified <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA as a new target for CRD-BP, and the transcript can also be protected from endonucleolytic cleavage by CRD-BP. These findings provided further support for the significant and global roles that CRD-BP play in regulating mRNA stability in cancer.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>This work was supported by a grant from Natural Science &#x00026; Engineering Research Council and Canadian Liver Foundation. C.H.L. is a Research Scientist of the National Cancer Institute of Canada supported with funds provided by the Canadian Cancer Society. We thank Andrea Gorrell for her assistance in the preparation of saturation-binding curves. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charge was provided by the NSERC Discovery Grant 227158.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levens</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstructing MYC</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730130</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nesbit</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tersak</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prochownik</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MYC oncogenes and human neoplastic disease</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3004</fpage><lpage>3016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10378696</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrick</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The half-life of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA in growing and serum-stimulated cells: influence of the coding and 3&#x02032; untranslated regions and role of ribosome translocation</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2119</fpage><lpage>2128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8114742</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>RPC</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C-<italic>myc</italic> oncogene expression in estrogen-dependent and -independent breast cancer</article-title><source>Clin. Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8432027</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrick</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokipcak</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA half-life <italic>in vitro</italic> by a protein capable of binding to a coding region determinant</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1992</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>642</fpage><lpage>654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1559612</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for a 3&#x02032;-5&#x02032; decay pathway for c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA in mammalian cells</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>16174</fpage><lpage>16179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10347171</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of c-myc mRNA decay <italic>in vitro</italic> by a phorbol ester-inducible, ribosome-associated component in differentiating megakaryoblasts</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>33336</fpage><lpage>33345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10931849</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of c-myc mRNA decay by translational pausing in a coding region instability determinant</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>3959</fpage><lpage>3969</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12024010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morello</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavenu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pournin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Babinet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; non-coding sequences of the c-<italic>myc</italic> gene, required in vitro for its post-transcriptional regulation, are dispensable <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1993</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1921</fpage><lpage>1929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8510935</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisdom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The protein coding region of c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA contains a sequence that specifies rapid mRNA turnover and induction by protein synthesis inhibitor</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1991</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1995415</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yielding</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WMF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coding elements in exons 2 and 3 target c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA downregulation during myogenic differentiation</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2698</fpage><lpage>2707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9111340</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prokipcak</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrick</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and properties of a protein that binds to the C-terminal coding region of human c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>9261</fpage><lpage>9269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8132663</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>GAR</given-names></name><name><surname>Betz</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leeds</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleisig</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokipcak</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The c-<italic>myc</italic> coding region determinant-binding protein: a member of a family of KH domain RNA-binding proteins</article-title><source>Nucleic Acid Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>5036</fpage><lpage>5044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9801297</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lykke-Andersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnsen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wewer</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A family of insulin-like growth factor II mRNA-binding proteins represses translation in late development</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1262</fpage><lpage>1270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9891060</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leeds</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kren</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Boylan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Betz</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruppuso</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental regulation of CRD-BP, an RNA-binding protein that stabilizes c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1997</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1279</fpage><lpage>1286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9178888</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>TVO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalbaeck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wewer</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dwarfism and impaired gut development in insulin-like growth factor II mRNA-binding protein 1-deficient mice</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>4448</fpage><lpage>4464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15121863</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahaira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Papaioannou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixera</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Evangelou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dafni</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>8q24 Copy number gains and expression of the c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA stabilizing protein <italic>CRD-BP</italic> in primary breast carcinomas</article-title><source>Int. J. Cancer</source><year>2003</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12532419</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemm</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Berberet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of an mRNA-binding protein in human colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>6544</fpage><lpage>6550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641779</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kottaridi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimitriadis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahaira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Talieri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannopoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Iliadis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Papaioannou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of the RNA-binding protein CRD-BP in brain and non-small cell lung tumors</article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><year>2004</year><volume>209</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15159028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourdeau-Heller</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulthard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meisner</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amplification in human breast cancer of a gene encoding a c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA-binding protein</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2756</fpage><lpage>2759</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10850408</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tessier</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitot</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammary tumor induction in transgenic mice expressing an RNA-binding protein</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14729626</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristenses</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic trafficking of IGF-II mRNA-binding protein by conserved KH domains</article-title><source>J. Cell Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>2087</fpage><lpage>2097</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11973350</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Runge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lykke-Andersen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wewer</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>H19 RNA binds four molecules of insulin-like growth factor II mRNA-binding protein</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>29562</fpage><lpage>29569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10875929</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atlas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginzburg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The insulin-like growth factor mRNA binding-protein IMP-1 and the Ras-regulatory protein G3BP associate with tau mRNA and HuD protein in differentiated P19 neuronal cells</article-title><source>J. Neurochem</source><year>2004</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15086518</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Oleynikov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kislaukis</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Taneja</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of a &#x003b2;-actin mRNA zipcode-binding protein</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2158</fpage><lpage>2165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9121465</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vikesaa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>TVO</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Borup</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wewer</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA-binding IMPs promote cell adhesion and invadopodia formation</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1456</fpage><lpage>1468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16541107</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noubissi</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Elcheva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakoori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ougolkov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Minamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CRD-BP mediates stabilization of &#x003b2;TrCP1 and c-<italic>myc</italic> mRNA in response to &#x003b2;-catenin signaling</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>441</volume><fpage>898</fpage><lpage>901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16778892</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahaira</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gritzapis</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotiropoulou</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavalakis</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Antsaklis</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Baxevanis</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Papamichail</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CRD-BP/IMP1 expression characterizes cord blood CD34+ stem cells and affects c-<italic>myc</italic> and IGF-II expression in MCF-7 cancer cells</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>20086</fpage><lpage>20093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15769738</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coulis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nardone</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokipcak</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of c-<italic>myc</italic> expression in cells by targeting an RNA-protein interaction using antisense oligonucleotides</article-title><source>Mol. Pharmacol</source><year>2000</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10692488</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrick</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeted knockdown of the RNA-binding protein CRD-BP promotes cell proliferation via insulin-like growth factor II-dependent pathway in human K562 leukemia cells</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>48716</fpage><lpage>48724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15355996</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergstrom</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Urquhart</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tafech</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of a novel mammalian endoribonuclease</article-title><source>J. Cell. Biochem</source><year>2006</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16317762</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarrous</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wesolowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrier-Takada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Function and subnuclear distribution of Rpp21, a protein subunit of the human ribonucleoprotein ribonuclease P</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>1164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11497433</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarrous</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Eder</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrier-Takada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoog</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autoantigenic properties of some protein subunits of catalytically active complexes of human ribonuclease P</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>1998</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9630247</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guerrier-Takada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Eder</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gopalan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of Rpp25, an RNA-binding protein subunit of human ribonuclease P</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12003489</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawn</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Efstratiadis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nucleotide sequence of the human &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> gene</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1980</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6254664</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tullius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dombroski</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydroxyl radical footprinting: high resolution information about DNA-protein contacts and applications to lambda repressor and Cro protein</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>1986</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>5469</fpage><lpage>5473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3090544</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Copley</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerks</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SMART: A web-based tool for the study of genetically mobile domains</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592234</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrier-Takada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein-RNA interactions in the subunits of human nuclear RNase P</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11455963</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Willemoes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequential dimerization of human zipcode-binding protein IMP1 on RNA: a cooperative mechanism providing RNP stability</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>4368</fpage><lpage>4376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15314207</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yisraeli</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>VICKZ proteins: a multi-talented family or regulatory RNA-binding proteins</article-title><source>Biol. Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15601260</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Git</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Standart</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The KH domains of Xenopus Vg1RBP mediate RNA binding and self-association</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1319</fpage><lpage>1333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12403469</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambudkar</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimchi-Sarfaty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauna</surname><given-names>ZE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>P-glycoprotein: from genomics to mechanism</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>7468</fpage><lpage>7485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576852</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased P-glycoprotein messenger RNA stability in rat liver tumors <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>J. Cell. Physiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9731740</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehaume</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shandro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of <italic>in vivo</italic> P-glycoprotein mRNA decay intermediates in normal liver but not in liver tumors</article-title><source>J. Cell. Physiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15744753</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Analysis of purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged proteins by SDS-PAGE. Recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged mouse CRD-BP was purified using Ni-NTA spin column and dialyzed prior to separation (2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g) (lane 3) on 12% SDS-PAGE and visualization by Coomasie blue staining. Recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged human Rpp20 (lane 2), Rpp21 (lane 4), Rpp25 (lane 5) and Rpp40 (lane 7) were also purified and dialyzed in a similar manner before its purity (2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g) being analyzed on Coomasie blue-stained SDS-PAGE.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1148f1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Electromobility shift assay showing binding of recombinant CRD-BP and Rpp25 to c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA. About 500&#x02009;nM of purified recombinant CRD-BP (lane 2) and purified recombinant Rpp20 (lanes 3&#x02013;5), Rpp21 (lanes 6&#x02013;8), Rpp25 (lanes 9&#x02013;11) and Rpp40 (lanes 12&#x02013;14) (at various concentrations as indicated) were incubated with 40&#x02009;nM [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 (&#x0223c;50&#x02009;000&#x02009;c.p.m). None (lane 1) indicates no protein was added. The positions of protein&#x02013;RNA complexes (Bound) and unbound RNA (Unbound) are indicated on the left.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1148f2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Electromobility shift competition assays with c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA, &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA or <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA. About 350&#x02009;nM of purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP was incubated with 40&#x02009;nM [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 (50&#x02009;000&#x02009;c.p.m) with or without the indicated molar excess of unlabeled competitor RNA. (<bold>A</bold>) 1&#x02013;10 molar excess of unlabeled c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 (lanes 3&#x02013;6), c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1792 (lanes 7&#x02013;10), <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA nts 746&#x02013;962 (lanes 11&#x02013;14) and &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA nts 1&#x02013;145 (lanes 15&#x02013;18) were used. (<bold>B</bold>) 10&#x02013;50 molar excess of unlabeled c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 (lanes 3 and 4), c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1792 (lanes 5 and 6), &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA nts 1&#x02013;145 (lanes 7 and 8) and <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA nts 746&#x02013;962 (lanes 9 and 10) were used.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1148f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>CRD-BP-binding affinity for c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA and &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA. (<bold>A</bold>) An electromobility shift assay showing binding to [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 by an increasing amount of purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP (0&#x02013;1470&#x02009;nM). (<bold>B</bold>) Binding activity in (<bold>A</bold>) was quantified using the PhorphorImager to compare the relative amount of radiolabeled unbound RNA shifted into slower-migrating Complex I and Complex II. Data obtained was then used to plot the saturation binding curve as shown. (<bold>C</bold>) An electromobility shift assay assessing the ability to bind to [<sup>32</sup>P] &#x003b2;-<italic>globin</italic> RNA nts 1&#x02013;145 by an increasing amount of purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP (0&#x02013;3070&#x02009;nM).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1148f4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>CRD-BP binding affinity for <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA. (<bold>A</bold>) An electromobility shift assay showing binding to [<sup>32</sup>P] <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA nts 746&#x02013;962 by an increasing amount of purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP (0&#x02013;4000&#x02009;nM). (<bold>B</bold>) Binding activity in (<bold>A</bold>) was quantified using the PhorphorImager to compare the relative amount of radiolabeled unbound RNA shifted into slower-migrating Complex I and Complex II. Data obtained from three separate experiments was then used to plot the saturation binding curve as shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1148f5"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>CRD-BP shields the c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA from endonucleolytic attack by a mammalian endoribonuclease. (<bold>A</bold>) One unit of the purified mammalian endoribonuclease was incubated with [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 as described in the Materials and methods section, with (lanes 4, 5, 9, 10, 14, 15) or without (lanes 3, 8 and 13) the presence of 500, 750 or 1500&#x02009;nM of purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP as shown. (<bold>B</bold>) As in (<bold>A</bold>), the purified endoribonuclease was incubated with the radiolabeled c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA in the absence (lane 2) or presence of 1500&#x02009;nM of Rpp20 (lane 4), Rpp21 (lane 6) and Rpp40 (lane 8). Lanes 3, 5 and 7 had the purified recombinant proteins only. Numbers on the right indicate the cleavage sites generated by the mammalian endoribonuclease on the CRD RNA substrates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1148f6"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>CRD-BP is capable of shielding <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA from endonucleolytic attack by the mammalian endoribonuclease. <bold>(A)</bold> One unit of the purified mammalian endoribonuclease was incubated with [<sup>32</sup>P] <italic>MDR</italic>-1 RNA nts 746&#x02013;962 as described in the Materials and methods section, without (lane 2) or with the presence of 500&#x02009;nM (lane 5), 750&#x02009;nM (lane 4) or 1500&#x02009;nM (lane 3) of purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP. Lane 2 had the input RNA only. <bold>(B)</bold> As in (<bold>A</bold>), the purified endoribonuclease was incubated with [<sup>32</sup>P] &#x003b2;<italic>-globin</italic> RNA nts 1&#x02013;145 without (lane 3) or with the presence of 750&#x02009;nM (lane 4) or 1500&#x02009;nM (lane 5) of purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP. Lane 1 had the input RNA only.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1148f7"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Mapping of CRD-BP-binding sites on c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA using the hydroxyl radical-mediated cleavage reaction. <bold>(A)</bold> 45&#x02009;nM [<sup>32</sup>P] c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886 was subjected to Fe(II)/EDTA cleavage reaction in EMSA-binding buffer in the absence (lane 3) or presence (lanes 4&#x02013;7) of 1500&#x02009;nM purified recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged CRD-BP. Reaction samples were run on a 8% denaturing polyacrylamide gel, fixed, dried and subjected to autoradiography as described in the Materials and methods section. Lane 8 is the input RNA. Lanes 1 and 2 represent RNase T1 digest and alkaline hydrolysis of the radiolabeled c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA respectively. Regions highlighted by rectangles showed significant reductions in cleavage. Numbers on the left indicate guanosine cleavage sites of RNase T1 digest and numbers on the right indicate the hydroxyl radical-mediated cleavage sites. <bold>(B)</bold> Identified CRD-BP-binding sites on sequences of c-<italic>myc</italic> CRD RNA nts 1705&#x02013;1886. Underlined sequences indicate the CRD-BP-binding sites as determined by the hydroxyl radical foot-printing in (<bold>A</bold>). Bolded sequences indicate the putative CRD-BP-binding sites as previously determined using antisense oligonucleotides competition method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>). Arrows indicate cleavage sites generated by the purified endoribonuclease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkl1148f8"/></fig></sec></back></article> 