<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties no_embargo?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Blood</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">blood</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Blood</journal-id><journal-title>Blood</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0006-4971</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1528-0020</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Hematology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2006/037655</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2006-07-037655</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17227833</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunobiology</subject></subj-group><series-title>Immunobiology</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Activation of the Hedgehog signaling pathway in T-lineage cells inhibits TCR repertoire selection in the thymus and peripheral T-cell activation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rowbotham</surname><given-names>Nicola J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hager-Theodorides</surname><given-names>Ariadne L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cebecauer</surname><given-names>Marek</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Divya K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drakopoulou</surname><given-names>Ekati</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>Julian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Outram</surname><given-names>Susan V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Crompton</surname><given-names>Tessa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Division of Cell and Molecular Biology, Imperial College London, Sir Alexander Fleming Building, South Kensington Campus, London, United Kingdom; </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Section of Molecular and Cellular Medicine, Imperial College London, Sir Alexander Fleming Building, South Kensington Campus, London, United Kingdom; </aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Immunology, Imperial College London, Hammersmith Hospital Campus, London, United Kingdom</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. --><volume>109</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>3757</fpage><lpage>3766</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date></history><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 by The American Society of Hematology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="creativecommons"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/us/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zh800907003757.pdf"/><abstract><p>TCR signal strength is involved in many cell fate decisions in the T-cell lineage. Here, we show that transcriptional events induced by Hedgehog (Hh) signaling reduced TCR signal strength in mice. Activation of Hh signaling in thymocytes in vivo by expression of a transgenic transcriptional-activator form of Gli2 (Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>) changed the outcome of TCR ligation at many stages of thymocyte development, allowing self-reactive cells to escape clonal deletion; reducing transgenic TCR-mediated positive selection; reducing the ratio of CD4/CD8 single-positive (SP) cells; and reducing cell surface CD5 expression. In contrast, in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus the ratio of CD4/CD8 cells and both positive and negative selection of a transgenic TCR were increased, demonstrating that Shh does indeed influence TCR repertoire selection and the transition from double-positive (DP) to SP cell in a physiological situation. In peripheral T cells, Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> expression attenuated T-cell activation and proliferation, by a mechanism upstream of ERK phosphorylation.</p></abstract><contract-sponsor id="CS200" xlink:href="http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/">Wellcome Trust</contract-sponsor><custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>PDF</meta-name><meta-value><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="zh800907003757.pdf"/></meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The Hedgehog (Hh) family of secreted intercellular signaling molecules specifies cell fate and patterning during embryonic development and is involved in homeostasis and renewal of adult tissues, including skin, gut, lung, blood, and thymus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8"/>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref></sup></p><p>The specialized environment of the thymus supports the maturation of lymphocyte precursors into functional T cells through stages defined by cell surface expression of developmentally regulated markers: CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> double-negative (DN) thymocytes differentiate to CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> double-positive (DP) cells that become mature CD4 or CD8 single-positive (SP) T cells. The DN population can be subdivided by expression of CD44 and CD25. The earliest CD44<sup>+</sup>CD25<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells (DN1) acquire CD25 (DN2), then lose CD44 expression (DN3) and become CD44<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD25<sup>&#x02212;</sup>DN (DN4) cells before differentiating to DP. The transition from DN to DP cell requires a functional pre-T-cell receptor (TCR) complex,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref></sup> whereas maturation from DP to mature SP involves positive selection of the &#x003b1;&#x003b2;TCR repertoire to ensure appropriate MHC restriction and negative selection of potentially self-reactive clones.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref></sup> This developmental program is regulated by the stroma, and one way in which the epithelium signals to developing thymocytes is by production of Sonic Hh (Shh).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup></p><p>The 3 mammalian Hh proteins (Shh, Indian Hh, and Desert Hh) share a common signaling pathway. Hh proteins bind their cell surface receptor Patched, releasing the signal transducer Smoothened (Smo) to transmit the Hh signal into the cell. At the end of this pathway are the transcription factors Gli1, Gli2, and Gli3.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> Gli1 acts exclusively as an activator of transcription and, although not essential for mouse development or Hh signaling, is itself a Hh target gene, so measurement of its transcription can be used as a readout of Hh signaling in a given population of cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref></sup> Gli2 and Gli3 undergo processing to function as positive or negative regulators of transcription, depending on the presence or absence of Hh signaling, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref></sup> Both are essential for mouse development and have distinct but partially overlapping functions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref></sup> Gli2 functions primarily as a transcriptional activator downstream of Hh signaling, and is necessary to initiate the first transcriptional changes induced by the Hh signal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref></sup> In contrast, in vivo Gli3 functions primarily as a transcriptional repressor in the absence of the Hh signal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref></sup></p><p>Analysis of Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, Gli3<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, and Smo-deficient (conditional, T lineage) thymi has shown that Hh signaling is a positive regulator of the early stages of thymocyte development, controlling homeostasis of DN progenitors and differentiation from DN1 to DN2.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup> Both the analysis of the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;5</sup> and Gli3<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;7</sup> thymus and in vitro experiments using wild-type mouse thymus explants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> have also suggested that Hh signaling is involved after TCR-&#x003b2; gene rearrangement at the transition from DN to DP cell. Surprisingly, however, conditional deletion of Smo from T-lineage cells failed to show any influence of loss of Hh signaling after the DN2 stage.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup> A role for Hh signaling has also been described in the activation of peripheral lymphocytes,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref></sup> although no defect in T-cell activation was detected in Smo-deficient lymphocytes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup></p><p>Here, we investigated the function of Hh signaling at late stages of thymocyte development and in T-cell activation. By analysis of the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus, we show that Shh influences TCR repertoire selection and the transition from DP to SP. We also show that T-cell&#x02013;autonomous activation of the Hh pathway in developing thymocytes inhibited TCR repertoire selection, altering differentiation to SP and the CD4/CD8 SP ratio. In addition, we demonstrate that in mature T cells the transcriptional changes induced by Hh reduce the ability of the TCR to signal for activation and proliferation, by a mechanism upstream of ERK phosphorylation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Construction of <italic>lck</italic>-Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic</title><p><italic>Gli2</italic>&#x00394;<italic>N<sub>2</sub></italic> cDNA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref></sup> was blunt-end cloned into the <italic>Bam</italic>HI site of the lck proximal promoter cassette.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref></sup> The 8.9-kb transgene was isolated by <italic>Not</italic>I digestion and purified using QIAEXII Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). CBA &#x000d7; C57BL/6 oocytes were injected.</p></sec><sec><title>Mice</title><p><italic>lck-Gli2</italic>&#x00394;<italic>N<sub>2</sub></italic> transgene-positive mice were backcrossed for more than 7 generations with C57BL/6 (B&#x00026;K Universal, Grimston, England). Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> and Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice were crossed with HY-TCR transgenic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref></sup> and B6.21.6&#x003b2;-TCR transgenics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref></sup> Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref></sup> were on a C57BL/6 background.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup> Mice were maintained under United Kingdom Home Office regulations.</p></sec><sec><title>Genotyping</title><p>DNA was extracted using DNeasy tissue kit (Qiagen). Real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) for genomic <italic>Gli2</italic>&#x00394;<italic>N<sub>2</sub></italic> was carried out on an iCycler (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA) using the iQSYBR Green Supermix (Bio-Rad) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Primers were Gli2F AGAACCTGAAGACACACCTGCG and Gli2R GAGGCATTGGAGAAGGCTTTG. To enable comparison between samples, <italic>Gli2</italic> levels were normalized using levels of the <italic>J1.1</italic> germ-line gene (primers were 5&#x02032;J1.1GL CCTCATCCTATGGCACTG and 3&#x02032;J1.1GL GCTTTGTCCGAAGAGAGAC). Embryo sex was determined as described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Cell sorting</title><p>Thymocytes were sorted on a MoFlo (Cytomation, Fort Collins, CO). DN1-4 populations were sorted using antibodies against CD25<sup>FITC</sup>, CD3/4/8<sup>PE</sup>, and CD44<sup>Cychrome</sup>. Staining with CD3<sup>FITC</sup>, CD4<sup>PE</sup>, and CD8<sup>Cychome</sup> allowed sorting of DPs and SPs and CD8<sup>FITC</sup>, CD4<sup>PE</sup>, and B220<sup>Cychrome</sup> allowed sorting of peripheral SPs and B cells. Cells collected fell within FSC/SSC live gate.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative RT-PCR for Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene expression</title><p>RNA was extracted using Absolutely RNA Miniprep kit (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA) from fluorescence-activated cell sorter (FACS) cells. cDNA was synthesized using Superscript II (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) and quantitative reverse-transcription (RT)&#x02013;PCR carried out as described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref></sup> Primers were Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>F AGAACCTGAAGACACACCTGCG and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>R GAGGCATTGGAGAAGGCTTTG.</p></sec><sec><title>Antibodies and flow cytometry</title><p>Cells were stained as described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref></sup> using directly conjugated antibodies from BD PharMingen (San Diego, CA) and analyzed on a FACScan (BD Biosciences, Basel, Switzerland). Live cells were gated according to FSC/SSC profiles. Data are representative of more than 3 experiments.</p><p>CFSE (Sigma-Aldrich) labeling was carried out in PBS and 10 &#x003bc;M CFSE for 10 minutes at 25&#x000b0;C in the dark.</p><p>D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic><sup>PE</sup> tetramer (ProImmune, Oxford, United Kingdom) staining was prior to other antibody staining in PBS for 15 minutes at 25&#x000b0;C in the dark.</p></sec><sec><title>In vitro T-cell activation</title><p>Splenic T cells were cultured at 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>/mL in AIM-V (Life Technologies), 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup> M 2ME (Sigma-Aldrich) at 37&#x000b0;C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 (azide-free [NA/LE; BD PharMingen]) were at 0.01 &#x003bc;g/mL of each, unless otherwise stated.</p></sec><sec><title>Fetal thymus organ culture (FTOC)</title><p>FTOC was as described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> Modified recombinant human Shh, as described,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> was a gift from Curis (Cambridge, MA).</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of Erk1 and Erk2 phosphorylation</title><p>Splenic T cells at 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> in OptiMEM (Invitrogen) media were activated with 1 &#x003bc;g/mL anti-CD3&#x003f5; and anti-CD28 antibodies and incubated on ice for 30 minutes. For stimulation, cells were transferred to 37&#x000b0;C for 5, 15, 30, 45, and 60 minutes in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. After a short spin, cells were lysed on ice for 40 minutes and analyzed by immunoblotting using anti-Erk1, anti-Erk2, anti&#x02013;phospho-Erk, and anti&#x02013;phospho-Erk2 (Cell Signaling, Beverly, MA) as described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref></sup></p><p>For FACS analysis of intracellular phospho-Erk activation and staining were performed as described.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Expression of <bold><italic>Gli1</italic></bold> in SP thymocytes</title><p>The Hh signaling pathway has previously been shown to be involved in regulation of thymocyte development at the transition from DN1 to DN2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup> and at the transition from DN to DP cell.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref></sup> Genes encoding components of the signaling pathway, including Smo and Gli1, are expressed by DN thymocytes, and anti-Smo staining and RT-PCR analysis of transcription in sorted DN subsets have both shown that their expression is highest in the DN2 subset.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup> To assess activation status of the Hh signaling pathway at later stages of thymocyte development, we analyzed transcription of the Hh-target gene <italic>Gli1</italic> in sorted thymocyte populations. We found that <italic>Gli1</italic> transcription was down-regulated in the DN4 subset and DP population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). We did, however, detect an 11-fold increase in <italic>Gli1</italic> transcription from the DP to CD4SP population, and a 4-fold increase from the DP to CD8SP population, indicating active Hh signaling at later stages of T-cell development, in SP cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A). The detection of <italic>Gli1</italic> transcription in the CD4 and CD8 SP subsets is consistent with high cell surface expression of Smo on about 9% of CD4SP and 20% of CD8SP thymocytes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> Shh is expressed by epithelial cells in the medulla and corticomedullary junction,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup> and therefore expression of Gli1 and Smo in SP thymocytes is consistent with their location in the thymus, as like the early DN populations,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref></sup> they are located near the source of Shh.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Expression of <italic>Gli1</italic> and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> in WT and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic mice</bold>. (A) Hh activation status, shown by quantitative RT-PCR analysis of <italic>gli1</italic> mRNA in FACS-sorted populations of the adult murine thymus. (B) Quantitative PCR of genomic <italic>Gli2</italic>&#x00394;<italic>N<sub>2</sub></italic>, showing high copy number of the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene. (C) Relative <italic>Gli2</italic>&#x00394;<italic>N<sub>2</sub></italic> expression, by quantitative RT-PCR analysis, in thymus, lymph node, and spleen (D) and up-regulation of <italic>Gli1</italic> transcription in Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic CD4SP thymocytes. Error bars show standard deviation (SD). Data are representative of at least 3 experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh80090700520001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Transgenic <bold><italic>Gli2</italic></bold> expression in thymocytes</title><p>Given that the Hh signaling pathway is active in SP thymocytes, we investigated the function of Hh signaling at later stages of thymocyte development. We made a transgenic mouse that expressed an N-terminally truncated form of Gli2 under the control of the lck promoter. This truncated form of Gli2 (Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>) behaves as an activator of transcription independent of upstream effects on the pathway, thus constitutively activating Hh-dependent transcription in cells that express it,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref></sup> and allowing study of the effect of pathway activation specifically in thymocytes. Use of this <italic>lck</italic> cassette restricts transgene expression to thymocytes without affecting the thymic stroma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref></sup> Two independent studies using the <italic>lck</italic> cassette to drive expression of a GFP reporter gene have shown transgenic expression first in the DN2 and DN3 subsets, and that full expression is achieved at DN4. Expression is maintained in DP, SP, and peripheral T-cell populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref></sup></p><p>Transgenic mice were produced and quantitative PCR of genomic DNA using primers that amplify both transgenic and genomic <italic>Gli2</italic> gene demonstrated high copy number (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>B). Quantitative RT-PCR demonstrated <italic>Gli2</italic>&#x00394;<italic>N<sub>2</sub></italic> expression in transgenic thymocytes, splenocytes, and lymph node cells, with varying expression levels corresponding to the proportion of T-lineage cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>C). To confirm that the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> protein was functional and that it activated transcription of Hh-target genes, we analyzed the transcription of <italic>Gli1</italic> in sorted CD4SP thymocytes from Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic and wild-type (WT) littermate thymi. We found an approximately 20-fold increase in <italic>Gli1</italic> transcription in transgenic thymocytes, confirming thymocyte-autonomous activation of the downstream transcriptional changes induced by Hh signaling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>D).</p></sec><sec><title>Hh signaling in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic influences the ratio of CD4/CD8 SP cells</title><p>We analyzed lymphocyte populations in Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic mice. Thymus, lymph nodes, and spleen were grossly normal, with no significant differences in lymphocyte numbers in thymus or spleen between Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic and WT littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). Analysis of CD4 and CD8 expression revealed a statistically significant reduction in the proportion of CD4SP cells and an increase in the proportion of CD8SP cells in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic thymus, relative to littermates. Typically, 6.8% of thymocytes were CD4SP and 2.6% were CD8SP in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic, compared with 9.9% and 1.7%, respectively, in WT littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B), and the average ratio of CD4SP/CD8SP cells was reduced from 3.7 in WT to 2.3 in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>C). We also observed a significant increase in the percentage of DP cells in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic thymus, compared with littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). To determine if the change in CD4/CD8 ratio was genuinely the result of changes in the proportions of mature T cells rather than an increase in pre-DP immature CD8SP cells (ISPs), we analyzed CD3 and HSA expression. CD3 and HSA expression in the SP populations of Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic and WT littermate thymi were identical (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>D-E), excluding an increase in the ISP population. In both spleen and lymph nodes, we found a reduction in the CD4/CD8 T-cell ratio and the overall percentage of CD4 and CD8 T cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Phenotype of Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic mice</bold>. (A) Relative cell number (calculated relative to the mean of WT littermates) in the thymus and spleen of WT (gray bars, n = 6) and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic (&#x025a1;, n = 6). (B) CD4 and CD8 profiles in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic mouse. Thymocytes from Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic and WT littermates were analyzed for CD4 and CD8 expression in the thymus (top panels), spleen (middle panels), and lymph node (bottom panels). Differences between the percentage of populations between transgenic and littermate were statistically significant as given: (thymus) CD4SP, <italic>P</italic> = .005; DP, <italic>P</italic> = .014; (spleen) CD4, <italic>P</italic> = .002; CD8, <italic>P</italic> = .001; and (lymph node) CD4, <italic>P</italic> = .005; CD8, <italic>P</italic> = .041. (C) Bar chart to show change in CD4/CD8 ratio in thymus (WT [n = 6], Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> [n = 6], <italic>P</italic> = .032). (D) CD3 expression on CD4 (top histograms) and CD8 (bottom histograms) SP thymocytes. (E) HSA expression on CD4 (top) and CD8 (bottom) SP thymocytes. (F) CD2 expression on DP (top), CD4SP (middle), and CD8SP (bottom) cells in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic (right panels) and the WT (left panels). (G) CD5 expression on CD8SP cells in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic thymus (gray line) compared with the WT (black line). The bar chart shows mean MFI for WT (&#x025a9;) and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic (&#x025a1;). (H) CD69 expression on DP (top), CD4 (middle), and CD8 (bottom) SP thymocytes. Numbers in dot plots or histograms indicate the percentage of cells falling in the quadrant, region, or marker. Error bars show standard error (SE). Data are representative of at least 3 experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh80090700520002"/></fig><p>Strength of TCR signaling can influence CD4/CD8 lineage commitment in the thymus, with a strong TCR signal favoring differentiation to CD4SP.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33"/>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref></sup> We therefore analyzed expression of cell surface molecules associated with TCR signaling in thymocytes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref></sup> Expression of CD2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref></sup> was significantly increased on the DP population in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic, from 59% in WT to 83% of DP cells in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>F), but was unaffected on SP populations. Expression of CD5, a molecule linked to attenuation of the TCR signal,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref></sup> was lower on DP and SP populations in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic compared with WT littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>G). In the CD8SP population, 72% stained brightly in WT compared with 45% in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic, and mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) was reduced from 113.9 in the WT to 80.9 in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>G). Expression of CD69, a marker associated with repertoire selection and T-cell activation, was higher on CD8SP thymocytes in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic, with, in a typical experiment, 74% staining positive compared with 60% in the WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>H).</p></sec><sec><title>Increased differentiation to CD4SP in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus</title><p>Given that activation of the Hh signaling pathway in developing thymocytes reduced the ratio of CD4/CD8 SP thymocytes, we asked if removal of the Shh signal would have the opposing effect. Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> embryos die before birth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref></sup> and have defects in DN thymocyte proliferation and differentiation, but in FTOC they accumulate a normal proportion of DP cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup> We therefore cultured E14.5 Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and littermate thymi and analyzed the production of CD4SP cells. After 3 and 6 days in culture, the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymi contained a significantly greater proportion of CD4SP cells than those of littermates, indicating that Shh negatively regulates the transition from DP to CD4SP cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A-C). In E14.5+6-day FTOC, only 30% of SP cells express high cell surface CD3.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup> Therefore to confirm that the increase in the CD4SP population was due to the accumulation of mature T cells, we also analyzed differentiation to SP cells in E17.5 Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and littermate FTOC after 7 days. On E17.5, the thymus contained approximately 70% DP cells and there was no significant difference in the proportion of DP cells between Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and littermate thymi. Mature SP cells had not arisen, facilitating investigation of the transition from DP to SP. In a typical experiment, the ratio of CD4/CD8 SP cells was increased from 2.6 in the Shh<sup>+/+</sup> to 3.4 in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> FTOC. The proportion of CD4SP cells was significantly increased from 13% in Shh<sup>+/+</sup> FTOC to 21.2% in Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> FTOC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D). There was no difference in the proportion of CD3<sup>high</sup> cells in each SP population between Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and Shh<sup>+/+</sup> littermate cultures, indicating that the increase in CD4SP cells was genuinely due to the accumulation of mature cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D). Of interest, CD69 expression was increased in the CD4SP Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D). Therefore, under all culture conditions the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus favored the production of CD4SP over CD8SP cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>E).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Increased differentiation to CD4SP in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus</bold>. (A) CD4 and CD8 staining of E14.5 Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup>, and Shh<sup>+/+</sup> FTOC littermates, cultured for 6 days. Mean thymus sizes were 2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> for Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, 1.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> for Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup>, and 1.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> for Shh<sup>+/+</sup>. (B-C) Bar charts to show the relative proportion of CD4SP thymocytes in E14.5 Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and littermate FTOC after 3 (B) and 6 (C) days in culture. For each thymus, the proportion of CD4SP cells was calculated relative to the mean proportion in WT littermates. The difference in the relative proportion of CD4SP cells between Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and Shh<sup>+/+</sup> thymi was statistically significant: <italic>P</italic> = .006 for 3-day cultures (WT [n = 7], Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> [n = 5]), <italic>P</italic> = .022 for 6-day cultures (WT [n = 7], Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> [n = 6]). (D) CD4 and CD8 staining of E17.5 Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup>, and Shh<sup>+/+</sup> FTOC littermates, cultured for 7 days. The average percentage of CD4SPs in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> was increased 1.4 times compared with littermates (<italic>P</italic> = .046). The ratio of CD4/CD8 SP cells was 2.6 in Shh<sup>+/+</sup> FTOC and 3.4 in Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> FTOC. Bar charts to show CD3 and CD69 expression on CD4 and CD8 SP thymocytes in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (&#x025a1;, n = 3) and littermates (&#x025a9;, n = 14). Mean thymus sizes were 9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> for Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, 1.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> for Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup>, and 1.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> for Shh<sup>+/+</sup>. (E) Bar chart to show mean CD4/CD8 ratio for the different culture conditions. (F) Bar chart to show mean SP/DP ratio for the different culture conditions. Error bars show SE. Data are representative of at least 3 experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh80090700520003"/></fig><p>When we compared the ratio of SP/DP in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus to that of littermates, we found an increased ratio under all culture conditions. Thus, despite the smaller size of the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup> the DP population gave rise to relatively more SP cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>F).</p></sec><sec><title>Shh treatment reduced the CD4/CD8 ratio and CD5 expression in thymus explants</title><p>Given that the production of mature CD4SP cells was increased in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus, we asked if treatment of WT FTOC with recombinant Shh (r-Shh) could reduce differentiation to CD4SP. We treated E17.5 FTOC with r-Shh for 7 days. Typically, the percentage of DP cells in r-Shh&#x02013;treated cultures increased to 78.5% compared with 70.7% in the control, whereas the proportion of CD4SP cells was decreased from 15% in control to 9.3% in treated cultures. When we compared the ratio of mature (CD3<sup>high</sup>) CD4/CD8 SP cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A), we found a dose-dependent reduction with maximum inhibition at 0.05 &#x003bc;g/mL r-Shh. CD5 expression was reduced in r-Shh&#x02013;treated FTOC relative to controls in DP and SP populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B), consistent with the duller expression observed in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic thymus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>G).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Shh treatment reduced CD5 expression and the CD4/CD8 ratio in thymus explants</bold>. (A) CD4 and CD8 profiles of 7-day C57BL/6 E17.5 FTOC control and treated with 0.05 &#x003bc;g/mL r-Shh. The bar chart shows the mean ratio of mature (CD3<sup>high</sup>) CD4/CD8 SP in 7-day FTOC for Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and C57BL/6 E17.5 cultured with the stated concentration of recombinant Shh (r-Shh). For all treatments, n = 4. Mean cell recovery was as follows: control, 1.87 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>; 0.5 &#x003bc;g/mL r-Shh, 1.66 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>; 0.05 &#x003bc;g/mL r-Shh, 2.07 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>; 0.005 &#x003bc;g/mL r-Shh, 2.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>; and 0.0005 &#x003bc;g/mL r-Shh, 1.54 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>. (B) CD5 expression on r-Shh&#x02013;treated FTOC. Overlaid histograms of CD5 expression gated on the subsets from the FACS plots above for control cultures (gray filled) and r-Shh&#x02013;treated cultures (gray line only, no fill). MFIs were (control/+ r-Shh) as follows: DP, 424.5/219.6; CD4SP, 1197.7/586.6; and CD8SP, 425.3/220.8. The bar chart shows MFI for the control (&#x025a9;) and Shh-treated (&#x025a1;) cultures. (C) CD4 and CD8 profiles of 10-day C57BL/6 E17.5 FTOC control and treated with 0.5 &#x003bc;g/mL r-Shh. Mean cell recovery was as follows: control, 1.34 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>; 0.5 &#x003bc;g/mL r-Shh, 1.44 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>. (D) Profiles of CD4 and CD8, gated on CD3<sup>high</sup> of 10-day C57BL/6 FTOC control and treated with 0.5 &#x003bc;g/mL r-Shh.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh80090700520004"/></fig><p>When E17.5 FTOC were cultured for 10 days, Shh treatment again reduced differentiation from DP to CD4SP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). Gating on CD3<sup>high</sup> cells revealed a relative increase in the proportion of CD8SP cells from 14.9% in the control to 27.1% in Shh-treated cultures, concomitant with the decrease in the CD4SP population. Overall, the ratio of mature (CD3<sup>high</sup>) CD4/CD8 SP cells was reduced from 4.7 in the control to 2.1 in the Shh-treated cultures.</p><p>Taken together, these data show that Shh signaling is involved in regulating differentiation from DP to SP and CD4/CD8 ratio. Absence of Shh increased production of CD4SP cells, but Hh pathway activation, both by thymocyte autonomous Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> expression in vivo and by treatment with r-Shh in vitro, decreased cell surface CD5 expression and the production of CD4SP cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Negative selection is compromised in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR transgenic male thymus</title><p>The pattern of expression of CD2, CD5, and CD69 in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> thymus together with the opposing effects of removal or activation of the Shh signal on differentiation from DP to CD4SP cell suggested that Hh signaling influences the later stages of thymocyte development by a TCR-dependent mechanism, and that activation of the Hh signaling pathway in thymocytes might lower the strength of the TCR signal. Therefore, to assess the effect of Hh signaling on repertoire selection we crossed the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic with transgenic mice expressing the HY-TCR.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref></sup> The HY-TCR recognizes a male-specific peptide from the <italic>Smcy</italic> gene presented by H-2D<sup>b</sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref></sup> allowing assessment of negative selection in male mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref></sup> As expected, male HY-TCR mice showed efficient clonal deletion of CD8SP and DP cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). However, in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR thymus we found an increase in the percentage of DP cells and the presence of a small population of CD8SPs that had escaped deletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). This population made up 2.5% of thymocytes and was absent in HY-TCR littermates. It expressed high levels of CD8 and CD69, and stained bright with anti-V&#x003b2;8 and D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic> tetramer, confirming that it expressed the transgenic male-reactive TCR and had genuinely escaped negative selection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). We found that a small proportion (&#x0223c; 3%) of peripheral lymph node cells expressed high levels of CD8 and stained brightly with D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic> tetramer in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR mice, which were absent in male HY-TCR littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B)</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> expression influences TCR repertoire selection</bold>. (A) Thymus phenotype of male mice with the transgenic HY-TCR. CD4 and CD8 expression in HY-TCR&#x02013;positive mice with (Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR) and HY-TCR littermates without the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene. Mean thymus sizes were 2.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> for HY-TCR and 2.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> for Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR. The histograms show D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic> tetramer, V&#x003b2;8, and CD69 staining on CD8SP cells from the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR. The bar chart shows the percentage of CD8 D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic>-positive cells in the HY-TCR (n = 12) and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR (n = 8) thymus (<italic>P</italic> = &#x0003c; .001). (B) Peripheral phenotype of male mice with the HY transgenic TCR. CD4 and CD8 profile of a Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR lymph node. The bar chart shows the percentage of CD8 D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic>-positive cells in HY-TCR (n = 12) and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR (n = 8) lymph node (<italic>P</italic> = &#x0003c; .001). The histograms show D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic> and V&#x003b2;8 expression on CD8 T cells from the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR. (C) Lymph node of male mice with the B6.2.16&#x003b2; transgenic TCR. Bar chart to show the relative number of CD8<sup>+</sup> D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic><sup>bright</sup> cells in B6.2.16&#x003b2;-positive mice (B6) and B6.2.16&#x003b2;Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>-positive mice (Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>B6) (<italic>P</italic> = .021, n = 4, n = 5, respectively). The histograms show V&#x003b2;8 expression on CD8 T cells. (D) Thymus phenotype of HY-TCR female mice. CD4 and CD8 profiles of HY-TCR and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR mice (left dot plots). Mean thymus sizes were 8.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> for HY-TCR and 8.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> for Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR. CD4 and CD8 profiles gated on D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic>-positive cells in the HY-TCR and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR thymus (right dot plots). The percentages of cells falling in the D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic>-positive gate were typically 9.6% in the HY-TCR and 9.4% in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR. (E) Peripheral phenotype of HY-TCR female mice. CD4 and CD8 profiles in HY-TCR and Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR mice. Numbers in dot plots or histograms indicate the percentage of cells falling in the quadrant, region, or marker. Error bars show SE. Data are representative of at least 3 experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh80090700520005"/></fig><p>In the male HY-TCR transgenic model, negative selection in the thymus can commence at an earlier developmental stage than would occur physiologically because of early expression of the &#x003b1;&#x003b2;TCR in DN cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref></sup> To confirm that inhibition of clonal deletion was not restricted to early TCR&#x003b1; expression, we analyzed the effect of the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene on negative selection in male TCR&#x003b2; chain&#x02013;only transgenic mice, B6.2.16&#x003b2;.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref></sup> The B6.2.16&#x003b2; mice express the same TCR&#x003b2; chain as the HY-TCR transgenic, but the TCR&#x003b1; chain is variable and male-reactive D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic>-binding T cells are deleted in the male animals. The proportion of CD8SP cells (all of which expressed the transgenic &#x003b2; chain) that stained brightly with D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic> tetramer in the lymph node was more than doubled in the presence of the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C). Thus, clonal deletion of self-reactive thymocytes was also compromised in Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>B6.2.16&#x003b2; male mice.</p></sec><sec><title>Hh signaling influences positive selection in HY-TCR transgenic female mice</title><p>In the female Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR thymus, we found an increased proportion of CD8SPs compared with the control HY-TCR female, together with a decrease in the CD4SP population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>D), as observed in the non-TCR transgenic Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> thymus. On first consideration, it therefore seemed that the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene might actually be enhancing positive selection of the transgenic &#x003b1;&#x003b2;TCR to the CD8 lineage. However, when we gated on D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic><sup>bright</sup> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>D), we consistently found a reduction in the proportion of CD8SP cells and increase in DP cells in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR thymus compared with littermates, indicative of reduced positive selection of the transgenic &#x003b1;&#x003b2;TCR. In a representative experiment the percentage of D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic><sup>bright</sup> cells that was CD8SP was reduced from 55.1% in the control HY-TCR thymus to 49.2% in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR thymus, whereas the total percentage of D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic><sup>bright</sup> thymocytes was unaffected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>D).</p><p>In lymph nodes, the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene caused a reduction in CD4 and CD8 peripheral T cells. The CD8 population was reduced from 14% to 10% and the CD4SP population from 35% to 23% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>E), suggesting that Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> expression also affected peripheral T-cell expansion and homeostasis.</p></sec><sec><title>Altered TCR repertoire selection in Shh mutant thymus</title><p>To ask if Shh affects TCR repertoire selection in a physiological situation, we introduced the transgenic HY-TCR onto the Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> background and compared positive selection in young adult female Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR and their littermate thymi. We found increased positive selection of the transgenic TCR to the CD8 lineage in the Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR thymus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A) with an overall increase in the proportion of CD8SP thymocytes from 11% to 16%. When we gated on D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic><sup>bright</sup> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A) the proportion of CD8SP cells was consistently increased, typically from 39% in the Shh<sup>+/+</sup> littermate to 49% in the Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> thymus, whereas the proportion of DP cells was decreased from 60% in the Shh<sup>+/+</sup> to 49% in the Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> thymus.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Altered TCR repertoire selection in Shh mutant thymus</bold>. (A) Thymus phenotype of 4-week-old Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR female mice. CD4 and CD8 profiles of HY-TCR and Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR littermate mice (left dot plots). Mean thymus sizes were 3.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> for HY-TCR and 4.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> for Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR. CD4 and CD8 profiles gated on D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic>-positive cells in the HY-TCR and Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR thymus (right dot plots). (B) Thymus phenotype of E17.5 Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR female FTOC cultured for 10 days. CD4 and CD8 profiles of HY-TCR and Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR littermate FTOC. Bar chart shows the relative percentage of transgenic (Tg) TCR<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>bright</sup> SP cells for HY-TCR (n = 3) and Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR (n = 3); <italic>P</italic> = .027. The histograms show V&#x003b2;8 and T3.70 (transgenic TCR&#x003b1; chain) staining on CD8SP cells. (C) Thymus phenotype of 12-day-old Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR male. CD4 and CD8 profiles of HY-TCR and Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR littermates. Mean thymus sizes were 2.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> for HY-TCR and 2.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>7</sup> for Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR. Bar charts show the relative percentage of transgenic (Tg) TCR<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>bright</sup> SP or DP cells for HY-TCR (n = 3) and Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR (n = 3); <italic>P</italic> = .019. The histograms show V&#x003b2;8 and T3.70 expression on CD8SP cells. (D) Thymus phenotype of E19 Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR male. CD4 and CD8 profiles of HY-TCR, Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR, and Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR littermates. Mean thymus sizes were 2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> for HY-TCR, 2.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> for Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR, and 1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> for Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR. Bar charts show the relative percentage of Tg TCR<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>bright</sup> SP or DP cells for HY-TCR (n = 4), Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR (n = 4, <italic>P</italic> = .034), and Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR (n = 3, <italic>P</italic> = .018). The histograms show D<sup>b</sup><italic>Smcy</italic> and T3.70 staining on CD8SP cells. Numbers in dot plots indicate the percentage of cells falling in the quadrant. Error bars show SE. Data are representative of at least 3 experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh80090700520006"/></fig><p>To analyze positive selection in the complete absence of Shh, we cultured female E17.5 Shh<sup>+/+</sup> HY-TCR and Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR littermate FTOC for 10 days. The proportion of HY-TCR<sup>+</sup> CD8SP cells was increased approximately 3-fold (<italic>P</italic> = .027), from 8% in the Shh<sup>+/+</sup> HY-TCR to 23% in the Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR thymus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). Thus, in contrast to the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>HY-TCR thymus, we found that in both the embryo and the adult, mutation of Shh increased positive selection of the HY-TCR.</p><p>In the adult male HY-TCR thymus, clonal deletion is efficient and complete (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A and Kisielow et al<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>), and so we could not test if reduction in Shh copy number increased deletion. In the embryo, clonal deletion starts at E18 and a significant proportion of DP and CD8SP cells persists at birth and in the neonate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref></sup> We therefore analyzed negative selection in the fetal and neonatal thymus.</p><p>In 12-day-old male Shh<sup>+/+</sup> HY-TCR thymi, we detected a small population of HY-TCR<sup>+</sup> CD8SP (&#x0223c; 5%) and DP (&#x0223c; 4%) cells, which were significantly reduced (<italic>P</italic> = .019) to approximately 3.5% and 2%, respectively, in Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> HY-TCR littermates, indicating more efficient clonal deletion in the Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> thymus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). On E19, the proportion of HY-TCR<sup>+</sup> CD8SP and DP cells was significantly reduced (<italic>P</italic> = .018) from 19% and 17%, respectively, in the Shh<sup>+/+</sup> thymus to only 12% and 4% in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> littermate thymus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>D). The Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> thymus gave an intermediate phenotype (<italic>P</italic> = .034). Therefore, we again found that removal of Shh increased the efficiency of TCR repertoire selection, in this case increasing negative selection of the self-reactive transgenic TCR. These data support the hypothesis that under physiological conditions, Shh modulates TCR signal strength in developing thymocytes.</p></sec><sec><title>Attenuated T-cell activation in peripheral Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic T cells</title><p>Given that activation or reduction of Hh signaling altered the outcome of TCR ligation in thymocytes, we investigated the effect of Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> expression on peripheral T-cell activation. We confirmed <italic>Gli2</italic>&#x00394;<italic>N<sub>2</sub></italic> transgene expression and up-regulation of <italic>Gli1</italic> transcription by quantitative RT-PCR in sorted CD4 and CD8 T-cell populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A). As expected from previous expression studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref></sup> the transgene was highly expressed in CD4 and CD8 T cells, and not detected in B cells. Transcription of <italic>Gli1</italic> was up-regulated in both T-cell populations, confirming functional activity of the transgene. To assay T-cell activation, we stimulated splenocytes with anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 antibodies. After 24 hours, induction of cell surface expression of the early activation marker CD69 was inhibited in both CD4 and CD8 T cells from Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic spleens. In a typical experiment, only 18% of Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic CD4 T cells expressed CD69, compared with more than 60% of WT CD4 T cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B). Expression of the later activation marker CD25 was also decreased in Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic cultures on both CD4 and CD8 T cells, from 47% and 72% in WT CD4 and CD8 T populations, respectively, to 17% and 9% in their Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B). These data show that activation of Hh signaling in T cells attenuated T-cell activation.</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> expression impairs TCR-induced activation and proliferation of peripheral T cells and reduces ERK phosphorylation</bold>. (A) Quantitative RT-PCR analysis of Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene expression in FACS-sorted peripheral T-cell populations (left graph). The right graph shows up-regulation of <italic>Gli1</italic> transcription on CD4 and CD8 T cells in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> (&#x025a9;) compared with the WT (&#x025a1;). Error bars represent SD. (B) Histograms showing the early activation marker CD69 (top panels) and the later activation marker CD25, on CD4 and CD8 SP cells after 24 hours in culture stimulated with 0.01 &#x003bc;g/mL of each of anti-CD3 and anti-CD28. Gray fill indicates WT; no fill, Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub>. Numbers indicate the percentage of cells falling within the marker. (In all unstimulated controls, CD69 expression was approximately 5%, and CD25 expression was approximately 8%; data not shown). (C) Bar graphs to show cell divisions using CFSE staining in CD4 cells cultured for 96 hours with 0.01 &#x003bc;g/mL of each of anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 with (middle panel) and without (left panel) 20 IU/mL IL-2. The numbers 0-7 represent the number of divisions for cells falling in the marker. Gray indicates WT; white, Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic. The bar graph on the far right shows the percentage of CFSE-labeled cells falling in the markers for 5 to 8 divisions for the WT and the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic with and without IL-2. (D) Bar graph shows proliferation for WT and the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic cultured in 0.1, 0.01, and 0.001 &#x003bc;g/mL of each of anti-CD3 and anti-CD28. (E) Western blot showing the levels of phosphorylated (upper panel) Erk1 and Erk2 kinases in WT and Gli&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic splenocytes stimulated with 1 &#x003bc;g/mL of each of anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 for the indicated period of time. For comparison, the total levels of Erk kinases expressed in the cytoplasm of stimulated cells is shown (lower panel). (F) Intracellular phosphorylated ERK (p-Erk) on CD4<sup>+</sup> cells. Top left histogram shows the CD4<sup>+</sup> gate. The right histograms show intracellular p-Erk levels in unactivated CD4<sup>+</sup> (dashed line) and CD4<sup>+</sup> activated with 1 &#x003bc;g/mL of each of anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 for 2 minutes (gray line). The bar chart shows the MFI (unactivated/activated) for WT (10.0/19.1) and Gli&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> (7.4/11.5). (G) Histograms to show basal intracellular p-Erk in WT (top, MFI = 45.2) and Gli&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> (bottom, MFI = 29.0) thymocytes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh80090700520007"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Proliferation of activated T cells is compromised by the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene</title><p>To assess proliferation, splenocytes were labeled with CFSE and stimulated with anti-CD3 and anti-CD28. The Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic T cells were unable to proliferate as well as their WT counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>C). After 96 hours, only 20% of Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic CD4 T cells had undergone 4 to 7 divisions compared with more than 50% of WT CD4 T cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>C). Addition of IL-2 to the cultures overcame the inhibition of proliferation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>C). We titrated the strength of activation signal given by anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 antibodies. Although at low antibody concentration proliferation was suboptimal in the WT cultures, we consistently saw approximately 50% fewer CD4 T cells that had undergone 4 or more divisions in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic cultures compared with WT cultures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>D).</p></sec><sec><title>Hh signaling reduces TCR signal strength and inhibits TCR-induced ERK phosphorylation</title><p>To measure directly the effect of Hh signaling on TCR signals, we stimulated splenocytes from Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic and littermate mice with antibodies against CD3 and CD28 and measured MAPK activation by following the kinetics of ERK phosphorylation by Western blot. Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> expression inhibited TCR-induced MAPK activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>E). In WT splenocytes, strong activation of ERK2 was observed within 5 minutes of stimulus, and full phosphorylation of ERK1 and ERK2 kinases was detected after 30 minutes. In contrast, activation of ERK2 in Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic splenocytes was much delayed and reduced, and ERK1 failed to activate to normal levels during the experiment. To confirm that this reduction in ERK phosphorylation was T-cell specific, we used a FACS-based assay<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref></sup> to compare Erk phosphorylation in the CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cell population. Gating on CD4<sup>+</sup> cells, the MFI of intracellular anti&#x02013;phospho-ERK on unactivated cells was slightly lower in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> compared with WT spleen. On TCR ligation, there was a clear shift in the WT intracellular anti&#x02013;phospho-ERK staining, with a doubling in MFI. In contrast, the shift in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> T cells was negligible (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>F). Thus, expression of the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene inhibited TCR-induced activation by a mechanism upstream of ERK phosphorylation.</p><p>Given that basal phospho-ERK levels were reduced in Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> peripheral T cells, we also measured ERK phosphorylation in thymocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>G). The MFI of intracellular anti&#x02013;phospho-ERK was reduced, typically from 45 in WT to 29 in Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> thymocytes. This reduction in basal ERK phosphorylation is consistent with reduction in TCR signal strength during repertoire selection in the Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Here, we show that the transcriptional events induced by activation of the Hh signaling pathway in mature peripheral T cells resulted in a reduction of TCR signal strength, profoundly inhibiting the ability of the TCR to transduce signals for activation and proliferation. Likewise, activation of the Hh signaling pathway in thymocytes changed the outcome of TCR ligation at many stages of development: allowing self-reactive T cells to escape clonal deletion; reducing transgenic TCR-mediated positive selection of CD8 T cells; and reducing the ratio of CD4/CD8 SP cells produced in the thymus. In contrast, in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus the CD4/CD8 ratio was affected in the opposite way, and differentiation from DP to CD4SP was increased. Both positive and negative selection of a transgenic TCR were also increased, demonstrating that Shh does indeed influence TCR repertoire selection and the transition from DP to SP cell in a physiological situation. Taken together, the consequences for thymocyte development of removal of the Shh signal (in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus), or activation of Hh signaling in vivo (by Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> expression) and in vitro (by Shh treatment), all strongly support the hypothesis that Hh signaling in thymocytes modulates TCR signal strength.</p><p>Reduction of TCR signal strength by Hh-dependent transcription has many consequences for thymocyte development and peripheral immunity, as the outcome of TCR ligation would depend on the Hh microenvironment of the cell. Hh proteins have been shown to function as morphogens,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref></sup> produced at localized sources and specifying different cell fates in a concentration-dependent manner. Thymocytes move through distinct areas of the thymus at different stages of their development,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref></sup> and therefore will receive different strengths of Hh signal at different stages. Our data suggest that their location in the thymus, relative to the source of Hh, will influence the outcome of TCR ligation (positive or negative selection, CD4/CD8 lineage decisions). Of interest, Shh is expressed by epithelial cells scattered in the medulla and corticomedullary junction, and the thymocyte populations that are located in this part of the thymus (early DN populations and SPs) show highest expression of the Hh-target gene <italic>Gli1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). As not all medullary epithelial cells express Shh,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></sup> it is possible that those that express Shh are specialized for a particular function in TCR repertoire selection.</p><p>In the periphery, Hh signaling could function to change the threshold of T-cell activation and influence TCR-dependent T-cell fate decisions, such as TH1/TH2 differentiation or the induction of anergy. Shh is expressed by follicular dendritic cells,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref></sup> but Hh proteins are also expressed in skin, gut, and lung, where they are involved in tissue homeostasis and renewal.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref></sup> These tissues as sites of frequent immune challenge by pathogens are also subject to many inflammatory and autoimmune diseases, and Hh expression could function to reduce the initial threshold for T-cell activation. Up-regulation of Hh proteins during renewal or remodeling after infection or tissue damage could further influence T-lymphocyte populations at sites of damage.</p><p>Inappropriate activation of the Hh signaling pathway has been implicated in many cancers,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref></sup> and expression of Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> under the control of the keratin-5 promoter increased the incidence of skin tumors in mice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref></sup> Of interest, we have not observed T-cell tumors in Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic mice, although we have maintained the colony for 3 years (N.J.R., unpublished observation, February 2004 to present).</p><p>Inhibition of TCR signaling by Hh-induced transcriptional changes involves compromised MAPKinase activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>E-G). It is unclear why addition of IL-2 restores proliferation of activated Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> peripheral T cells, but one possibility is that the defect in proliferation is directly due to a decrease in IL2 transcription caused by the reduction in ERK activation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref></sup> How Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> inhibits TCR-induced ERK phosphorylation remains to be determined, but both TCR and Hh signaling require PKA activity, which may therefore be involved in interactions between the 2 pathways.</p><p>It has previously been reported that addition of Shh to partially purified T-cell populations in vitro enhanced the induction of T-cell activation and proliferation by suboptimal concentrations of anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 antibody, whereas addition of anti-Hh antibody to these cultures reduced activation and proliferation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref></sup> In contrast, our data indicate that the Hh pathway can inhibit T-cell activation and proliferation. There are several possible explanations for this discrepancy: Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgene expression was restricted to T cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A), but addition of Shh to partially purified T-cell populations might affect T-cell activation indirectly through another cell type present in the culture. Alternatively, differences in the method or strength of activation of the signaling pathway may lead to differences in the relative timing of complete induction of Hh and TCR signaling.</p><p>Recently,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup> conditional deletion of Smo from T-lineage cells has failed to reveal any positive or negative influence on anti-CD3 induced T-cell proliferation in vitro. From the data presented here, we predict that Smo-deficient T cells transduce a stronger TCR signal than WT T cells, and therefore that differences in proliferation would be detectable only if a suboptimal anti-CD3 signal were given. In the same study, early Smo deletion in the thymus confirmed that Hh positively signals for survival and proliferation of early DN cells,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup> but did not influence later stages of T-cell development. Our experiments show that Hh signaling is involved at the transition from DP to SP cell and in TCR repertoire selection. We observed increased CD4/CD8 ratio and TCR repertoire selection in the Shh<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> thymus after backcrossing our Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> colony onto a pure C57BL/6 background<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></sup> and introducing a transgenic TCR, whereas in the conditional Smo study the mice were outbred and effects on TCR repertoire were not examined.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref></sup></p><p>We have previously shown that addition of Shh to FTOC negatively regulated the transition from DN to DP cell, whereas treatment with anti-Hh antibody enhanced differentiation to DP cell.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref></sup> The Gli2&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> transgenic confirms that Hh can act as a negative regulator of TCR signaling, but inhibition of pre-TCR signaling for differentiation from DN to DP cell was not observed. Similarly, transgenic mice that express dominant-negative components of the MAPKinase cascade under the control of the <italic>lck</italic> promoter have failed to show reduced differentiation to DP cell, despite the fact that MAPKinase activation is downstream of pre-TCR signaling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref></sup> The reason why use of this transgenic cassette is not ideal for dissecting signaling events downstream of the pre-TCR signal is unclear, but it may reflect incomplete transgene expression in the DN subsets,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref></sup> or powerful pre-TCR independent mechanisms that allow recovery of the DP population.</p><p>In summary, we have shown that that the Hh signaling pathway influences TCR repertoire selection in the thymus and can reduce the strength of the TCR signal in mature peripheral T cells, having profound effects for T-cell development and function. It will be important to test the consequences of Hh-induced reduction in TCR signal strength in peripheral immunity and human disease.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>An Inside <italic>Blood</italic> analysis of this article appears at the front of this issue.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>The publication costs of this article were defrayed in part by page charge payment. Therefore, and solely to indicate this fact, this article is hereby marked &#x0201c;advertisement&#x0201d; in accordance with 18 USC section 1734.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by the MRC, BBSRC, Leukemia Research Fund, and Wellcome Trust</p><p>We thank Ross Anders for microinjection, Tony Magee for his support, Derek Davies (CRUK FACS laboratory) for sorting, Philip Beachy for Shh<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice, Hiroshi Sasaki for the Gli&#x00394;N<sub>2</sub> plasmid, and Curis for r-Shh.</p></ack><sec><title>Authorship</title><p>Contribution: All authors contributed experimentally and in preparation of the paper.</p><p>Conflict-of-interest disclosure: The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p><p>Correspondence: Tessa Crompton, Division of Cell and Molecular Biology, Imperial College London, Sir Alexander Fleming Building, South Kensington Campus, London SW7 2AZ, United Kingdom; e-mail: <email>t.crompton@imperial.ac.uk</email>.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingham</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hedgehog signaling in animal development: paradigms and principles.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>3059</fpage><lpage>3087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731473</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taipale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beachy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Hedgehog and Wnt signalling pathways in cancer.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>411</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11357142</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Murdoch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sonic hedgehog induces the proliferation of primitive human hematopoietic cells via BMP regulation.</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175816</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Outram</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Varas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepicelli</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Crompton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hedgehog signaling regulates differentiation from double-negative to double-positive thymocyte.</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10981962</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hager-Theodorides</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Outram</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Varas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crompton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced thymocyte development in sonic hedgehog knockout embryos.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2004</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>2296</fpage><lpage>2306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14764698</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacedon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Varas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Lopez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of hedgehog proteins in the human thymus.</article-title><source>J Histochem Cytochem</source><year>2003</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1557</fpage><lpage>1566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14566027</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hager-Theodorides</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dessens</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Outram</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Crompton</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The transcription factor Gli3 regulates differentiation of fetal CD4- CD8- double-negative thymocytes.</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2005</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>1296</fpage><lpage>1304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855276</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andaloussi</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mashayekhi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aifantis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hedgehog signaling controls thymocyte progenitor homeostasis and differentiation in the thymus.</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16518394</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutierrez-Frias</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacedon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Lopez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sonic hedgehog regulates early human thymocyte differentiation by counteracting the IL-7-induced development of CD34+ precursor cells.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2004</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>5046</fpage><lpage>5053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15470048</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuniga-Pflucker</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of thymocyte differentiation: pre-TCR signals and beta-selection.</article-title><source>Semin Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12220932</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Boehmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisielow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Negative selection of the T-cell repertoire: where and when does it occur?</article-title><source>Immunol Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>209</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16448549</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T-cell development and the CD4-CD8 lineage decision.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12033737</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mouse Gli1 mutants are viable but have defects in SHH signaling in combination with a Gli2 mutation.</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2000</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>1593</fpage><lpage>1605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10725236</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishizaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakafuku</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of Gli2 and Gli3 activities by an amino-terminal repression domain: implication of Gli2 and Gli3 as primary mediators of Shh signaling.</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1999</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>3915</fpage><lpage>3924</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10433919</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Freer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zinyk</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Specific and redundant functions of Gli2 and Gli3 zinc finger genes in skeletal patterning and development.</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1997</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9006072</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matise</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyner</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gli2 is required for induction of floor plate and adjacent cells, but not most ventral neurons in the mouse central nervous system.</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1998</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>2759</fpage><lpage>2770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9655799</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Auerbach</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyner</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gli2, but not Gli1, is required for initial Shh signaling and ectopic activation of the Shh pathway.</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>4753</fpage><lpage>4761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12361967</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>te Welscher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Teran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ros</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutual genetic antagonism involving GLI3 and dHAND prepatterns the vertebrate limb bud mesenchyme prior to SHH signaling.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11850405</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowrey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sonic hedgehog promotes cell cycle progression in activated peripheral CD4(+) T lymphocytes.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>1869</fpage><lpage>1875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12165511</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowrey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakelin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sonic hedgehog signaling modulates activation of and cytokine production by human peripheral CD4+ T cells.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>5451</fpage><lpage>5457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12421920</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaffin</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Beals</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkie</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbush</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlmutter</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissection of thymocyte signaling pathways by in vivo expression of pertussis toxin ADP-ribosyltransferase.</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1990</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3821</fpage><lpage>3829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2123451</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kisielow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bluthmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Staerz</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>von Boehmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tolerance in T-cell-receptor transgenic mice involves deletion of nonmature CD4+8+ thymocytes.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1988</year><volume>333</volume><fpage>742</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3260350</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uematsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dembic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In transgenic mice the introduced functional T cell receptor beta gene prevents expression of endogenous beta genes.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1988</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3258191</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Litingtung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cyclopia and defective axial patterning in mice lacking Sonic hedgehog gene function.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8837770</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and sequence analysis of a mouse Y chromosome RNA transcript expressed in the testis.</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1987</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2959</fpage><lpage>2969</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3562242</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cebecauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CD8+ cytotoxic T lymphocyte activation by soluble major histocompatibility complex-peptide dimers.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>23820</fpage><lpage>23828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805102</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosewell</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Treisman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ternary complex factor SAP-1 is required for Erk-mediated thymocyte positive selection.</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14770179</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Prockop</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Porritt</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrie</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping precursor movement through the postnatal thymus reveals specific microenvironments supporting defined stages of early lymphoid development.</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11457887</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buckland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-ordination of the expression of the protein tyrosine kinase p56(lck) with the pre-T cell receptor during thymocyte development.</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10602022</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progression of T cell lineage restriction in the earliest subpopulation of murine adult thymus visualized by the expression of lck proximal promoter activity.</article-title><source>Int Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11133839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kappes</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CD4-CD8 lineage commitment: an inside view.</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16034433</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bommhardt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Basson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Krummrei</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamoyska</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of the extracellular signal-related kinase/mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway discriminates CD4 versus CD8 lineage commitment in the thymus.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1999</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10395662</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strength of signal: a fundamental mechanism for cell fate specification.</article-title><source>Immunol Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>209</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16448542</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernandez-Hoyos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothenberg</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberola-Ila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lck activity controls CD4/CD8 T cell lineage commitment.</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10755618</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikemizu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fugger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Merwe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nature of molecular recognition by T cells.</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12605231</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azzam</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>DeJarnette</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fine tuning of TCR signaling by CD5.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>5464</fpage><lpage>5472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11313384</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markiewicz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Girao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Opferman</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term T cell memory requires the surface expression of self-peptide/major histocompatibility complex molecules.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>3065</fpage><lpage>3070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9501216</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandau</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jameson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogquist</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The timing of TCR alpha expression critically influences T cell development and selection.</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>202</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15998791</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teh</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgulya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>von Boehmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kisielow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early deletion and late positive selection of T cells expressing a male-specific receptor in T-cell receptor transgenic mice.</article-title><source>Dev Immunol</source><year>1990</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2152099</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Boehmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental biology of T cells in T cell-receptor transgenic mice.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>1990</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2188673</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurdon</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourillot</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphogen gradient interpretation.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>413</volume><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11677596</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacedon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Diez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sonic hedgehog is produced by follicular dendritic cells and protects germinal center B cells from apoptosis.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>1456</fpage><lpage>1461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15661904</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Goich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dissecting the oncogenic potential of Gli2: deletion of an NH(2)-terminal fragment alters skin tumor phenotype.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>5308</fpage><lpage>5316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12235001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamagishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatanaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel ERK-dependent signaling process that regulates interleukin-2 expression in a late phase of T cell activation.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>15685</fpage><lpage>15692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12595531</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitehurst</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Geppert</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEK1 and the extracellular signal-regulated kinases are required for the stimulation of IL-2 gene transcription in T cells.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>1020</fpage><lpage>1029</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8557975</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 