<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pgen</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS Genetics</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7390</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7404</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030107</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PLGE-RA-0015R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plge-03-07-02</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Drosophila</subject><subject>Insects</subject><subject>Arthropods</subject><subject>Animals</subject><subject>Eukaryotes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evolution of <italic>hydra,</italic> a Recently Evolved Testis-Expressed Gene with Nine Alternative First Exons in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Evolution of<italic>hydra</italic> Gene in<italic>Drosophila</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Shou-Tao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Hsin-Chien</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barbash</surname><given-names>Daniel A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Hsiao-Pei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Faculty of Life Sciences and Institute of Genome Sciences, National Yang-Ming University, Taipei, Taiwan, Republic of China </aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, United States of America </aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Singh Malik</surname><given-names>Harmit</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref rid="edit1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>hy31&#x00040;cornell.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e107</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date></history><copyright-statement><bold>Copyright:</bold> &#x000a9; 2007 Chen et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><!--<related-article related-article-type="preprint" xlink:title="Research Article" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pgen.0030107.eor" id="RA1" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:type="simple" >Evolution of hydra, a Recently Evolved Testis-Expressed Gene with Nine Alternative First Exons in Drosophila melanogaster</related-article>--><abstract><p>We describe here the <italic>Drosophila</italic> gene <italic>hydra</italic> that appears to have originated de novo in the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup and subsequently evolved in both structure and expression level in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content> and its sibling species. <italic>D. melanogaster hydra</italic> encodes a predicted protein of ~300 amino acids with no apparent similarity to any previously known proteins. The syntenic region flanking <italic>hydra</italic> on both sides is found in both <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. ananassae</named-content> and <italic>D. pseudoobscura,</italic> but <italic>hydra</italic> is found only in <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup species, suggesting that it originated less than ~13 million y ago. Exon 1 of <italic>hydra</italic> has undergone recurrent duplications, leading to the formation of nine tandem alternative exon 1s in <italic>D. melanogaster.</italic> Seven of these alternative exons are flanked on their 3&#x02032; side by the transposon <italic>DINE-1</italic> (<italic>Drosophila</italic> interspersed element-1). We demonstrate that at least four of the nine duplicated exon 1s can function as alternative transcription start sites. The entire <italic>hydra</italic> locus has also duplicated in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. sechellia</named-content>. <italic>D. melanogaster hydra</italic> is expressed most intensely in the proximal testis, suggesting a role in late-stage spermatogenesis. The coding region of <italic>hydra</italic> has a relatively high Ka/Ks ratio between species, but the ratio is less than 1 in all comparisons, suggesting that <italic>hydra</italic> is subject to functional constraint. Analysis of sequence polymorphism and divergence of <italic>hydra</italic> shows that it has evolved under positive selection in the lineage leading to <italic>D. melanogaster.</italic> The dramatic structural changes surrounding the first exons do not affect the tissue specificity of gene expression: <italic>hydra</italic> is expressed predominantly in the testes in <italic>D. melanogaster, D. simulans,</italic> and <italic>D. yakuba.</italic> However, we have found that expression level changed dramatically (~ &#x0003e;20-fold) between <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <italic>D. simulans.</italic> While <italic>hydra</italic> initially evolved in the absence of nearby transposable element insertions, we suggest that the subsequent accumulation of repetitive sequences in the <italic>hydra</italic> region may have contributed to structural and expression-level evolution by inducing rearrangements and causing local heterochromatinization. Our analysis further shows that recurrent evolution of both gene structure and expression level may be characteristics of newly evolved genes. We also suggest that late-stage spermatogenesis is the functional target for newly evolved and rapidly evolving male-specific genes.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><sec id="st1"><title/><p>Similar groups of animals have similar numbers of genes, but not all of these genes are the same. While some genes are highly conserved and can be easily and uniquely identified in species ranging from yeast to plants to humans, other genes are sometimes found in only a small number or even in a single species. Such newly evolved genes may help produce traits that make species unique. We describe here a newly evolved gene called <italic>hydra</italic> that occurs only in a small subgroup of <italic>Drosophila</italic> species. <italic>hydra</italic> is expressed in the testes, suggesting that it may have a function in male fertility. <italic>hydra</italic> has evolved significantly in its structure and protein-coding sequence among species. The authors named the gene <italic>hydra</italic> after the nine-headed monster slain by Hercules because in one species, <italic>Drosophila melanogaster, hydra</italic> has nine potential alternative first exons. Perhaps because of this or other structural changes, the level of RNA made by <italic>hydra</italic> differs significantly between one pair of species. This analysis reveals that newly created genes may evolve rapidly in sequence, structure, and expression level.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>citation</meta-name><meta-value>Chen ST, Cheng HC, Barbash DA, Yang HP (2007) Evolution of <italic>hydra</italic>, a recently evolved testis-expressed gene with nine alternative first exons in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>. PLoS Genet 3(7): e107. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pgen.0030107">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030107</ext-link></meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Much of the genetic novelty that accompanies speciation and organismal evolution is driven by reutilization of pre-existing genetic information. In an influential essay, Francois Jacob likened evolution to a process of tinkering &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b001">1</xref>&#x0005d;. After the primordial evolution of truly new macromolecules and mechanisms of replication, Jacob suggested that much of phenotypic novelty arises from reusing, recombining, and altering the function of available genes.</p><p>This view of evolution is strongly supported by studies of new-gene evolution. The vast majority of newly evolved genes can be attributed to duplication of pre-existing genes. These duplication events can range from single-gene events to duplications of entire genomes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b002">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b003">3</xref>&#x0005d;. Much of protein evolution also conforms to Jacob's view, as new proteins are often generated from shuffling pre-existing protein domains &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b004">4</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>The tinkering view of evolution does not rule out the occasional generation of novel protein sequences. One question then is whether and by what mechanisms such novel proteins evolve. Presumably novel proteins derive from noncoding sequences that acquire appropriate transcriptional and translational regulatory sequences. Experimental evolution studies suggest that random sequences of proteins can acquire biological functions at frequencies that are, surprisingly, greater than miniscule &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b005">5</xref>&#x0005d;. A recent study reported the exciting finding of several such candidate de novo genes in <italic>Drosophila</italic> that may be functional, based on RNA expression analysis &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b006">6</xref>&#x0005d;. A large number of new exons have also been identified in rodents that appear to have derived from incorporation of intronic sequences into mRNAs &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b007">7</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>A large fraction of eukaryotic genomes is composed of transposable elements (TEs). Because the TE component of genomes can evolve rapidly, TEs have a major impact on genome evolution &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b008">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b010">10</xref>&#x0005d;. TEs are widely considered to be selfish parasites that are deleterious to their host's fitness &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b011">11</xref>&#x0005d;, and most are likely eliminated quickly by natural selection. However, accumulating evidence has also shown that TEs can serve as an important source of genetic variation and genomic novelty &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b008">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b012">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b014">14</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>TEs can generate genetic novelty by at least five different mechanisms. First, the reverse transcriptase enzyme from retrotransposons can generate duplicated retroposed genes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b015">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b017">17</xref>&#x0005d; or generate chimeric fusion genes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b015">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b018">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b021">21</xref>&#x0005d;. Second, TEs can change expression patterns of adjacent genes by providing novel regulatory elements or by disrupting host gene regulatory functions &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b014">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b022">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b026">26</xref>&#x0005d;. Third, coding regions from TEs such as envelope proteins and transposase enzymes can be incorporated by the host species to modify or even create new host protein-coding genes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b013">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b027">27</xref>&#x0005d;. Fourth, TEs can contribute to noncoding regions (untranslated regions &#x0005b;UTRs&#x0005d;) of genes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b012">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b024">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b028">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b030">30</xref>&#x0005d;. Fifth, TE insertions create multiple highly homologous sites throughout the genome that can cause duplications by ectopic recombination &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b009">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b031">31</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>Comparisons between genomes have proven to be a powerful way to identify new genes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b032">32</xref>&#x0005d; and to reconstruct the early history of new-gene evolution &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b002">2</xref>&#x0005d;. This approach has provided new data for models and mechanisms leading to new-gene evolution &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b033">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b035">35</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>Such a comparative approach is used here to investigate the evolutionary history of a recently evolved gene in <italic>Drosophila.</italic> We report the characterization of the gene <italic>hydra,</italic> located in the pericentric region of the X chromosome in <italic>D. melanogaster. hydra</italic> was originally reported as predicted gene <italic>CG1338</italic> &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b036">36</xref>&#x0005d;. We show that <italic>hydra</italic> originated in the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup of <italic>Drosophila</italic> and subsequently experienced dramatic changes in its gene structure, including the formation of multiple alternative first exons, most of which are associated with the transposon <italic>DINE-1</italic> (<italic>Drosophila</italic> interspersed element-1)<italic>.</italic> We also investigate the history and impact of these gene-structure changes at both the DNA sequence and RNA expression levels by comparison among species of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup<italic>.</italic> We suggest that new genes will tend to evolve rapidly in coding sequence (CDS), gene structure, and gene-expression level. We also suggest that TE accumulation can cause local heterochromatinization that can in turn have a major impact on the evolution of gene structure and gene expression.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>The <italic>hydra</italic> Gene Is Restricted to the <italic>melanogaster</italic> Subgroup</title><p><italic>CG1338</italic> is located near the pericentric region of the X chromosome in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> (cytological region 19E1). We first became interested in <italic>CG1338</italic> during a genome-wide analysis of the transposon <italic>DINE-1</italic> in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> genome. We present evidence below that <italic>CG1338</italic> contains nine duplicated first exons in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content>. Because of these nine duplicated exon 1s (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>A), we propose to rename this gene <italic>hydra,</italic> after the nine-headed monster slain by Hercules.</p><fig id="pgen-0030107-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Evolution of <italic>hydra</italic> in <italic>Drosophila</italic> Species</title><p>(A) The <italic>hydra</italic> region of the X-chromosome of <italic>D. melanogaster,</italic> based on FlyBase genome browser release 4.3. The <italic>hydra</italic> gene was previously annotated as producing two alternative transcripts, RA and RB, derived from alternative exon 1s. The proposed annotation of seven additional exon 1s is based on evidence presented here.</p><p>(B) Evolution of <italic>hydra</italic> region and <italic>hydra</italic> gene structure in seven Drosophila species. <italic>hydra</italic> and the flanking gene <italic>CG1835</italic> are located in a recently expanded region between <italic>run</italic> and <italic>cyp6v1. hydra</italic> originated in the common ancestor of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup (arrow A). In <italic>D. melanogaster,</italic> this region between <italic>run</italic> and <italic>cyp6v1</italic> is ~32 kb (10 kb from the 3&#x02032; end of <italic>hydra</italic> to <italic>cyp6v1</italic> and 17 kb from the 5&#x02032; end of <italic>hydra</italic> to <italic>run</italic>), but is only ~26 kb apart in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. ananassae</named-content> and <italic>D. pseudoobscura,</italic> where both <italic>hydra</italic> and <italic>CG1835</italic> are missing. <italic>hydra</italic> has gone through multiple cycles of duplication and rearrangement in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and its sibling species, and accumulated insertions of the transposon <italic>DINE-1</italic> and other repetitive sequences (arrow B). <italic>CG1835</italic> is on the opposite strand from all other genes, as indicated by its leftward-pointing arrow. Three copies of <italic>hydra</italic> are found on two unlinked scaffolds in <italic>D. sechellia.</italic> Note that the distances are not to scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.g001"/></fig><p>We found that the gene region surrounding <italic>hydra</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> contains dense repeats of <italic>DINE-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>A). <italic>DINE-1,</italic> also named <italic>INE-1</italic> or <italic>DNAREP1&#x0005f;DM,</italic> is a highly abundant transposon that is predominantly found in the heterochromatic regions of the <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> genome &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b037">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b038">38</xref>&#x0005d; and is believed to have invaded the <italic>Drosophila</italic> genome before the diversification of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b037">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b040">40</xref>&#x0005d;. Further analysis showed that <italic>hydra</italic> is flanked by two blocks of tandem repeats, with duplicated fragments of <italic>DINE-1</italic> in the 5&#x02032; end and an undefined 500-bp repeat in the 3&#x02032; end. Using available genomic contigs from various <italic>Drosophila</italic> species (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://flybase.net/blast">http://flybase.net/blast</ext-link>), we found that the ~7-kb region surrounding <italic>hydra,</italic> including the adjacent gene <italic>CG1835,</italic> only exists in species of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup, but not in other species outside of the subgroup. BLAST searches using unique sequences from <italic>hydra</italic> identified no similar sequences in other regions of these genomes. We suggest that <italic>hydra</italic> evolved recently in the species of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). This conclusion was confirmed by Southern hybridization under low stringency using <italic>hydra</italic> exons 2&#x02013;4 from <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> as the probe with DNA extracted from <italic>D. melanogaster, D. simulans, D. yakuba, D. erecta, D. ananassae, D. pseudoobscura,</italic> and <italic>D. virilis.</italic> Hybridization signals were only detected in flies of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup (i.e., <italic>D. melanogaster, D. simulans, D. yakuba, D. erecta</italic>), but not in the other species (unpublished data). TBLASTN searches to the nonredundant (nr) or whole-genome shotgun (wgs) databases found no hits to non-<italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup <italic>Drosophila</italic> species with E values &#x0003c; 0.001.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Evolution of the Gene Structure of <italic>hydra</italic></title><p>According to the Flybase genome annotation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.flybase.org">http://www.flybase.org</ext-link>), <italic>hydra</italic> of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> contains four exons, and two types of transcripts (type A and type B), which are transcribed using alternative first exons. Our analysis of the <italic>hydra</italic> gene region suggested that there are seven additional putative first exons similar to the two annotated first exons located in a region of dense <italic>DINE-1s</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>A; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se001">Text S1</xref>). These seven additional potential first exons share similarity with the two annotated exon 1s in their CDSs (which are nine codons long) and in their 5&#x02032; upstream regions. The first of these duplicated exons may be nonfunctional because it creates a stop codon when spliced to exon 2, assuming that it has the same structure and splicing pattern as the other 8 exons. Alternatively, this first exon 1 may use a different 3&#x02032; splice site, although no such evidence was found in our 5&#x02032; rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE) analysis described below (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pgen-0030107-t001" content-type="2col" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Relative Usage of Different Exon 1s of <italic>hydra,</italic> Determined by 5&#x02032; RACE</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.t001"/></table-wrap><p>Our further analysis of multiple lines of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> (and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content>) with Southern hybridization detected substantial length variation in the gene region, presumably due to length variation in the exon 1 region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Although we have not determined the sequence structure of these alleles, the length variation observed is consistent with the hypothesis that the number of alternative first exons varies in <italic>D. melanogaster.</italic> In contrast, there is only a single exon 1 in the orthologous region of <italic>hydra</italic> from the species <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. erecta</named-content> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se005">Texts S5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se006">S6</xref>), and there is no length polymorphism in this region in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> (unpublished data). This suggests that the dramatic gene structure change by duplication of exon 1 in <italic>hydra</italic> occurred within ~5&#x02013;13 million y, after the divergence of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b041">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b042">42</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><fig id="pgen-0030107-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Length Variation of the Exon 1 Region of <italic>hydra</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content></title><p>(A) Location of the probes (thick black lines) and restriction enzyme SacII cutting sites in <italic>hydra</italic> of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> (top) and <italic>D. simulans</italic> (bottom)<italic>.</italic> Note that the region homologous to the probe is duplicated in <italic>D. simulans.</italic></p><p>(B&#x02013;C) Southern hybridization of genomic DNA extracted from multiple lines of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> (B) and <italic>D. simulans</italic> (C)<italic>. D. melanogaster</italic> lines are all from Zimbabwe, Africa. <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> lines 1&#x02013;4 are from California, United States; lines 5&#x02013;7 are from Zimbabwe, Africa; and lines 8&#x02013;14 are from Madagascar, Africa.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.g002"/></fig><p>By comparing the orthologous sequences of <italic>hydra</italic> using the released assembled genomic sequences of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <italic>D. sechellia,</italic> we found that this region has undergone local duplications in both species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>B; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se002">Texts S2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se004">S4</xref>). Determining the precise structure of the <italic>hydra</italic> region in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. sechellia</named-content> will require further sequence analysis due to low sequence coverage of this region. We have, however, confirmed by Southern analysis that <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> does have two copies of <italic>hydra</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g002">Figure 2</xref>C). In <italic>D. simulans,</italic> we find that one of these copies has two potential exon 1s. In <italic>D. sechellia,</italic> we identified two unlinked contigs containing <italic>hydra</italic>-homologous sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). Scaffold 8 contains the syntenic genes <italic>run</italic> and <italic>cyp6v1</italic> flanking a single copy of <italic>hydra.</italic> This copy of <italic>hydra</italic> contains two putative exon 1s. Scaffold 600 contains two tandem copies of <italic>hydra,</italic> each of which contains two or three putative exon 1s. These data suggest the possibility that <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. sechellia</named-content> has three copies of <italic>hydra,</italic> although further analysis will be required to determine the relative locations of these apparent duplicated copies that are on different scaffolds. Despite this uncertainty, we were able to investigate the phylogenetic relationship of these copies of <italic>hydra.</italic> Using either the sequence between exons 2&#x02013;4, inclusive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g003">Figure 3</xref>A; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se007">Text S7</xref>) or of intron 1 (unpublished data), we obtained similar phylogenetic trees that suggest that <italic>hydra</italic> duplicated independently in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <italic>D. sechellia.</italic> Because both gene regions produce the same phylogeny and these sequences span over 1,300 bp in all species, we consider it unlikely that this phylogenetic signal of independent duplications could be due to gene conversion.</p><fig id="pgen-0030107-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic Trees of <italic>hydra</italic></title><p>Trees are based on (A) exon 2&#x02013;4 sequences and (B) exon 1, including putative 5&#x02032; UTR sequences. The trees were built using the neighbor-joining method according to the Jukes-Cantor substitution model. Branch lengths are proportional to the number of nucleotide substitutions. Percentage bootstrap values are shown at each node (500 replicates). In (B), sequences mel 1&#x02013;9 correspond to the alternative exon 1s of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>B. Sequences Ra and Rb are from the annotated transcripts of <italic>D. melanogaster hydra</italic> in FlyBase. <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <italic>D. sechellia</italic> exon 1s are labeled as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>B. Note that mel 6 is part of group B but clusters with group A, presumably because of having a divergent 5&#x02032; UTR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.g003"/></fig><p>Upon further investigation of the intronic sequences next to exon 1, we found that seven out of the nine duplicated exon 1s in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and several of the duplicated exon 1s in both <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. sechellia</named-content> are immediately followed by <italic>DINE-1</italic> sequences, while in other species of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup, including <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> and <italic>D. erecta,</italic> there are no <italic>DINE-1s</italic> in this region. We thought it likely for two reasons that insertion of <italic>DINE-1</italic> adjacent to <italic>hydra</italic> exon 1 occurred in the common ancestor of <italic>D. melanogaster, D. simulans,</italic> and <italic>D. sechellia.</italic> First, it seems highly unlikely that a TE would insert independently at the same location in different species. Second, <italic>DINE-1</italic> is thought to have been active and then to have become transpositionally inactive before these species diverged &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b038">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b040">40</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>To test this hypothesis and to understand the evolutionary history and mechanism that resulted in the exon 1 duplications of <italic>hydra,</italic> we performed phylogenetic analysis of all the available exon 1s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g003">Figure 3</xref>B; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se008">Text S8</xref>). We found that <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> S2 and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. sechellia</named-content> C3 are outgroups to all other exon 1s. Both of these exons are flanked by <italic>DINE-1</italic> sequence, which is consistent with our above suggestion that <italic>DINE-1</italic> insertion in this region is ancestral (at time B in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). If this inference of the ancestral state of exon 1 in these three species is correct, it is interesting to note that <italic>DINE-1</italic> does not flank every exon 1. Our data would then suggest that either <italic>DINE-1</italic> was lost next to some duplicated exon 1s or that some exon 1s duplicated without duplicating the adjacent <italic>DINE-1.</italic></p><p>The relationships among the remaining <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. sechellia</named-content> exon 1s suggest that exon 1 duplicated before the speciation of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. sechellia</named-content> to generate the exon 1 groups S1/S3 and C1/C4/C6, with another duplication event generating exon 1 group C2/C5/C7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g003">Figure 3</xref>B). Both this tree and the one made using the rest of the locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g003">Figure 3</xref>A) suggest that after these exon 1 duplications, the entire locus duplicated independently in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <italic>D. sechellia.</italic></p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g003">Figure 3</xref>B also suggests that exon 1 duplicated independently in <italic>D. melanogaster.</italic> Based on the sequence similarity of predicted exon 1 sequences, the duplicated first exons of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> can be divided into three groups: group A, containing the first, second, third, and fifth duplicated exon 1s; group B, containing the fourth, seventh, eighth, and ninth duplicated exon 1s; and group C, containing the sixth duplicated exon 1. The first and the ninth exon 1s are the previously annotated exon 1s for transcript types RA and RB, respectively. Our phylogenetic analysis showed that exon 1s adjacent to each other are generally more closely related (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g003">Figure 3</xref>B). These results suggest that both the exon 1s and their flanking <italic>DINE-1</italic>s were duplicated together, and that unequal crossing-over is the major mechanism generating the tandemly duplicated exons.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><italic>hydra</italic> Is Expressed Predominantly in Adult Testes</title><p>RT-PCR analysis demonstrated that <italic>hydra</italic> is expressed in adult male testes in all three species tested: <italic>D. melanogaster, D. simulans,</italic> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g004">Figure 4</xref>). This result demonstrates that the expression pattern of <italic>hydra</italic> is conserved despite having a very different gene structure in these species. In one out of two stocks of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> that we examined, we also detected a low level of expression in the male carcass from which testes were removed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g004">Figure 4</xref>B). This expression pattern is consistent with <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> EST data: among ten ESTs in GenBank that match <italic>hydra</italic>, nine are from testis cDNA libraries, and one is from a larval fat-body library. We further investigated the pattern of expression of <italic>hydra</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> by in situ hybridization. We found that <italic>hydra</italic> is expressed most intensely in the proximal region of the testis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g005">Figure 5</xref>), where mature sperm are formed, suggesting that <italic>hydra</italic> functions in late stages of sperm development.</p><fig id="pgen-0030107-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Expression of <italic>hydra</italic> detected by RT-PCR</title><p>(A) <italic>D. melanogaster, D. simulans,</italic> and <italic>D. yakuba.</italic></p><p>(B) Canton S line of <italic>D. melanogaster.</italic></p><p>M, DNA kb size marker; G, genomic DNA; T, adult testis RNA; O, RNA from whole body of males with testis removed; &#x0002b;, positive control for cDNA O using primers for the gene <italic>GAPDH</italic>; &#x02212;, negative PCR control. RNA was extracted from strain ORC of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> (A), California strain w54 of <italic>D. simulans,</italic> and Tai18E2 of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content>. Note that expression of <italic>hydra</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> is specific to testis in the ORC strain (A), but slight expression was detected in other tissues in the Canton S strain (B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.g004"/></fig><fig id="pgen-0030107-g005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>In Situ Hybridization of DIG-Labeled Antisense RNA (A) and Sense Control RNA (B) of <italic>hydra</italic> to Testes of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content></title><p>Expression is strongest in the proximal region of testes. ag, accessory glands; ed, ejaculatory duct.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Functional Consequences of the Evolving Gene Structure of <italic>hydra</italic></title><p>To study the impact of exon 1 duplication on gene expression, we asked if each of the duplicated exons could function as a transcriptional start site. To determine whether each putative exon 1 is functional in <italic>D. melanogaster,</italic> we needed to use a technique that could distinguish these very similar potential transcripts. We therefore performed 5&#x02032; RACE analysis using RNA extracted from adult male testes of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and analyzed the sequences of 58 clones. The previously described Ra and Rb transcripts differ by three nucleotides at positions &#x02212;21 to &#x02212;23 in their 5&#x02032; UTRs as well as by a nonsynonymous polymorphism in their second codon. We designate alternative first exons 1, 2, 3, and 5 as class A (similar to Ra), and alternative first exons 4, 6, 7, 8, and 9 as class B (similar to Rb).</p><p>Some of these sequences can be further distinguished by additional polymorphisms further 5&#x02032; in the 5&#x02032; UTRs. Six different groups of alternative transcripts could be potentially distinguished, with two of these groups containing two or three identical first exons (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t001">Table 1</xref>). Among our 58 5&#x02032; RACE clones, four out of six of these groups were represented at least twice, demonstrating that at least four different alternative first exons in <italic>hydra</italic> are functional.</p><p>We also analyzed to see if each duplicated first exon contains core promoter sequences known to be important for the initiation of transcription of <italic>Drosophila</italic> genes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b043">43</xref>&#x0005d;. We looked specifically for the TFIIB recognition element (&#x02212;37 to &#x02212;32 bp, GGGCGCC or CCACGCC), TATA box (&#x02212;31to &#x02212;26 bp; TATAAA); initiator (&#x02212;1 to &#x0002b;4 bp; TCA(G/T)T(T/C)), and downstream promoter element (&#x0002b;28 to &#x0002b;32 bp; (A/G)G(A/T)(G/T)(G/A/C)). We found that almost all duplicated exon 1s contain all four core promoter sequences, with two exceptions: the sixth and the ninth duplicated exon 1s do not contain the downstream promoter element and the TATA box, respectively. Since both of these exons are used (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t001">Table 1</xref>), our results suggest that these two elements are not essential for transcription of <italic>hydra.</italic></p><p>Using the sequences of the clones from 5&#x02032; RACE, we also mapped the sites for transcription initiation. We found that most transcripts of <italic>hydra</italic> do not use a fixed site for transcription initiation. Instead, &#x0201c;slippery promoters&#x0201d; were found to be used in different exon 1s, as described for other <italic>Drosophila</italic> genes by Yasuhara et al. &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b044">44</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>We also tested whether <italic>hydra</italic> structural evolution might lead to expression-level differences between sibling species by quantifying <italic>hydra</italic> expression levels in five wild lines of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and in four wild lines of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g006">Figure 6</xref>). Strikingly, <italic>hydra</italic> was expressed at a substantially higher level in all <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> lines compared with all <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> lines. Among all pair-wise comparisons, the fold increase in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> ranged from ~4 to ~150, with the mean fold difference being ~22. These data indicate that <italic>hydra</italic> has lower expression in <italic>D. melanogaster,</italic> despite having multiple alternative transcription start sites.</p><fig id="pgen-0030107-g006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Relative Abundance of <italic>hydra</italic> mRNA Quantified by Real-Time RT-PCR in Various Lines of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content></title><p>For each line, the abundance of <italic>hydra</italic> relative to <italic>GAPDH</italic> was determined. This value was then compared for each line relative to <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> Canton S (mel&#x0005f;CS), which is normalized here to a value of 1. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Nonneutral Evolution of <italic>hydra</italic></title><p><italic>hydra</italic> contains an intact reading frame in all <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup species, encoding a predicted protein of 302, 280, and 308 amino acids in <italic>D. melanogaster, D. simulans,</italic> and <italic>D. yakuba,</italic> respectively. We calculated Ka/Ks ratios of the coding region of <italic>hydra</italic> among species in the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t002">Table 2</xref>). The ratio is &#x0003c;1 in all comparisons, suggesting that <italic>hydra</italic> is evolving under some degree of functional constraint.</p><table-wrap id="pgen-0030107-t002" content-type="2col" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of Ka and Ks Analysis of <italic>hydra</italic> among Four Species of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> Subgroup</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.t002"/></table-wrap><p>To gain further insight into the evolution of <italic>hydra,</italic> we collected population samples from <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> and <italic>D. simulans,</italic> which have the highest interspecific Ka/Ks ratio of 0.75 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se009">Texts S9</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se010">S10</xref>). We found that the nucleotide diversity at both synonymous (&#x003c0;s) and nonsynonymous (&#x003c0;a) sites in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> is similar to the average of other functional genes, with about ten times more polymorphism at synonymous sites relative to nonsynonymous sites (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t003">Table 3</xref>). In contrast, there is not much difference between &#x003c0;s and &#x003c0;a in <italic>D. simulans,</italic> where &#x003c0;s is much lower than the average of other genes for this species &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b045">45</xref>&#x0005d;. In order to further investigate whether this unusual pattern of nucleotide diversity (similar levels of synonymous and nonsynonymous polymorphism) in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> is lineage specific, we studied polymorphism in <italic>D. yakuba.</italic> &#x003c0;s and &#x003c0;a of <italic>hydra</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> are similar to those of <italic>D. melanogaster,</italic> and &#x003c0;s is similar to the average value (0.0127) of six X-linked loci in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b046">46</xref>&#x0005d;, suggesting that the unusual pattern of nucleotide diversity of <italic>hydra</italic> is restricted only to <italic>D. simulans.</italic> The approximately equal values of &#x003c0;s and &#x003c0;a in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> may suggest that <italic>hydra</italic> is under reduced functional constraint in <italic>D. simulans.</italic> Two findings suggest, however, that <italic>hydra</italic> is not a pseudogene in <italic>D. simulans.</italic> First, it has an intact open reading frame, and second, <italic>hydra</italic> is expressed in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and has a similar expression pattern to other species (see above).</p><table-wrap id="pgen-0030107-t003" content-type="1col" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Summary of Polymorphism Data from <italic>hydra</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content>, <italic>D. simulans,</italic> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.t003"/></table-wrap><p>Results of the McDonald-Kreitman (MK) test &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b047">47</xref>&#x0005d; among these three species are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t004">Table 4</xref>. Neutral evolution of <italic>hydra</italic> can be rejected between <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <italic>D. yakuba,</italic> which we suggest is caused by the large number of nonsynonymous substitutions between these species. There is also a large amount of nonsynonymous divergence between <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <italic>D. simulans.</italic> We do not, however, reject neutrality in this case, likely due to the unusually low &#x003c0;s in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> discussed above (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t003">Table 3</xref>). Thus, these results suggest that <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> is the most likely lineage in which <italic>hydra</italic> has experienced positive selection.</p><table-wrap id="pgen-0030107-t004" content-type="2col" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>MK Tests for Nonneutral Evolution of <italic>hydra</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pgen.0030107.t004"/></table-wrap><p>To confirm this conclusion, we tested to see if the nonneutral evolution of <italic>hydra</italic> occurred in a lineage-specific pattern by performing polarized substitution analysis with the MK test (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t004">Table 4</xref>). Replacements were polarized to each species lineage using <italic>D. yakuba hydra</italic> as an outgroup sequence. The polarized MK test is significant only in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> lineage.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s3a"><title><italic>hydra</italic> Is a Recently Originated Functional Gene</title><p>We identified the gene <italic>hydra</italic> in <italic>D. melanogaster,</italic> but could only identify orthologs within other <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup species. Using both BLAST searches of full-genome sequences with the 6-kb region flanking <italic>hydra</italic> and Southern hybridization, we were unable to identify <italic>hydra</italic> from <italic>D. ananassae, D. pseudoobscura,</italic> or <italic>D. virilis.</italic> We were, however, able to identify the syntenic region in these species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). These data strongly suggest that <italic>hydra</italic> originated in the common ancestor of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup.</p><p>All available evidence also suggests that <italic>hydra</italic> is a functional gene. First, all <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup species contain intact open reading frames with no stop codons, even though there are many insertions and deletions in the <italic>hydra</italic> CDS among species. Second, Ka/Ks values between all species are less than 1, suggesting that <italic>hydra</italic> is under functional constraint (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t002">Table 2</xref>). Third, the level of polymorphism of <italic>hydra</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> is similar to known functionally important genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t003">Table 3</xref>). Fourth, RT-PCR and in situ hybridization show that <italic>hydra</italic> is predominantly expressed in male testes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g004">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g005">5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><italic>hydra</italic> Shares Common Features of New-Gene Evolution</title><p>Several other cases of new-gene evolution in <italic>Drosophila</italic> have been studied &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b002">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b048">48</xref>&#x0005d;. Examples include (1) <italic>Jingwei,</italic> a chimeric gene that evolved as a result of the insertion of an <italic>Adh</italic> retrosequence into a duplicated locus in the <italic>D. teissieri/D. yakuba</italic> lineage &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b019">19</xref>&#x0005d;; (2) <italic>Sdic,</italic> which originated through a complex set of rearrangements, including a gene fusion between the gene encoding the cell adhesion protein annexin X and a cytoplasmic dynein intermediate chain (<italic>Sdic</italic> encodes a novel sperm-specific dynein found only in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content>) &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b049">49</xref>&#x0005d;; (3) <italic>Sphinx,</italic> a recently evolved gene apparently created by both retroposition and exon shuffling, which produces a novel noncoding RNA gene found only in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b033">33</xref>&#x0005d;; (4) <italic>mkg,</italic> a gene family generated originally as retroposed duplicates about 1&#x02013;2 million y ago that further evolved by individual members undergoing gene fission and fusion events &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b035">35</xref>&#x0005d;; (5) <italic>K81,</italic> a gene that arose through duplication by retroposition after the radiation of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup and acquired a new male germline&#x02013;specific function &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b050">50</xref>&#x0005d;; (6) <italic>Dntf-2r,</italic> a rapidly evolving male-specific gene in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and sibling species, which originated from retroposition &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b034">34</xref>&#x0005d;; and (7) five protein-coding genes which appear to have originated in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> from noncoding DNA and evolved male-biased expression &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b006">6</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>Despite the diverse mechanisms involved in the creation of these young genes in <italic>Drosophila,</italic> there are two features common to most of them: (1) they evolve rapidly in sequence, including at nonsynonymous sites for protein-coding genes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b019">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b020">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b034">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b049">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b051">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b052">52</xref>&#x0005d;; and (2) their expression is often male-specific, and in many cases testis-specific &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b052">52</xref>&#x0005d;. This expression pattern was also often found in a large survey of new retroposed genes &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b017">17</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p><italic>hydra</italic> shares both of these characteristics. The Ka and Ks values between <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <italic>D. simulans</italic> were substantially higher than the average values of most other genes, and the Ka/Ks ratio ranged from 0.44 to 0.75 in all species compared (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t002">Table 2</xref>). These high values may be explained by accelerated functional divergence following the origin of new genes. However, the elevated Ka/Ks ratio could also result from an elevated mutation rate and reduced selective constraint. To further investigate the evolution of <italic>hydra,</italic> we analyzed the level of polymorphism and divergence among <italic>D. melanogaster, D. simulans,</italic> and <italic>D. yakuba.</italic> Our population genetics analyses rejected the null hypothesis of neutral evolution in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pgen-0030107-t004">Table 4</xref>). This rejection appears to be due to a significant excess of fixed differences at nonsynonymous sites in <italic>D. melanogaster,</italic> suggesting that positive selection has driven the evolution of <italic>hydra</italic> in <italic>D. melanogaster.</italic></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><italic>hydra</italic> Is Expressed in the Basal Part of the Testis</title><p>The male-specific expression pattern is a second feature that <italic>hydra</italic> shares with other new genes. For many newly evolved genes, male-specific or testis-specific expression has been demonstrated by RT-PCR, but the spatial expression patterns are unknown, making it difficult to refine our knowledge of what aspects of testis development or spermatogenesis may be under selection. We determined that <italic>hydra</italic> is expressed most intensely in the basal (proximal) part of the testis in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> by in situ hybridization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g005">Figure 5</xref>). This localization pattern suggests that <italic>hydra</italic> may have a function in late-stage spermatogenesis or sperm differentiation. We note that <italic>hydra</italic> is X-linked, which suggests that it escapes from the X inactivation that occurs during spermatogenesis &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b053">53</xref>&#x0005d;. Our results also stand in contrast to results from genome-wide studies that suggest that genes with male-biased expression as well as newly evolved testis-specific genes tend to be autosomal &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b017">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b054">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b055">55</xref>&#x0005d;. Interestingly, the newly evolved testis-expressed genes <italic>Sdic</italic> and <italic>CG15323</italic> are also located in polytene region 19 of the X chromosome &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b006">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b049">49</xref>&#x0005d;.</p><p>Several studies have shown that genes with male-biased expression have significantly faster rates of evolution than genes with female-biased or unbiased expression &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b056">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b057">57</xref>&#x0005d;. This difference is caused primarily by a higher Ka in the male-biased genes. Sexual selection is likely to be driving this acceleration of male-biased genes, but functional tests will be required to understand fully the role of selection. Our study of <italic>hydra</italic> suggests that late-stage spermatogenesis may be the key developmental process to investigate further for functional differences between species.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Novel Aspects of <italic>hydra: hydra</italic> Has Undergone Recurrent Structural Evolution</title><p>Our analysis of <italic>hydra</italic> reveals several aspects that are unusual or unique compared with other newly evolved genes. One novel feature of <italic>hydra</italic> is that it has experienced recurrent structural evolution in the lineages leading to both <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>). We can infer the likely occurrence of three independent structural changes to <italic>hydra.</italic> One is a duplication of exon 1 in the common ancestor of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <italic>D. sechellia.</italic> Second is a duplication of the whole locus in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <italic>D. sechellia.</italic> Although uncertainties remain about the structure of the <italic>hydra</italic> region in <italic>D. sechellia,</italic> our phylogenetic analyses suggest that <italic>hydra</italic> duplicated independently in these two species. Third is the further duplication of seven additional exon 1s in <italic>D. melanogaster.</italic> Our phylogenetic analysis suggests that these additional duplication events occurred only in <italic>D. melanogaster,</italic> rather than in the common ancestor of <italic>D. melanogaster, D. simulans,</italic> and <italic>D. sechellia,</italic> followed by loss in the latter two species. It is possible, however, that the phylogenetic signal could be erroneous if homogenization occurred by continual gene conversion and/or unequal crossing over among these short duplicated exons.</p><p>The duplicated exon 1 in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. sechellia</named-content> and most of the additional exon 1 duplications in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> are flanked by partial <italic>DINE-1</italic> elements. <italic>DINE-1</italic> is not associated with <italic>hydra</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> or <italic>D. erecta.</italic> Genome-wide analyses of <italic>DINE-1</italic> suggest that <italic>DINE-1</italic> was transpositionally active and then silenced in the common ancestor of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <italic>D. yakuba,</italic> followed by another round of activity and silencing in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b039">39</xref>&#x0005d;. These findings would suggest then that <italic>DINE-1</italic> inserted ancestrally in <italic>hydra,</italic> followed by loss in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> lineage but not the <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> lineage. An alternative scenario is that <italic>DINE-1</italic> may have inserted in <italic>hydra</italic> during a period of activity in the <italic>D. melanogaster/D. simulans</italic> ancestor after divergence from <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> that was too brief to have a left a genome-wide footprint.</p><p>Regardless of the timing of the initial <italic>DINE-1</italic> insertion into <italic>hydra,</italic> the further duplications of exon 1 in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> were unlikely to have occurred by <italic>DINE-1</italic> transposition because alternative exon 1s two through eight contain UTR and CDSs that are adjacent to rather than within the <italic>DINE-1</italic> sequences. As noted above, the phylogenetic relationships among these alternative exons 1s suggest that they originated by unequal crossing over. <italic>DINE-1</italic> may have promoted these duplications by increasing the homology among exon 1s. While we lack evidence for a direct role of <italic>DINE-1</italic> in driving <italic>hydra</italic> structural evolution, our results do suggest that a property of transposable elements that is usually considered to be deleterious&#x02014;their ability to cause ectopic recombination and unequal crossing over&#x02014;may also contribute to structural evolution of genes. We have observed other cases of structural variation associated with <italic>DINE-1</italic> insertions in the <italic>melanogaster</italic> species complex (unpublished data). For most genes, evolving under strong functional constraint, a <italic>DINE-1</italic> insertion that causes structural changes in the locus is likely to be highly deleterious. However, for a newly evolved gene like <italic>hydra,</italic> there may be more flexibility in terms of tolerating gene structure changes. We also suggest that as a gene evolves in structure, it may accelerate the rate of CDS evolution.</p><p>More generally, our evidence that <italic>hydra</italic> has undergone multiple and independent structural changes suggests that gene structure as well as CDSs may evolve rapidly in new genes, even without any association with transposable elements. One other example is the <italic>monkey king</italic> gene family in <italic>Drosophila,</italic> which has undergone rapid structural changes caused by gene fission &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b035">35</xref>&#x0005d;.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><italic>hydra</italic> Expression Level Is Evolving</title><p>A second novel aspect compared with other studies of newly evolved genes is that <italic>hydra</italic> expression level has dramatically changed between sibling species. Our quantitative RT-PCR results showed that the expression level of <italic>hydra</italic> between <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> is highly different (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g006">Figure 6</xref>). <italic>hydra</italic> in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> is expressed at least 20-fold less on average than in <italic>D. simulans.</italic> Why is the expression level so different between these two closely related species?</p><p>Two hypotheses may explain the decreased <italic>hydra</italic> expression in <italic>D. melanogaster.</italic> First, it may be caused by competition or interference among the tandemly duplicated heads during the transcription initiation stage. In this model, incomplete transcription initiation complexes would form at multiple heads. Reduced transcription initiation could result from either sequestration of transcription factors or direct interference among promoters. Second, it may be the result of differences in the degree of heterochromatinization of the <italic>hydra</italic> region between <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <italic>D. simulans. hydra</italic> is located near the pericentromeric region of the X chromosome. This region may be under continuous pressure from encroachment of the nearby heterochromatic pericentromere, leading to species-specific differences in chromatin states. Increased numbers of TE insertions are one characteristic of heterochromatic regions, and the large number of <italic>DINE-1</italic> insertions in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> is consistent with the hypothesis that the <italic>hydra</italic> region is partially heterochromatic.</p><p>Our views on the evolution of genome structure and function have changed dramatically in the past decade as more whole-genome sequences have become available in various species. Repetitive elements are a major cause of structural changes and instability in genomes. At the cytological level, chromosome rearrangements often occur at repetitive sites &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b031">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b058">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b059">59</xref>&#x0005d;. Our identification of the <italic>hydra</italic> gene suggests that repetitive elements also contribute to the formation and evolution of new genes by causing structural changes in gene organization, driving the evolution of new exons and transcription start sites, and promoting divergence in gene expression.</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><italic>hydra</italic> Is a Rare Example of De Novo Gene Creation</title><p>One of our most striking findings is that <italic>hydra</italic> appears to have been created de novo rather than being a duplicate of a pre-existing gene. Two pieces of evidence support this hypothesis. First, <italic>hydra</italic> (and <italic>CG1835</italic>) are found only in <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup species. The surrounding ~26 kb of DNA is found in other <italic>Drosophila</italic> species that lack <italic>hydra</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). Second, <italic>hydra</italic> shares no homology with any known or predicted proteins. Arguing against this hypothesis of de novo origin is the fact that all forms of <italic>hydra</italic> contain four predicted exons. One might expect that a recently evolved de novo gene would have a simpler one-exon structure, as has been observed for several candidate de novo genes in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b006">6</xref>&#x0005d;. Nevertheless, if <italic>hydra</italic> does have an ortholog in <italic>Drosophila</italic> outside of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup, it must have evolved so rapidly as to share no detectable similarity with any predicted proteins, including in multiple <italic>Drosophila</italic> genomes or other insect genomes that have been completely sequenced. If there is a highly diverged <italic>hydra</italic> parental gene or ortholog in other <italic>Drosophila,</italic> it also must have transposed to a novel genomic location in the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup. Considering all the available data, we suggest instead that <italic>hydra</italic> evolved de novo from DNA sequence that inserted between <italic>run</italic> and <italic>cyp6v1</italic> in the common ancestor of the <italic>melanogaster</italic> subgroup.</p></sec><sec id="s3g"><title>The Dynamic Nature of New Genes</title><p>The most common fate of newly formed genes is disappearance. For example, about 85&#x00025; of the genes duplicated during the yeast whole-genome duplication have been lost in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b003">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b060">60</xref>&#x0005d;. New genes therefore can be viewed as analogous to mutations, with most being neutral or deleterious in effect and therefore subject to elimination. A common characteristic of successful new exons and new genes is a high rate of CDS evolution &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b007">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b020">20</xref>&#x0005d;, and <italic>hydra</italic> shows this evolutionary pattern. Our discovery of <italic>hydra</italic> suggests that gene expression level and gene structure may also evolve rapidly and recurrently in new genes. We suggest that the successful retention of new genes requires maximal variation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Fly strains.</title><p>Flies used in this study include: (1) isofemale lines of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> (WI) from Sergey Nuzhdin (University of California Davis, Winters, California, United States); (2) strains of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> from worldwide populations: California (CA), Canton S (CS), Taiwan (TWN), Oregon R (ORC), France 3V-1 (Fr3V-1) (gift of S. C. Tsaur, Academia Sinica, Taiwan); (3) isofemale lines of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> from African populations (mad, sz, su, zk lines; gift of John Pool, Cornell University, Ithaca, New York, United States), and one line each from France (W54) and Japan (W60); (4) isofemale lines of <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> (cy lines) from Africa (gift of Peter Andolfatto, University of California San Diego, United States); and (5) strains of <italic>Drosophila</italic> species, including <italic>D. yakuba</italic> (Tai18E2, and 286.82&#x02013;90), <italic>D. erecta, D. ananassae, D. virilis,</italic> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. pseudoobscura</named-content> (gift of S. C. Tsaur).</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>DNA preparation and analysis of DNA sequences.</title><p>DNA was extracted from pools of ~50 male flies from each line by a standard phenol-chloroform extraction followed by ethanol precipitation. Primers to amplify and sequence the <italic>hydra</italic> gene regions from <italic>D. melanogaster, D</italic>. <italic>simulans,</italic> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> were designed using the homologous sequences obtained from BLAST searches against Flybase genome databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.flybase.org/blast">http://www.flybase.org/blast</ext-link>). Primers for both <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> are IN1&#x0005f;F (5&#x02032;-GCGTTTGTACACTTGGCAAC) and 3UR (5&#x02032;-TGATGTAGGAATATGCGTTGC), and for <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> are yakE2&#x0005f;F (5&#x02032;-CTTCAGAGAACCCCAACCAA) and yakE3&#x0005f;R (5&#x02032;-CTTGCAATTATCCGGATTGC). In <italic>D. simulans,</italic> the primer pair specifically amplifies the second duplicate of <italic>hydra,</italic> which is adjacent to the S3 alternative exon 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g001">Figure 1</xref>B). Other primer sequences and PCR amplification conditions are available upon request. PCR products were directly sequenced in both direction using ABI BigDye (Applied Biosystems, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.appliedbiosystems.com">http://www.appliedbiosystems.com</ext-link>) technologies under slight modification of the manufacturer's suggested protocols. All alleles were sequenced on both strands. Sequences are deposited in GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Genbank">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Genbank</ext-link>) under accession numbers EF596837&#x02013;EF596877.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Southern hybridization.</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from 60&#x02013;70 flies of each line with phenol-chloroform, was ethanol precipitated, and was diluted to a final concentration of about 5 &#x003bc;g/&#x003bc;l. A total of 15 &#x003bc;g DNA was then digested separately with SacII, separated on a 0.8&#x00025; agarose gel, and transferred to a nylon membrane by Southern blotting. Probes were from PCR product using DNA template from <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> with primers hydra&#x0005f;rep500&#x0005f;R2 (5&#x02032;-CAGT(T/C)AGACCTCTCTGAAATC) and E2&#x0005f;146R (5&#x02032;- GGTTGGAATCCTCTGGAGTGTTGG), and were prepared by DIG-labeling Nick translation kit (Roche, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.roche.com">http://www.roche.com</ext-link>). Hybridizations were done at 50 &#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>RNA preparation, RT-PCR, 5&#x02032;- RACE, and molecular cloning.</title><p>Testes of adult males aged 2&#x02013;5 d old were dissected in PBS buffer and immediately transferred to PBS buffer on ice. RNAs were extracted with Trizol (Invitrogen, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.invitrogen.com">http://www.invitrogen.com</ext-link>). After a brief vortex mixing, the mixture was incubated at 4 &#x000b0;C for 15 min and then centrifuged at low speed to obtain phase separation. The aqueous phase was transferred to a fresh tube, to which an equal volume of isopropanol was added in the presence of 3 &#x003bc;l glycogen. The mixture was kept at &#x02212;20 &#x000b0;C for 30 min, followed by centrifugation. The RNA pellet thus obtained was washed with 70&#x00025; chilled ethanol, repelleted, and air dried. The final RNA pellet was dissolved in 20 &#x003bc;l DEPC-treated distilled water and was used in at least two RT reactions.</p><p>RT was performed using the Superscript II RT kit obtained from Life Technologies (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.invitrogen.com">http://www.invitrogen.com</ext-link>) using oligo(dT)<sub>12&#x02013;18</sub> as the primer. The RT products were dissolved in 20 &#x003bc;l sterile distilled water and 1 &#x003bc;l was used for each PCR. For 5&#x02032;-RACE), first strand synthesis using the lock-docking oligo(dT) primer and 35 cycles of PCR amplification were performed using the SMART RACE cDNA Amplification Kit purchased from Clontech (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clontech.com">http://www.clontech.com</ext-link>). The <italic>hydra</italic>-specific primers used in this study are E3&#x0005f;110R (5&#x02032;-TGGATTTTACGCCGCTCCT). 5&#x02032; RACE&#x02013;derived PCR products were subcloned into the pGEM-T vector (Promega, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.promega.com">http://www.promega.com</ext-link>) using a standard cloning procedure, and 61 clones were picked randomly for DNA sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Quantitative PCR.</title><p>A total of 50 testes of each line were collected from 3-d-old males. Testes were homogenized in Trizol (Invitrogen), and total RNA was phenol-chloroform extracted, ethanol precipitated, and cleaned up with RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.qiagen.com">http://www.qiagen.com</ext-link>) and RNase free DNase Set (Qiagen). About 200 ng of total RNA was used for synthesizing cDNA with TaqMan Reverse Transcription Reagents (Applied Biosystems) using oligo-dT as the primer, following the manufacturer's instruction.</p><p>Quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) was performed using the Lightcycler-FastStart DNA Master SYBR Green I kit (Roche), according to the manufacturer's instructions. Primers used were E2&#x0005f;222F (5&#x02032;-ATGTGGCAAAGGTCCAGAAT) and E3&#x0005f;110R (5&#x02032;-TGGATTTTACGCCGCTCCT), which are complementary to exon 2 and 3 of <italic>hydra,</italic> respectively. Note that this primer pair cannot distinguish transcripts derived from the two duplicates of <italic>hydra</italic> in <italic>D. simulans.</italic> PCR quality and specificity was verified by melting curve dissociation analysis and gel electrophoresis of the amplified products. Relative transcript abundance of <italic>hydra</italic> was calculated using the second derivative maximum values from the linear regression of cycle number versus log concentration of the amplified gene. Amplification of the control gene <italic>GADPH</italic> was used for normalization. Sequences of the primers used are GADPH&#x0005f;F: 5&#x02032;-AAGGGAATCCTGGGCTACAC and GADPH&#x0005f;R: 5&#x02032;-CGGTTGGAGTAACCGAACTC.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>In situ hybridization.</title><p>Digoxigenin-labeled antisense and sense control riboprobes were generated from a cDNA containing the sequence of exon 2 and 3 of <italic>hydra</italic> cloned into a pBluescript vector. Probes were synthesized using DIG RNA labeling mix (Roche), followed by treatment with 2 U DNAse (Promega) and incubation in carbonate buffer for 40 min at 65 &#x000b0;C as described in &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b061">61</xref>&#x0005d;. Probes were then ethanol precipitated, air dried, and resuspended in 200 &#x003bc;l hybridization buffer. Probes were used at a dilution of 1:50 during hybridization.</p><p>Testes were dissected in 1&#x000d7; PBS and kept on ice until fixation. Two fixations were done with 4&#x00025; formaldehyde in 1&#x000d7; PBS for 20 min on ice. After washing twice in PBS/0.1&#x00025; Triton-X, protease treatment and all following steps were done as described in &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b061">61</xref>&#x0005d;. Hybridizations were done at 60 &#x000b0;C overnight.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Identification of <italic>hydra</italic> orthologs.</title><p>Orthologs of <italic>hydra</italic> were from the following prepublication genome sequences: <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content> sequence from the Washington University Genome Sequencing Center (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.wustl.edu">http://genome.wustl.edu</ext-link>); <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. sechellia</named-content> sequence from the Broad Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broad.mit.edu">http://www.broad.mit.edu</ext-link>); and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. erecta</named-content> sequence from Agencourt Bioscience (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.agencourt.com">http://www.agencourt.com</ext-link>). Sequences of <italic>hydra</italic> from these species were annotated by maximizing homology to the <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content> sequence, and are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se001">Texts S1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se006">S6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Sequence analysis.</title><p>Sequences were aligned using ClustalW &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b062">62</xref>&#x0005d;, with some manual adjustment to keep gaps in-frame in coding regions. Phylogenetic analyses were performed using Mega 3.1 &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b063">63</xref>&#x0005d;. Sequence polymorphism and divergence analysis were done using DnaSP 4.10 &#x0005b;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pgen-0030107-b064">64</xref>&#x0005d;. The effective number of synonymous and nonsynonymous sites, Ka and Ks values, and pairwise divergence for synonymous sites based on Kimura's two-parameter model were estimated.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se001"><label>Text S1</label><caption><title>Annotation in GenBank Format of <italic>hydra</italic> Region Sequences in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. melanogaster</named-content></title><p>(54 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd001.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se002"><label>Text S2</label><caption><title>Annotation in GenBank Format of <italic>hydra</italic> Region Sequences in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. simulans</named-content></title><p>(71 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd002.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se003"><label>Text S3</label><caption><title>Annotation in GenBank Format of <italic>hydra</italic> Region Sequences in <italic>D. sechellia scaf 8</italic></title><p>(42 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd003.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se004"><label>Text S4</label><caption><title>Annotation in GenBank Format of <italic>hydra</italic> Region Sequences in <italic>D. sechellia scaf 600</italic></title><p>(13 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd004.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se005"><label>Text S5</label><caption><title>Annotation in GenBank Format of <italic>hydra</italic> Region Sequences in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. yakuba</named-content></title><p>(43 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd005.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se006"><label>Text S6</label><caption><title>Annotation in GenBank Format of <italic>hydra</italic> Region Sequences in <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. erecta</named-content></title><p>(43 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd006.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se007"><label>Text S7</label><caption><title>Alignments in FASTA Format of <italic>hydra</italic> Exons 2&#x02013;4 Used for the Phylogenetic Analysis in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g003">Figure 3</xref></title><p>(7 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd007.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se008"><label>Text S8</label><caption><title>Alignments in FASTA Format of <italic>hydra</italic> Exon 1 (Including Predicted 5&#x02032; UTRs) Used for the Phylogenetic Analysis in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen-0030107-g003">Figure 3</xref></title><p>(5 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd008.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se009"><label>Text S9</label><caption><title>Alignment of All DNA Sequences Used in the Polymorphism and Divergence Analyses</title><p>(84 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd009.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen-0030107-se010"><label>Text S10</label><caption><title>Alignment of Amino Acid Sequences Based on the DNA Alignment in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen-0030107-se009">Text S9</xref></title><p>(12 KB TXT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pgen.0030107.sd010.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Daven Presgraves and Henry Sun for helpful discussions, and Manyuan Long and the anonymous reviewers for insightful comments on the manuscript. We also thank Shun-Chern Tsaur, John Pool, Peter Andolfatto, and Sergey Nuzhdin for providing fly strains for population genetics studies, and Hong-Ya Liao for technical assistance.</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CDS</term><def><p>coding sequence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>DINE-1</italic></term><def><p><italic>Drosophila</italic> interspersed element-1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MK test</term><def><p>McDonald-Kreitman test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RACE</term><def><p>rapid amplification of cDNA ends</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TE</term><def><p>transposable element</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UTR</term><def><p>untranslated region</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pgen-0030107-b001"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1977</year><article-title>Evolution and tinkering</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>196</volume><fpage>1161</fpage><lpage>1166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">860134</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b002"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Betran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>The origin of new genes: Glimpses from the young and old</article-title><source>Nat Rev Gen</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>875</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b003"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Molecular evidence for an ancient duplication of the entire yeast genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>387</volume><fpage>708</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9192896</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b004"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doolittle</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>The multiplicity of domains in proteins</article-title><source>Ann Rev Biochem</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7574483</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b005"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Makino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Urabe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yomo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Can an arbitrary sequence evolve towards acquiring a biological function?</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12574862</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b006"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindfors</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Novel genes derived from noncoding DNA in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content> are frequently X-linked and exhibit testis-biased expression</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>9935</fpage><lpage>9939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16777968</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b007"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Origin and evolution of new exons in rodents</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>1258</fpage><lpage>1264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16109974</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b008"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kidwell</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lisch</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Transposable elements and host genome evolution</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10675923</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b009"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazazian</surname><given-names>HH</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Mobile elements: Drivers of genome evolution</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>303</volume><fpage>1626</fpage><lpage>1632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15016989</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b010"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brookfield</surname><given-names>JFY</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The ecology of the genome-mobile DNA elements and their hosts</article-title><source>Nat Rev Gen</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>136</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b011"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawkins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1976</year><source>The selfish gene</source><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><page-count count="224"/></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b012"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>An evolutionarily conserved germ cell-specific hnRNP is encoded by a retrotransposed gene</article-title><source>Hum Mol Gen</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>2117</fpage><lpage>2124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10958650</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b013"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Turning junk into gold: Domestication of transposable elements and the creation of new genes in eukaryotes</article-title><source>Bioessays</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16937363</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b014"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Britten</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Mobile elements inserted in the distant past have taken on important functions</article-title><source>Gene</source><volume>205</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9461392</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b015"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vinckenbosch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupanloup</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaessmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Evolutionary fate of retroposed gene copies in the human genome</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>3220</fpage><lpage>3225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16492757</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b016"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaessmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Betran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Extensive gene traffic on the mammalian X chromosome</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>303</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739461</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b017"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Betran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Retroposed new genes out of the X in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Genome Res</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>1854</fpage><lpage>1859</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12466289</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nozawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aotsuka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>A novel chimeric gene, <italic>siren,</italic> with retroposed promoter sequence in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila bipectinata</named-content> complex</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>171</volume><fpage>1719</fpage><lpage>1727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16143626</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b019"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Langley</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Natural selection and the origin of <italic>jingwei,</italic> a chimeric processed functional gene in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><volume>260</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7682012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b020"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Parallel evolution of chimeric fusion genes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>11373</fpage><lpage>11378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16076957</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b021"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XHF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chasin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Comparison of multiple vertebrate genomes reveals the birth and evolution of human exons</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>13427</fpage><lpage>13432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16938881</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b022"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Boffelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Boonmark</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Apolipoprotein(a) gene enhancer resides within a LINE element</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>273</volume><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9422746</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b023"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medstrand</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Lagemaat</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Svenback</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Impact of transposable elements on the evolution of mammalian gene regulation</article-title><source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16093686</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b024"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van de Lagemaat</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mager</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Medstrand</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Transposable elements in mammals promote regulatory variation and diversification of genes with specialized functions</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>530</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14550626</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b025"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlenke</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Strong selective sweep associated with a transposon insertion in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila simulans</named-content></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>1626</fpage><lpage>1631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14745026</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b026"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogozin</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name><surname>Glazko</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Origin of a substantial fraction of human regulatory sequences from transposable elements</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12547512</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b027"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Henikoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Positive selection of <italic>Iris,</italic> a retroviral envelope-derived host gene in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content></article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>e44.</elocation-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b028"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Britten</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Coding sequences of functioning human genes derived entirely from mobile element sequences</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>16825</fpage><lpage>16830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15546984</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b029"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nekrutenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Transposable elements are found in a large number of human protein-coding genes</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11672845</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b030"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aminetzach</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Macpherson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Pesticide resistance via transposition-mediated adaptive gene truncation in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Science</source><volume>309</volume><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16051794</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b031"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>It takes two transposons to tango: Transposable-element-mediated chromosomal rearrangements</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11050333</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b032"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yandell</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabor Miklos</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Comparative genomics of the eukaryotes</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>287</volume><fpage>2204</fpage><lpage>2215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731134</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b033"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nevo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Origin of <italic>sphinx,</italic> a young chimeric RNA gene in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>4448</fpage><lpage>4453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11904380</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b034"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Betran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title><italic>Dntf-2r,</italic> a young <italic>Drosophila</italic> retroposed gene with specific male expression under positive Darwinian selection</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>164</volume><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12871908</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b035"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Duplication-degeneration as a mechanism of gene fission and the origin of new genes in <italic>Drosophila</italic> species</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15064762</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b036"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Celniker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gocayne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>The genome sequence of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content></article-title><source>Science</source><volume>287</volume><fpage>2185</fpage><lpage>2195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731132</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b037"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quesneville</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrieu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Autard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nouaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Combined evidence annotation of transposable elements in genome sequence</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>e22.</elocation-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b038"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapitonov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Molecular paleontology of transposable elements in the <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> genome</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>6569</fpage><lpage>6574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12743378</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b039"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Rapid sequence turnover at an intergenic locus in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>670</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739245</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b040"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Genome-wide comparative analysis of the highly abundant transposable element <italic>DINE-1</italic> suggests a recent transpositional burst in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila yakuba</named-content></article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>173</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387876</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b041"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Satta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Paleo-demography of the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content> subgroup: Application of the maximum likelihood method</article-title><source>Genes Genet Syst</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10650839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b042"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Temporal patterns of fruit fly <italic>(Drosophila)</italic> evolution revealed by mutation clocks</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12949132</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b043"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Niemann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Computational analysis of core promoters in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> genome</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>research0087.0081</fpage><lpage>research0087.0012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12537576</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b044"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yasuhara</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>DeCrease</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakimoto</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Evolution of heterochromatic genes of <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>10958</fpage><lpage>10963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16033869</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b045"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andolfatto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Contrasting patterns of X-linked and autosomal nucleotide variation in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila simulans</named-content></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11230529</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b046"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bachtrog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andolfatto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Extensive introgression of mitochondrial DNA relative to nuclear genes in the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila yakuba</named-content> species group</article-title><source>Evolution Int J Org Evolution</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16610321</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b047"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreitman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Adaptative protein evolution at the <italic>Adh</italic> locus in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>351</volume><fpage>652</fpage><lpage>654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1904993</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b048"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Presgraves</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Evolutionary genomics: New genes for new jobs</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>R52</fpage><lpage>R53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15668155</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b049"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nurminsky</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurminskaya</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>De Aguiar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Selective sweep of a newly evolved sperm-specific gene in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>396</volume><fpage>572</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9859991</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b050"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loppin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepetit</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Couble</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Karr</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Origin and neofunctionalization of a <italic>Drosophila</italic> paternal effect gene essential for zygote viability</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15668163</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b051"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Custer</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Origin and evolution of a chimeric fusion gene in <italic>Drosophila subobscura, D. madeirensis</italic> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">D. guanche</named-content></article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>170</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15781692</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b052"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arguello</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Origination of an X-linked testes chimeric gene by illegitimate recombination in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e77.</elocation-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b053"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lifschytz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsley</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year><article-title>The role of X-chromosome inactivation during spermatogenesis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>69</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4621547</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b054"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Paucity of genes on the <italic>Drosophila</italic> X chromosome showing male-biased expression</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>299</volume><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12511656</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b055"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Castillo-Davis</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Meiklejohn</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Sex-dependent gene expression and evolution of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> transcriptome</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>300</volume><fpage>1742</fpage><lpage>1745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12805547</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b056"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hambuch</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Molecular evolution of sex-biased genes in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>2130</fpage><lpage>2139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15282334</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b057"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jagadeeshan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Rapidly evolving genes of <italic>Drosophila:</italic> Differing levels of selective pressure in testis, ovary, and head tissues between sibling species</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>1793</fpage><lpage>1801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15917496</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b058"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caceres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbadilla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Generation of a widespread <italic>Drosophila</italic> inversion by a transposable element</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>285</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10411506</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b059"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanguri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeke</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Voytas</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Transposable elements and genome organization: A comprehensive survey of retrotransposons revealed by the complete <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> genome sequence</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9582191</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b060"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kellis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Birren</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Proof and evolutionary analysis of ancient genome duplication in the yeast <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content></article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>428</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15004568</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b061"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>In situ hybridization to whole-mount <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos</article-title><comment>In:</comment><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Krieg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>A laboratory guide to RNA: Isolation, analysis, and synthesis</source><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley-Liss, Inc</publisher-name><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>369</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b062"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>CLUSTAL W: Improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, positions-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>4673</fpage><lpage>4680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b063"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>MEGA 3: Integrated software for molecular evolutionary genetics analysis and sequence alignment</article-title><source>Brief Bioinform</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15260895</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pgen-0030107-b064"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>DnaSP version 3: An integrated program for molecular population genetics and molecular evolution analysis</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10089204</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="n102" fn-type="previously-at"><p>A previous version of this article appeared as an Early Online Release on May 16, 2007 (doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pgen.0030107.eor">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030107.eor</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn id="ack1" fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author contributions.</bold> HPY designed the research. STC, HCC, DAB, and HPY performed the experiments. STC, HCC, and HPY analyzed the data. DAB and HPY wrote the paper.</p></fn><fn id="ack2" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by a grant (NSC 93&#x02013;2311-B-010&#x02013;008) to HPY from National Sciences Council, Taiwan.</p></fn><fn id="ack3" fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing interests.</bold> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article> 