<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkg731</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg731</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">12954762</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ligand-independent activation of estrogen receptor &#x003b1; by XBP-1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Lihua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Jinghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Jianhua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Hongjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Qiujun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Zonghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Cuifen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Qinong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="gkg731fn1">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x993d038.0x9b19b28"><label>1</label>Beijing Institute of Biotechnology, Beijing 100850, Peoples Republic of China, <label>2</label>Fujian Science and Technology University, Fuzhou 350002, Peoples Republic of China and <label>3</label>Beijing Institute of Radiation Medicine, Beijing 100850, Peoples Republic of China </aff><author-notes><fn id="gkg731fn1"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>To whom correspondence should be addressed at Beijing Institute of Biotechnology, 27 Tai-Ping Lu Rd, Beijing 100850, Peoples Republic of China. Tel: &#x0002b;86 10 6818 0809; Fax: &#x0002b;86 10 6824 8045; Email: <email>yeqn@nic.bmi.ac.cn</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><volume>31</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>5266</fpage><lpage>5274</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nar.oupjournals.org/content/vol31/issue18/"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2003</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2003 Oxford University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2003</copyright-year><abstract><p>The estrogen receptor (ER) is a member of a large superfamily of nuclear receptors that regulates the transcription of estrogen-responsive genes. Several recent studies have demonstrated that XBP-1 mRNA expression is associated with ER&#x003b1; status in breast tumors. However, the role of XBP-1 in ER&#x003b1; signaling remains to be elucidated. More recently, two forms of XBP-1 were identified due to its unconventional splicing. We refer to the spliced and unspliced forms of XBP-1 as XBP-1S and XBP-1U, respectively. Here, we report that XBP-1S and XBP-1U enhanced ER&#x003b1;-dependent transcriptional activity in a ligand-independent manner. XBP-1S had stronger activity than XBP-1U. The maximal effects of XBP-1S and XBP-1U on ER&#x003b1; transactivation were observed when they were co-expressed with full-length ER&#x003b1;. SRC-1, the p160 steroid receptor coactivator family member, synergized with XBP-1S or XBP-1U to potentiate ER&#x003b1; activity. XBP-1S and XBP-1U bound to the ER&#x003b1; both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> in a ligand-independent fashion. XBP-1S and XBP-1U interacted with the ER&#x003b1; region containing the DNA-binding domain. The ER&#x003b1;-interacting regions on XBP-1S and XBP-1U have been mapped to two regions, including the N-terminal basic region leucine zipper domain (bZIP) and the C-terminal activation domain. The bZIP-deleted mutants of XBP-1S and XBP-1U completely abolished ER&#x003b1; transactivation by XBP-1S and XBP-1U. These findings suggest that XBP-1S and XBP-1U may directly modulate ER&#x003b1; signaling in both the absence and presence of estrogen and, therefore, may play important roles in the proliferation of normal and malignant estrogen-regulated tissues.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The estrogen receptor (ER) belongs to a superfamily of nuclear receptors that act as ligand-activated transcription factors &#x0005b;for reviews see Klinge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c1">1</xref>), Katzenellenbogen and Katzenellenbogen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c2">2</xref>), and Aranda and Pascual (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c3">3</xref>)&#x0005d;. Based on structural and functional similarities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c5">5</xref>), the nuclear receptors can be subdivided into six regions (A&#x02013;F). Two domains are well conserved among nuclear receptors, the highly conserved C domain serving to direct DNA binding and the moderately conserved C-terminal E&#x0002f;F domain forming a pocket for ligand binding. The ligand-binding domain (LBD) contains a ligand-dependent transcriptional activation function (AF-2), whereas the quite divergent A&#x0002f;B domain contains another transactivation function (AF-1), which is constitutive in the absence of ligand. There are two isoforms of ERs, namely ER&#x003b1; and ER&#x003b2; &#x0005b;Kuiper <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c7">7</xref>), and references therein&#x0005d;. Activation of ER&#x003b1; is responsible for many biological processes, including cell growth and differentiation, morphogenesis and programmed cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c9">9</xref>). In addition, ER&#x003b1; plays an important role in the development and progression of breast cancer by regulating genes and signaling pathways involved in cellular proliferation. Regulation of gene expression by the ER&#x003b1; requires the coordinate activity of ligand binding, phosphorylation and cofactor interactions, with particular combinations probably resulting in the tissue-specific responses elicited by the receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c13">13</xref>). However, the intracellular signaling pathways modulating these components and regulating ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity are not fully understood.</p><p>Human X box-binding protein 1 (XBP-1), originally identified as a protein binding to the <italic>cis</italic>-acting X box present in the promoter regions of target genes, is a basic region leucine zipper (bZIP) protein in the CREB&#x0002f;ATF (cAMP response element-binding protein&#x0002f;activating transcription factor) family of transcription factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c14">14</xref>). XBP-1 has been found to be ubiquitously expressed in adult tissues but preferentially expressed in fetal exocrine glands, osteoblasts, chondroblasts and liver (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c15">15</xref>). XBP-1 is essential for the growth of hepatocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c16">16</xref>), as XBP-1-deficient embryos die <italic>in utero</italic> from severe liver hypoplasia and the resultant fatal anemia. In human multiple myeloma cells, XBP-1 has been shown to be implicated in the proliferation of malignant plasma cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c17">17</xref>). Since the cloning of XBP-1 over 10 years ago (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c14">14</xref>), there has been general acceptance that only one XBP-1 existed. More recently, however, XBP-1 mRNA has been shown to be unconventionally spliced by IRE1 in response to endoplasmic reticulum stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c19">19</xref>), resulting in production of a highly active transcription factor that can activate the mammalian unfolded protein response (UPR). The unconventional splicing of XBP-1 mRNA results in a frameshift at amino acid 165 of the unspliced XBP-1. Thus, unspliced and spliced XBP-1 mRNA encode proteins of 261 and 376 amino acids, respectively, with the identical N-terminal regions containing the bZIP domain. We refer to the spliced and unspliced forms of XBP-1 as XBP-1S and XBP-1U, respectively.</p><p>XBP-1 has been reported to be expressed at high levels in ER&#x003b1;-positive breast tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c25">25</xref>), although the forms of XBP-1 are unknown. Using cDNA arrays, Perou <italic>et al</italic>. described that variation of the ER&#x003b1; gene in 65 surgical specimens of human breast tumors from 42 different individuals paralleled variation in the expression of the XBP-1 gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c20">20</xref>). Bertucci <italic>et al</italic>. compared the gene expression profiles in ER&#x003b1;-positive breast cancers (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 23) versus ER&#x003b1;-negative breast cancers (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 11) with cDNA array technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c22">22</xref>). The XBP-1 mRNA expression in ER&#x003b1;-positive breast cancers was 2.7-fold as much as that in ER&#x003b1;-negative breast cancers. SAGE (serial analysis of gene expression) showed that XBP-1 appeared to be highly expressed in cancerous mammary epithelial cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c26">26</xref>). Because of the importance of ER&#x003b1; signaling in the regulation of breast cancer development and progression, we investigated the potential role of XBP-1 in ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity. Here, we show that both XBP-1S and XBP-1U enhance ER&#x003b1; transactivation in breast cancer and non-breast cells in a ligand-independent manner. We further present <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> evidence that XBP-1S and XBP-1U interact with ER&#x003b1;&#x0002c; and that deletion of the N-terminal portion of XBP-1S and XBP-1U fully abolishes the ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity by XBP-1S and XBP-1U.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Plasmids</title><p>The following plasmids have been described previously: pERE-LUC (estrogen-responsive element-containing luciferase reporter) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c27">27</xref>), a kind gift from Dr Ming-jer Tsai (Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX); pcDNA3-ER&#x003b1; (human ER&#x003b1; expression vector) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c27">27</xref>); pCMX-SRC-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c28">28</xref>), a kind gift from Dr Rosalie M. Uht (University of Virginia, VA); pcDNA-hAR &#x0005b;human androgen receptor (AR) expression vector&#x0005d; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c29">29</xref>); and PSA-LUC &#x0005b;androgen responsive element (ARE)-containing luciferase reporter&#x0005d; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c29">29</xref>), a generous gift from Dr Chinghai Kao (University of Indiana, Indianapolis, IN). To construct pcDNA3-FLAG-XBP-1S, full-length human XBP-1S cDNA was obtained by standard PCR amplification from an ovary two-hybrid cDNA library (Clontech). Full-length human XBP-1U cDNA was obtained using recombinant PCR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c27">27</xref>). The amplified XBP-1S and XBP-1U cDNAs were both cloned into pcDNA3 vector harboring FLAG epitope sequence (pcDNA3-FLAG), and the constructs were confirmed by sequencing. Deletion mutants of XBP-1S and XBP-1U were constructed by inserting PCR-generated fragments from the corresponding XBP-1 cDNAs into the pcDNA3-FLAG vector. The expression vectors for ER&#x003b1; AF-1 (amino acids 1&#x02013;282) and ER&#x003b1; AF-2 (amino acids 178&#x02013;595) were constructed by introducing the cDNAs into pcDNA3 (Invitrogen). Constructs encoding GST fusion proteins were prepared by amplification of each sequence by standard PCR methods, and the resulting fragments were cloned in-frame into pGEX-KG (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech), using appropriate restriction sites as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c30">30</xref>). The constructs were partially sequenced to confirm the correct orientation.</p></sec><sec><title>Mammalian cell transfection and luciferase assay</title><p>MDA-MB-435, MCF-7 and 293T cells were routinely cultured in Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified Eagle&#x02019;s medium (DMEM) (Invitrogen) containing 10&#x00025; newborn calf serum at 37&#x000b0;C in a humidified atmosphere of 5&#x00025; CO<sub>2</sub> in air. For transfection, MDA-MB-435, MCF-7 and 293T cells were seeded in 12-well plates containing phenol red-free RPMI 1640 medium (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10&#x00025; charcoal dextran-treated fetal bovine serum (Hyclone). The cells were transfected using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) with 0.2 &#x000b5;g of ERE-LUC or PSA-LUC reporter plasmid, 50 ng of ER&#x003b1; or AR expression vector, 0.1 &#x000b5;g of &#x003b2;-galactosidase reporter, and 20 ng&#x02013;0.5 &#x000b5;g of the expression vectors for XBP-1S or XBP-1U, and the respective empty vector was used to adjust the total amount of DNA. After treatment with 10 nM 17&#x003b2;-estradiol (E<sub>2</sub>; for ER&#x003b1;) or 2 nM R1881 (for AR) for 24 h, the transfected cells were harvested, and luciferase and &#x003b2;-galactosidase activities were determined as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c27">27</xref>). &#x003b2;-Galactosidase activity was used as an internal control for transfection efficiency. All experiments were repeated at least three times with similar results.</p></sec><sec><title>GST pull-down assay</title><p>GST and GST fusion proteins were expressed and purified according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (Pharmacia), with the induction of protein expression performed at 20&#x000b0;C overnight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c30">30</xref>). The expression vector for ER&#x003b1;, XBP-1S or XBP-1U was used for <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription and translation in the TNT Reticulocyte Lysate System (Promega). The <sup>35</sup>S-labeled ER&#x003b1;, XBP-1S or XBP-1U was mixed with 10 &#x000b5;g of GST derivatives bound to glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads in 0.5 ml of binding buffer &#x0005b;50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 0.3 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), 0.1&#x00025; NP-40 and protease inhibitor tablets from Roche&#x0005d;. The binding reaction was performed at 4&#x000b0;C overnight and the beads were subsequently washed four times with the washing buffer (the same as the binding buffer), 30 min each time. The beads were eluted in 10 &#x000b5;l of 2&#x000d7; SDS&#x02013;PAGE sample buffer and the proteins were resolved on a 10&#x00025; denaturing gel. The gel was then dried and exposed to X-ray films overnight.</p></sec><sec><title>Co-immunoprecipitation</title><p>293T cells were transfected using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). At 24 h post-transfection, cells were washed twice with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and lysed in 0.5 ml of lysis buffer (50 mM Tris at pH 8.0, 500 mM NaCl, 0.5&#x00025; NP-40, 1 mM DTT and protease inhibitor tablets from Roche). After brief sonication, the lysate was centrifuged at 14 000 r.p.m. for 15 min at 4&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was used for subsequent co-immunoprecipitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c30">30</xref>). A 15 &#x000b5;l aliquot of 50&#x00025; slurry of the anti-FLAG agarose beads (Sigma-Aldrich) was used in each immunoprecipitation. Immunoprecipitation was performed overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. The beads were centrifuged at 3000 r.p.m. for 2 min, and washed four times with the washing buffer (the same as the lysis buffer), with each wash lasting at least 30 min. The precipitates were then eluted in 30 &#x000b5;l of 2&#x000d7; SDS&#x02013;PAGE sample buffer and loaded on SDS&#x02013;polyacrylamide gels, followed by western blotting according to the standard procedures. A 4 &#x000b5;l aliquot of the input crude extract was used for detecting protein expression levels. The ER&#x003b1; proteins were detected using an anti-ER&#x003b1; polyclonal antibody (HC-20; Santa Cruz Biotechnology).</p></sec><sec><title>Gel shift assay</title><p>The double-stranded oligonucleotide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c31">31</xref>), corresponding to the consensus ERE (5&#x02032;-AGCTCTTTGATCAGGTCACTGTGACCTGACTTT-3&#x02032;) or mutant ERE (EREM; 5&#x02032;-AGCTCTTTGATCAGTACACTGTGACCTGACTTT-3&#x02032;), was <sup>32</sup>P-labeled using T4 polynucleotide kinase (Promega). Binding reactions (20 &#x000b5;l) were performed in the presence or absence of ligands (1 &#x000b5;M) for 30 min using <italic>in vitro</italic> translated protein or the same amount of unprogrammed lysate (Promega) in 10 mM Tris pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 4&#x00025; glycerol, 0.5 mM EDTA, 0.5 mM DTT and 0.1 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;&#x000b5;l poly(dT&#x02013;dC). The labeled ERE (0.5 ng) or EREM (0.5 ng) was then added, incubated for 20 min at room temperature, and analyzed on a 5&#x00025; polyacrylamide gel. Protein&#x02013;DNA binding was visualized by autoradiography.</p></sec><sec><title>RT&#x02013;PCR analysis</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using TRIzol reagent according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol (Invitrogen). First strand cDNA was reverse transcribed from 1.0 &#x000b5;g of total RNA with oligo(dT) primers using AMV reverse transcriptase as recommended by the supplier (Promega). A 1 &#x000b5;l aliquot of the first strand cDNA synthesis reaction mixture was used for PCR amplification in a total volume of 50 &#x000b5;l. The oligonucleotides 5&#x02032;-TCTGCTGAGTCCGCAGCAG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GAAAAGGGAGGCTGGTAAGGAAC-3&#x02032; were used for amplification of a 233 bp fragment of XBP-1S, and 5&#x02032;-TGGTTGCTGAAGAGGAGGCGGAAG-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-GAGATGTTCTGGAGGGGTGACAACTG-3&#x02032; for amplification of a 136 bp fragment of XBP-1U. PCR amplifications were performed for 35 cycles using the following cycling parameters: 94&#x000b0;C for 1 min, 68&#x000b0;C for 1 min and 72&#x000b0;C for 1 min. The RT&#x02013;PCR products were purified and ligated to a T vector, and the resulting positive clones were sequenced. &#x003b2;-Actin was amplified as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c32">32</xref>), and used as an internal control.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Potentiation of ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity by XBP-1S and XBP-1U</title><p>To investigate the effects of the XBP-1 proteins on ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity, human breast cancer MDA-MB-435 cells, which lack the ER&#x003b1;, were co-transfected with the estrogen response element-containing reporter ERE-LUC, ER&#x003b1; and increasing amounts of XBP-1S or XBP-1U. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f1">1</xref>A, in the absence and presence of E<sub>2</sub>, 0.5 &#x000b5;g of XBP-1S enhanced the transcriptional activity of ER&#x003b1; 32- and 15-fold, respectively, whereas 0.5 &#x000b5;g of XBP-1U only enhanced ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity 2.1- and 2.2-fold, respectively. This might be explained by the structural differences between the C-terminal transactivation domains of XBP-1S and XBP-1U. Both XBP-1S and XBP-1U increased ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activation in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f1">1</xref>A). It is important to note that the magnitude of the ligand-independent activation of the ER&#x003b1; by XBP-1S (0.5 &#x000b5;g) was 5-fold higher than that observed with E<sub>2</sub> (10 nM), and that XBP-1S and estrogen were synergistic in stimulating estrogen-regulated transcription. The activity of the ERE-LUC reporter activated by XBP-1S and XBP-1U decreased dramatically in the absence of exogeneous ER&#x003b1; (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f1">1</xref>B), indicating that ER&#x003b1; itself was required for the maximal effects of XBP-1S and XBP-1U on ERE-LUC reporter transcription.</p><p>To examine the effects of antiestrogens on ER&#x003b1; transactivation by XBP-1S and XBP-1U, MDA-MB-435 cells were co-transfected with the ERE-LUC reporter, ER&#x003b1; and XBP-1S or XBP-1U, and subsequently treated with antiestrogens, 4-hydroxytamoxifen (4-OHT) and ICI 182,780 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f1">1</xref>C). Both ICI 182,780 and 4-OHT completely blocked the effects of XBP-1U on ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity in the presence or absence of E<sub>2</sub>, whereas both ICI 182,780 and, to a lesser extent, 4-OHT reduced but did not abolish the ability of XBP-1S to transactivate ER&#x003b1;.</p><p>To determine whether the observed effects of XBP-1S and XBP-1U on ER&#x003b1; transactivation were specific to MDA-MB-435 cells, human breast cancer cell line MCF-7 and human embryonic kidney cell line 293T were used in co-transfection experiments. Although ER&#x003b1; transactivation by XBP-1S in MCF-7 and 293T cells was of a lower magnitude than in MDA-MB-435 cells, similar results were observed (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkg731tb1">1</xref>). The transcriptional activity of ER&#x003b1; co-activated by XBP-1S was always greater than that co-activated by XBP-1U. Thus, XBP-1S and XBP-1U can act as positive regulators of ER&#x003b1;-dependent transcriptional activation in a variety of mammalian cell lines. To verify that this E<sub>2</sub>-independent enhanced transcriptional activity was not a result of increased ER&#x003b1; protein production, we examined protein expression in whole-cell extracts using western blotting analysis. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f2">2</xref> shows that ER&#x003b1; levels were not increased by XBP-1S or XBP-1U expression. In addition, the greater effects of XBP-1S on ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activation were also not attributable to its high expression level. Conversely, the expression level of XBP-1S was lower than that of XBP-1U (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f2">2</xref>). Together, our results suggest that XBP-1S and XBP-1U could function as a co-regulator to enhance ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity in a ligand-independent manner.</p><p>To determine the specificity of XBP-1S and XBP-1U in ER&#x003b1;-mediated transactivation, we tested the effects of XBP-1S and XBP-1U on AR-mediated transactivation using the ARE-containing reporter construct PSA-LUC. As expected, transcription of the reporter was induced by an androgen, R1881, in MDA-MB-435, MCF-7 and 293T cells (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkg731tb2">2</xref>). XBP-1S and XBP-1U failed, however, to enhance AR-mediated transcription in both the presence and absence of R1881. Conversely, in the presence and absence of R1881, XBP-1S decreased AR transcriptional activity &#x0223c;2- and 4-fold, respectively, in MCF-7 and 293T cells (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkg731tb2">2</xref>). This result suggests that XBP-1S and XBP-1U may not be general co-activators for steroid receptors.</p></sec><sec><title>Both the N- and C-terminal domains of ER&#x003b1; contribute to ER&#x003b1; transactivation by XBP-1S and XBP-1U</title><p>To determine which domain of ER&#x003b1; is involved in the co-activation of ER&#x003b1; by XBP-1S and XBP-1U, ER&#x003b1; constructs containing N-terminal AF-1 and DNA-binding domain (DBD) (ABC domain) or C-terminal AF-2 and DBD (CDEF domain) were co-expressed with XBP-1S or XBP-1U in MDA-MB-435 cells. XBP-1S and, to a lesser extent, XBP-1U enhanced both the constitutive transactivation activity of AF-1 and ligand-dependent transcriptional activity of AF-2 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f3">3</xref>). However, co-expression of XBP-1S or XBP-1U with full-length ER&#x003b1; resulted in a more efficient enhancement of the reporter transcriptional activity (2- to 5-fold), compared with ABC and CDEF domains expressed separately (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f3">3</xref>). Thus, both N- and C-terminal domains of ER&#x003b1; contribute to ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity by XBP-1S and XBP-1U.</p></sec><sec><title>Cooperative co-activation of ER&#x003b1; by XBP-1 and SRC-1</title><p>SRC-1 is a member of the p160 steroid receptor coactivator (SRC) family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c33">33</xref>). SRC-1 interacts with ER&#x003b1; and stimulates E<sub>2</sub>-mediated gene transcription. SRC-1 enhances the interaction between the N-terminal AF-1-containing and C-terminal AF-2-containing regions of the ER&#x003b1;, allowing for full ER&#x003b1; activation. To determine whether XBP-1 plays a role in SRC-1-mediated co-activation of the ER&#x003b1;, MDA-MB-435 cells were co-transfected with the ERE-LUC reporter construct and expression vectors for XBP-1 and SRC-1 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkg731tb3">3</xref>). As expected, in the absence of E<sub>2</sub>, transfection of XBP-1S or XBP-1U alone co-activated ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity, whereas transfection of SRC-1 did not have a significant effect. Co-transfection with XBP-1S or XBP-1U, plus SRC-1 expression vectors gave greater than additive effects of XBP-1S or XBP-1U and SRC-1 measured independently. In the presence of E<sub>2</sub>, XBP-1S, XBP-1U and SRC-1 all enhanced ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity to different levels. When SRC-1 was co-expressed with either XBP-1S or XBP-1U, however, the ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity was cooperatively enhanced. Therefore, the synergistic enhancement of ER&#x003b1; activity by co-expression of SRC-1 and XBP-1S or XBP-1U is ligand independent.</p></sec><sec><title>Interaction of XBP-1S and XBP-1U with ER&#x003b1; <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic></title><p>Our observation that XBP-1S and XBP-1U could function as a co-regulator to enhance ligand-independent ER&#x003b1; transactivation suggested that XBP-1S and XBP-1U might physically interact with ER&#x003b1;. To test this possibility, GST pull-down experiments were performed in which <italic>in vitro</italic> translated &#x0005b;<sup>35</sup>S&#x0005d;methionine-labeled XBP-1S or XBP-1U was incubated with full-length GST&#x02013;ER&#x003b1;. The binding of XBP-1S and XBP-1U to GST&#x02013;ER&#x003b1;, but not to GST, was observed in both the absence and presence of E<sub>2</sub> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f4">4</xref>A). E<sub>2</sub> did not increase the interaction of XBP-1S and XBP-1U with GST&#x02013;ER&#x003b1;. Notably, the binding of XBP-1S to ER&#x003b1; was stronger than that of XBP-1U to ER&#x003b1;.</p><p>To determine whether XBP-1S and XBP-1U interact with ER&#x003b1; <italic>in vivo</italic>, 293T cells were transfected with ER&#x003b1; and FLAG-tagged XBP-1S or XBP-1U and cultured in both the absence (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f4">4</xref>B) and presence of 10 nM E<sub>2</sub> (data not shown). FLAG-XBP-1S or XBP-1U was immunoprecipitated from cell lysates by an anti-FLAG antibody and analyzed for ER&#x003b1; binding by western blotting analysis. The results showed that ER&#x003b1; could be co-immunoprecipitated in a ligand-independent manner in the presence, but not in the absence, of FLAG-XBP-1S or FLAG-XBP-1U (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f4">4</xref>B, and data not shown). Consistent with the co-activation results, the binding of XBP-1S to ER&#x003b1; was stronger than that of XBP-1U to ER&#x003b1;. The <italic>in vivo</italic> interaction of XBP-1S and XBP-1U with ER&#x003b1; was unlikely to be mediated by nucleic acids, as it was not affected by the treatment with ethidium bromide that disrupts DNA&#x02013;protein interaction (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Mapping of the ER&#x003b1; and XBP-1 interaction domains</title><p>To determine which region of ER&#x003b1; binds to XBP-1S or XBP-1U, GST pull-down experiments were performed. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f4">4</xref>C, the GST&#x02013;ER&#x003b1;(180&#x02013;282) containing the DBD bound specifically to <italic>in vitro</italic> translated &#x0005b;<sup>35</sup>S&#x0005d;methionine-labeled XBP-1S or XBP-1U, but the GST-ER&#x003b1;(1&#x02013;185) containing the AF-1 and the GST&#x02013;ER&#x003b1;(282&#x02013;595) containing the AF-2 did not. Consistent with the <italic>in vivo</italic> binding results, XBP-1S interacted with GST&#x02013;ER&#x003b1;(180&#x02013;282) <italic>in vitro</italic> more strongly than XBP-1U.</p><p>XBP-1S and XBP-1U are proteins of 261 and 376 amino acids, respectively, with an identical N-terminus (amino acids 1&#x02013;164). To delineate the domains in the XBP-1S and XBP-1U that mediate the protein&#x02013;protein interaction with ER&#x003b1;, a series of mutant GST&#x02013;XBP-1 fusion proteins were used in GST pull-down experiments (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f4">4</xref>D). Deletion of the XBP-1 N-terminal amino acids (1&#x02013;82) reduced but did not abolish the ability of the XBP-1 proteins to bind to the ER&#x003b1;. Either region (amino acids 1&#x02013;101, containing the bZIP domain, or either amino acids 148&#x02013;376 or amino acids 148&#x02013;261, containing the transactivation domain) of XBP-1S or XBP-1U was sufficient for ER&#x003b1; binding. However, the full-length GST&#x02013;XBP-1 interacted with ER&#x003b1; more strongly than any GST&#x02013;XBP-1 fragments. In addition, GST&#x02013;XBP-1S associated with ER&#x003b1; more strongly than GST&#x02013;XBP-1U.</p></sec><sec><title>The N-terminal portion of XBP-1 is required for ER&#x003b1; transactivation function</title><p>To test the possibility that the maximal interaction of XBP-1S and XBP-1U with ER&#x003b1; is required for the enhancement of ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activation, mutants of XBP-1S and XBP-1U (&#x00394;XBP-1S and &#x00394;XBP-1U) were made in which the N-terminal region from amino acids 1 to 82 was deleted. MDA-MB-435 cells were co-transfected with the ERE-LUC reporter, ER&#x003b1; and either FLAG-tagged XBP-1S, XBP-1U, &#x00394;XBP-1S or &#x00394;XBP-1U. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f5">5</xref>A, the mutations lacking some of the ER&#x003b1;-binding sites completely abolished the ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activation in a ligand-independent manner. This is not attributable to decreased expression of the &#x00394;XBP-1S and the &#x00394;XBP-1U deletion mutants. In contrast, &#x00394;XBP-1S and &#x00394;XBP-1U were expressed at higher levels than XBP-1S and XBP-1U (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f5">5</xref>B). Taken together, these findings suggest that the XBP-1S and XBP-1U action of ER&#x003b1; by their maximal binding contributes to the transactivation function of ER&#x003b1;.</p></sec><sec><title>Neither XBP-1S nor XBP-1U binds to ERE</title><p>The transcription factor XBP-1 was found to bind preferably to the cAMP responsive element (CRE)-like element GATGACGTG(T&#x0002f;G)nnn(A&#x0002f;T)T (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c34">34</xref>). ER&#x003b1; binds to the ERE GGTCAnnnTGACC. Since both XBP-1 and ER&#x003b1; target sequences have the sequence TGAC, we tested whether XBP-1S and XBP-1U bind to the consensus ERE, using a gel shift assay. As expected, the <sup>32</sup>P-labeled ERE, but not mutant ERE (EREM), bound to <italic>in vitro</italic>-translated ER&#x003b1; in the absence or presence of E<sub>2</sub> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f6">6</xref> and data not shown). The binding was specifically inhibited by a 100-fold molar excess of a cold ERE oligonucleotide. Moreover, neither XBP-1S nor XBP-1U bound to the ERE.</p></sec><sec><title>XBP-1S and XBP-1U mRNAs are expressed in breast cancer cell lines</title><p>Human XBP-1 (XBP-1U) was originally isolated as a transcription factor which binds to the X2 box present in the promoter region of human major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class II genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c14">14</xref>). More recently, XBP-1U mRNA was found to be spliced in response to the endoplasmic reticulum stress, resulting in XBP-1S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c19">19</xref>). To determine whether XBP-1S mRNA is expressed in breast cancer cells, we prepared mRNA from five ER-positive (MCF10A, T47D, MCF7, ZR75-1 and BT474) and five ER-negative (MDA-MB-436, MDA-MB-435, MDA-MB-231, SKBR3 and MDA-MB-453) breast cancer cell lines and performed RT&#x02013;PCR using primers specific for the unique XBP-1S region. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f7">7</xref>, in addition to XBP-1U mRNA, we could also detect XBP-1S mRNA in all of the breast cancer cell lines tested. The identity of XBP-1S detected was further confirmed by DNA sequencing. XBP-1S was also expressed in the immortalized normal breast epithelial cell line MCF-10A, although at a lower level. Since a limited number of breast cancer cell lines were examined, there is no significant correlation between XBP-1 and ER&#x003b1; expression. However, both XBP-1S and XBP-1U were widely expressed in breast cancer cells. Interestingly, XBP-1S was also expressed in mammary and ovary two-hybrid cDNA libraries, which were prepared from the corresponding tissues of individuals who died from trauma, indicating that XBP-1S is more widely expressed than previously thought. After searching expressed sequence tags (ESTs) for XBP-1S in GenBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/blast">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/blast</ext-link>), we also found that human XBP-1S mRNA is expressed in breast adenocarcinoma, lung tumor, stomach, brain, skin and pancreas, and mouse XBP-1S is expressed in mammary tumor, lung tumor metastatic to mammary, and neural retina. Taken together, these data suggest that, like XBP-1U, XBP-1S may play a critical role under physiological and pathological conditions.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Several recent studies using cDNA microarray analysis have shown that XBP-1 mRNA expression is associated with ER&#x003b1; status in breast tumors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c25">25</xref>), although the forms of XBP-1 are unknown. This raises at least two possibilities: (i) XBP-1 participates in regulating the ER&#x003b1; promoter or ER&#x003b1; in regulating the XBP-1 promoter; and (ii) XBP-1 interacts with ER&#x003b1;. In this manuscript, we report for the first time that XBP-1 physically and functionally interacts with ER&#x003b1; in a ligand-independent manner. Since XBP-1S and XBP-1U do not bind to the ERE, it is possible that ER&#x003b1; recruits XBP-1 to the ERE-containing promoter to stimulate gene transcription.</p><p>ER&#x003b1; has been shown to interact with a number of cofactors, including co-activators and co-repressors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c1">1</xref>). Almost all of the co-activators enhance ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity in a ligand-dependent fashion. They include the SRC-1 family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c35">35</xref>), CBP&#x0002f;p300 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c37">37</xref>), p68 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c38">38</xref>), ARA70 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c39">39</xref>) and many others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c1">1</xref>). In addition to the conventional ligand-dependent regulation of the activity of ER&#x003b1;, ER&#x003b1; has been shown to be activated by non-steroidal agents including dopamine and growth factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c40">40</xref>). This ligand-independent activation is possibly due to the ER&#x003b1; phosphorylation. However, by definition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c1">1</xref>), none of the agents are co-activators, as they do not interact with ER&#x003b1;. Cyclin D1 is the first co-activator to have been shown to enhance ER&#x003b1; transactivation in a ligand-independent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c43">43</xref>). Cyclin D1 acts through physical association to activate ER&#x003b1;. To the best of our knowledge, XBP-1 is the second co-activator to enhance ligand-independent ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activation. XBP-1S, the spliced form of XBP-1, is more potent in ER&#x003b1; activation than XBP-1U, the unspliced form of XBP-1. This is consistent with the stronger binding affinity of XBP-1S for ER&#x003b1; both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. Effects of antiestrogens on the cyclin D1-induced activation of the ER&#x003b1; are controversial. Neuman <italic>et al</italic>. have shown that ICI 182,780 and, to a lesser extent, 4-OHT significantly inhibit cyclin D1-mediated activation of the ER&#x003b1;, which is in contrast to the findings of Zwijsen <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c42">42</xref>). In our study, both ICI 182,780 and 4-OHT inhibited the effects of XBP-1 on ER&#x003b1; activity in a similar manner to that reported by Neuman <italic>et al</italic>.</p><p>Co-activators that interact with the DBD of nuclear receptors are less characterized or defined. Our study showed that XBP-1S and XBP-1U interact with the ER&#x003b1; region containing the DBD. Recently, several co-activators that interact with the DBDs of nuclear receptors have been reported, including GT198 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c44">44</xref>) and SNURF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c45">45</xref>). GT198 interacted with the DBD of glucocorticoid receptor (GR) and potently stimulated transcription mediated by GR. SNURF is a small RING finger protein that co-activates AR-mediated transcription through interaction with the DBD of AR. Since the DBDs of nuclear receptors are highly conserved, we determined the effects of XBP-1U and XBP-1S on AR-mediated transcription. In contrast to the co-activation of ER&#x003b1; by XBP-1S and XBP-1U, XBP-1S decreased transcriptional activity of AR in a cell type-dependent manner, whereas XBP-1U had little effect on AR transcriptional activation (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkg731tb2">2</xref>). This may be exemplified by the cofactor RIP140 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c50">50</xref>). This cofactor interacts with ER&#x003b1; and increases ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity in the presence of E<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c51">51</xref>). RIP140 has also been shown to act as a co-activator for the rat AR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c47">47</xref>). However, recent studies have indicated that RIP140 represses the transcriptional activation of the GR and the orphan nuclear receptor TR2 by interaction with the receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c49">49</xref>). It will be interesting to examine the effects of XBP-1S and XBP-1U on the transcriptional activities of other nuclear receptors.</p><p>Although XBP-1 mRNA expression levels have been shown to be elevated during cancer development and progression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c26">26</xref>), the forms of XBP-1 are unclear. Initially, XBP-1U was thought to be the only form of XBP-1 mRNA expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c14">14</xref>). Recently, it was shown that XBP-1S was expressed in response to endoplasmic reticulum stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c19">19</xref>). XBP-1S was also found to be induced during the differentiation of antibody-secreting B cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c50">50</xref>). We report here that XBP-1S mRNA is constitutively expressed in breast cancer cell lines as well as an immortalized human mammary epithelial cell line. Future experiments are required to test whether XBP-1S is expressed in clinical samples. Since the XBP-1 mRNA expression pattern is highly correlated with ER&#x003b1; and highly upregulated in a subset of breast cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg731c26">26</xref>), XBP-1, especially XBP-1S, may play an important role in breast cancer growth and represent a new target for therapeutic intervention.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig id="gkg731f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p> XBP-1S and XBP-1U enhance ER&#x003b1;-mediated transactivation in MDA-MB-435 cells. (<bold>A</bold>) Effects of XBP-1S and XBP-1U on ER&#x003b1;-mediated transactivation. Cells were co-transfected with 0.2 &#x000b5;g of ERE-LUC, 50 ng of the expression plasmid for ER&#x003b1; and increasing amounts of the expression vector for either XBP-1S or XBP-1U as indicated. Cells were then treated with control (0.1&#x00025; ethanol) vehicle or 10 nM E<sub>2</sub> for 24 h before luciferase assay. The LUC activity obtained on transfection of ERE-LUC and ER&#x003b1; without exogenous XBP-1S and XBP-1U in the absence of E<sub>2</sub> was set as 1. Results are expressed as means &#x000b1; SE for three independent experiments. (<bold>B</bold>) Effect of ER&#x003b1; on ERE-LUC reporter gene transcription by XBP-1S and XBP-1U. Cells were co-transfected with 0.2 &#x000b5;g of ERE-LUC and 0.5 &#x000b5;g of the expression vector for either XBP-1S or XBP-1U in both the absence and presence of the expression plasmid for ER&#x003b1;&#x0002e; Cells were then treated and analyzed as in (A). (<bold>C</bold>) Effects of antiestrogens on ERE-LUC reporter gene transcription by XBP-1S and XBP-1U. Cells were co-transfected with 0.2 &#x000b5;g of ERE-LUC, 50 ng of the expression plasmid for ER&#x003b1; and 0.5 &#x000b5;g of the expression vector for either XBP-1S or XBP-1U. Cells were then treated with control (0.1&#x00025; ethanol) vehicle, 10 nM E<sub>2</sub>, 100 nM 4-OHT or 100 nM ICI 182,780 for 24 h before luciferase assay. Cells were analyzed as in (A).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg731f1"/></fig><fig id="gkg731f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p> Western blotting showing the ER&#x003b1;, XBP-1S and XBP-1U protein levels in 293T cells. Cells were transfected as in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkg731tb1">1</xref>. Whole-cell extracts were prepared, and equivalent amounts of each extract were probed with anti-ER&#x003b1; antibody (H-184; Santa Cruz Biotech) or anti-XBP-1 antibody (SC-7160; Santa Cruz Biotechnology).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg731f2"/></fig><fig id="gkg731f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p> Both N- and C-terminal domains contribute to ER&#x003b1; transcriptional activity regulated by XBP-1S and XBP-1U. MDA-MB-435 cells were co-transfected with 50 ng of the expression vector for ER&#x003b1;, ER&#x003b1; ABC domain or ER&#x003b1; CDEF domain, 0.2 &#x000b5;g of ERE-LUC and 0.5 &#x000b5;g of the expression vector for either XBP-1S or XBP-1U as indicated. The LUC activity obtained on transfection of ERE-LUC without exogenous ER&#x003b1;&#x0002c; ER&#x003b1; ABC domain, ER&#x003b1; CDEF domain, XBP-1S and XBP-1U in the absence of E<sub>2</sub> was set as 1. Results are expressed as means &#x000b1; SE for three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg731f3"/></fig><fig id="gkg731f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p> XBP-1S and XBP-1U bind to ER&#x003b1; <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic>. (<bold>A</bold>) Interaction of XBP-1S and XBP-1U with ER&#x003b1; <italic>in vitro</italic>. GST pull-down assay was performed as described in Materials and Methods. Full-length GST&#x02013;ER&#x003b1; fusion proteins, immobilized on beads, were mixed with <italic>in vitro</italic> translation reaction mixtures of XBP-1S or XBP-1U in the absence or presence of E<sub>2</sub> (10<sup>&#x02013;6</sup> M) as indicated. The bound proteins were subjected to SDS&#x02013;PAGE followed by autoradiography. (<bold>B</bold>) Interactions between either XBP-1S or XBP-1U and ER&#x003b1; <italic>in vivo</italic>. 293T cells were co-transfected with the expression vectors for either the FLAG-tagged XBP-1 or the FLAG-tagged XBP-1U and ER&#x003b1; as indicated. Lysates from the transfected cells were immunoprecipitated (IP) using anti-FLAG antibody (Sigma-Aldrich), and the immunoprecipitates were probed with an anti-ER&#x003b1; antibody (HC-20; Santa Cruz Biotech). (<bold>C</bold>) Mapping of interaction regions of XBP-1S and XBP-1U in ER&#x003b1;. GST pull-down assay was performed using <sup>35</sup>S-labeled XBP-1S or XBP-1U and fusion proteins between GST and three different ER&#x003b1; fragments. (<bold>D</bold>) Mapping of the ER&#x003b1; interaction region in XBP-1S and XBP-1U. GST pull-down assay was performed using <sup>35</sup>S-labeled ER&#x003b1; and fusion proteins between GST and six different XBP-1 fragments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg731f4a"/><graphic xlink:href="gkg731f4b"/></fig><fig id="gkg731f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p> The deletion mutants of XBP-1S and XBP-1U abolished the ER&#x003b1; transactivation. (<bold>A</bold>) MDA-MB-435 cells were co-transfected with 0.2 &#x000b5;g of ERE-LUC, 50 ng of the expression plasmid for ER&#x003b1; and 0.5 &#x000b5;g of the expression vector for FLAG-tagged XBP-1S, XBP-1S&#x00394;82, XBP-1U or XBP-1U&#x00394;82 as indicated. Cells were then treated with control (0.1&#x00025; ethanol) vehicle or 10 nM E<sub>2</sub> for 24 h before luciferase assay. The LUC activity obtained on transfection of ERE-LUC and ER&#x003b1; without exogenous XBP-1 and its derivatives in the absence of E<sub>2</sub> was set as 1. Results are expressed as means &#x000b1; SE for three independent experiments. (<bold>B</bold>) Western blotting showing expression of FLAG-tagged XBP-1S, XBP-1S&#x00394;82, XBP-1U and XBP-1U&#x00394;82. Cells were transfected as in (A). Whole-cell extracts were prepared, and equivalent amounts of each extract were probed with anti-FLAG antibody (Sigma-Aldrich).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg731f5"/></fig><fig id="gkg731f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p> Neither XBP-1S nor XBP-1U binds to ERE. Gel shift assay was performed as described in Materials and Methods. The <sup>32</sup>P-labeled ERE probe was incubated with the <italic>in vitro</italic>-translated ER&#x003b1;, XBP-1S and XBP-1U proteins as indicated, in the presence of 1 &#x000b5;M E<sub>2</sub>. For competition experiments, a 100-fold molar excess of unlabeled ERE was mixed with the radioactive probe. The <sup>32</sup>P-labeled mutant ERE (EREM) probe was used as a negative control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg731f6"/></fig><fig id="gkg731f7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p> XBP-1 mRNA expression in breast cancer cell lines. RT&#x02013;PCR from the selected cell lines and cDNA libraries was performed as described in Materials and Methods. &#x003b2;-Actin was used as an internal control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg731f7"/></fig><table-wrap id="gkg731tb1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>XBP-1S and XBP-1U enhance ER&#x003b1;-mediated transactivation</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">Expressed proteins</th><th colspan="4" align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">Activation of transcription (fold activation)</th></tr><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">MCF7 cells</th><th colspan="2" align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">293T cells</th></tr><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">&#x000a0;</th><th align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">&#x02013;E<sub>2</sub></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">&#x0002b;E<sub>2</sub></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">&#x02013;E<sub>2</sub></th><th align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">&#x0002b;E<sub>2</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ER&#x003b1;</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">3.9 &#x000b1; 0.3</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">5.3 &#x000b1; 0.6</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ER&#x003b1;, XBP-1S</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">5.1 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">14.0 &#x000b1; 1.2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">7.6 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">28.8 &#x000b1; 3.0</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ER&#x003b1;, XBP-1U</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">2.0 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">7.3 &#x000b1; 0.5</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">2.7 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">10.3 &#x000b1; 0.6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Cells were transfected, treated and analyzed as described in the legend to Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f1">1</xref>A.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="gkg731tb2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>XBP-1S and XBP-1U do not enhance AR-mediated transactivation</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col/><col/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col/><col align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">Expressed proteins</th><th colspan="6" valign="top">Activation of transcription (fold activation)</th></tr><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="2" valign="top">MDA-MB-435 cells</th><th colspan="2" valign="top">MCF7 cells</th><th colspan="2" valign="top">293T cells</th></tr><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">&#x000a0;</th><th valign="top">&#x02013;R1881</th><th align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">&#x0002b;R1881</th><th valign="top">&#x02013;R1881</th><th align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">&#x0002b;R1881</th><th valign="top">&#x02013;R1881</th><th align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">&#x0002b;R1881</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">AR</td><td valign="top">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">10.2 &#x000b1; 1.2</td><td valign="top">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">12.5 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td valign="top">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">20.5 &#x000b1; 0.8</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">AR, XBP-1S</td><td valign="top">0.62 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">14.1 &#x000b1; 3.3</td><td valign="top">0.25 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">6.6 &#x000b1; 1.9</td><td valign="top">0.27 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">9.6 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">AR, XBP-1U</td><td valign="top">1.2 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">14.2 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td valign="top">1.2 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">10.7 &#x000b1; 2.8</td><td valign="top">0.94 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#x000b1;">20.5 &#x000b1; 3.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Cells were co-transfected with 0.2 &#x000b5;g of PSA-LUC, 50 ng of the expression plasmid for AR and 0.5 &#x000b5;g of the expression vector for either XBP-1S or XBP-1U, as indicated. Cells were then treated with control (0.1&#x00025; ethanol) vehicle or 2 nM R1881 for 24 h before luciferase assay. The LUC activity obtained on transfection of PSA-LUC and AR without exogenous XBP-1S and XBP-1U in the absence of R1881 was set as 1.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="gkg731tb3"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Synergistic enhancement of ER&#x003b1; activity by SRC-1 and XBP-1</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">Expressed proteins</th><th colspan="2" valign="top">Activation of transcription (fold activation)</th></tr><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">&#x02013;E<sub>2</sub></th><th valign="top">&#x0002b;E<sub>2</sub></th><td>&#x000a0;</td></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ER&#x003b1;</td><td valign="top">1</td><td valign="top">4.0 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ER&#x003b1;, XBP-1S</td><td valign="top">22.5 &#x000b1; 1.5</td><td valign="top">68.4 &#x000b1; 5.8</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ER&#x003b1;, XBP-1U</td><td valign="top">1.9 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td valign="top">9.2 &#x000b1; 0.9</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ER&#x003b1;, SRC-1</td><td valign="top">1.1 &#x000b1; 0.1</td><td valign="top">11.4 &#x000b1; 1.0</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ER&#x003b1;, SRC-1, XBP-1S</td><td valign="top">53.2 &#x000b1; 2.9</td><td valign="top">136.3 &#x000b1; 7.7</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ER&#x003b1;, SRC-1, XBP-1U</td><td valign="top">5.3 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td valign="top">37.1 &#x000b1; 2.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>MDA-MB-435 cells were co-transfected with 0.2 &#x003bc;g of ERE-LUC, 50 ng of the expression vector for ER&#x003b1;, 0.5 &#x003bc;g of the expression vector for SRC-1 and 0.5 &#x003bc;g of the expression vector for either XBP-1S or XBP-1U, as indicated. Cells were treated and analyzed as described in the legend to Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg731f1">1</xref>A.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><ack><sec><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank Rong Li for sharing reagents, Philip Leder and Fen Zhou for kindly providing the MCF10A, MDA-MB-435, MDA-MB-436, MDA-MB-453, ZR75-1, SKBR3 and BT474 cell lines, and Hsiang-Fu Kung for critical reading of the manuscript. This work was supported by Innovative Grant from AMMS and SRF for ROCS, and Fujian Qian Bai Wan Outstanding Scientist Plan Grant.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="gkg731c1"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Klinge</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name> (2000) Estrogen receptor interaction with co-activators and co-repressors. <source>Steroids</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>251</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10751636</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c2"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Katzenellenbogen</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name> and Katzenellenbogen,J.A. (2000) Estrogen receptor transcription and transactivation: estrogen receptor alpha and estrogen receptor beta: regulation by selective estrogen receptor modulators and importance in breast cancer. <source>Breast Cancer Res.</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>344</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11250726</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c3"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and Pascual,A. (2001) Nuclear hormone receptors and gene expression. <source>Physiol. Rev.</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>1269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1304</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11427696</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c4"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Krust</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, Green,S., Argos,P., Kumar,V., Walter,P., Bornert,J.M. and Chambon,P. (1986) The chicken oestrogen receptor sequence: homology with v-erbA and the human oestrogen and glucocorticoid receptors. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>891</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>897</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3755102</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c5"><label>5.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Mangelsdorf</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name>, Thummel,C., Beato,M., Herrlich,P., Schutz,G., Umesono,K., Blumberg,B., Kastner,P., Mark,M. and Chambon,P. (1995) The nuclear receptor superfamily: the second decade, <source>Cell</source>, <volume>83</volume>, <fpage>835</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>839</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8521507</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c6"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name>, Enmark,E., Pelto-Huikko,M., Nilsson,S. and Gustafsson,J.A. (1996) Cloning of a novel receptor expressed in rat prostate and ovary. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>93</volume>, <fpage>5925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5930</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8650195</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c7"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name>, Carlsson,B., Grandien,K., Enmark,E., Haggblad,J., Nilsson,S. and Gustafsson,J.A. (1997) Comparison of the ligand binding specificity and transcript tissue distribution of estrogen receptors alpha and beta. <source>Endocrinology</source>, <volume>138</volume>, <fpage>863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>870</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9048584</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c8"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Katzenellenbogen</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name> (1996) Estrogen receptors: bioactivities and interactions with cell signaling pathways. <source>Biol. Reprod.</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8788178</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c9"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Katzenellenbogen</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name>, Montano,M.M., Ekena,K., Herman,M.E. and McInerney,E.M. (1997) Antiestrogens: mechanisms of action and resistance in breast cancer. <source>Breast Cancer Res. Treat.</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9164675</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c10"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Robyr</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, Wolffe,A.P. and Wahli,W. (2000) Nuclear hormone receptor coregulators in action: diversity for shared tasks. <source>Mol. Endocrinol.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>347</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10707952</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c11"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Schapira</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Raaka,B.M., Samuels,H.H. and Abagyan,R. (2000) Rational discovery of novel nuclear hormone receptor antagonists. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>1008</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1013</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10655475</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c12"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name> (1996) Steroid hormone receptors and their regulation by phosphorylation. <source>Biochem. J.</source>, <volume>319</volume>, <fpage>657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>667</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8920964</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c13"><label>13.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name>, Knoblauch,R. and Garabedian,M.J. (2001) Rho GTPases as modulators of the estrogen receptor transcriptional response. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>276</volume>, <fpage>3231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3237</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11060289</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c14"><label>14.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Liou</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name>, Boothby,M.R., Finn,P.W., Davidon,R., Nabavi,N., Zeleznik-Le,N.J., Ting,J.P. and Glimcher,L.H. (1990) A new member of the leucine zipper class of proteins that binds to the HLA DR alpha promoter. <source>Science</source>, <volume>247</volume>, <fpage>1581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1584</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2321018</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c15"><label>15.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Clauss</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name>, Gravallese,E.M., Darling,J.M., Shapiro,F., Glimcher,M.J. and Glimcher,L.H. (1993) <italic>In situ</italic> hybridization studies suggest a role for the basic region-leucine zipper protein hXBP-1 in exocrine gland and skeletal development during mouse embryogenesis. <source>Dev. Dyn.</source>, <volume>197</volume>, <fpage>146</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>156</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7693055</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c16"><label>16.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Riemold</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name>, Etkin,A., Clauss,I., Perkins,A., Friend,D.S., Zhang,J., Horton,H.F., Scott,A., Orkin,S.H., Byrne,M.C., Grusby,M.J. and Glimcher,L.H. (2000) An essential role in liver development for transcription factor XBP-1. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>157</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10652269</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c17"><label>17.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Riemold</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name>, Iwakoshi,N.N., Manis,J., Vallabhajosyula,P., Szomolanyi-Tsuda,E., Gravallese,E.M., Friend,D., Grusby,M.J., Alt,F. and Glimcher,L.H. (2001) Plasma cell differentiation requires the transcription factor XBP-1. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>412</volume>, <fpage>300</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11460154</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c18"><label>18.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, Matsui,T., Yamamoto,A., Okada,T. and Mori,K. (2001) XBP1 mRNA is induced by ATF6 and spliced by IRE1 in response to ER stress to produce a highly active transcription factor. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>881</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>891</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11779464</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c19"><label>19.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Calfon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Zeng,H., Urano,F., Till,J.H., Hubbard,S.R., Harding,H.P., Clark,S.G. and Ron,D. (2002) IRE1 couples endoplasmic reticulum load to secretory capacity by processing the XBP-1 mRNA. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>415</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11780124</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c20"><label>20.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Perou</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name>, Sorlie,T., Eisen,M.B., van de Rijn,M., Jeffrey,S.S., Rees,C.A., Pollack,J.R., Ross,D.T., Johnsen,H., Akslen,L.A., Fluge,O., Pergamenschikov,A., Williams,C., Zhu,S.X., Lonning,P.E., Borresen-Dale,A.L., Brown,P.O. and Botstein,D. (2000) Molecular portraits of human breast tumours. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>406</volume>, <fpage>747</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>752</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10963602</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c21"><label>21.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>van't Veer</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name>, Dai,H., van de Vijver,M.J., He,Y.D., Hart,A.A., Mao,M., Peterse,H.L., van der Kooy,K., Marton,M.J., Witteveen,A.T., Schreiber,G.J., Kerkhoven,R.M., Roberts,C., Linsley,P.S., Bernards,R. and Friend,S.H. (2002) Gene expression profiling predicts clinical outcome of breast cancer. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>415</volume>, <fpage>530</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>536</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11823860</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c22"><label>22.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bertucci</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Houlgatte,R., Benziane,A., Granjeaud,S., Adelaide,J., Tagett,R., Loriod,B., Jacquemier,J., Viens,P., Jordan,B., Birnbaum,D. and Nguyen,C. (2000) Gene expression profiling of primary breast carcinomas using arrays of candidate genes. <source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>2981</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2991</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11115842</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c23"><label>23.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bertucci</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Nasser,V., Granjeaud,S., Eisinger,F., Adelaide,J., Tagett,R., Loriod,B. Giaconia,A., Benziane,A., Devilard,E., Jacquemier,J., Viens,P., Nguyen,C., Birnbaum,D. and Houlgatte,R. (2002) Gene expression profiles of poor-prognosis primary breast cancer correlate with survival. <source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>872</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11971868</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c24"><label>24.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Iwao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, Matoba,R., Ueno,N., Ando,A., Miyoshi,Y., Matsubara,K., Noguchi,S. and Kato,K. (2002) Molecular classification of primary breast tumors possessing distinct prognostic properties. <source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>206</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11809729</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c25"><label>25.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Blanchette,C., Dressman,H., Huang,E., Ishida,S., Spang,R., Zuzan,H., Olson,J.A.J., Marks,J.R. and Nevins,J.R. (2001) Predicting the clinical status of human breast cancer by using gene expression profiles. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>11462</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11467</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11562467</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c26"><label>26.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name>, Krop,I.E., Nasser,S., Sgroi,D., Kaelin,C.M., Marks,J.R., Riggins,G. and Polyak,K. (2001) A SAGE (serial analysis of gene expression) view of breast tumor progression. <source>Cancer Res.</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>5697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5702</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11479200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c27"><label>27.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, Chung,L.W., Cinar,B., Li,S. and Zhau,H.E. (2000) Identification and characterization of estrogen receptor variants in prostate cancer cell lines. <source>J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11179905</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c28"><label>28.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X.F.,</given-names></name> Anderson,C.M., Ma,H., Hong,H., Uht,R.M., Kushner,P.J. and Stallcup,M.R. (1998) Nuclear receptor-binding sites of coactivators glucocorticoid receptor interacting protein 1 (GRIP1) and steroid receptor coactivator 1 (SRC-1): multiple motifs and different binding specificities. <source>Mol. Endocrinol.</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>302</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>313</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9482670</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c29"><label>29.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Cinar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, Koeneman,K.S., Edlund,M., Prins,G.S., Zhau,H.E. and Chung,L.W. (2001) Androgen receptor mediates the reduced tumor growth, enhanced androgen responsiveness and selected target gene transactivation in a human prostate cancer cell line. <source>Cancer Res.</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>7310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7317</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11585771</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c30"><label>30.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, Hu,Y.F., Zhong,H., Nye,A.C., Belmont,A.S. and Li,R. (2001) BRCA1-induced large-scale chromatin unfolding and allele-specific effects of cancer-predisposing mutations. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source>, <volume>155</volume>, <fpage>911</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>921</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739404</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c31"><label>31.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lazennec</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, Bresson,D., Lucas,A., Chauveau,C. and Vignon,F. (2001) ER&#x003b2; inhibits proliferation and invasion of breast cancer cells. <source>Endocrinology</source>, <volume>142</volume>, <fpage>4120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4130</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11517191</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c32"><label>32.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, Chung,L.W., Li,S. and Zhau,H.E. (2000) Identification of a novel FAS&#x0002f;ER-alpha fusion transcript expressed in human cancer cells. <source>Biochim. Biophys Acta</source>, <volume>1493</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>377</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11018265</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c33"><label>33.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Klinge</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name> (2000) Estrogen receptor interaction with co-activators and co-repressors. <source>Steroids</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>251</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10751636</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c34"><label>34.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Clauss</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name>, Chu,M., Zhao,J. and Glimcher,L.H. (1996) The basic domain&#x0002f;leucine zipper protein hXBP-1 preferentially binds to and transactivates CRE-like sequences containg an ACGT core. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1855</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1864</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8657566</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c35"><label>35.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Glass,C.K. and Rosenfeld,M.G. (1999) Coactivator and corepressor complexes in nuclear receptor function. <source>Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10322133</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c36"><label>36.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Chakravarti</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, LaMorte,V.J., Nelson,M.C., Nakajima,T., Schulman,I.G., Juguilon,H., Montminy,M. and Evans,R.M. (1996) Role of CBP&#x0002f;p300 in nuclear receptor signalling. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>383</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8779723</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c37"><label>37.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name>, Ku,G., Zhou,N., Scully,R. and Livingston,D.M. (1996) The nuclear hormone receptor coactivator SRC-1 is a specific target of p300. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>93</volume>, <fpage>10626</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10631</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8855229</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c38"><label>38.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Endoh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, Maruyama,K., Masuhiro,Y., Kobayashi,Y., Goto,M., Tai,H., Yanagisawa,J., Metzger,D., Hashimoto,S. and Kato,S. (1999) Purification and identification of p68 RNA helicase acting as a transcriptional coactivator specific for the activation function 1 of human estrogen receptor alpha. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>5363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5372</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10409727</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c39"><label>39.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Alen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, Claessens,F., Schoenmakers,E., Swinnen,J.V., Verhoeven,G., Rombauts,W. and Peeters,B. (1999) Interaction of the putative androgen receptor-specific coactivator ARA70&#x0002f;ELE1alpha with multiple steroid receptors and identification of an internally deleted ELE1beta isoform. <source>Mol. Endocrinol.</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9892017</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c40"><label>40.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name> and Zhang,Y. (1998) Ligand-independent activation of steroid hormone receptors. <source>J. Mol. Med.</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>479</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9660165</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c41"><label>41.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Zwijsen</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name>, Wientjens,E., Klompmaker,R., van der Sman,J., Bernards,R. and Michalides,R.J. (1997) CDK-independent activation of estrogen receptor by cyclin D1. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>415</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9039267</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c42"><label>42.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, Ladha,M.H., Lin,N., Upton,T.M., Miller,S.J., DiRenzo,J., Pestell,R.G., Hinds,P.W., Dowdy,S.F., Brown,M. and Ewen,M.E. (1997) Cyclin D1 stimulation of estrogen receptor transcriptional activity independent of cdk4. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>5338</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5347</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9271411</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c43"><label>43.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, Ladha,M.H., McMahon,C., Sutherland,R.L. and Ewen,M.E. (2000) Regulation of the functional interaction between cyclin D1 and the estrogen receptor. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>8667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8675</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11073968</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c44"><label>44.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Cardona,G.R., Henrion-Caude,A. and Chin,W.W. (2002) Identification and characterization of a tissue-specific coactivator, GT198, that interacts with the DNA-binding domains of nuclear receptors. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>369</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739747</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c45"><label>45.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Moilanen</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name>, Poukka,H., Karvonen,U., Hakli,M., Janne,O.A. and Palvimo,J.J. (1998) Identification of a novel RING finger protein as a coregulator in steroid receptor-mediated gene transcription. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>5128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9710597</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c46"><label>46.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>L'Horset</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Dauvois,S., Heery,D.M., Cavailles,V. and Parker,M.G. (1996) RIP-140 interacts with multiple nuclear receptors by means of two distinct sites. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>6029</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8887632</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c47"><label>47.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikonen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, Palvimo,J.J and Janne,O.A. (1997) Interaction between the amino- and carboxyl-terminal regions of the rat androgen receptor modulates transcriptional activity and is influenced by nuclear receptor coactivators. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>272</volume>, <fpage>29821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29828</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9368054</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c48"><label>48.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Subramaniam</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name> Treuter,E. and Okret,S. (1999) Receptor interacting protein RIP140 inhibits both positive and negative gene regulation by glucocorticoids. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>274</volume>, <fpage>18121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18127</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10364267</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c49"><label>49.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name>, Chinpaisal,C. and Wei,L.N. (1998) Cloning and characterization of mouse RIP140, a corepressor for nuclear orphan receptor TR2. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>6745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6755</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9774688</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c50"><label>50.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Gass</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name>, Gifford,N.M. and Brewer,J.W. (2002) Activation of an unfolded protein response during differentiation of antibody-secreting B cells. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>277</volume>, <fpage>49047</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49054</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12374812</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg731c51"><label>51.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Cavailles</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, Dauvois,S., L&#x02019;Horset,F., Lopez,G., Hoare,S., Kushner,P.J. and Parker,M.G. (1995) Nuclear factor RIP140 modulates transcriptional activation by the estrogen receptor. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>3741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3751</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7641693</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 