<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Evol Biol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Evolutionary Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2148</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2148-7-178</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17900370</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-7-178</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular evolution of <italic>Phox</italic>-related regulatory subunits for NADPH oxidase enzymes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>Tsukasa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tkawaha@emory.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>J David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>noxdoc@mac.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology and Laboratory Medicine, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, Georgia, 30322, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/7/178"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2007 Kawahara and Lambeth; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kawahara and Lambeth; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author> Kawahara Tsukasa tkawaha@emory.edu </dc:author><dc:title> Molecular evolution of Phox-related regulatory subunits for NADPH oxidase enzymes </dc:title><dc:date>2007</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Evolutionary Biology 7(1): 178-. (2007)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2148(2007)7:1&#x0003c;178&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2148</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The reactive oxygen-generating <underline>N</underline>ADPH <underline>ox</underline>idases (Noxes) function in a variety of biological roles, and can be broadly classified into those that are regulated by subunit interactions and those that are regulated by calcium. The prototypical subunit-regulated Nox, Nox2, is the membrane-associated catalytic subunit of the phagocyte NADPH-oxidase. Nox2 forms a heterodimer with the integral membrane protein, p22<italic>phox</italic>, and this heterodimer binds to the regulatory subunits p47<italic>phox</italic>, p67<italic>phox</italic>, p40<italic>phox </italic>and the small GTPase Rac, triggering superoxide generation. Nox-organizer protein 1 (NOXO1) and Nox-activator 1 (NOXA1), respective homologs of p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox</italic>, together with p22<italic>phox </italic>and Rac, activate Nox1, a non-phagocytic homolog of Nox2. NOXO1 and p22<italic>phox </italic>also regulate Nox3, whereas Nox4 requires only p22<italic>phox</italic>. In this study, we have assembled and analyzed amino acid sequences of Nox regulatory subunit orthologs from vertebrates, a urochordate, an echinoderm, a mollusc, a cnidarian, a choanoflagellate, fungi and a slime mold amoeba to investigate the evolutionary history of these subunits.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Ancestral p47<italic>phox</italic>, p67<italic>phox</italic>, and p22<italic>phox </italic>genes are broadly seen in the metazoa, except for the ecdysozoans. The choanoflagellate <italic>Monosiga brevicollis</italic>, the unicellular organism that is the closest relatives of multicellular animals, encodes early prototypes of p22<italic>phox</italic>, p47<italic>phox </italic>as well as the earliest known Nox2-like ancestor of the Nox1-3 subfamily. p67<italic>phox- </italic>and p47<italic>phox</italic>-like genes are seen in the sea urchin <italic>Strongylocentrotus purpuratus </italic>and the limpet <italic>Lottia gigantea </italic>that also possess Nox2-like co-orthologs of vertebrate Nox1-3. Duplication of primordial p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox </italic>genes occurred in vertebrates, with the duplicated branches evolving into NOXO1 and NOXA1. Analysis of characteristic domains of regulatory subunits suggests a novel view of the evolution of Nox: in fish, p40<italic>phox </italic>participated in regulating both Nox1 and Nox2, but after the appearance of mammals, Nox1 (but not Nox2) became independent of p40<italic>phox</italic>. In the fish <italic>Oryzias latipes</italic>, a NOXO1 ortholog retains an autoinhibitory region that is characteristic of mammalian p47<italic>phox</italic>, and this was subsequently lost from NOXO1 in later vertebrates. Detailed amino acid sequence comparisons identified both putative key residues conserved in characteristic domains and previously unidentified conserved regions. Also, candidate organizer/activator proteins in fungi and amoeba are identified and hypothetical activation models are suggested.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This is the first report to provide the comprehensive view of the molecular evolution of regulatory subunits for Nox enzymes. This approach provides clues for understanding the evolution of biochemical and physiological functions for regulatory-subunit-dependent Nox enzymes.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Nox enzymes (reactive oxygen-generating NADPH-oxidases) diverged early in evolution into calcium-regulated Noxes (e.g., Nox5 and the Duox enzymes) and Noxes that are activated by binding to regulatory subunits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. The most extensively studied of the latter is the <underline>ph</underline>agocyte NAPDH-<underline>ox</underline>idase (<italic>Phox</italic>), whose role in host defense has been documented at length [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Professional phagocytes such as neutrophils and macrophages produce large amounts of superoxide, with secondary production of other microbicidal reactive oxygen species (ROS). Superoxide is generated by the <italic>Phox</italic>, which consists of the catalytic subunit gp91<italic>phox </italic>(a.k.a. Nox2), along with the regulatory subunits p22<italic>phox</italic>, p67<italic>phox</italic>, p47<italic>phox</italic>, p40<italic>phox</italic>, and the small GTPase, Rac [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. The importance of the oxidase is demonstrated by the inherited condition, chronic granulomatous disease (CGD), in which absent or mutated <italic>Phox </italic>proteins result in an inability of phagocytes to kill microbes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p><p>Nox2 and p22<italic>phox </italic>are integral membrane proteins that form a heterodimer referred to as flavocytochrome <italic>b</italic><sub>558</sub>. In resting cells, flavocytochrome <italic>b</italic>558 is inactive and p47<italic>phox</italic>, p67<italic>phox</italic>, and p40<italic>phox </italic>are all present in the cytoplasm. Cell activation is accompanied by phosphorylation of p47<italic>phox </italic>and probably other <italic>Phox</italic>-regulatory subunits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], and by guanine nucleotide exchange factors that convert Rac-GDP to Rac-GTP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. These events trigger assembly of these proteins at the membrane, resulting in activation of Nox2. An intricate set of protein-protein interactions facilitates the binding of the regulatory subunits to the membrane components and to each other, and these interactions are mediated by well-characterized modular interaction domains. For example, p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox </italic>bind via a C-terminal proline-rich region (PRR) in p47<italic>phox </italic>and a C-terminal Src homology 3 (SH3) domain in p67<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. In the non-activated cell, the p47<italic>phox</italic>-p67<italic>phox </italic>complex fails to bind to flavocytochrome <italic>b</italic><sub>558</sub>, due to an unusual autoinhibitory mechanism. In the resting cell, tandem SH3 domains in p47<italic>phox </italic>(referred to as the <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain) bind to an auto-inhibitory region (AIR), preventing the <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain from binding to the PRR of p22<italic>phox</italic>. Upon cell activation, serine residues of the AIR become phosphorylated, releasing the <italic>bis-</italic>SH3 domain so that it can now bind to p22<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. In addition, p47<italic>phox </italic>possesses another membrane-binding region, the PX domain, which binds to the headgroups of phosphatidylinositols present in the membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Together, these interactions with membrane lipids and p22<italic>phox </italic>promote the assembly of p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox </italic>with flavocytochrome <italic>b</italic><sub>558</sub>. Concurrently, Rac-GTP translocates to the membrane where it interacts with the N-terminal tetratricopeptide repeat (TPR) region of p67<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. An activation domain (AD) in p67<italic>phox</italic>, which is conformationally regulated by Rac binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], activates the hydride transfer from NADPH to FAD in Nox2. Subsequent electron transfer through two heme groups permits reduction of oxygen to form superoxide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. p40<italic>phox </italic>binds through its <italic>Phox</italic>/Bem 1 (PB1) domain to a partner PB1 domain in p67<italic>phox </italic>and facilitates the assembly of p67<italic>phox</italic>-p47<italic>phox </italic>at the membrane through lipid binding via its PX domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Although no CGD patients have been described with mutations in p40<italic>phox</italic>, neutrophils from p40<italic>phox</italic>-knockout mice exhibit CGD-like severe defects in Nox2-derived oxidant-dependent bacterial killing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], also suggesting that p40<italic>phox </italic>is a crucial component for Nox2 function.</p><p>The first homologue of gp91<italic>phox </italic>identified was Nox1, which is abundantly expressed in non-phagocyte cells including gastrointestinal epithelium and vascular smooth muscle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. Subsequently, additional homologues were identified, and the Nox/Duox family in humans now consists of seven members: Nox1 though Nox5, Duox1 and Duox2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. All members of Nox/Duox family contain the six transmembrane &#x003b1;-helical heme-binding domain and an FAD domain containing an NADPH binding site, which together constitute the "Nox domain"[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Nox5 and Duox1/2 contain a calcium-binding EF-hand motif. The evolution of these Noxes and their calcium-binding domains were considered in the recent article [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] and are not discussed here. The remaining Noxes, Nox1-4, require p22<italic>phox </italic>for activity, and Nox1-3 all require additional <italic>Phox</italic>-like regulatory subunits, reviewed recently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>].</p><p>Nox1, like gp91<italic>phox</italic>, is activated by regulatory subunits: NOXO1 (Nox-organizer protein 1) is a homologue of p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1 (Nox-activator protein 1) is a homologue of p67<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Recent studies have also demonstrated activation of the Nox1 system by Rac1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. NOXO1 and NOXA1 are co-expressed with Nox1 in colon epithelium and gastric mucosa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>], consistent with <italic>in vivo </italic>regulation of Nox1 by these novel subunits. Activation of Nox1 by regulatory subunits differs in two major respects compared to gp91<italic>phox</italic>. First, NOXO1 lacks the AIR and its associated regulatory phosphorylation sites that are present in p47<italic>phox</italic>. Consistent with the domain structure, NOXO1 co-localizes with Nox1/p22<italic>phox </italic>complex constitutively at/near the plasma membrane <italic>in vivo </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. On the other hand, a recent study revealed that the <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain of NOXO1 bind to the extremely C-terminal PRR of NOXO1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Phosphorylation-independent disruption of the intramolecular interaction facilitates NOXO1 binding to the PRR of p22<italic>phox</italic>. Second, NOXA1 lacks critical basic amino acid residues in its PB1 domain that are important for binding to p40<italic>phox</italic>. NOXA1 does not interact with p40<italic>phox</italic>, making human Nox1 activity independent of p40<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Furthermore, human NOXA1 lacks the central SH3 domain that is present in p67<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>], but whose function is unknown. Like Nox1, Nox3 is also regulated by p22<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1, but in humans does not require NOXA1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. In comparison, Nox4 requires p22<italic>phox </italic>for activity, but other known regulatory subunits are not needed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>].</p><p>Another subfamily of the Noxes is the NoxA/NoxB group, found in a slime mold amoeba and fungi. These fungal Nox genes have been identified in most ascomycetes except for hemiascomycete yeasts, and also in higher basidiomycetes and chytridiomycotes (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]). No Nox gene has been identified in fungi that belong to Zygomycota and Micropordia. These NoxA/NoxB genes are closely related to the subunit-regulated Noxes according to taxonomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. A non-animal homologue of p67<italic>phox</italic>/NOXA1 was described in slime mold amoeba <italic>Dictyostelium discoideum </italic>(<italic>D. discoideum</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. The p67<italic>phox </italic>homolog (referred to here as the Dd-p67-like) of <italic>D. discoideum </italic>possesses the N-terminal TPR region and PB1 domain characteristic of p67<italic>phox</italic>, but lacks the SH3 domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. A p67<italic>phox </italic>homolog Nox-regulator (NOXR) was also reported in some fungi including ascomycetes and higher basidiomycetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. The basic motif structure of NOXR is similar to that of <italic>D. discoideum</italic>. A NOXR-deficient mutant of the ascomycete <italic>Epichl&#x000f6;e festucae </italic>shows decreased ROS-generation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. Taken together, these data suggest that NOXR regulates NoxA and/or NoxB in the slime mold and fungi, although this has not been tested directly.</p><p>Herein, we assembled and analyzed experimentally cloned and computationally predicted amino acid sequences of the <italic>Phox</italic>-related regulatory subunits p47<italic>phox</italic>, NOXO1, p67<italic>phox</italic>, NOXA1, p40<italic>phox</italic>, p22<italic>phox</italic>, and NOXR from 10 vertebrates, one urochordate, one echinoderm, one mollusc, one cnidarian, one choanoflagellate, 13 fungi, and one slime mold amoeba. Using this large set of amino acid sequences, we report: (i) the occurrence and origin of <italic>Phox</italic>-like subunits during evolution, (ii) identification of putative key amino acid residues conserved in regulatory subunits, (iii) the description of putative new modular regions that are conserved among <italic>Phox</italic>-related regulatory subunits, (iv) the molecular evolution of characteristic domains of the <italic>Phox</italic>-related regulatory subunits, and (v) a prediction of novel fungal and amoebal Nox organizer/enhancer subunits based on sequence analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Occurrence of <italic>Phox</italic>-related regulatory subunits</title><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref> summarizes the occurrence of subunit-dependent-like Nox orthologs along with the <italic>Phox</italic>-like regulatory subunit orthologs in the genomes of deutrostomes, fungi, a slime mold amoeba. The tetrapods [human <italic>Homo sapiens </italic>(<italic>H. sapiens</italic>), dog <italic>Canis familliaris </italic>(<italic>C. familliaris</italic>), rat <italic>Rattus norvegicus </italic>(<italic>R. norvegicus</italic>), mouse <italic>Mus musculus </italic>(<italic>M. musculus</italic>), chicken <italic>Gallus gallus </italic>(<italic>G. gallus</italic>), frog <italic>Xenopus tropicalis </italic>(<italic>X. tropicalis</italic>)], and the two teleost fish [zebrafish <italic>Danio rerio </italic>(<italic>D. rerio</italic>), medaka <italic>Oryzias latipes </italic>(<italic>O. latipes</italic>)] have two isologs of Nox organizer proteins (p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1), two isologs of Nox activator proteins (p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1), and single isologs of p40<italic>phox </italic>and p22<italic>phox </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>, the sequences are provided in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). The pufferfish <italic>Takifugu rubripes </italic>(<italic>T. rubripes</italic>), which has a compact genome size, ~400 megabase (Mb) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>], lacks NOXO1 and NOXA1 although it possesses both Nox1 and Nox2 as well as p22<italic>phox</italic>, p47<italic>phox</italic>, p67<italic>phox</italic>, and p40<italic>phox </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), in contrast to <italic>D. rerio </italic>and <italic>O. latipes </italic>that have less compact genomes (1680&#x02013;2280 Mb and 870&#x02013;1100 Mb, respectively, according to the Animal Genome Size Database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]). Interestingly, <italic>Tetraodon nigroviridis </italic>(<italic>T. nigroviridis</italic>), another species of pufferfish, which also possesses a compact genome, ~340 Mb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>], encodes a NOXO1 ortholog, but not NOXA1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Relationships between the phylogenic tree of species and the occurrence of <italic>Phox</italic>-reated regulatory subunits</bold>. (<italic>A</italic>) Summary of the occurrence of Nox-regulatory subunit genes in vertebrates, a urochordate, an echinoderm, fungi, and a slime mold amoeba are shown. <italic>Asterisks </italic>indicate that the gene is a co-ortholog ancestor of all members of the vertebrate Nox1-3 subgroup. Superscripted letters represent: (<italic>a</italic>), a partial amino acid sequence predicted from genomic DNA fragment (nucleotides 713622&#x02013;713565 of GenBank&#x02122; No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NW_001471438.1">NW_001471438.1</ext-link>), (<italic>b</italic>) the gene taxonomy is discussed in the text. (<italic>B</italic>) Summary of the occurrence of Nox-regulatory subunit genes within Deuterostomia. The number in the fork of each branch indicates the estimated time in millions of years (Mya, millions of years ago) since a given species diverged. A schematic phylogeny and the estimated time of occurrence of species were created from genomic information [62, 125]. Branch lengths are for illustrative purposes and are not proportional to time since divergence.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-1"/></fig><p>The earlier chordate <italic>Ciona intestinalis </italic>(<italic>C. intestinalis</italic>) possesses a Nox2 ortholog, but not Nox1 or Nox3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. The sea urchin <italic>Strongylocentrotus purpuratus </italic>(<italic>S. purpuratus</italic>) belongs to Echinodermata, which diverged early from an ancestor common to urochordates and vertebrates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. <italic>S. purpuratus</italic>, possesses two Nox2 genes, Nox2A and Nox2B, and an analysis of the taxonomy Noxes demonstrates that these Nox2 genes are related to the common ancestor gene of vertebrate Nox1, Nox2 and Nox3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>possesses single copies of p47<italic>phox-</italic>, p67<italic>phox-</italic>, and p22<italic>phox</italic>-like genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>], which presumably regulate its Nox2 ortholog (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). The <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>genome possesses single copies of p47<italic>phox</italic>- and p67<italic>phox</italic>-like genes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). No p22<italic>phox </italic>ortholog of <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>was identified using a BLAST search of recently published genome sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Because the <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein has a highly conserved tandem SH3 region that in other species binds to the C-terminal proline-rich region (PRR) of p22<italic>phox</italic>, it seems likely that <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>has an as-yet unidentified p22<italic>phox </italic>homologue.</p><p>Using the estimated time of evolution of deuterostomes based on Hox gene clusters to construct a phylogenetic tree [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>], we illustrate the occurrence during evolution of the <italic>Phox</italic>-related regulatory subunits(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). The phylogenic tree suggests an evolutionary model in which duplication of both the p47<italic>phox </italic>gene and the p67<italic>phox </italic>gene occurred at a time corresponding to the appearance of vertebrates, with the NOXO1 and NOXA1 genes subsequently evolving as distinct regulatory subunits in vertebrates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). This appearance of NOXO1 and NOXA1 coincided with the emergence of Nox1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The pufferfish <italic>T. rubripes </italic>and <italic>T. nigroviridis </italic>are considered to have evolved from an <italic>O. latipes </italic>ancestor approximately 186 million years ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. This tree suggests that NOXA1 and NOXO1 of <italic>T. rubripes </italic>and NOXA1 of <italic>T. nigroviridis </italic>have been lost during the decrease in genome sizes in these species (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). In contrast to the co-appearance of p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox </italic>orthologs with the earliest Nox2 ortholog in <italic>S. purpuratus</italic>, p40<italic>phox </italic>appeared later, in vertebrates, and was not found in the genomes of either <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>or <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). The situation of the regulatory subunits of other primitive animals and a choanoflagellate is described below.</p><p>A homologue of p67<italic>phox</italic>/NOXA1 occurs in the slime mold amoeba (<italic>D. discoideum</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Fungal genomes of <italic>Aspergillus nidulans </italic>(<italic>A. nidulans</italic>), <italic>Magnaporthe grisea </italic>(<italic>M. grisea</italic>), and <italic>Fusarium graminearum </italic>(<italic>F. graminearum</italic>), all members of Ascomycota, also possess NOXR, a homolog of p67<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). However, <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae </italic>(<italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>) that also belongs to Ascomycota does not possess any Nox or NOXR orthologs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Some basidiomycetes [<italic>Coprinopsis cinerea </italic>(<italic>C. cinerea</italic>), <italic>Laccaria bicolor </italic>(<italic>L. bicolor</italic>), and <italic>Postia placenta </italic>(<italic>P. placenta</italic>)] also possess NOXR and NoxA/B genes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). The situation of the regulatory subunits of other fungi is described below. Interestingly, the fungi seem to lack precise homologues of p47<italic>phox</italic>/NOXO1 or its binding partner p22<italic>phox </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Recently, the possibility of p22<italic>phox</italic>-like gene in the <italic>D. discoideum </italic>genome was suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>], but it is not clear whether the gene represents an ancestral p22<italic>phox</italic>, a later adaptation or a functionally unrelated protein. We discuss the possibilities below based on a comparison of the amino acid sequences of amoebal p22<italic>phox </italic>and other p22<italic>phox </italic>orthologs. In addition, we identified other predicted proteins encoded in fungal and amoebal genomes that may function as (a) binding partner(s) of the Nox activator proteins (described below), suggesting the early evolutionary origin not only of the activator protein, but also possibly of a rudimentary organizer subunit.</p></sec><sec><title>Synteny of NOXO1 ad NOXA1 genes in vertebrates</title><p>An extensive BLAST search has failed to identify the NOXA1 gene in the pufferfish <italic>T. rubripes </italic>and <italic>T. nigroviridis </italic>genomes, as indicated in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. In addition to the absence of NOXA1, <italic>T. rubripes </italic>seems to have lost the NOXO1 gene. To substantiate that the NOXO1 and NOXA1 genes were indeed absent, we compared chromosomal synteny (the preserved chromosomal order of genes among organisms) of NOXO1 in vertebrates. The human NOXO1 gene is preceded by SYNGR3 and GFER genes on chromosome 16 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>, abbreviations of gene names are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>), and followed by TBL3, RPS2 and RPL3L. Synteny was preserved in mammals and the chicken <italic>G. gallus</italic>. The frog <italic>X. tropicalis </italic>lacks SYNGR3, but other markers are preserved. Among fish, <italic>T. nigroviridis </italic>conserved part of the mammalian synteny: NOXO1, TBL3, RPS2, and RPL3L and instead of SYNGR3 and GFER, C17orf39 is positioned next to NOXO1. Synteny of the <italic>T. rubripes </italic>genome was very similar to that of <italic>T. nigroviridis</italic>, although it lacks a NOXO1 ortholog (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Two fishes, <italic>D. rerio </italic>and <italic>O. latipes</italic>, genomes possess NOXO1 genes, but with greater variations in synteny;although TBL3 and C17orf39 were present in the same chromosome as NOXO1, other linked markers were not seen (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). The gene markers C17orf39 and TBL3 of <italic>O. latipes </italic>are present on a separate chromosome from that of NOXO1. Thus, the synteny analysis of the <italic>T. rubripes </italic>genomes shows that the NOXO1 gene was indeed lost during evolution.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Syntenies of NOXO1 and NOXA1 genes</bold>. Syntenies of the indicated vertebrate NOXO1 (<italic>A</italic>) and NOXA1 (<italic>B</italic>) genes are shown. Genes are aligned in columns to illustrate orthology. Chromosome (Chr) or scaffold (Sc) number is indicated on the right. Abbreviations of gene names are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-2"/></fig><p>The synteny of genetic markers surrounding NOXA1 was highly conserved in <italic>H. sapiens</italic>, <italic>C. familliaris</italic>, <italic>M. musculus, G. gallus </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). Both NOXA1 and the linked markers of <italic>R. norvegicus </italic>were present in chromosome 3, with a long insert between NOXA1and ENTPD8 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). In the genome of <italic>X. tropicalis</italic>, synteny was more varied in that NOXA1 and ENTPD8 were present in the same scaffold, but other markers were not seen. Synteny of fish NOXA1 was preserved among the class but different from other vertebrates. <italic>O. latipes </italic>and <italic>D. rerio </italic>NOXA1 genes are preceded by MAN1B1 and DPP7 on chromosome 9 and 5, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). <italic>T. nigroviridis </italic>possesses two markers MAN1B1 and DPP7, but lacks the NOXA1 ortholog. Synteny of <italic>T. rubripes </italic>is similar to that of <italic>D. rerio</italic>, but a NOXA1 ortholog is absent. Thus, the synteny of NOXA1 had considerable variation, and this analysis indicates that NOXA1 orthologs were lost during the evolution of the two pufferfish genomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of putative critical amino acids conserved among p47<italic>phox</italic>/NOXO1 orthologs</title><p>The PX domain of p47<italic>phox </italic>binds with highest affinity to phosphatidylinositol 3,4-bisphosphate [PtdIns(3,4)P<sub>2</sub>], and with lower but significant affinity to PtdIns(3,4,5)P<sub>3</sub>, PtdIns(3,5)P<sub>2 </sub>and PtdIns(3)P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The PX domain of human NOXO1 shows a different lipid binding specificity, with highest affinity for PtdIns(3,5)P<sub>2</sub>, PtdIns(5)P, and PtdIns(4)P and lower affinity for PtdIns(3)P and PtdIns(3,4)P<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>]. Both PX and <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domains are seen in all p47<italic>phox</italic>/NOXO1 orthologs of deuterostomes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Comparison of the sequences of the organizer proteins allowed identification of amino acid residues that are highly conserved (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Eleven highly conserved residues were identified in the PX domain, and 22 in the <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domains (arrows in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). Arg-42, Pro-73, and Arg-90 of the PX-domain and Trp-193, Phe-209, and Trp-263 of the <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain (human-p47<italic>phox </italic>numbering, black boxes in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>) were previously shown by mutational analyses to be essential for the activation of human Nox2 by p47<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Identification of highly conserved residues of Nox organizer proteins</bold>. Species names were abbreviated as follows: v-, vertebrate; Hs, <italic>H. sapiens</italic>; Cf, <italic>C. familliaris</italic>; Rn, <italic>R. norvegicus</italic>; Mm, <italic>M. musculus</italic>; Gg, <italic>G. gallus</italic>; Xt, <italic>X. tropicalis</italic>, Dr, <italic>D. rerio</italic>; Tr, <italic>T. rubripes</italic>; Tn, <italic>T. nigroviridis</italic>; Ol, <italic>O. latipes</italic>; Ci, <italic>C. intestinalis</italic>; Sp, <italic>S. purpuratus</italic>. (<italic>A</italic>) Schematic domain structures of Nox organizer are shown; PX, <italic>Phox </italic>homology; SH3, the Src homology 3; AIR, autoinhibitory region; PRR, proline-rich region; C-tail, C-terminal tail region. Orthologs that possess these domains are shown below the domains. Amino acid residues indicate conserved amino acids in all Nox-organizers. Residue numbers correspond to those of the human p47<italic>phox </italic>protein sequence. Letters in <italic>solid boxes </italic>indicate the residues that have been previously proven by mutational analyses to be essential for the human Nox2 activation [24, 68, 126]. (<italic>B</italic>) Molecular taxonomy was created comparing by the sequence spanning the PX and <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domains. (<italic>C</italic>) Alignment of amino acid sequences of the AIR. Letters in <italic>solid boxes </italic>indicate residues previously shown to be essential for human Nox2 activation, determined by mutational analyses [20] and also key residues responsible for interactions with the <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain, shown by X-ray crystallography [21]. (<italic>D</italic>) Alignment of amino acid sequences of the PRR and C-tail regions. Letters in <italic>solid boxes </italic>indicate the residues that have been shown by mutational analyses to be important for binding to p67<italic>phox </italic>[18, 72]. <italic>An arrow head </italic>indicates a residue corresponding to a phosphorylation site of human p47<italic>phox </italic>[19].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-3"/></fig><p>While the PX and <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domains are shared among all p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1 orthologs including those of <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>and <italic>C. intestinalis</italic>, the molecular taxonomy of the regions (excluding the variable C-terminal regulator docking regions) reveals that vertebrate p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1 families form distinct subgroups (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>), likely accounting, for example, for differences in lipid binding specificities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. The phylogenic tree supports an evolutionary model in which the p47<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins of <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>and <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>(#21 and 20 of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>, respectively) branch from a root that is closely related to the primordial ancestors of both p47<italic>phox </italic>(#1&#x02013;10 of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>) and NOXO1 (#11&#x02013;19 of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>).</p><p>To maintain p47<italic>phox </italic>strictly in an inactive state that cannot bind to p22<italic>phox</italic>, human p47<italic>phox </italic>masks its <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain with the AIR region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>], and this region is absent in human NOXO1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Therefore Nox2 activity is considered more tightly controlled than Nox1 activity. Most residues essential for the function of the AIR (e.g., Pro-299, Pro-300, Arg-301, Arg-302, Ser-303, Ser- 304 and Ser-328 of human p47<italic>phox</italic>), are well conserved among all vertebrate p47<italic>phox </italic>proteins (black boxes of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). Interestingly <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>and <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p47<italic>phox </italic>proteins possessed the AIR-like region (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>possesses two Nox2-like proteins Nox2A and 2B that are co-orthologs of vertebrate Noxes 1&#x02013;3; the presence of a p47<italic>phox </italic>ortholog harboring the AIR suggests that this primitive Nox system functions analogously to the mammalian Nox2 system. All NOXO1 orthologs lack the AIR, with one exception, the teleost fish <italic>O. latipes</italic>, which retains the predicted AIR in both the p47<italic>phox </italic>and the NOXO1 genes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). Thus, this analysis supports an evolutionary model in which the NOXO1 "AIR-independent" Nox1 and Nox3 activation systems originated from the p47<italic>phox</italic>-like "AIR-dependent" Nox2 regulatory system. The <italic>O. latipes </italic>NOXO1, which contains the AIR, represents an evolutionary remnant reflecting the transition from AIR-dependence to -independence.</p><p>The heterodimerization of human p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox </italic>is dependent on the interaction between the C-terminal PRR of p47<italic>phox </italic>and the C-terminal SH3 domain of p67<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>]. Both of these regions were conserved in vertebrate p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox </italic>orthologs, but not in orthologs of lower organisms (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). The alignment of vertebrate p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1 amino acid sequences demonstrates that in addition to the PRR, the C-terminal region immediately following the PRR ("C-tail" in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>) was also highly conserved. The PRR of p47<italic>phox </italic>isologs possesses four strictly conserved residues (Pro-363, Pro-366, Arg-368, Pro-369; human-p47<italic>phox </italic>numbering), and the C-tail region had an additional four identical amino acids (Ile-374, Arg-377, Cys-378, and Thr-382; human-p47<italic>phox </italic>numbering) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). Consistent with these identities, the essential binding roles of three residues (Pro-363, Pro-366, Arg-368, indicated by black boxes of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>) were previously demonstrated by mutational analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. The C-tail region is thought to enhance the interaction between the PRR of p47<italic>phox </italic>and the SH3 domain of p67<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], since simultaneous mutation of six of these residues (Leu-373, Ile-374, Arg-377, Thr-382, Lys-383, and Lys-385; human-p47<italic>phox </italic>numbering, indicated by black boxes of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>) significantly decreased the binding of the p47<italic>phox </italic>PRR to the p67<italic>phox </italic>SH3 domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>]. Four of these residues (Ile-374, Arg-377, Thr-382, and Lys-383) are highly conserved among both p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1 proteins, but two other residues (Leu-373 and Lys-385; human-p47<italic>phox </italic>numbering) were conserved only in p47<italic>phox </italic>orthologs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). This suggests that the binding affinities of p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1 toward their respective activator protein SH3 domains may differ due to differences in these residues. Ser-379 in the C-tail region of human p47<italic>phox </italic>is a phosphorylation site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]; the phosphorylation of which negatively regulates binding of the PRR and C-tail regions to the p67<italic>phox </italic>SH3 domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>]. The threonine or serine residue is conserved at the position in all vertebrate p47<italic>phox </italic>and <italic>G. gallus</italic>, <italic>D. rerio </italic>and <italic>O. latipes </italic>NOXO1 (indicated by <italic>an arrow head </italic>in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>), indicating that NOXO1 proteins of these species retain this feature of p47<italic>phox </italic>which is subsequently lost in higher vertebrate NOXO1.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>T. rubripes </italic>C17orf39 ortholog as a candidate NOXO1-like protein</title><p>The NOXO1 gene seems to have been lost from the <italic>T. rubripes </italic>genome, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>. On the other hand, orthologs of chromosome 17 open reading frame 39 (C17orf39) gene predicted by the ensembl transcript model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>] are present adjacent to the NOXO1 genes in the <italic>D. rerio </italic>and <italic>T. nigroviridis </italic>genomes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). Amino acid sequences of these C17orf39 orthologs showed conserved PRR and polybasic regions (Figure. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>, respectively, indicated by black boxes). In addition to the PRR and polybasic region, the <italic>T. rubripes </italic>C17orf39 ortholog has an extended region that encodes domains analogous to the C-terminal regions of NOXO1; these contain the <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain, PRR and C-tail region (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). The sequence of <italic>T. rubripes </italic>C17orf39 possesses the 22 residues that are conserved in <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domains of p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>) and the eight key residues conserved in the PRR and C-tail regions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref>). A phosphorylation site corresponding to Ser-379 residue of human p47<italic>phox </italic>is also conserved in the <italic>T. rubripes </italic>C17orf39 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref>). Although the function of C17orf39 has not been established in any species, its NOXO1-like domain structure suggests that the C17orf39 ortholog of <italic>T. rubripes </italic>may function in place of the authentic NOXO1.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Hypothetical function of <italic>T. rubripes </italic>C17orf39 protein as a Nox organizer protein</bold>. (<italic>A</italic>) Schematic domain structures of C17orf39 and NOXO1. Names of orthologs that possess domains are shown to the left of structures. <italic>T. rubripes </italic>C17orf39 was located in scaffold 141 (<italic>Sc 141</italic>). Abbreviations of species names and most domains are shown in Figure 3; "basic" indicates a lysine/arginine-rich polybasic region. (<italic>B</italic>) Alignments of the PRR and basic regions of C17orf39. Letters in <italic>solid boxes </italic>indicate conserved the proline residues in the PRR and lysines and arginines in the basic region. (<italic>C</italic>) Comparison of <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain among <italic>T. rubripes </italic>C17orf39, human NOXO1, and human p47<italic>phox</italic>. (<italic>D</italic>) Comparison of PRR and C-tail regions among <italic>T. rubripes </italic>C17orf39, human NOXO1, and human p47<italic>phox</italic>. Letters in <italic>solid boxes </italic>indicate the evolutionally conserved residues that have been identified in Figure 3 (<italic>C</italic>, <italic>D</italic>). <italic>An arrow head </italic>indicates a residue corresponding to a phosphorylation site of human p47<italic>phox</italic>. Identical residues are shown by <italic>asterisks </italic>(<italic>B</italic>-<italic>D</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Identification of putative critical amino acids conserved among p67<italic>phox</italic>/NOXA1 orthologs</title><p>Alignment of the amino acid sequences of the 24 Nox-activator proteins (including amoebal and fungal isologs) identified 13 conserved amino acids in the TPR domains (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). This includes two residues that have been identified as essential for binding human p67<italic>phox </italic>to Rac, as determined by the crystal structure of the complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>, filled boxes). The AD was first identified by mutagenesis of p67<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Val-204 of human p67<italic>phox </italic>and the corresponding residue Val-205 of human NOXA1 are crucial for respective activation of Nox2 and Nox1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. All orthologs of p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1, and one fungal NOXR (<italic>A. nidulans</italic>-NOXR) conserve this valine residue (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). The two fungal NOXR (<italic>M. grisea </italic>and <italic>F. graminearum</italic>) retained the hydrophobic amino acid leucine instead of valine at this position (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). Similarly, the second AD-like region of <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like protein (Sp-p67<italic>phox</italic>-C) conserved an isoleucine residue at this position. In contrast, Dd-p67-like protein lacked a typical AD sequence (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). The N-terminal region containing the TPR and AD can be considered as the "Nox-activating region", a module that cooperates with Rac to activate Nox enzymatic activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>]. Taxonomy of the "Nox-activating region" (corresponding to residues 1&#x02013;212 of human p67<italic>phox</italic>) reveals distinct subgroups corresponding to NOXA1 and to p67<italic>phox</italic>, and shows that the NOXR proteins of fungi also represent a distinct subgroup (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). A fourth rather diverse subgroup is comprised of p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins that include those of <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>and <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>(numbers 19&#x02013;21 in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). Taken together with the taxonomy of p47<italic>phox </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>) and of Noxes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], these data support an evolutionary model in which duplication of both the p67<italic>phox </italic>and p47<italic>phox </italic>genes occurred in vertebrates at a time corresponding to the appearance of Nox1. In contrast to fungal NOXR, Dd-p67-like protein appeared to branch from a root shared with sea urchin-p67<italic>phox</italic>-like genes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>); however, the bootstrap value was only 35% raising uncertainty as to which subgroup the amoebal p67-like protein belongs. Nevertheless, amoebal p67-like protein is clearly distinct from the NOXR group.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Identification of highly conserved residues of Nox activator proteins</bold>. Abbreviations of species names are shown in Figure 3. (<italic>A</italic>) Schematic domains structures of p67<italic>phox </italic>are shown; TPR, the tetratricopeptide repeats; AD, activation domain; ADSIS, AD-SH3 Intervening Sequence; PB1, <italic>Phox</italic>/Bem 1; OPCA motif, OPR/PC/AID motif. Abbreviations of other domain names are given in Figure 3. Names of orthologs that possess certain domains are shown below the domains. Amino acid residues indicate conserved amino acids in all indicated proteins, and the residue numbers correspond to that of human p67<italic>phox</italic>.<italic>An asterisk </italic>indicates that fungal NOXR possess the OPCA motif. Letters in <italic>solid boxes </italic>indicate residues previously proven by mutational analyses [27] and by X-ray crystallographic structure analysis [28] to be important for binding to Rac (TRP) or p47<italic>phox </italic>(SH3-B). (<italic>B</italic>) Molecular taxonomy was built by the length corresponding to the TPR and AD domains. Species names are abbreviated as shown in Figure 3 and as follows: An, <italic>A. nidulans</italic>; Mg, <italic>M. grisea</italic>; Fg, <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. (<italic>C</italic>-<italic>E</italic>) Alignments of the AD, ADSIS, and PB1 domains are shown. (<italic>C</italic>) Letters in <italic>a solid box </italic>indicate residues that have been proven by mutational analyses to be essential for activation of human Nox2 [30]. Letters in <italic>a gray box </italic>indicate basic residues that might correlate with a functional PB1 domain. (<italic>D</italic>) Amino acid residues identical among vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>ortholog sequences are indicated by <italic>asterisks</italic>. Letters in <italic>gray boxes </italic>indicate amino acid residues conserved in the putative ADSIS region. (<italic>E</italic>) Letters in <italic>solid boxes </italic>indicate the key basic residues required to bind to another PB1 domain, as shown by X-ray crystallographic structural analysis [32]. K355 and K382 indicate lysine residues of the human p67<italic>phox</italic>. "&#x003b2;1" and "&#x003b1;1" indicate the first &#x003b2;-sheet and the first &#x003b1;-helical structures of PB1 domain [32]. (<italic>F</italic>) Proposed model for a cooperation of a basic residue of AD (K196 of the human p67<italic>phox </italic>sequence) with a functional PB1 domain.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-5"/></fig><p>In contrast to the C-terminal SH3 domain (SH3-B) of activator proteins which is seen in all vertebrate activator proteins, the central SH3 domain (SH3-A) was seen only in vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Comparison of sequences of all vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>orthologs identified 31 highly conserved amino acids in this SH3 domain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). In addition, a region between AD and SH3-A (termed here the ADSIS region for " <underline>AD</underline>-<underline>S</underline>H3 <underline>I</underline>ntervening <underline>S</underline>equence") was strictly conserved among vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>isologs, but was not seen in others, such as NOXA1 and NOXR. A consensus sequence was identified in this region (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>). A PRR-like region (residues 227&#x02013;231 of human p67<italic>phox</italic>) was seen in ADSIS region, but it does not conserve in all vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>isologs based on the deduced sequences (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>). The role of the putative region is currently unknown, but may involve a function related to SH3-A because it coincides with the presence of SH3-A. Despite the high conservation of SH3-A among vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>orthologs, the role of this domain is not defined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>].</p><p>The PB1 domain was present in all vertebrate p67<italic>phox</italic>, in vertebrate NOXA1 and in fungal NOXR and amoebal p67-like protein, but not in <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>and <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). The crystal structure of the heterodimer between the PB1 domains of p67<italic>phox </italic>and p40<italic>phox </italic>domain demonstrated that Lys-355 and Lys-382 in human p67<italic>phox </italic>are essential to bind the PB1 domain of p40<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>]. Residues corresponding to Lys-355 and Lys-382 of human p67<italic>phox </italic>are conserved not only in the vertebrate p67<italic>phox</italic>, but also in the NOXA1 orthologs of chicken (<italic>G. gallus</italic>) and fish (<italic>D. rerio </italic>and <italic>O. latipes</italic>) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>). This suggests that in addition to its well-described role in activating Nox2, p40<italic>phox </italic>probably also participates in activating Nox1 in chicken and fish (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>). On the other hand, NOXA1 of <italic>X. tropicalis </italic>has lost both of these p40<italic>phox</italic>-interacting residues. Thus, these data support an evolutionary model in which p40<italic>phox </italic>originally participated in regulating <italic>both </italic>Nox1 and Nox2 in vertebrates, but after the appearance of mammals, Nox1 (but not Nox2) became independent of p40<italic>phox</italic>. The lack of a PB1 domain in both <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>and <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins is consistent with the absence of p40<italic>phox </italic>orthologs in these species (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>).</p><p>The analysis of PB1 domain sequences in Nox activators also suggests an unexpected relationship between the AD and the PB1 domain. AD regions of all vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>contain a positively charged residue, <italic>e.g</italic>., Lys-196 of h-p67<italic>phox </italic>(indicated by <italic>gray boxes </italic>in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). This basic residue is also completely conserved in NOXA1 orthologs of <italic>G. gallus, D. rerio </italic>and <italic>O. latipes </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>), which retain functional PB1 domains (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>), but not in the other NOXA1 and p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>) (with the single exception of the C-terminal AD-like region of <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like protein). Interestingly, the fungal NOXR, which possess these key basic residues in their PB1 domains (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>), also conserves this basic residue in their AD regions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). Thus, the presence of a functional PB1 domain correlates strongly with the presence of a positively charged residue corresponding to position 196 in the human p67<italic>phox </italic>sequence, and may point to the functional cooperation of these two regions, e.g. in binding to p40<italic>phox </italic>or other functionally analogous proteins in fungi (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). Alternatively, the positively charged residue in AD region might be related to the tail-to-tail interaction between vertebrate p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox </italic>(and NOXO1-NOXA1 of early vertebrates) because a sequence analysis of Nox organizers that is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref> suggests that the conserved residue also co-occurs with the phosphorylation site in the C-tail region of all vertebrate p47<italic>phox </italic>and early vertebrate NOXO1. Thus, co-appearance and co-disappearance of evolutionarily conserved residue provides a hint to find an unknown relationship between regulatory-subunits.</p><p>SH3-B was seen in all vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1 orthologs and in <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like protein (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Among these orthologs, seven conserved amino acid residues in SH3-B were identified (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>), and the residues include a tryptophan (Trp-494; human p67<italic>phox</italic>- numbering) that was previously shown to be crucial for interaction with the C-terminal PRR of Nox organizer proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of putative critical amino acids conserved among p40<italic>phox </italic>orthologs</title><p>Mammalian p40<italic>phox </italic>is considered to be an enhancer of Nox2 activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>]. p40<italic>phox </italic>orthologs emerged in vertebrates (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>) coincident with the appearance of the PB1 domain of p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins. Fungal NOXR and amoebal p67-like proteins also possess the PB1 domains (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>), but their genomes do not encode a distinct p40<italic>phox </italic>ortholog. The protein sequences of vertebrate p40<italic>phox </italic>orthologs are highly conserved; the canonical PX, SH3, and PB1 domains are all seen among vertebrate p40<italic>phox </italic>orthologs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). Alignment of ten vertebrate p40<italic>phox </italic>orthologs showed 48 conserved amino acid residues in the PX domain (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>), including Phe-35, Arg-57, Tyr-59, Leu-65, Arg-105 (human p40<italic>phox </italic>numbering) that have been demonstrated to be essential for phospholipid-binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>]. Phylogenic analysis using the trimmed PX domain sequences (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>) does not reveal obvious sub-families. Recently a novel intramolecular interaction in p40<italic>phox </italic>between the PX and PB1 domains was reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>]. The interface between the PX and PB1 domains consists of a hydrophobic pocket by Phe-35 of the PX domain and Val-257, Pro-265, Leu-273 and Phe-320 of the PB1 domain and ionic interactions between His-38, Arg-58, and Arg-60 of the PX domain and Glu-259 and Asp-269 of the PB1 domain (human p40<italic>phox </italic>numbering) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. The residue corresponding to the Leu-273 is much varied among vertebrate p40<italic>phox </italic>proteins (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>), suggesting that the residue is less crucial than that previously proposed if the interaction is important in other vertebrates than human. The residue to His-38 is often replaced by tyrosine. The majority of other residues are conserved, but there are some exceptions: residues corresponding to Arg-60 in <italic>X. tropicalis </italic>p40<italic>phox </italic>and to Glu-259 and Asp-269 in rat p40<italic>phox </italic>(see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Identification of highly conserved residues of p40<italic>phox</italic></bold>. (<italic>A</italic>) A schematic structure of p40<italic>phox </italic>domains is shown; proline-basic region, P-basic. Abbreviations of domain names are described in legends to other Figures. Letters in <italic>gray boxes </italic>indicate highly conserved proline and basic amino acid residues in the P-basic region. Letters in <italic>solid boxes </italic>indicate key acidic residues of OPCA motif that have been demonstrated by X-ray crystallographic structure [32]. K355 and K382 indicate two residues of human p67<italic>phox </italic>that interact with the OPCA motif. (<italic>B</italic>) Molecular taxonomy was generated by the alignment of amino acid sequences of PX domain. Species name abbreviations are given in Figure 3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-6"/></fig><p>To the best of our knowledge, a role for the SH3 domain of p40<italic>phox </italic>has not been defined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Eighteen amino acids are conserved in the SH3 domain (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). Between the PX and SH3 domains, we identified a new conserved region of 15 amino acids that is rich in proline, arginine and lysine, and is therefore designated the "proline-basic (P-basic) domain" (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). This putative region is not essential for PtdIns(3)P-binding by the p40<italic>phox </italic>PX domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>]. An intramolecular interaction between the PX and PB1 domains seem not to be related to P-basic region according to the structure of full length p40<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. The structural analysis demonstrates that P-basic region forms a separate motif and is situated closely to the PX domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>], indicating that it might support the cell membrane-binding function of p40<italic>phox </italic>together with the PX-domain. Alternatively, the P-basic region might interact with the SH3 domain of p40<italic>phox </italic>in a manner similar to the interaction between the AIR and the tandem SH3 of human p47<italic>phox</italic>. Interestingly, Thr-154 of human p40<italic>phox</italic>, located in the center of P-basic region, has been identified as a phosphorylation site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], and this residue is entirely conserved among all vertebrate p40<italic>phox </italic>orthologs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>).</p><p>The PB1 domain of human p40<italic>phox </italic>harbors acidic amino acids forming the "OPCA (<underline>O</underline>PR/<underline>PC</underline>/<underline>A</underline>ID) motif". An OPCA motif contains four distinctive acidic residues that are essential for binding to conserved basic residues in the p67<italic>phox </italic>PB1 domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. The four acidic residues, Asp-289, Glu-291, Asp-293 and Asp-302 (human p40<italic>phox </italic>numbering) are conserved in all orthologs with the exception of a glutamine rather than a glutamic acid in the position of <italic>C. familliaris </italic>p40<italic>phox </italic>that corresponds to Glu-291 of human p40<italic>phox </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of putative critical amino acids conserved among p22<italic>phox </italic>orthologs</title><p>Human p22<italic>phox </italic>contains two predicted transmembrane regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>] and forms a stabilizing heterocomplex with Nox2 as well as Nox1, Nox3, and Nox4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. The PRR of p22<italic>phox </italic>is the only motif in this protein whose role in Nox activation has been demonstrated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The PRR is highly conserved among all p22<italic>phox </italic>orthologs (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>, the sequences are provided in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>), consistent with its role as a docking site for the <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain of organizer proteins. In addition, a total of 38 amino acids were identical in all p22<italic>phox </italic>sequences (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>), suggesting important additional functions, particularly for the N-terminal regions preceding TM1. Within these conserved residues, we identified a region rich in arginine and lysine (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>), and is therefore designated the polybasic region (indicated as "basic" in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). A short sequence containing multiple basic amino acid residues has been proposed to contribute to recruitment of proteins to membrane sub-regions and to function in receptor-internalization via interaction with phospholipids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>]. According to our preliminary data, mutation in the polybasic region of p22<italic>phox </italic>did not affect extracellular ROS production from Nox2-transfected human embryonic kidney 293 cells (T. Kawahara and J. D. Lambeth, unpublished observations). This implies that the putative conserved region might function in a role unrelated to the enzymatic activity of Nox2, <italic>e.g</italic>. in phagocytosis or receptor-mediated endocytosis.</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Identification of highly conserved residues of p22<italic>phox</italic></bold>. (<italic>A</italic>) Schematic domains structures of p22<italic>phox </italic>are shown; TM1 and TM2 represent the predicted 1<sup>st </sup>and 2<sup>nd </sup>transmembrane region; PRR, proline-rich region; basic, a lysine- and arginine-rich conserved domain. Indicated above the schematic structure are putative key amino acid residues that are conserved in p22<italic>phox </italic>orthologs, and the residue numbers correspond to those of human p22<italic>phox</italic>. Detailed alignment of the polybasic region <italic>(B) </italic>and the PRR <italic>(C) </italic>are shown. Letters in <italic>solid boxes </italic>indicate the residues that have been proven by mutational analyses to be important for binding to p47<italic>phox </italic>and/or activation of human Nox2 [53, 75, 127, 128]. (<italic>D</italic>) Molecular taxonomy was generated based on the alignment of amino acid sequences of full-length p22<italic>phox</italic>. Species name abbreviations are given in Figure 3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-7"/></fig><p>As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, a p22<italic>phox</italic>-like protein was not identified in <italic>S. purpuratus</italic>, but because the genome sequence of this organism is incomplete and because a p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein with a conserved <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain is present, we suggest that this organism probably possesses an undiscovered p22<italic>phox</italic>-like protein, or a protein that serves an analogous function. Our analysis did not provide convincing evidence for a p22<italic>phox </italic>isolog in slime mold amoeba. Lardy <italic>et al</italic>. argued that this organism may possess a membrane-associated p22<italic>phox-</italic>like protein (GenBank&#x02122; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AY221170">AY221170</ext-link>); predicted p22<italic>phox</italic>-like gene-null <italic>D. discoideum </italic>mutant is unable to produce spores, similar to <italic>nox</italic>-null mutants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. However according to our analysis, this protein is highly divergent in amino acid sequence compared with the consensus sequence obtained from all other organisms, showing disagreement in 24 out of the 38 conserved residues shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>. Thus, further investigation is needed to judge whether the gene emerged as a later adaptation or whether it represents a primitive p22<italic>phox </italic>gene.</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular evolution of domains of Nox organizers and activators in Deuterostomia</title><p>As described above, comparisons of the amino acid sequences of the Nox regulatory subunit orthologs revealed certain features of the evolution of characteristic domains. Some key residues and domains are summarized in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, which shows the proposed evolution of organizer and activator proteins. The p47<italic>phox </italic>orthologs of all vertebrates (top four left-hand panels in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>) have identical domain structures, which include the PX domain, <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain, AIR, and PRR. On the other hand, the domain composition of NOXO1 (right-hand panels in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>) changed during the evolution from fish to tetrapods: the NOXO1 orthologs of tetrapods and fish all possessed the PX domain, <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain, and PRR. However, the predicted AIR (including key conserved residues, for details, see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>) is also present in <italic>O. latipes </italic>but is absent in <italic>D. rerio </italic>and tetrapods (right-hand panels in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). Despite the presence of the AIR in <italic>O. latipes </italic>NOXO1, it is clearly distinguished by sequence homology and synteny from a p47<italic>phox </italic>isolog, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>. Thus, initially, following gene duplication from p47<italic>phox</italic>, NOXO1 retained the AIR regulatory feature of p47<italic>phox</italic>, and this feature was subsequently lost.</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Evolution of domains of p47<italic>phox </italic>/NOXO1 and p67<italic>phox </italic>/NOXA1 orthologs</bold>. Shown is a schematic representation of identified domains and known or predicted inter- and intra-molecular interactions among p47<italic>phox</italic>/NOXO1 and p67<italic>phox</italic>/NOXA1 orthologs in "mammals" (<italic>H. sapiens</italic>), <italic>G. gallus</italic>, <italic>D. rerio</italic>, <italic>O. latipes</italic>, <italic>C. intestinalis</italic>, and <italic>S. purpuratus</italic>. <italic>Solid lines </italic>indicate interactions that have been demonstrated experimentally. <italic>Broken lines </italic>indicate predicted or proposed interactions based on sequences analysis and correspondence to experimentally demonstrated interactions in other species. The inferior diagram indicates deduced generalized structural features of p47<italic>phox- </italic>and p67<italic>phox-</italic>like proteins. Abbreviations of domain names are given in legends to other Figures.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-8"/></fig><p>Like vertebrate isologs of p47<italic>phox</italic>, the p47<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins of <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>and <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>possess the PX domain, <italic>bis-</italic>SH3 domain, and AIR. However, these isologs differ considerably in the C-terminal regions that, in higher forms, interact with p67<italic>phox </italic>isologs. The C-terminus of the <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>p47<italic>phox </italic>lacks the PRR, but motif scanning by PROSITE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>] demonstrates the p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein contains, instead, additional SH3 domain [residues 340&#x02013;399 of Ci-p47<italic>phox </italic>protein, GenBank&#x02122; No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NM_001033828">NM_001033828</ext-link>]. The <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein also lacked the C-terminal PRR, but instead had two additional SH3 domains (residues 367&#x02013;430 and 561&#x02013;618 of Sp-p47<italic>phox</italic>, GenBank&#x02122; No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="XP_001183696">XP_001183696</ext-link>) separated by two PRRs (residues 453&#x02013;460 and 476&#x02013;484 of Sp-p47<italic>phox</italic>) (bottom two left-hand panels in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>).</p><p>All vertebrate orthologs of p67<italic>phox </italic>have the same domains seen in human p67<italic>phox </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, left panels). Importantly, all p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1 proteins possess the AD region, which has been shown to be critical for activating superoxide generation in Nox2 and Nox1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. The TPR motif is present in all species, and the two critical residues for Rac-binding, Asp-67 and Arg-102 of human p67<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], are conserved among all vertebrate isologs of p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1 (top four panels in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>), supporting the idea that binding to Rac is a conserved feature of vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>andNOXA1. The N-terminal domain structures of <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>and <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins are similar to those of vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). Both p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins possess a TPR domain retaining the two critical Rac-binding residues (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). In addition, <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like protein possesses a second set of TPR and AD-like domains. Both TRP domains retain conserved essential Rac-binding residues, but the second AD-like domain was not well conserved as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>. Thus, Rac binding is likely to be an evolutionarily conserved feature among all p67<italic>phox</italic>/NOXA1 proteins.</p><p>In mammals, binding between the PB1 domains of p67<italic>phox </italic>and p40<italic>phox </italic>has been shown to mediate heterodimer formation. The crystal structure of the heterodimer of the PB1 domains from p67<italic>phox </italic>and p40<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] demonstrated that Lys-355 and Lys-382 in human p67<italic>phox </italic>are essential to bind to the PB1 domain of p40<italic>phox</italic>, and mutation of Lys-355 of human p67<italic>phox </italic>abolished binding to p40<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>]. These crucial residues are entirely conserved in the PB1 domains of all vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>proteins, which imply that they all bind to p40<italic>phox </italic>(top four left-hand panels in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). In contrast to vertebrate p67<italic>phox</italic>, mammalian NOXA1 does not retain these two key amino acids (a top right-hand panel of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>), explaining the failure of NOXA1 to bind to p40<italic>phox </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. However, the chicken <italic>G. gallus</italic>, and the fish <italic>D. rerio </italic>and <italic>O. latipes </italic>NOXA1 completely conserve these two residues, and an OPCA motif of p40<italic>phox </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), which is essential for binding to the p67<italic>phox </italic>PB1 domain are highly conserved. The conservations of key residues suggest that in these fish, binding to p40<italic>phox </italic>may be retained (from the second to fourth panels in right hand of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). Thus, the loss of function of p40<italic>phox </italic>can be traced in the evolution of NOXA1. Both <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>and <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins lack a PB1 domain, consistent with the absence of p40<italic>phox </italic>orthologs.</p><p>The PX-domain of human p40<italic>phox </italic>specifically binds to PtdIns(3)P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>]. Therefore, p40<italic>phox </italic>accumulates during phagocytosis at early endosomes, which are rich in PtdIns(3)P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>]. <italic>T. rubripes </italic>p40<italic>phox </italic>is expressed in a wide range of tissues including the gastrointestinal tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>], while Nox2 expression is restricted to the blood and kidney. Although Nox1 expression in fish or the other non-mammal organisms is not clear, our analysis suggest that Nox1 of fish and birds might function, along with the p40<italic>phox </italic>orthologs, in endocytosis, <italic>e.g</italic>., in receptor-internalization. This novel relationship between Nox1 and p40<italic>phox </italic>may provide a clue to understanding the physiological role of Nox1 in vertebrates.</p><p>The vertebrate p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1 orthologs all have the C-terminal SH3 domain that, in human, mediates binding to the PRR of p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1, respectively. This supports the idea that all of the vertebrate forms of these proteins mediate protein interactions via tail-to-tail binding between the SH3 domain of the activator protein and the PRR of the organizer protein. We further suggest that even though the structures of the C-termini of p47<italic>phox</italic>- and p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins in <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>and in <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>differ from the vertebrate proteins, the same sort of tail-to-tail binding of these p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins to the corresponding p47<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins occurs as diagrammed at the bottom of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>. For example, we suggest that the C-terminal putative PRRs of <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins (residues 256&#x02013;348 of Ci-p67<italic>phox </italic>protein, GenBank&#x02122; No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NM_001033827">NM_001033827</ext-link>) binds to the C-terminal SH3 domain of the p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein as indicated by a broken line in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>, reversing the mode of interaction seen in the vertebrate proteins but accomplishing the same function. Similarly, SH3 domains and putative PRRs in the C-terminus of <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein may interact with the PRRs and the SH3 domains in the C-terminus of <italic>S. purpura</italic>tus p67<italic>phox</italic>, respectively. Thus, while domains in the C-termini of p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox </italic>orthologs are not conserved during evolution, the model shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> suggests that the "docking function" has been retained. The model suggests three functional modules within the organizer protein/activator protein complex: 1), a "membrane-binding/cytochrome docking region" on the organizer protein that is comprised of the phospholipids-binding PX domain and the tandem SH3 region that binds to the PRR of p22<italic>phox</italic>; 2) a "Nox-activating region" that contains the Rac-binding TPR domain and the AD, which together cooperate to stimulate the activity of the Nox catalytic domain; and 3) a "regulator-docking region" which uses evolutionarily variable but paired docking modules that link the "membrane-binding/cytochrome docking region" of p47<italic>phox </italic>to the "Nox-activating region" of p67<italic>phox </italic>(bottom panel in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Occurrence and origin of <italic>Phox</italic>-like regulatory subunits during evolution of Metazoa and Choanoflagellata</title><p>In addition to regulatory subunit-dependent Nox proteins of the Deuterostomia, we assembled predicted regulatory subunits and the subunit-regulated Nox isolog sequences present in the genomes of following species: the sea anemone <italic>Nematostella vectensis </italic>(<italic>N. vectensis</italic>), the limpet <italic>Lottia gigantea </italic>(<italic>L. gigantea</italic>), the marine choanoflagellate <italic>Monosiga brevicollis </italic>(<italic>M. brevicollis</italic>) (see Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref>). According to the recent phylogeny based on small ribosomal subunit gene and other molecular tools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>], the bilaterian animals consist of three clades: Deuterostomia, Lophotrochozoa, and Ecdysozoa. A gastropod snail, the limpet <italic>L. gigantea</italic>, belongs to the Lophotrochozoa, and p67<italic>phox</italic>, p47<italic>phox</italic>, p22<italic>phox</italic>-like genes are found in this genome (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). The predicted motif structures by the Pfam program are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9B</xref>; characteristic motifs of p67<italic>phox </italic>(TPR domain and AD-like region) and p47<italic>phox </italic>(PX domain and AIR-like region) as well as the key residues (detailed alignments are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref>) are conserved. The genome of <italic>L. gigantea </italic>also possesses an ancestral Nox2 gene as a co-ortholog of vertebrate Nox1-3 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref> and see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>) like Nox2 isologs in primitive deuterostomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. On the other hand, any distinct regulatory subunit genes were not found in seven species that belongs to Ecdysozoa including two nemotodes (<italic>Caenorhabditis elegans </italic>and <italic>Caenorhabditis briggsae</italic>), four insects (<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>, <italic>Apis mellifera</italic>, <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>, <italic>Aedes aegypt</italic>), and one non-insect arthropod (the waterflea <italic>Daphnia pulex</italic>) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><bold>Relationship between the evolution of eukaryotes and the occurrence of <italic>Phox </italic>-related regulatory subunits</bold>. (<italic>A</italic>) A phylogeny of eukaryotes was created based largely on genetic information [90, 100]. Branch lengths are for illustrative purposes and are not proportional to phylogenetic distances of groups. Details of deusterostomes are shown in Figure 1. "n.i." indicates none identified or reported. "co-ortho. of v-Nox1-3" indicates that the gene is a co-ortholog ancestor of all members of the vertebrate Nox1-3 subgroup. The number in a parenthesis (e.g. [129, 130, 131]) indicates a reference number. (<italic>B</italic>) Predicted domains structures of newly identified putative regulatory subunit-like proteins are shown; P, proline-rich region. The sequences are provided in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>. Abbreviations of domain names are described in legends to other Figures. (C) Sequences of putative AIR-like region are shown. <italic>Underlines </italic>indicate residues that agree with a consensus sequence of protein kinase C substrate. <italic>Bold letters </italic>indicate predicted phosphorylation sites in AIR-like regions. Abbreviations: Hs, <italic>H. sapiens</italic>; Sp, <italic>S. purpuratus</italic>; <italic>Nv, N. vectensis</italic>; Lg, <italic>L. gigantea</italic>; Mb, <italic>M. brevicollis</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-9"/></fig><p>Before the emergence of bilateral animals, cnidarians split from the main animal lineage and the genome retained many of the features present in last common ancestor of animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>]. The starlet sea anemone <italic>N. vectensis </italic>that belongs to the Cnidaria, conserves p47<italic>phox</italic>-, p22<italic>phox</italic>-like genes, and two ancestral Nox2 genes, Nox2A and 2B (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). The characteristic motifs of the putative regulatory subunits are predicted by the Pfam program and shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9B</xref> (alignments are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref>). <italic>N. vectensis </italic>p47<italic>phox </italic>possesses PX and <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domains. The isolog also possesses a putative polybasic region within the sequence corresponding to the AIR of the human p47<italic>phox </italic>gene. A polybasic region is a class III consensus motif for binding to a SH3 domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>]; therefore, this may implicate the polybasic region as a prototype of the AIR. Although the current version of the <italic>N. vectensis </italic>genome does not encode an obvious p67<italic>phox</italic>-like gene, the presence of multiple SH3 domains in <italic>N. vectensis </italic>p47<italic>phox </italic>points to an unidentified p67<italic>phox </italic>ortholog or an unknown PRR-containing binding partner. Although cnidarians have no specialized immune cells, the <italic>N. vectensis </italic>genome possesses orthologous genes to Toll/Toll-like receptors, complement C3-like molecules, and a redox-sensitive transcription factor nuclear factor-&#x003ba;B that are orthologs of key components of innate immunity in vertebrates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">92</xref>]. Further study needs to identify an original role of <italic>Phox</italic>-type NADPH oxidase in the primitive multicellular animals.</p><p>One clear implication of these genomic and detailed sequence analyses described above is that the hypothetical ancestor of primitive animals might conserve the <italic>Phox</italic>-type NADPH-oxidase system. In the middle of the nineteenth century, a striking structural resemblance between the collar cells, so-called "choanocytes", of primitive animal sponges and a group of protists the choanoflagellates has been noted ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">93</xref>], reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>]). A line of recent phylogenic analyses suggests that the metazoa including sponges, cnidarians, and other animals constitutes a monophyletic clade closely related to the Choanoflagellata [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">95</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B96">96</xref>]; therefore, the choanoflagellates are considered to be the organisms that are close in evolution to the all modern animals. The unicellular marine choanoflagellate <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>has been reported as a closer relatives to the hypothetical ancestor of all multicellular animals based on the comparative analyses of animal-specific genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">98</xref>]. Interestingly, the genome of <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>possesses p47<italic>phox</italic>- and p22<italic>phox</italic>-like genes (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A,B</xref>), but a BLAST searching in the current <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>genomic database failed to identify a dinstinct p67<italic>phox </italic>ortholog. Furthermore, Nox2-like gene is present in the <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>genome sequence (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). Interestingly, a taxonomy of Nox domains demonstrates that <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>Nox2-like gene diverges from the monophyletic clade of all metazoan Nox2 genes containing other ancestral Nox2 and all vertebrate Nox1-3, but it differs from Nox4 and fungal NoxA/NoxB subfamilies (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). The <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein possesses AIR-like region that conserves a serine residue consistent with a consensus motif of a putative substrate of protein kinase C (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9C</xref>); therefore, this implies that ROS-generating activity of the most primitive Nox2-like protein is also strictly regulated by phosphorylation as seen in mammalian phagocyte NADPH-oxidase. The physiological function of the primordial Nox2 enzyme in <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>is unknown, but the early appearance of the <italic>Phox</italic>-like Nox system in the unicellular flagellate suggests the presence of a fundamental and essential role of the regulatory subunit-dependent Nox in a unicellular living.</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref> also summarizes the occurrence of Nox4, Nox5, and Duox isologs in genomes of the metazoa and the choanoflagellate, adding to information published previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Duox orthologs are present in all analyzed genomes of the Bilateria (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). Nox5 genes occur broadly in the genomes of Metazoa, but not in Nematoda. Nox4 genes appear after the emergence of chordates, but is not seen in the echinoderm <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Interestingly, gene search that covers a wide range demonstrates that Nox4-like genes are also present in a lophotrochozoan (<italic>L. gigantea</italic>), a cnidarian (<italic>N. vectensis</italic>), but not in the ecdysozoans (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>, and the taxonomy of Nox is shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). The choanoflagellate <italic>M. brevicolli </italic>do not possess Nox4, Nox5, and Duox orthologs, at least based on the current genomic database. In the kingdom Plantae, the moss <italic>Physcomitrella patens </italic>(<italic>P. patens</italic>) possess double EF-hand- containing Noxes like the higher land plants <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana </italic>(<italic>A. thaliana</italic>) and <italic>Oryza sativa </italic>(<italic>O. sativa</italic>) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). Despite a kingdom distinct from plants, the oomycete <italic>Phytophthora sojae </italic>(<italic>P. sojae</italic>) also possesses single or double EF-hand(s)-containing Noxes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B99">99</xref>], at least three genes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). Here we referred to them as <italic>P. patens </italic>and <italic>P. sojae </italic>rboh (respiratory burst oxidase homolog) to represent the remarkable resemblance to the higher plant Noxes, so-called rboh, in the respects of taxonomy of the Nox domains (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). In the kingdoms Plantae and Chomista, a distinct regulatory subunit was not seen. However, higher plant genomes possess a novel protein family conserved domain structures similar to p67<italic>phox </italic>as descried below. <italic>Naegleria gruberi </italic>(<italic>N. gruberi</italic>) is a widespread soil and freshwater amoeboflagellate that belongs to the phylum Perocolozoa, the kingdom Protozoa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">100</xref>]. Although <italic>N. gruberi </italic>is a free-living organism, it is not related to species of the phylum Amoebozoa with sequenced genomes, such as <italic>D. discoideum </italic>and <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic>, but it is close to pathogenic relatives (e.g. <italic>Naegleria fowleri</italic>) that can cause amoebic meningitis. We identified single Nox gene of <italic>N. gruberi </italic>from the genome (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>), together with five putative <italic>Fre </italic>ortholog genes that have similar domain structures to that of Nox domain (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S9">9</xref>). According to a phylogenetic taxonomy of Nox domain, the <italic>N. gruberi </italic>Nox is close to <italic>D. discoideum </italic>NoxA/NoxB proteins (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>); therefore, it is referred to as <italic>N. gruberi </italic>NoxA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). Nox regulatory subunit gene has not been found in the current version of genomic database, but it might contain a prototype of regulatory subunits according to the Nox taxonomy.</p></sec><sec><title>SH3PXD2 as a p47<italic>phox </italic>family member</title><p>As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9</xref>, a choanoflagellate and primitive animals possess p47<italic>phox</italic>-like genes as well as ancestral Nox2 and PRR-containing p22<italic>phox </italic>genes. On the other hand, further BLASTP search in the animal genomes using the <italic>M. brevicolli </italic>p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein sequence suggested the presence of a protein family proteins related to the primitive p47<italic>phox </italic>in higher animals, encoding the <bold>"</bold>SH3 and PX domains 2" protein (SH3PXD2) (sequences and alignments are provided in Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S10">10</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S11">11</xref>, respectively). The encoded protein is composed of an N-terminal PX domain and a central <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domain, plus two or three additional SH3 domains in the C-terminal half of the molecule (see the motif structure in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10A</xref>). The SH3PXD2 gene is present in a urochordate, but was not seen in an echinoderm and other primitive metazoan species (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10B</xref>). In vertebrates, two isozymes SH3PXD2a and 2b were found (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10A</xref>). Interestingly the <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>p47<italic>phox</italic>-like gene and other primitive animal p47<italic>phox</italic>-like genes are related more closely to the SH3PXD2 gene subfamily than to the vertebrate p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1 subfamilies (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10A</xref>). The physiological function of SH3PXD2a is suggested by only a few papers; human SH3PXD2a protein (a.k.a. Tks5) is involved in the protease-driven invasion of cancer cells and the neurotoxicity induced by amyloid-beta [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B101">101</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B102">102</xref>]. A protein binding to SH3PXD2a is also little known, but recently N-WASP (Wiskott-Aldrich Syndrome protein) was proposed as a candidate that binds to the third SH3 domain of the human SH3PXD2a [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B101">101</xref>]. The physiological role as well as the binding partner of SH3PXD2b is unknown. However, the clear phylogenetic relationship of the SH3PXD2 gene family to the larger family of Nox-regulatory organizing proteins suggests that the genes might be involved in regulating Nox activity. Alternatively, SH3PXD2 proteins may have diverged to perform unrelated functions (e.g., to regulate other enzymes or signaling pathways). Thus, the <italic>M. brevilcollis </italic>p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein evolved from a hypothetical p47<italic>phox </italic>ancestor, and the SH3PXD2 genes diverged from the lineage of the p47<italic>phox</italic>-like gene following the emergence of chordates but prior to NOXO1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10B</xref>). The vertebrate p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1 were somehow able to eliminate the additional SH3 domains in the "regulator-docking region", as proposed in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p><bold>Evolution of a vast family of p47<italic>phox </italic>proteins</bold>. (A) Molecular taxonomy of the p47<italic>phox </italic>and related proteins is shown. The sequences of SH3PXD2 orthologs are provided in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S10">10</xref>. Predicted domains structures of <italic>H. sapiens </italic>(p47<italic>phox</italic>, NOXO1, SH3PXD2a, 2b) and <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>(p47<italic>phox</italic>-like) proteins are shown near to each subfamily: P, proline-rich region; C, C-tail region. An <italic>asterisk </italic>indicates the appearance of a <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>SH3PXD2 branch from a common root of the p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein. Abbreviations of species names and other domains are given in other Figures. (B) A schematic drawing to show a hypothetical evolution of an expanded p47<italic>phox</italic>-like gene family. Branches are for illustrative purposes and are not proportional to rates of divergence.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-10"/></fig></sec><sec><title>What is the regulatory subunit binding partner for fungal NOXR?</title><p>Fungi (<italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>M. grisea</italic>, and <italic>F. graminearum</italic>) belong to Ascomycota [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>] and possess the NOXR gene as a p67<italic>phox </italic>ortholog (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A</xref>). NOXR encodes a PB1 domain homologous to that in p67<italic>phox</italic>, but these organisms do not possess a p40<italic>phox </italic>ortholog (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>, two important basic residues in the PB1 domains are conserved in all NOXR proteins. The conservation of these residues implies the existence of an unknown NOXR binding partner(s) containing a PB1 domain with an OPCA motif (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11A</xref>). A BLAST search of a database of computationally predicted amino acid sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B103">103</xref>] from the genomes of <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>M. grisea</italic>, and <italic>F. graminearum </italic>was performed using as a query sequence the PB1 domain of human p40<italic>phox </italic>(residues 237&#x02013;339; GenBank&#x02122; No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NP_000622">NP_000622</ext-link>). In addition to NOXR, three sequences harboring PB1 domains were identified in the fungi. These were: "SH3-SH3-PX-SRR-PB1", "CDC24-RhoGEF-PB1" and "(CBS)n-PB1" proteins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11B</xref> and see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S12">12</xref>), so-named for their domain structures in sequence from N- to C-termini. SRR indicates a serine-rich region. The three predicted proteins were encoded in all three fungal genomes, and all three possessed acidic OPCA motifs in their PB1 domains (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F11"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p><bold>Predicted binding partners of fungal NOXR and activation models of fungal Nox</bold>. (<italic>A</italic>) A hypothetical domain structure of a predicted NOXR partner is shown. (<italic>B</italic>) Domain structures of fungal proteins with PB1 domains meeting criteria for possible NOXR-partners are shown, along with their GenBank&#x02122; accession numbers. Abbreviations: An, <italic>A. nidulans</italic>; Mg, <italic>M. grisea</italic>; Fg, <italic>F. graminearum</italic>. (<italic>C</italic>) Aligned OPCA motifs of candidate NOXR partners are compared with the corresponding region in p40<italic>phox </italic>and the yeast isolog (the first and second alignments). Amino acid residues conserved among fungal ortholog sequences are indicated by <italic>asterisks</italic>. (<italic>D</italic>) A proposed model for activation of fungal Nox by NOXR and Bem1 protein. (<italic>E</italic>) A proposed model for activation of fungal Nox by NOXR and Cdc24. (<italic>F</italic>) A proposed model for activation of fungal Nox by CBSn-PB1 proteins. RhoGEF, Rho guanine nucleotide exchange factor; CBS, cystathionine beta-synthase; Abbreviations of other domain names are described in legends to other Figures.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-11"/></fig><p>The "SH3-SH3-PX-SRR-PB1" protein contains a similar domain structure to yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>Bem1p (Bud Emergence 1, GenBank&#x02122; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NP_009759">NP_009759</ext-link>), but differs in that the PB1 domain of <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>Bem1p does not contain the OPCA motif [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>]. A speculative model for the regulation of fungal Nox by the Bem1 ortholog is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11D</xref>, wherein Bem1 ortholog is proposed to play a role as an organizer protein, analogous to the roles of p47<italic>phox </italic>and p40<italic>phox </italic>in mammals. According to this model, PB1-PB1 interaction mediates the linkage between the "regulator-docking regions" suggested in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>. PX-domain of the <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>Bem1 facilitates a protein to anchor to a membrane lipid layer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B104">104</xref>]. Fungi do not have a PRR-containing p22<italic>phox </italic>ortholog (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), but NoxA and NoxB in the three fungi has a distinctive highly conserved a class II PRR motif [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>] (e.g. 423&#x02013;428 residues of Mg-NoxA) and class III (e.g. 447&#x02013;452 residues of Mg-NoxB) near the predicted NADPH-binding sub-regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Thus the hypothetical functions of the <italic>bis-</italic>SH3 and PX domains indicate the analogous function as a "membrane-binding/cytochrome docking region" of Nox organizer. Because <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>Bem1 is involved in establishment of cell polarity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B105">105</xref>], the proposed interaction between fungal NOXR and Bem1 orthologs may point to a function of Nox-derived ROS in cell polarity.</p><p>A second model is suggested by the "CDC24-RhoGEF-PB1" protein, which is an ortholog of <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>Cdc24p (GenBank&#x02122; accession number <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AAA82871">AAA82871</ext-link>). According to this "exchanger model", the PB1-mediated heterodimer formation localizes the RhoGEF domain which then catalyzes the conversion of Rac-GDP to the active Rac-GTP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11E</xref>). The model is supported by a recent report showed that fungal NOXR binds to the fungal Rac homologue in the GTP form [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>].</p><p>An "energy sensor" function for NOXR is shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11F</xref>, and is based on the occurrence of the CBS (cystathione beta-synthase) domain in the putative binding partner. The CBS domain senses cellular energy status by binding adenosine nucleotides; it occurs in a range of proteins including AMP-activated protein kinase, which is activated by AMP and inhibited by ATP via the CBS domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B106">106</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B107">107</xref>]. Such a function might be related to the requirement of Nox enzyme for reduced pyridine nucleotide, thus affecting cellular energetics.</p><p>Fungal Nox and NOXR isologs are seen not only in fungi belonging to Ascomycota, but also some basidiomycetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. To explore the likelihood of the fungal Nox activation mechanisms suggested in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">11</xref>, the occurrence of NOXR, Bem1, Cdc24, and CBSn-PB1 isologs were compared in 13 fungal genomes spanning the four fungal divisions: Ascomycota, Basidiomycota, Zygomycota, and Chytridiomycota (sequences are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S12">12</xref>). Bem1, Cdc24, and CBSn-PB1 genes are present in most of the fungal genomes, with the exception of Cdc24 in <italic>Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis </italic>(<italic>B. dendrobatidis</italic>), and these proteins all conserved the PB1 domains with some exceptions; <italic>Y. lipolytica </italic>NOXR and <italic>Coprinopsis cinerea </italic>Cdc24 isologs lack the PB1 domain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref>). In addition to the absence of Nox and NOXR isolog genes in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, the Nox and NOXR isologs are absent in the genomes of <italic>Candida albicans, Yarrowia lipolytica </italic>(<italic>Y. lipolytica</italic>) and <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe </italic>(<italic>S. pombe</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. A Nox gene is absent in the genomes of <italic>Y. lipolytica </italic>and <italic>Phycomyces blakesleeanus </italic>(<italic>P. blakesleeanus</italic>) despite the presence of NOXR isologs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. The <italic>P. blakesleeanus </italic>genome possesses two Bem1 and CBS-PB1 genes and all conserved the PB1 domains. We investigated the conservation of two basic residues of the PB1 domain corresponding to the Lys-355 and -382 residues of human p67<italic>phox </italic>and the four acidic residues in OPCA motif corresponding to the Asp-289, Glu-291, and Asp-293, -302 residues of human p40<italic>phox</italic>. Comparison of the PB1 domains in these fungal proteins by alignment and analyses by the Pfam program demonstrate that the two basic and four acidic residues are conserved in the fungal NOXR, Bem1, Cdc24, and CBSn-PB1 with a few exceptions; the OPCA motifs in Bem1 isologs of <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>and <italic>C. albicans </italic>has been lost (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">12</xref> and the sequences and detailed alignments are shown in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S13">13</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S14">14</xref>, respectively). The high conservation of the motif strongly implies that these PB1 domains mediate functionally important oligomerizations. Future functional studies will clarify the roles of these proteins in fungal Nox functions.</p><fig position="float" id="F12"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p><bold>Conservations of NOXR, Bem1, Cdc24, and CBSn-PB1 genes and characteristic residues of PB1 domains in fungal genomes</bold>. (<italic>A</italic>) "basic" and "OPCA" in parenthesis indicate key residues that are required to form a dimer between two PB1 domains; two "basic" residues and four in "OPCA" motif residues correspond to Lys-355 and Lys-382 of human p67<italic>phox </italic>and Asp-289, Glu-291, Asp-293 and Asp-302 of human p40<italic>phox</italic>, respectively. Divisions of Fungi are shown in <italic>bold</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-12"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Predicted binding partners for <italic>D. discoideum </italic>p67-like protein</title><p>Like fungal NOXRs, the PB1 domain of <italic>D. discoideum </italic>p67-like protein also possesses two basic residues, Lys-313 and Lys-340 residues, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5E</xref>. A BLAST search demonstrates that the <italic>D. discoideum </italic>genome possesses five predicted PB1 domain-containing proteins (referred to here as "Dd-PB1-A to -E"). All except Dd-PB1-D conserve the OPCA motif (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13</xref>, and see details in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S15">15</xref>). Dd-PB1-A protein (GenBank No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="XP_639165">XP_639165</ext-link>) is partially identical to <italic>D. discoideum </italic>MEK kinase &#x003b1; (GenBank No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AAC97114">AAC97114</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B108">108</xref>]. It is possible that the serine/threonine kinase domain might phosphorylate the amoebal Noxes or the p67-like protein to stimulate ROS generation, analogous to other regulatory phosphorylations of Nox and their regulatory subunits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B109">109</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B111">111</xref>]. Another interesting point of the Dd-PB1-A protein is to contain the F-box and a WD40 repeat regions that function as a ubiquitin ligase component E3. Further investigations to identify a binding partner will lead to understand functional relationships between Nox and the Dd-PB1 proteins.</p><fig position="float" id="F13"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p><bold>Predicted candidate binding partners of <italic>D. discoideum </italic>p67-like protein</bold>. Predicted domain structures of Dd-p67-like protein and candidates of binding partners are shown. "basic" and "OPCA" in <italic>parenthesis </italic>indicate six characteristic residues of PB1 domain as shown in Figure 12. Abbreviations: kinase, protein serine/threonine kinase domain; F, F-box; WD40, WD40 repeat; WW, WW domain; ZZ, ZZ type zinc-finger.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-13"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Do p67<italic>phox</italic>-like genes exist in plants?</title><p>The land plants, <italic>A. thaliana </italic>and <italic>O. sativa </italic>possess the multiple EF-hand-containing Nox proteins, At-rboh-A to -J [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B112">112</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B113">113</xref>] and Os-rboh-A [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B114">114</xref>] to -H, respectively. However, there is no report of <italic>Phox</italic>-related regulatory subunit homologs in plant genomes. Unexpectedly BLAST search using PB1 domain sequences demonstrates that <italic>A. thaliana </italic>possesses a unique family of genes encoding four proteins that possess both TPR and PB1 domains (GenBank accession No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NP_194935">NP_194935</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NP_180101">NP_180101</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NP_197536">NP_197536</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NP_564794">NP_564794</ext-link>). The <italic>O. sativa </italic>genome also possesses a similar gene (GenBank accession No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="BAD31284">BAD31284</ext-link>). Herein, we refer to this family as "hypothetical p67<italic>phox</italic>-like (hypo-p67-L)". The expressions of at least the two identified genes, At-hypo-p67-L1 and -L4, were confirmed according to the EST database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B115">115</xref>].</p><p>Domain structures of the <italic>A. thaliana </italic>and <italic>O. sativa </italic>hypo-p67-L proteins are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14A</xref> (sequences are provided in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S16">16</xref>). The six residues characteristic of the PB1 domains are conserved in all sequences (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14A</xref>, and see the alignment in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S17">17</xref>). This predicts that the hypo-p67-L proteins will form a heteromeric or homomeric complex via PB1-PB1-interaction. In addition to the hypo-p67-L gene family, the <italic>A. thaliana </italic>genome possessed at least 27 isolated genes encoding the PB1 domain [e.g. protein kinase family protein (GenBank No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NP_200569">NP_200569</ext-link>), CBSn-PB1 ortholog (GenBank No. <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="NP_181191">NP_181191</ext-link>), see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S18">18</xref>]. Alignment of putative AD-like domains of the <italic>A. thaliana </italic>proteins with human p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1 show that the <italic>A. thaliana </italic>hypo-p67-L1 and -L2 proteins conserve the functionally critical valine residue (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14B</xref>). Moreover, a lysine residue corresponding to Lys-196 of human p67<italic>phox </italic>that is correlated to the appearance of functional PB1 domain is also conserved in two of them (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14B</xref>). On the other hand, the sequences do not conserve residues in the TPR domain known to be essential for binding to Rac [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Biological functions for this putative family are unknown and further investigations are needed.</p><fig position="float" id="F14"><label>Figure 14</label><caption><p><bold>Predicted p67<italic>phox- </italic>like proteins in higher plants</bold>. (A) Predicted domain structures of hypothetical p67<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins (At-hypo-p67-L1 to -L4, Os-hypo-p67-L1) of <italic>A. thaliana </italic>and <italic>O. sativa</italic>, and a fungal <italic>F. graminearum </italic>(Fg-) NOXR are shown, along with their GenBank&#x02122; accession numbers. "basic" and "OPCA" in parenthesis indicate six characteristic residues of PB1 domains as shown in Figure 12. "D" and "R" below the TPR region of Fg-NOXR represent two conserved amino acid residues that are important for binding to Rac as indicated in Figure 5. (B) Alignments of the putative AD-like regions are shown (see details in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S17">17</xref>). <italic>Boxes </italic>indicate lysine and valine residues corresponding to the Lys-196 and Val-204 of human p67<italic>phox</italic>, respectively. <italic>Underlines </italic>in alignment indicates amino acid with a hydropholic side group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-14"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, we reported here an exhaustive analysis of the <italic>Phox</italic>-related regulatory subunits for Nox enzymes from a total of 32 species in the Eukaryota including 10 vertebrates. The present study, viewed in the context of the evolution of Noxes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], reveals that regulatory subunits co-evolved with their respective Noxes; Nox2 with p67<italic>phox</italic>/p47<italic>phox</italic>; Nox1 with NOXO1/NOXA1; ancestral Nox2 as co-ortholog of vertebrate Nox1-3 with p67<italic>phox</italic>/p47<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins; fungal and amoebal NoxA/B with NOXR (and possibly new components). By comparing amino acid sequences of the regulatory subunits, putative key amino acid residues and conserved region previously undefined were identified, e.g. ADSIS. These conserved residues are likely to be important in conserved catalytic or regulatory functions of Nox proteins, although, the detailed biochemical roles of most of these residues are not yet fully understood. The analysis of the <italic>Phox</italic>-related regulatory subunits points to a novel evolutionary history of Nox regulatory proteins. The earliest Nox2 and p47<italic>phox</italic>- and p22<italic>phox</italic>-like genes are appearing in the unicellular choanoflagellate before the emergence of the metazoa. Duplication of primordial p47<italic>phox</italic>- and p67<italic>phox</italic>-like genes occurred in vertebrates, resulting in the emergence of NOXO1-p47<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1-p67<italic>phox </italic>genes, respectively. Supporting this evolutionary origin, the NOXO1 protein in the fish <italic>O. latipes </italic>still retains the p47<italic>phox</italic>-characteristic "AIR". A predicted motif structure of ancestral p47<italic>phox </italic>suggests a greatly expanded family of p47<italic>phox </italic>including SH3PXD2 in the animal lineages. Detailed sequence analyses proposed an evolution model that p40<italic>phox </italic>originally participated in regulating both Nox1 and Nox2 in early vertebrates, but in mammals the regulation of Nox1 became independent of p40<italic>phox</italic>. Thus, this report provides keys to understand the evolutionary history of Nox and the regulatory subunits, and provides new information that may be useful in elucidating new molecular details of the activation mechanisms of Nox enzymes including the human orthologs.</p><p>Note: While we were in the process of revising this manuscript, a review article about structure and function of the PB1 domain appeared [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B116">116</xref>]. The review will help to understand the structural features of the PB1 domain that are often mentioned in the present study. In the article, authors also described the presence of the hypothetical genes coding TPR and PB1 domain-containing proteins in the <italic>A. thaliana </italic>genomes and argued about a possibility of <italic>A. thaliana </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Gene identification</title><p>Homologues/orthologs of Nox/Duox and regulatory subunits sequences were assembled from the following species: <italic>H. sapiens</italic>, (human), <italic>C. familliaris </italic>(dog), <italic>R. norvegicus </italic>(rat), <italic>M. musculus </italic>(mouse), <italic>G. gallus </italic>(chicken), <italic>X. tropicalis </italic>(frog), <italic>D. rerio </italic>(zebrafish), <italic>T. rubripes </italic>(fugu), <italic>T. nigroviridis </italic>(tetraodon), <italic>O. latipes </italic>(medaka), <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>(ascidian), <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>(sea urchin), <italic>D. pulex </italic>(waterflea), C.<italic>briggsae </italic>(nematode), <italic>C. elegans </italic>(nematode), <italic>N. vectensis </italic>(sea anemone), <italic>L. gigantea </italic>(gastropod snail), <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>(choanoflagellate), <italic>D. discoideum </italic>(slime mold amoeba), <italic>C. merolae </italic>(red alga), <italic>A. nidulans </italic>(fungus-An), <italic>M. grisea </italic>(fungus-Mg), <italic>F. graminearum </italic>(fungus-Fg), <italic>S. cerevisiae </italic>(fungus-Sc), <italic>C. albicans </italic>(fungus-Ca), <italic>Y. lipolytica </italic>(fungus-Yl), <italic>S. pombe </italic>(fungus-Sp), <italic>Coprinopsis cinerea </italic>(<italic>C. cinerea</italic>, fungus-Cc), <italic>L. bicolor </italic>(fungus-Lb), <italic>P. placenta </italic>(fungus-Pp), <italic>Puccinia graminis </italic>(<italic>P. graminis</italic>, fungus-Pg), <italic>P. blakesleeanus </italic>(fungus-Pb), <italic>B. dendrobatidis </italic>(fungus-Bd), <italic>P. sojae </italic>(oomycete), <italic>Phaeodactylum tricornutum </italic>(<italic>P. tricornutum</italic>, diatom), <italic>Physcomitrella patens </italic>(<italic>P. patens </italic>moss), <italic>A. thaliana </italic>(land plant), and <italic>O. sativa </italic>(land plant). Using NCBI-HomoloGene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B117">117</xref>], existing homologues/orthologs of regulatory subunits were assembled: p47<italic>phox</italic>, NOXO1, p67<italic>phox</italic>, NOXA1, p40<italic>phox </italic>and p22<italic>phox </italic>orthologs of human, dog, mouse, rat, and p47<italic>phox </italic>and p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXO1 orthologs of chicken. In addition, we assembled amino acid sequences that have been cloned and reported: p47<italic>phox</italic>, p67<italic>phox</italic>, and p22<italic>phox </italic>of <italic>T. rubripes </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>] and <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]; p67-like protein of <italic>D. discoideum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]; NOXR of fungi including <italic>A. nidulans, M. grisea</italic>, <italic>F. graminearum </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. Based on these sequences, BLASTP searches were performed to obtain predicted regulatory subunits, related Nox genes (including genes that has been reported such as <italic>P. sojae </italic>rboh [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B99">99</xref>], <italic>C. merolae </italic>rboh1/2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B118">118</xref>], <italic>P. tricornutum </italic>rboh1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B118">118</xref>]), new regulator-binging partners, using the NCBI protein database for vertebrates, <italic>C. intestinalis, C. briggsae, D. discoideum, A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>O. sativa </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B103">103</xref>], <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>], and for fungi (<italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>M. grisea</italic>, <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, <italic>S. cerevisiae, C. albicans, Y. lipolytica, S. pombe, C. cinerea</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B119">119</xref>], the Doe Joint Genome Institute database for <italic>L. bicolor, P. placenta</italic>, <italic>D. pulex</italic>, <italic>N. vectensis</italic>, <italic>L. gigantea</italic>, <italic>M. brevicollis, P. blakesleeanus, P. sojae, P. tricornutum</italic>, <italic>P. patens </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B120">120</xref>], and the Broad Institute FGI database for <italic>P. graminis </italic>and <italic>B. dendrobatidis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B121">121</xref>]. Sequences that had more than 50% identity to the sequence of the closest template were chosen as orthologs or isologs. Assembled sequences, including newly defined, were annotated based on molecular taxonomy analysis of the domains characteristic in each regulator. Characteristic motifs of the regulatory subunits are predicted by the Pfam program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B122">122</xref>]. All amino acid sequences and the accession numbers of assembled and analyzed regulator orthologs are listed in Additional material (see Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S18">18</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Phylogenic analysis and synteny</title><p>Multiple sequence alignment and phylogenetic analyses were carried out with ClustalW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B123">123</xref>] and trees were reconstructed by the neighbor-joining method as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Amino acid sequences of regulatory subunits were trimmed and aligned to the domains indicated in each figure. Bootstrap values of 1,000 replications are shown at the branches as percentages. Equivalent to 0.1 amino acid substitutions per site indicate evolutionary distances as inferior bars. To elucidate the synteny, we used the Ensembl AlignSliceView program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B124">124</xref>]. Conserved marker genes among the genomes of vertebrates are defined (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>Nox, NADPH oxidase; Duox, dual oxidase; ROS, reactive oxygen species; TM, transmembrane; NOXO1, Nox Organizer 1; NOXA1, Nox Activator 1: TPR, the tetratricopeptide repeats; AD, activation domain; SH3, Src homology 3; PX, <italic>Phox </italic>homology domain; PRR, proline-rich region; P-basic, proline-basic region; PB1, <italic>Phox</italic>/Bem 1; OPCA motif, OPR/PC/AID motif; ADSIS, AD-SH3 Intervening Sequence; SH3PXD2, SH3 and PX domains 2; SRR, serine-rich region; RhoGEF, Rho guanine nucleotide exchange factor; CBS, cystathionine beta-synthase.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author(s) declares that there are no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>The majority of the work here described was carried out by TK. JDL critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content and data analysis. Both authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Amino acid sequences of Nox regulatory subunits of 12 dueterostomes, three fungi, and a slime mold amoeba; p47<italic>phox</italic>, NOXO1, p67<italic>phox</italic>, NOXA1, NOXR, p40<italic>phox</italic>, p22<italic>phox</italic></bold>. Amino acid sequences Nox and Duox proteins of <italic>H. sapiens</italic>, <italic>C. familliaris</italic>, <italic>R. norvegicus</italic>, <italic>M. musculus</italic>, <italic>G. gallus</italic>, <italic>X. tropicalis</italic>, <italic>D. rerio</italic>, <italic>T. rubripes</italic>, <italic>T. nigroviridis</italic>, <italic>O. latipes, C. intestinalis</italic>, <italic>S. purpuratus</italic>, <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>M. grisea</italic>, <italic>F. graminearum </italic>and <italic>D. discoideum </italic>are provided.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>Abbreviations of gene names in Figure </bold><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. Names of the marker genes used in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> are provided.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>Alignment of characterized domains of Nox regulatory subunits</bold>. Alignments of (i) PX and tandem SH3 domains of Nox organizers of deuterostomes, (ii) TPR and activation domains of Nox activators of deuterostomes and fungi (<italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>M. grisea</italic>, <italic>F. graminearum</italic>) and amoeba, (iii) the N-terminal SH3 domain of vertebrate p67<italic>phox</italic>, (iv) PB1 domain of p67<italic>phox </italic>and NOXA1 of vertebrates and NOXR of fungi (<italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>M. grisea</italic>, <italic>F. graminearum</italic>) and amoeba, (v) the C-terminal SH3 domain of vertebrate p67<italic>phox</italic>, vertebrate NOXA1 and <italic>S. purpuratus </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like protein, (vi) PX domain of vertebrate p40<italic>phox</italic>, (vii) Proline (P)-basic, SH3 and PB1 domain of vertebrate p40<italic>phox</italic>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S3.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p><bold>Alignment of full-length p22<italic>phox </italic>(vertebrate p22<italic>phox </italic>and <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>p22<italic>phox</italic>-like protein)</bold>. Alignments of p22<italic>phox </italic>of chordates.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S4.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional file 5</title><p><bold>Amino acid sequences of Nox/Duox proteins</bold>. Amino acid sequences Nox and Duox proteins of the waterflea <italic>D. pulex</italic>, the gastropod snail-limpet <italic>L. gigantea</italic>, the nematode <italic>C. briggsae</italic>, the sea anemone <italic>N. vectensis</italic>, the choanoflagellate <italic>M. brevicollis</italic>, the fungi (<italic>C. cinerea</italic>, <italic>L. bicolor</italic>, <italic>P. placenta</italic>, <italic>P. graminis</italic>, <italic>P. blackesleeanus</italic>, and <italic>B. dendrobatidis</italic>), the plant <italic>O. sativa</italic>, and the red alga <italic>C. merolae </italic>are provided.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S5.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6"><caption><title>Additional file 6</title><p><bold>Molecular taxonomy of Nox and Duox proteins containing newly identified sequences</bold>. molecular taxonomy built by amino acid sequences of Nox and Duox proteins of <italic>D. pulex</italic>, <italic>L. gigantea</italic>, C.<italic>briggsae</italic>, <italic>N. vectensis</italic>, <italic>M. brevicollis, C. intestinalis</italic>, <italic>S. purpuratus</italic>, and <italic>H. sapiens </italic>is shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S6.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7"><caption><title>Additional file 7</title><p><bold>Amino acid sequences of putative Nox regulatory subunits of <italic>L. gigantea</italic>, <italic>N. vectensis, M. brevicollis</italic></bold>. Amino acid sequences of putative regulatory subunit proteins of <italic>L. gigantea </italic>(p47<italic>phox-</italic>, p67<italic>phox-</italic>, p22<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins), <italic>N. vectensis </italic>(p47<italic>phox-</italic>, p22<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins), and <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>(p47<italic>phox-</italic>, p22<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins) are provided.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S7.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S8"><caption><title>Additional file 8</title><p><bold>Alignments of putative regulatory subunit proteins of <italic>L. gigantea</italic>(p47<italic>phox-</italic>, p67<italic>phox-</italic>, p22<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins), <italic>N. vectensis </italic>(p47<italic>phox-</italic>, p22<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins), and <italic>M. brevicollis </italic>(p47<italic>phox-</italic>, p22<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins)</bold>. Alignment of p67<italic>phox</italic>-like protein (<italic>L. gigantea </italic>and <italic>H. sapiens</italic>), p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein (<italic>L. gigantea, N. vectensis</italic>, <italic>M. brevicollis, S. purpuratus</italic>, and <italic>H. sapiens</italic>), p22<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins (<italic>L. gigantea, N. vectensis</italic>, <italic>M. brevicollis</italic>, and <italic>H. sapiens</italic>) are provided.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S8.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S9"><caption><title>Additional file 9</title><p><bold>Amino acid sequences of Fre of an amoeboflagellate</bold>. Amino acid sequences of predicted Fre proteins of the amoeboflagellate <italic>Naegleria gruberi </italic>are provided.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S9.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S10"><caption><title>Additional file 10</title><p><bold>Amino acid sequences of SH3PXD2 proteins</bold>. Amino acid sequences vertebrate and urochordate SH3 and PX domains 2 (SH3PXD2) proteins are provided. Alignments of PX and <italic>bis</italic>-SH3 domains of SH3PXD2, p47<italic>phox</italic>, NOXO1, p47<italic>phox</italic>-like proteins are shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S10.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S11"><caption><title>Additional file 11</title><p><bold>Alignment of vertebrate p47<italic>phox</italic>, vertebrate NOXO1, p47<italic>phox</italic>-like protein, and chordate SH3PXD2 proteins</bold>. Alignments of SH3PXD2a and 2b of <italic>H. sapiens</italic>, <italic>C. familliaris</italic>, <italic>R. norvegicus</italic>, <italic>M. musculus</italic>, <italic>G. gallus</italic>, <italic>X. tropicalis</italic>, <italic>D. rerio</italic>, <italic>T. rubripes</italic>, <italic>T. nigroviridis</italic>, <italic>O. latipes</italic>, and <italic>C. intestinalis </italic>with other p47<italic>phox </italic>family proteins are shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S11.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S12"><caption><title>Additional file 12</title><p><bold>Amino acid sequences and alignment of predicted fungal NOXR partner: Bem1, Cdc24, CBSn-PB1</bold>. Amino acid sequences Bem1, Cdc24, CBSn-PB1 of <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>M. grisea </italic>and <italic>F. graminearum </italic>are provided. Alignments of each gene family are shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S12.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S13"><caption><title>Additional file 13</title><p><bold>Amino acid sequences of NOXR, Bem1, Cdc24, and CBSn-PB1 proteins of other fungi than <italic>M. grisea</italic>, <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, and <italic>A. nidulans</italic></bold>. Amino acid sequences Bem1, Cdc24, and CBSn-PB1 proteins of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, <italic>C. albicans</italic>, <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic>, <italic>S. pombe</italic>, <italic>C. cinerea</italic>, <italic>L. bicolor</italic>, <italic>P. placenta</italic>, <italic>P. graminis</italic>, <italic>P. blakesleeanus</italic>, and <italic>B. dendrobatidis </italic>are provided.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S13.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S14"><caption><title>Additional file 14</title><p><bold>Alignments of fungal NOXR, Bem1, Cdc24, and CBSn-PB1 amino acid sequences</bold>. Alignments of fungal NOXR, Bem1, Cdc24, and CBSn-PB1 of <italic>A. nidulans</italic>, <italic>M. grisea, F. graminearum S. cerevisiae</italic>, <italic>C. albicans</italic>, <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic>, <italic>S. pombe</italic>, <italic>C. cinerea</italic>, <italic>L. bicolor</italic>, <italic>P. placenta</italic>, <italic>P. graminis</italic>, <italic>P. blakesleeanus</italic>, and <italic>B. dendrobatidis </italic>are provided.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S14.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S15"><caption><title>Additional file 15</title><p><bold>Amino acid sequences of PB1 domain-containing proteins of <italic>D. discoideum </italic>and alignment of PB1 domains</bold>. Amino acid sequences of PB1 domain-containing proteins of the slime mold amoeba <italic>D. discoideum </italic>(Dd-PB1-A to -E) and an alignment of the PB1 domians are provided.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S15.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S16"><caption><title>Additional file 16</title><p><bold>Amino acid sequences of hypothetical p67<italic>phox</italic>-like (hypo-p67-L) of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>and <italic>Oryzae sativa</italic></bold>. Sequences of <italic>A. thaliana </italic>and <italic>O. sativa </italic>proteins that contain the TPR and PB1 domains (At-hypo-p67-L1 to L4 and Or-hypo-p67-L1) are shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S16.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S17"><caption><title>Additional file 17</title><p><bold>Alignment of hypothetical p67<italic>phox</italic>-like (hypo-p67-L) of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana </italic>and <italic>Oryza sativa</italic></bold>. (i) Alignment of four hypo-p67-L1 to -L4 of <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, (ii) comparison of TPR and AD domain between the <italic>A. thaliana </italic>and <italic>O. sativa </italic>proteins (At-hypo-p67-L1-4 and Os-hypo-p67-L1) and human p67<italic>phox </italic>(1&#x02013;212 residues) and NOXA1 (1&#x02013;213 residues) proteins are shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S17.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S18"><caption><title>Additional file 18</title><p><bold>ID numbers of hypothetical PB1 domain-containing genes of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>,except for hypo-p67-L genes</bold>. a total of 27 ID numbers of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana </italic>genes are shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-7-178-S18.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We express our appreciation to Mrs. Heather Jackson for reading and commenting on the manuscript and to Dr. Yasushi Okamura for suggesting sea urchin genome research. We thank Drs. Seiji Takeda and Takehiko Ueyama for commenting about <italic>A. thaliana </italic>p67<italic>phox</italic>-like genes and a conserved lysine residue in AD of p67<italic>phox</italic>, respectively. We also thank anonymous reviewers for suggestive comments to improve content of the manuscript. We are grateful to Mrs. Asami Kawahara for great cooperation and patience during long nights and weekends of endless computational analysis at home. This work was supported by NIH grants CA105116 and GM067717.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular evolution of the reactive oxygen-generating NADPH oxidase (Nox/Duox) family of enzymes</article-title><source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lardy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOX family NADPH oxidases: Not just in mammals</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><year>2007</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>1112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17400358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biochi.2007.01.012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vignais</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The superoxide-generating NADPH oxidase; structural aspects and activation mechanism</article-title><source>Cellular and Molecular Life Sciences</source><year>2002</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1428</fpage><lpage>1459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12440767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-002-8520-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heyworth</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Curnutte</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic granulomatous disease</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Immunology</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14499268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0952-7915(03)00109-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nox enzymes, ROS, and chronic disease: an example of antagonistic pleiotropy</article-title><source>Free Radical Biology and Medicine</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17602948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2007.03.027</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nauseef</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assembly of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase</article-title><source>Histochemistry and Cell Biology</source><year>2004</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15293055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00418-004-0679-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geiszt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NADPH oxidases: new kids on the block</article-title><source>Cardiovascular Research</source><year>2006</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16765921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cardiores.2006.05.004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leto</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiszt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of Nox family NADPH oxidases in host defense</article-title><source>Antioxidants &#x00026; Redox Signaling</source><year>2006</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1549</fpage><lpage>1561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16987010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOX enzymes and the biology of reactive oxygen</article-title><source>Nature Review Immunology</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri1312</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular composition and regulation of the Nox family NAD(P)H oxidases</article-title><source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications</source><year>2005</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16157295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2005.08.210</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Diebold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of Nox and Duox enzymatic activity and expression</article-title><source>Free Radical Biology and Medicine</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17602947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2007.03.028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishibashi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanegasaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical and mutational analysis of chronic granulomatous disease in Japan with special reference to gp91-phox and p22-phox deficiency</article-title><source>Human Genetics</source><year>2000</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10914676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004390000288</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bionda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Bruggen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eppink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stasia</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of two-amino acid substitutions in gp91 phox in a patient with X-linked flavocytochrome b558-positive chronic granulomatous disease by means of transgenic PLB-985 cells</article-title><source>Human Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15338276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00439-004-1173-z</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Wientjes</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The major phosphorylation site of the NADPH oxidase component p67phox is Thr233</article-title><source>Biochemical Journal</source><year>1999</year><volume>338</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9931304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/0264-6021:3380099</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Regier</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sergeant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jesaitis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McPhail</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation of p22phox is mediated by phospholipase D-dependent and -independent mechanisms. Correlation of NADPH oxidase activity and p22phox phosphorylation</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>28406</fpage><lpage>28412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10893420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M004703200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouin</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandvaux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vignais</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p40(phox) is phosphorylated on threonine 154 and serine 315 during activation of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase. Implication of a protein kinase c-type kinase in the phosphorylation process</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>30097</fpage><lpage>30103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9804763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.46.30097</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knaus</surname><given-names>UG</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyworth</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Curnutte</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokoch</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of phagocyte oxygen radical production by the GTP-binding protein Rac 2</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1991</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>1512</fpage><lpage>1515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1660188</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diverse recognition of non-PxxP peptide ligands by the SH3 domains from p67(phox), Grb2 and Pex13p</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>4268</fpage><lpage>4276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/cdf428</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Benna</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Faust</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Babior</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The phosphorylation of the respiratory burst oxidase component p47phox during neutrophil activation</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>23431</fpage><lpage>23436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8089108</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ago</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism for phosphorylation-induced activation of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase protein p47(phox). Triple replacement of serines 303, 304, and 328 with aspartates disrupts the SH3 domain-mediated intramolecular interaction in p47(phox), thereby activating the oxidase</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>33644</fpage><lpage>33653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10559253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.47.33644</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groemping</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapouge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smerdon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rittinger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular basis of phosphorylation-induced activation of the NADPH oxidase</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12732142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00314-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rotrosen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leto</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation of neutrophil 47-kDa cytosolic oxidase factor. Translocation to membrane is associated with distinct phosphorylation events</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1990</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>19910</fpage><lpage>19915</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2246268</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ago</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuribayashi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PX domain as a novel phosphoinositide- binding module</article-title><source>Biochemical &#x00026; Biophysical Research Communications</source><year>2001</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11563857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2001.5629</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbary</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantley</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PX domains of p47phox and p40phox bind to lipid products of PI(3)K</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11433300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35083070</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karathanassis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahelin</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Perisic</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacold</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Binding of the PX domain of p47(phox) to phosphatidylinositol 3,4-bisphosphate and phosphatidic acid is masked by an intramolecular interaction</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>5057</fpage><lpage>5068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12356722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/cdf519</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ligeti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tardif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vignais</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of O2- generating oxidase of bovine neutrophils in a cell-free system. Interaction of a cytosolic factor with the plasma membrane and control by G nucleotides</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1989</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>7116</fpage><lpage>7123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2554964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00443a050</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Terasawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshige</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tetratricopeptide repeat (TPR) motifs of p67phox participate in interaction with the small GTPase Rac and activation of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>25051</fpage><lpage>25060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10455184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.35.25051</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lapouge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamblin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smerdon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rittinger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the TPR domain of p67phox in complex with Rac.GTP</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>907</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11090627</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarfstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorzalczany</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizrahi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Berdichevsky</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Molshanski-Mor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinbaum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirshberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagher</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual role of Rac in the assembly of NADPH oxidase, tethering to the membrane and activation of p67phox: a study based on mutagenesis of p67phox-Rac1 chimeras</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>16007</fpage><lpage>16016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14761978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M312394200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>JLR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Motalebi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of the neutrophil respiratory burst oxidase: Identification of an activation domain in p67<italic>phox</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>16663</fpage><lpage>16668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9642219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.27.16663</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nisimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Motalebi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The p67<italic>phox </italic>activation domain regulates electron transfer flow from NADPH to flavin in flavocytochrome <italic>b</italic><sub>558</sub></article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>22999</fpage><lpage>23005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10438466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.33.22999</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Perisic</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PB1 domain-mediated heterodimerization in NADPH oxidase and signaling complexes of atypical protein kinase C with Par6 and p62</article-title><source>Molecular Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12887891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1097-2765(03)00246-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuribayashi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakamatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsunawaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The adaptor protein p40(phox) as a positive regulator of the superoxide-producing phagocyte oxidase</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>6312</fpage><lpage>6320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12456638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/cdf642</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ago</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitajima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshige</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PC motif: a novel and evolutionarily conserved sequence involved in interaction between p40phox and p67phox, SH3 domain-containing cytosolic factors of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase</article-title><source>European Journal of Biochemistry</source><year>1998</year><volume>251</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9490029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1432-1327.1998.2510583.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neutrophils from p40phox-/- mice exhibit severe defects in NADPH oxidase regulation and oxidant-dependent bacterial killing</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><year>2006</year><volume>203</volume><fpage>1927</fpage><lpage>1937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16880254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20052069</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassegue</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorescu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Griendling</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell transformation by the superoxide-generating oxidase Mox1</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>401</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10485709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/43459</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The NOX family of ROS-generating NADPH oxidases: physiology and pathophysiology</article-title><source>Physiological Reviews</source><year>2007</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17237347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00044.2005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banfi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two novel proteins activate superoxide generation by the NADPH oxidase NOX1</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>3510</fpage><lpage>3513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12473664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C200613200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geiszt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lekstrom</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Witta</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leto</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteins Homologous to p47phox and p67phox Support Superoxide Production by NAD(P)H Oxidase 1 in Colon Epithelial Cells</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>20006</fpage><lpage>20012</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12657628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M301289200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Taura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohjima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Izaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel human homologues of p47phox and p67phox participate in activation of superoxide-producing NADPH oxidases</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>25234</fpage><lpage>25246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12716910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M212856200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOXO1, Regulation of Lipid Binding, Localization, and Activation of Nox1 by the Phox Homology (PX) Domain</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>4737</fpage><lpage>4742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14617635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M305968200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Geiszt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leto</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of Rac1 in activation of multicomponent Nox1- and Nox3-based NADPH oxidases</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>2160</fpage><lpage>2174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16507994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.26.6.2160-2174.2006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohjima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Teshima-Kondo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsunawaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokutan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Helicobacter pylori lipopolysaccharide activates Rac1 and transcription of NADPH oxidase Nox1 and its organizer NOXO1 in guinea pig gastric mucosal cells</article-title><source>American Journal of Physiology &#x02013; Cell Physiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>288</volume><fpage>C450</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15469954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpcell.00319.2004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Diebold</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nox1-dependent reactive oxygen generation is regulated by Rac1</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>17718</fpage><lpage>17726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16636067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M512751200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct involvement of the small GTPase Rac in activation of the superoxide-producing NADPH oxidase Nox1</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>21857</fpage><lpage>21868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16762923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M513665200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Teshima-Kondo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsunawaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokutan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate oxidase 1 in oxidative burst response to Toll-like receptor 5 signaling in large intestinal epithelial cells</article-title><source>The Journal of Immunology</source><year>2004</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>3051</fpage><lpage>3058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14978110</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction between the SH3 domains and C-terminal proline-rich region in NADPH oxidase organizer 1 (Noxo1)</article-title><source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications</source><year>2007</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>560</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17126813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2006.11.060</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banfi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Malgrange</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Knisz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois-Dauphin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOX3, a superoxide-generating NADPH oxidase of the inner ear</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>46065</fpage><lpage>46072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15326186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M403046200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritsick</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nox3 regulation by NOXO1, p47phox and p67phox</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2004</year></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Knisz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltrusaitis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigmund</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thalmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Verpy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Banfi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of NADPH oxidase organizer 1 results in severe imbalance</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16431374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2005.12.025</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The NADPH oxidase Nox3 constitutively produces superoxide in a p22phox-dependent manner: its regulation by oxidase organizers and activators</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>23328</fpage><lpage>23339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15824103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M414548200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambasta</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Griendling</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandes</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct interaction of the novel Nox proteins with p22phox is required for the formation of a functionally active NADPH oxidase</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>45935</fpage><lpage>45941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15322091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M406486200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritsick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Point mutations in the proline-rich region of p22phox are dominant inhibitors of Nox1- and Nox2-dependent reactive oxygen generation</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>31859</fpage><lpage>31869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15994299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M501882200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martyn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Frederick</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>von Loehneysen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinauer</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Knaus</surname><given-names>UG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of Nox4 reveals unique characteristics compared to other NADPH oxidases</article-title><source>Cellular Signalling</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15927447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cellsig.2005.03.023</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NADPH oxidases in fungi: Diverse roles of reactive oxygen species in fungal cellular differentiation</article-title><source>Fungal Genetics and Biology</source><year>2007</year></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lardy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bof</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Paclet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Satre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NADPH oxidase homologs are required for normal cell differentiation and morphogenesis in Dictyostelium discoideum</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source><year>2005</year><volume>1744</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15950752</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A p67Phox-like regulator is recruited to control hyphal branching in a fungal-grass mutualistic symbiosis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2807</fpage><lpage>2821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17041146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.046169</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stupka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Christoffels</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rash</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome shotgun assembly and analysis of the genome of Fugu rubripes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>1301</fpage><lpage>1310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12142439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1072104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Animal-Genome-Size-Database</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://http//www.genomesize.com"/></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaillon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Aury</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stange-Thomann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauceli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouneau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozouf-Costaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome duplication in the teleost fish Tetraodon nigroviridis reveals the early vertebrate proto-karyotype</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>431</volume><fpage>946</fpage><lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15496914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03025</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moroi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Satake</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Azumi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritomo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of NADPH oxidase genes (Nox2, p22, p47, and p67) and Nox4 gene expressed in blood cells of juvenile Ciona intestinalis</article-title><source>Immunogenetics</source><year>2005</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>520</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16025326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00251-005-0010-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Sea Urchin Genome Sequencing Consortium</collab><name><surname>Sodergren</surname><given-names>EWG</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Angerer</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Angerer</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnone</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elphick</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ettensohn</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Foltz</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamdoun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzluff</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>McClay</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mushegian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rast</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorndyke</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vacquier</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wessel</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsik</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ermolaeva</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hlavina</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Landrum</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maglott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Panopoulou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Poustka</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapojnikov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Souvorov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Solovyev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Worley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedrigo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Garfield</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Haygood</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Primus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Satija</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Severson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Garay</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Milosavljevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Killian</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilt</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Belle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonneau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cormier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Guerra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Geneviere</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelkar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulner-Lorillon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstone</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Epel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Howard-Ashby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scally</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stegeman</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Allgood</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cool</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Judkins</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>McCafferty</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Musante</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Obar</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawson</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossetti</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Leone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Istrail</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Materna</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Samanta</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolc</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tongprasit</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergeron</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandhorst</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berney</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottjer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Calestani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>QA</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhaik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Graur</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosdet</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Heesun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fugmann</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Loza-Coll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Majeske</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Messier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Pancer</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Terwilliger</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Agca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Arboleda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Churcher</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallbook</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Idris</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Olinski</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Raible</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessmar-Raible</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaasterland</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Galindo</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunaratne</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Juliano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinukawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moy</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Neill</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raisch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reade</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Townley</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Voronina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Amore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Branno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalieri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Duboc</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Duloquin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Flytzanis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gache</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapraz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Locascio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Matassi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Matranga</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Range</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rottinger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Beane</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomason</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wikramanayke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chacko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cree</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dugan-Rocha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hines</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hume</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolivet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Miner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazareth</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Okwuonu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genome of the sea urchin Strongylocentrotus purpuratus</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>314</volume><fpage>941</fpage><lpage>952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17095691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1133609</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>NCBI-Sea-Urchin-Genome-Database</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/seq/BlastGen/BlastGen.cgi?taxid=7668"/></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoegg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hox clusters as models for vertebrate genome evolution</article-title><source>Trends in Genetics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15967537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2005.06.004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Taura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression and function of Noxo1gamma, an alternative splicing form of the NADPH oxidase organizer 1</article-title><source>FEBS Journal</source><year>2006</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>3663</fpage><lpage>3677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16911517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2006.05371.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshige</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anionic amphiphile-independent activation of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase in a cell-free system by p47<sup><italic>phox </italic></sup>and p67<sup><italic>phox </italic></sup>both in C terminally truncated forms</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>4232</fpage><lpage>4236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9461621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.7.4232</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagasawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebisu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new role of Pro-73 of p47phox in the activation of neutrophil NADPH oxidase</article-title><source>Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics</source><year>2003</year><volume>416</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12859985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-9861(03)00296-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobuhisa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuzawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Torikai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR solution structure of the tandem Src homology 3 domains of p47phox complexed with a p22phox-derived proline-rich peptide</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>3660</fpage><lpage>3668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16326715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M505193200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ago</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuribayashi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation of p47phox directs phox homology domain from SH3 domain toward phosphoinositides, leading to phagocyte NADPH oxidase activation</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>4474</fpage><lpage>4479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12672956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0735712100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gout</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterfield</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An SH3 domain and proline-rich sequence mediate an interaction between two components of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase complex</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>13752</fpage><lpage>13755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8188650</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leusen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluiter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilarius</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoeven</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolscher</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between the cytosolic components p47phox and p67phox of the human neutrophil NADPH oxidase that are not required for activation in the cell-free system</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>11216</fpage><lpage>11221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7744754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.270.19.11216</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuribayashi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nobuhisa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshige</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A region C-terminal to the proline-rich core of p47phox regulates activation of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase by interacting with the C-terminal SH3 domain of p67phox</article-title><source>Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics</source><year>2005</year><volume>444</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16297854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2005.10.012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curwen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyras</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clamp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Ensembl automatic gene annotation system</article-title><source>Genome Research</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>942</fpage><lpage>950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15123590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.1858004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diebold</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokoch</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular basis for Rac2 regulation of phagocyte NADPH oxidase</article-title><source>Nature Immunology</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11224519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/85259</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>de Mendez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assembly of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase: binding of Src homology 3 domains to proline-rich targets</article-title><source>The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Online of the United State of America</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>10650</fpage><lpage>10654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.22.10650</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ago</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel modular domain PB1 recognizes PC motif to mediate functional protein-protein interactions</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>3938</fpage><lpage>3946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11483497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/20.15.3938</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gauss</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunger</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemsen</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson-Overton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Prigge</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular analysis of the bison phagocyte NADPH oxidase: cloning and sequencing of five NADPH oxidase cDNAs</article-title><source>Comparative Biochemistry &#x00026; Physiology Part B, Biochemistry &#x00026; Molecular Biology</source><year>2002</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1096-4959(02)00090-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gauss</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mascolo</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemsen</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunger</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and sequencing of rabbit leukocyte NADPH oxidase genes reveals a unique p67(phox) homolog</article-title><source>Journal of Leukocyte Biology</source><year>2002</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11818454</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Virbasius</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomerleau</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The p40phox and p47phox PX domains of NADPH oxidase target cell membranes via direct and indirect recruitment by phosphoinositides</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>4512</fpage><lpage>4518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11729195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109520200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B80"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stahelin</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Burian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruzik</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane binding mechanisms of the PX domains of NADPH oxidase p40phox and p47phox</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>14469</fpage><lpage>14479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12556460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M212579200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B81"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsujibe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Regulated Adaptor Function of p40phox: Distinct p67phox Membrane Targeting by p40phox and by p47phox</article-title><source>Molecular and Cellular Biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>454</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B82"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honbou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Minakami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuzawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamakura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Full-length p40phox structure suggests a basis for regulation mechanism of its membrane binding</article-title><source>EMBO Journal</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1176</fpage><lpage>1186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17290225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7601561</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B83"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Burritt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baniulis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Foubert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinauer</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkos</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jesaitis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-specific inhibitors of NADPH oxidase activity and structural probes of flavocytochrome b: characterization of six monoclonal antibodies to the p22phox subunit</article-title><source>The Journal of Immunology</source><year>2004</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>7349</fpage><lpage>7357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15585859</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B84"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varnai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thyagarajan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohacs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapidly inducible changes in phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate levels influence multiple regulatory functions of the lipid in intact living cells</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17088424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200607116</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B85"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Wandless</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PI(3,4,5)P3 and PI(4,5)P2 lipids target proteins with polybasic clusters to the plasma membrane</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>314</volume><fpage>1458</fpage><lpage>1461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17095657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1134389</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B86"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Eto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatsuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lennartz</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isoform-specific membrane targeting mechanism of Rac during Fc gamma R-mediated phagocytosis: positive charge-dependent and independent targeting mechanism of Rac to the phagosome</article-title><source>Journal of Immunology</source><year>2005</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>2381</fpage><lpage>2390</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B87"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>PROSITE-database</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ca.expasy.org/prosite/"/></citation></ref><ref id="B88"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Stull</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaffe</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinauer</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The phosphoinositide-binding protein p40phox activates the NADPH oxidase during FcgammaIIA receptor-induced phagocytosis</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source><year>2006</year><volume>203</volume><fpage>1915</fpage><lpage>1925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16880255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20052085</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B89"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suenaga</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshiura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritomo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ototake</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and sequencing of Japanese pufferfish (Takifugu rubripes) NADPH oxidase cDNAs</article-title><source>Developmental &#x00026; Comparative Immunology</source><year>2004</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>911</fpage><lpage>925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15183032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dci.2004.03.002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B90"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halanych</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The new view of animal phylogeny</article-title><source>Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics</source><year>2004</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.35.112202.130124</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B91"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specificity and versatility of SH3 and other proline-recognition domains: structural basis and implication for cellular signal transduction</article-title><source>Biochemical Journal</source><year>2005</year><volume>390</volume><fpage>641</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16134966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20050315</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B92"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmrich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalturin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Funayama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Agata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The innate immune repertoire in Cnidaria-ancestral complexity and stochastic gene loss</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>R59.51</fpage><lpage>R59.13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17437634</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B93"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James-Clark</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Note on the infusoria flagellata and the spongiae ciliatae</article-title><source>American Journal of Science</source><year>1866</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>114</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B94"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leadbeater</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of animals-choanoflagellates and sponges</article-title><source>Water and Atmosphere</source><year>2001</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B95"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snell</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Furlong</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>PWH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hsp70 sequences indicate that choanoflagellates are closely related to animals</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11448773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(01)00275-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B96"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A receptor tyrosine kinase from choanoflagellates: molecular insights into early animal evolution</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>15032</fpage><lpage>15037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.261477698</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B97"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hittinger</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of key cell signaling and adhesion protein family predates animal origins</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>301</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12869759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1083853</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B98"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The unicellular ancestry of animal development</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15363407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2004.08.010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B99"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lalucque</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Silar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NADPH oxidase: an enzyme for multicellularity</article-title><source>TRENDS in Microbiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12526848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0966-842X(02)00007-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B100"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalier-Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Only six Kingdoms of life</article-title><source>Proceedings Royal Society of London B</source><year>2004</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>1251</fpage><lpage>1262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2004.2705</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B101"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seals</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Azucena</surname><given-names>EF</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Pass</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesfay</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodrow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Resau</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtneidge</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The adaptor protein Tks5/Fish is required for podosome formation and function, and for the protease-driven invasion of cancer cells</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15710328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2005.01.006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B102"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malinin</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seubert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Griswold-Prenner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amyloid-beta neurotoxicity is mediated by FISH adapter protein and ADAM12 metalloprotease activity</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>3058</fpage><lpage>3063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15710903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0408237102</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B103"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>NCBI-BLAST</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://http//www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/"/></citation></ref><ref id="B104"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stahelin</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Karathanassis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural and Membrane Binding Analysis of the Phox Homology Domain of Bem1p: BASIS OF PHOSPHATIDYLINOSITOL 4-PHOSPHATE SPECIFICITY</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>25737</fpage><lpage>25747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17581820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M702861200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B105"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>France</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Novick</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The polarity-establishment component Bem1p interacts with the exocyst complex through the Sec15p subunit</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16478783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.02849</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B106"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ignoul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggermont</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CBS domains: structure, function, and pathology in human proteins</article-title><source>American Journal of Physiology &#x02013; Cell Physiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>C1369</fpage><lpage>1378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16275737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpcell.00282.2005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B107"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawley</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Anis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Scullion</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardie</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CBS domains form energy-sensing modules whose binding of adenosine ligands is disrupted by disease mutations</article-title><source>The Journal of Clinical Investigation</source><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14722619</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B108"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Firtel</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel, putative MEK kinase controls developmental timing and spatial patterning in Dictyostelium and is regulated by ubiquitin-mediated protein degradation</article-title><source>Genes and Development</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3564</fpage><lpage>3578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9832508</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B109"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohura</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Doke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calcium-dependent protein kinases regulate the production of reactive oxygen species by potato NADPH oxidase</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1065</fpage><lpage>1080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17400895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.048884</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B110"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jagnandan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Banfi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuehr</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrero</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel mechanism of activation of NADPH oxidase 5. calcium sensitization via phosphorylation</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>6469</fpage><lpage>6507</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B111"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serrander</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaquet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Plastre</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnaudeau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Demaurex</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlegel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOX5 is expressed at the plasma membrane and generates superoxide in response to protein kinase C activation</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><year>2007</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1159</fpage><lpage>1167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17587483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biochi.2007.05.004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B112"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carol</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of reactive oxygen species in cell growth: lessons from root hairs</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1829</fpage><lpage>1834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16720604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erj201</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B113"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Damude</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A plant homolog of the neutrophil NADPH oxidase gp91phox subunit gene encodes a plasma membrane protein with Ca2+ binding motifs</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9490748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.10.2.255</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B114"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groom</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fordham-Skelton</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>rbohA, a rice homologue of the mammalian gp91phox respiratory burst oxidase gene</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>1996</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8811865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1996.10030515.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B115"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>TIGR-Arabidopsis-thaliana-Protein-Database</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tigrblast.tigr.org/er-blast/index.cgi?project=ath1"/></citation></ref><ref id="B116"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamakura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and function of the PB1 domain, a protein interaction module conserved in animals, fungi, amoebas, and plants</article-title><source>Sci STKE</source><year>2007</year><volume>401</volume></citation></ref><ref id="B117"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>NCBI-HomoloGene</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?db=homologene"/></citation></ref><ref id="B118"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herve</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Collen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Corre</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NADPH oxidases in Eukaryotes: red algae provide new hints!</article-title><source>Current Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16344959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00294-005-0044-z</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B119"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>NCBI-Fungi-Genomes-BLAST-server</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sutils/genom_table.cgi?organism=fungi"/></citation></ref><ref id="B120"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>JGI-Genomes-Database</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.jgi-psf.org/euk_home.html"/></citation></ref><ref id="B121"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Broad-Institute-Genomes-database</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broad.mit.edu/cgi-bin/annotation/fgi/blast_page.cgi"/></citation></ref><ref id="B122"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Pfam-search</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/Pfam/"/></citation></ref><ref id="B123"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>ClustalW</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://http//www.ddbj.nig.ac.jp/search/clustalw-j.html"/></citation></ref><ref id="B124"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Ensembl-AlignSliceView-program</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org/Homo_sapiens/alignsliceview"/></citation></ref><ref id="B125"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origin and evolution of model organisms</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12415314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg929</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B126"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kage</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukumaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshige</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assembly and activation of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase: Specific Interaction of the N-terminal Src homology 3 domain of p47phox with p22phox is required for activation of the NADPH oxidase complex</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1996</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>22152</fpage><lpage>22158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8703027</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B127"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kage</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunoi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukumaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Minakami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshige</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of Src homology 3 domains in assembly and activation of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>5345</fpage><lpage>5349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8202490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.12.5345</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B128"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nobuhisa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of the superoxide-producing phagocyte NADPH oxidase requires co-operation between the tandem SH3 domains of p47phox in recognition of a polyproline type II helix and an adjacent alpha-helix of p22phox</article-title><source>Biochemical Journal</source><year>2006</year><volume>396</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16460309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20051899</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B129"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edens</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharling</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinkade</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Edens</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Benian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyrosine cross-linking of extracellullar matrix is catalyzed by Duox, a multidomain oxidase/peroxidase with homology to the phagocyte oxidase subunit gp91phox</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Biology</source><year>2001</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>879</fpage><lpage>891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11514595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200103132</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B130"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A direct role for dual oxidase in Drosophila gut immunity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>310</volume><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1117311</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B131"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ritsick</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Edens</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Finnerty</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambeth</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nox regulation of smooth muscle contraction</article-title><source>Free Radical Biology &#x00026; Medicine</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17561091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2007.03.006</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 