<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm917</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17981836</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Nucleic Acid Enzymes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ribonuclease P processes polycistronic tRNA transcripts in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> independent of ribonuclease E</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>Bijoy K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>Sidney R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Genetics, University of Georgia, Athens, GA 30602, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed.<phone>+1 706 542 8000</phone><fax>+1 706 542 3910;</fax>Email: <email>skushner@uga.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><!--For NAR: both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><month>12</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>35</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>7614</fpage><lpage>7625</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date></history><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/)">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/)</ext-link> which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license><abstract><p>The first step in the current model for the processing and maturation of mono- and polycistronic tRNA precursors in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> involves initial cleavages by RNase E 1&#x02013;3 nt downstream of each chromosomally encoded CCA determinant. Subsequently, each mature 5&#x02032; terminus is generated by single RNase P cleavage, while the 3&#x02032; terminus undergoes exonucleolytic processing by a combination of 3&#x02032; &#x02192; 5&#x02032; exonucleases. Here we describe for the first time a previously unidentified pathway for the maturation of tRNAs in polycistronic operons (<italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic>) where the processing of the primary transcripts is independent of RNase E. Rather, RNase P cleavages separate the individual tRNA precursors with the concomitant formation of their mature 5&#x02032; termini. Furthermore, both polynucleotide phosphorylase (PNPase) and RNase II are required for the removal of the 3&#x02032; Rho-dependent terminator sequences. Our data indicate that RNase P substrate recognition is more complex than previously envisioned.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Transfer RNAs (tRNAs) serve as adapter molecules for translating the genetic code into protein sequences. In <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, the 86 tRNA genes are frequently embedded in complex operons containing either other tRNAs, rRNAs (ribosomal RNAs) or mRNAs (messenger RNAs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). All the tRNA genes, including those that are monocistronic, are transcribed as precursors that undergo a series of processing steps at both their 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; termini to produce the mature species that are substrates for the respective tRNA synthetases.</p><p>Extensive studies on the enzymes associated with the maturation of the 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; termini of tRNAs in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2 B3 B4 B5">2&#x02013;5</xref>) have led to a consensus pathway by which it is believed that every tRNA precursor is matured (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Specifically, this model states that for both mono- and polycistronic precursors RNase E is required to generate pre-tRNAs that contain a limited number of extra nucleotides at their 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; termini (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6 B7 B8 B9">6&#x02013;9</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). However, the observation of considerable differences in the efficiency of RNase E cleavage among a large number of tRNA precursors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>) suggested that tRNA abundance was primarily controlled either by the differences in the cleavage specificity of RNase E for the primary transcripts and/or the existence of a processing pathway that was independent of RNase E. In fact, a recent study by Deana and Belasco (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) suggested the existence of an alternative processing mechanism for RNase E-dependent tRNAs in <italic>rne-1</italic> mutants that did not involve its homolog, RNase G. However, they did not realize at that time that there is a significant amount of residual RNase E activity present in an <italic>rne-1</italic> strain at the non-permissive temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). <fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>RNase E-dependent maturation of tRNA precursors. In operons such as <italic>glyW cysT leuZ</italic> and <italic>argX hisR leuT proM</italic>, RNase E initiates processing by cleaving 1&#x02013;2 nt downstream of the CCA determinant of each tRNA within the operon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) leading to the formation of immature tRNAs, which are further processed by RNase P to generate mature 5&#x02032; termini. The mature 3&#x02032; ends result primarily from the activity of RNase T, but RNase PH, RNase D, RNase BN and RNase II can substitute in the absence of RNase T (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm917f1"/></fig></p><p>The most promising candidate that could serve as an alternative processing enzyme is actually RNase P, a ribonucleoprotein that consists of a protein (C5) encoded by <italic>rnpA</italic> and an RNA (M1) subunit encoded by <italic>rnpB</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). The RNA component of the holoenzyme is responsible for the catalytic activity of the enzyme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>) and is found in all organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). In fact, experiments conducted using a temperature-sensitive RNase P allele [<italic>rnpA49</italic>, a mutation of arginine to histidine in the C5 protein subunit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>)] have suggested that the enzyme is required to mature the 5&#x02032; terminus of all tRNA precursors and plays a role in cleaving some polycistronic mRNAs and tRNA precursors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16 B17 B18 B19 B20 B21 B22">16&#x02013;22</xref>).</p><p>It has been suggested that the absence of RNase E inhibits RNase P activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6 B7 B8">6&#x02013;8</xref>), since RNase P has reduced activity when there are long 3&#x02032; precursor sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Thus it has been argued that in general RNase P generates the mature 5&#x02032; terminus only after an initial RNase E cleavage event (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Subsequently, the mature 3&#x02032; terminus is obtained through the combined action of RNase T, RNase BN, RNase D, RNase II and RNase PH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>).</p><p>In this communication, we demonstrate a previously uncharacterized pathway for the processing of the <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcripts into their component pre-tRNAs that only involves RNase P. Using various experimental approaches, we show that the primary transcripts of these operons are dramatically stabilized in an <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant with a concomitant decrease in the level of corresponding mature tRNAs. In contrast, no significant effect of RNase E was observed at any stage in the processing of these tRNAs. Furthermore, the predicted Rho-dependent terminators of both primary transcripts appeared to be primarily removed exonucleolytically by a combination of RNase II and PNPase.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Bacterial strains and plasmids</title><p>The <italic>E. coli</italic> strains used in this study were all derived from MG1693 (<italic>thyA715 rph-1</italic>) provided by the <italic>E. coli</italic> Genetic Stock Center, Yale University. The <italic>rne-1</italic> and <italic>rnpA49</italic> alleles encode temperature-sensitive RNase E and RNase P proteins, respectively, that are unable to support cell viability at 44&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). SK5665 (<italic>rne-1 thyA715 rph-1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>), SK2525 (<italic>rnpA49 thyA715 rph-1 rbsD296</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), SK2534 (<italic>rne-1 rnpA49 thyA715 rph-1 rbsD296</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), SK10019 (<italic>pnp</italic>&#x025b5;<italic>683</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>), CMA201 (&#x00394;<italic>rnb thyA715 rph-1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) and SK5726 (<italic>pnp-7 rnb-500 thyA715 rph-1</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>) have been previously described. A P1 lysate grown on SK2525 (<italic>rnpA49 rbsD296::</italic>Tn<italic>10</italic> was used to transduce both SK10019 (<italic>pnp</italic>&#x00394;<italic>683</italic>) and SK5726 (<italic>pnp-7 rnb-500</italic>) to construct SK10443 (<italic>rnpA49 thyA715 rph-1 rbsD296</italic>::Tn<italic>10 pnp</italic>&#x00394;<italic>683</italic>) and SK10451(<italic>rnpA49 thyA715 rph-1 rbsD296</italic>::Tn<italic>10 pnp-7 rnb-500</italic>), respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Growth of bacterial strains and isolation of total RNA</title><p>Bacterial strains were routinely grown with vigorous shaking in Luria broth supplemented with thymine (50 &#x003bc;g/ml) at 30&#x000b0;C until they reached a cell density of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup>/ml (40 Klett units above background, No. 42 green filter) after which the cultures were shifted to 44&#x000b0;C. For complete inactivation of the temperature-sensitive RNase E protein encoded by the <italic>rne-1</italic> allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), the cultures were maintained in exponential growth at 44&#x000b0;C for 2 h by periodic dilutions with fresh pre-warmed medium. When appropriate, tetracycline or streptomycin (20 &#x003bc;g/ml) were added to the medium. For half-life determinations, rifampicin (500 &#x003bc;g/ml, solubilized in dimethyl sulfoxide) and nalidixic acid (20 &#x003bc;g/ml) were added to the growing cultures at 50 Klett units and the first sample (0 min) was removed 75 s later. Total RNA was extracted as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). All RNA preparations were further treated with DNase I using the DNA-free kit&#x02122; (Ambion) to remove any residual DNA contamination. To ensure equal loading of all RNA samples during northern and primer extension analysis, each RNA sample was first quantified by measuring the OD<sub>260</sub>. Subsequently, the RNA samples (500 ng) were normalized by quantifying Vistra Green (Amersham Bioscience) stained 16S and 23S rRNAs in agarose mini-gels using a PhosphorImager (Amersham Bioscience, Storm 840).</p></sec><sec><title>Northern analysis</title><p>Total RNA was separated in 6% polyacrylamide gels containing 8 M urea in TBE [Tris&#x02013;Borate&#x02013;EDTA buffer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>)]. The RNA was transferred onto Magnacharge nylon membranes (GE Water &#x00026; Processing Technologies) by electroblotting in TAE (Tris&#x02013;Acetate&#x02013;EDTA) buffer and probed with appropriate <sup>32</sup>P-labeled oligonucleotides. Oligonucleotide probes were 5&#x02032; end-labeled with T4 polynucleotide kinase (NEB). In many cases, the same northern blot was probed successively with different oligonucleotides after stripping off the previous probe in boiling SDS (0.5%) solution. The prehybridization (4&#x02013;5 h) and the hybridization of oligonucleotide probes (overnight) to the membrane were carried out using a hybridizing solution (2 &#x000d7; SSC, 0.2% SDS and 0.25% non-fat dry milk, autoclaved) at a temperature that was below 10&#x000b0;C of the <italic>T</italic><sub>m</sub> of the corresponding oligonucleotide. Each membrane was washed three times (15 min each in 0.3% SDS and 2 &#x000d7; SSC) at room temperature. Band intensities were quantitated with a PhosphorImager. The half-lives of the <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> tRNA precursor transcripts in wild type and <italic>rne-1</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>A) were conservatively estimated to be &#x0003c;30 s, since we could not see any transcripts at 0 min, which represented a period of only 75 s after following the addition of rifampicin.</p></sec><sec><title>Primer extension</title><p>Primer extension analysis of the <italic>valV valW</italic> operon was carried out essentially as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>) with the following modifications. Sterile distilled water (80 &#x003bc;l) was added to each reverse transcription reaction mixture (20 &#x003bc;l) and the total volume extracted with 100 &#x003bc;l of phenol:chloroform (5 : 1, Ambion) solution. The reverse transcription products were precipitated at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C after the addition of 0.1 volume of sodium acetate (3 M, pH 5.2), 1 &#x003bc;l of GlycoBlue&#x02122; (Ambion) and 2.5 volume of ethanol (100%) to the aqueous supernatant. Each pellet was dissolved in 2.5 &#x003bc;l of the stop solution from the Promega <italic>fmol</italic>&#x000ae; DNA cycle sequencing kit. The nucleotide sequence was obtained from a PCR DNA product (amplified from wild-type genomic DNA using primers upstream and downstream of the <italic>valV valW</italic> operon) using the Promega <italic>fmol</italic> sequencing kit and the primer VALV-W (primer b, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A) that was also used for the reverse transcription. The sequences were analyzed on a 6% PAGE containing 8 M urea. <fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Analysis of the processing of <italic>valV valW</italic> operon. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of <italic>valV valW</italic> operon (not drawn to scale). Relative positions of the oligonucleotide probes (a: VALV-UP, b: VALV-W, c: VALW and d: VALW-TER) used in the northern analysis are shown below the diagram. (<bold>B</bold>) Northern analysis of <italic>valV valW</italic> operon. Total RNA (12 &#x003bc;g/lane) was separated on 6% PAGE, transferred to nylon membrane and probed multiple times as described in the Materials and Methods section. The autoradiograms shown were from the same blot successively probed with c, b and a. The genotypes of the strains used were noted against each lane. The RNA molecular weight (nts) size standards (Invitrogen) and the graphical structures of the <italic>valV valW</italic> processing intermediates are shown to the left. The names for the processing intermediates of <italic>valV valW</italic> transcripts are shown to the right. Relative quantity (RQ) of mature tRNA<sup>Val</sup> in various genetic backgrounds was calculated by setting the wild-type level at 1. Processed fraction (PF) denotes the fraction of a given mature tRNA relative to the total amount of that tRNA (processed and unprocessed) in the specific genetic background. RQ and PF were obtained from the average of two independent experiments. The bands marked with asterisks (*) on the c probed blot were due to weak hybridization to <italic>val</italic> operons independent of <italic>valV valW</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm917f2"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Oligonucleotide probes and primers</title><p>The sequences of all the oligonucleotides used in the experiments reported here are available on request.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Endonucleolytic processing of the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript does not require RNase E</title><p>Although it has been shown by bioinformatics and biochemical analysis that RNase E is involved in the maturation of a large number of <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), the fact that the enzyme appeared to process some tRNAs more efficiently than others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>) suggested the possibility of an alternative maturation pathway that did not involve RNase E. Furthermore, we noted that the intergenic region of the <italic>valV</italic> operon (containing <italic>valV</italic> and <italic>valW</italic>, which encodes tRNA<sup>Val/GAC</sup>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A) was only 4 nt in length (UCCU, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) and did not contain an obvious A/U-rich RNase E cleavage site. In addition, unlike the transcripts of other operons that have been shown to be dependent on RNase E for their maturation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript appeared to be terminated in a Rho-dependent fashion, since the downstream sequences do not contain any predicted secondary structures and the downstream gene (<italic>ydhR</italic>) is not cotranscribed with <italic>valV valW</italic> (data not shown). Accordingly, we analyzed the maturation of <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript using northern blot analysis with steady-state RNA isolated from a series of strains (wild-type, <italic>rne-1</italic>, <italic>rnpA49</italic> and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic>) that had been shifted to 44&#x000b0;C for 120 min to inactivate the temperature-sensitive RNase E and RNase P proteins. <table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Comparison of nucleotide sequences downstream of CCA determinants in various tRNA genes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tRNA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Known RNase E cleavage site</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tyrT</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CCA</underline>U&#x02193;AAUUC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>lysY</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CCA</underline>G&#x02193;UUUUA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hisR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CCA</underline>UU&#x02193;AUUA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cysT</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CCA</underline>CU&#x02193;UUCU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>leuQ</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CCA</underline>AACGAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>leuP</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CCA</underline>AAAACC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>leuV</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CCA</underline>AUUAUC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>valV</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CCA</underline>UCCU<bold>GC</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ValW</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>CCA</underline>GAUUUU</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p><sup>a</sup>This species is at the end of an operon. Sequences are part of the mature downstream tRNA. After <italic>leuV</italic> and <italic>valW</italic> there are unstructured Rho-dependent terminators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="TF2"><p><sup>b</sup>Bold letters represent the 5&#x02032; mature terminus of <italic>valW</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Since the coding sequences of <italic>valV</italic> and <italic>valW</italic> are nearly identical, but are considerably different from the remaining five tRNA<sup>Val</sup> genes (<italic>valU</italic>, <italic>valX</italic>, <italic>valY</italic>, <italic>valT</italic> and <italic>valZ</italic>), we initially probed the blot with an oligonucleotide complementary to both <italic>valV</italic> and <italic>valW</italic> (probe c, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, only the mature tRNA<sup>Val</sup> species was visible in the wild-type control and <italic>rne-1</italic> mutant (lanes 1&#x02013;2). In striking contrast, the most prominent species in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> strain were two high molecular weight intermediates (VW1 and VW2) that appeared to contain both <italic>valV</italic> and <italic>valW</italic> based on their size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lane 3). Interestingly, the level of VW1 increased &#x0223c;3-fold and the VW2 transcript completely disappeared in the <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lane 4). Importantly, both the relative quantity (RQ) as well as the processed fraction (PF) of the two tRNA<sup>Val</sup> species encoded by <italic>valV</italic> and <italic>valW</italic> did not change significantly in the <italic>rne-1</italic> mutant compared to the wild-type control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 1&#x02013;2). In contrast, both the RQ and PF of tRNA<sup>Val</sup> decreased between 5- and 10-fold in <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant relative to the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 3&#x02013;4).</p><p>We hypothesized that the additional low intensity bands present in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 3&#x02013;4, *) arose from weak hybridization of probe c to a tRNA<sup>Val</sup> coding sequence derived from a different operon. In order to confirm this and to determine the composition of the VW1 and VW2 transcripts more precisely, the blot was probed with the oligonucleotide b (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A), which was complementary to the intergenic region between <italic>valV</italic> and <italic>valW</italic> but would not hybridize to either the <italic>valV</italic> or <italic>valW</italic> mature tRNAS. In agreement with the results obtained with probe c, no transcripts were detected in either the wild-type or <italic>rne-1</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 5&#x02013;6). However, the two processing intermediates (VW1 and VW2) seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B (lanes 3&#x02013;4) also accumulated in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 7&#x02013;8). Furthermore, the transcript VW2 was missing and the level of the VW1 intermediate increased &#x0223c;3-fold in the <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> double mutant compared to the <italic>rnpA49</italic> single mutant, similar to what was observed with probe c. Significantly, the other species (*) observed with probe c, were not detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 7 and 8).</p><p>To assess the composition of the 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; termini of VW1 and VW2, additional probing was carried out with oligonucleotides a and d (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). While probe a hybridized to VW1 only, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 9&#x02013;12), probe d failed to detect either of the processing intermediates (data not shown). This indicated that VW1 retained the complete 5&#x02032; leader sequence but was missing the 3&#x02032; downstream sequences associated with the Rho-dependent transcription terminator. In contrast, VW2 missed both the 3&#x02032; downstream sequences as well some portion of the 5&#x02032; leader region.</p></sec><sec><title>RNase E cleaves inefficiently in the non-A/U-rich 5&#x02032; leader of the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript in an <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant</title><p>The data described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B indicated that the VW2 intermediate seen in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 3 and 7) arose from RNase E cleavage(s) in the 5&#x02032; leader region of VW1, since this species was missing in the <italic>rnpA49 rne-1</italic> double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 4 and 8). Accordingly, the 5&#x02032; termini of the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcripts were determined in wild-type, <italic>rnpA49</italic> and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> strains using primer extension analysis. Two primer extension products (I and II) terminating at positions 18 (C) and 19 (C) nt, respectively, upstream of the 5&#x02032; mature end of tRNA<sup>Val</sup> were detected in the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). Since no other larger products were observed, I and II represented two distinct transcription initiation sites for the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript. This conclusion was supported by the presence of upstream consensus &#x02212;10 (4/6) and &#x02212;35 (5/6) sequences associated with a &#x003c3;<sup>70</sup> promoter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). <fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Primer extension analysis to determine the 5&#x02032; ends of <italic>valV valW</italic> transcripts. (<bold>A</bold>) Autoradiograph of the primer extension analysis. The reverse transcription products of total RNA (10 &#x003bc;g/lane) isolated from wild-type (MG1693), <italic>rnpA49</italic> (SK2525) and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> (SK2534) strains using the primer b (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>A) were separated on a 6% PAGE as described in the Materials and Methods section. The CTAG sequencing reactions were carried out using the same primer and a PCR DNA fragment containing <italic>valV valW</italic> operon as template. The two transcription initiation sites (I and II) and three RNase E endonucleolytic cleavage sites (III, IV and V) are indicated. Part of the nucleotide sequences showing the primer termination sites (boxed nucleotides) sites are also shown. (<bold>B</bold>) The nucleotide sequences of the promoter regions of <italic>valV valW</italic> operon showing the determined transcription start (bent arrows) and endonucleolytic processing (arrows) sites. Lower case g is the 5&#x02032; mature end of <italic>valV</italic> tRNA. The putative &#x02212;10 and &#x02212;35 sequences (underlined) are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm917f3"/></fig></p><p>Consistent with the northern analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B), the level of primer extension products (I and II) increased dramatically in both the <italic>rnpA49</italic> single and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> double mutants compared to the wild-type control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). In addition, three additional major primer extension products (III-V) located 10, 8 and 6 nt upstream of the 5&#x02032; mature end of tRNA<sup>Val</sup> were reproducibly detected in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). Bands IV and V were absent and the intensity of band III was reduced in both the wild-type and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A), suggesting that they were generated only in the absence of RNase P by inefficient RNase E cleavages within a non-A/U-rich region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B).</p></sec><sec><title>Inactivation of RNase P dramatically stabilizes the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript</title><p>It has been noted previously that the half-lives of most <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA precursors are so short that it is not possible to accurately measure them in wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). In agreement with these results, we could not determine a half-life for the processing intermediates VW1 and VW2 in either wild type or <italic>rne-1</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). However, in both the <italic>rnpA49</italic> and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> strains, the VW1 transcript had a half-life of &#x0003e;32 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B). Interestingly, there was a slow accumulation of the VW2 species in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> strain that was significantly reduced in the <italic>rnpA49 rne-1</italic> double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B). <fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Decay of the processing intermediates of <italic>valV valW</italic> operon. (<bold>A</bold>) Autoradiogram of northern analysis showing the decay of <italic>valV valW</italic> transcripts (VW1 and VW2) in the wild type (MG1693), <italic>rne-1</italic> (SK5665), <italic>rnpA49</italic> (SK2525) and rne<italic>-1 rnpA49</italic> (SK2534) mutants. Total RNA (1 &#x003bc;g/lane) from different strains was isolated at times (minutes after rifampicin addition) indicated at the top of the blot and was separated on 6% PAGE, transferred to nylon membrane and probed with probe b (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A) as described in the Materials and Methods section. Two northern blots (one for wild type and <italic>rne-1</italic> and another for <italic>rnpA49</italic> and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> strains) were run independently. (<bold>B</bold>) A graphical presentation of the amounts of VW1 (open square: <italic>rnpA49</italic>, open circle: <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic>) and VW2 (open diamond: <italic>rnpA49</italic>) in various genetic backgrounds. The intensity of the bands in (A) was quantified with a Storm 840 PhosphorImager (Amersham Bioscience) and the values (log of the percentage of transcript present compared to the 0 min time point) were plotted as a function of time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm917f4"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>RNase P is essential for the endonucleolytic processing of the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> primary transcript</title><p>In determining if transcripts from additional polycistronic tRNA operons might be endonucleolytically matured exclusively by RNase P, we noted from previous studies that several high molecular weight species containing leucine tRNAs accumulated at the non-permissive temperature in an <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Of the six leucine tRNAs, the operons containing <italic>leuT</italic> and <italic>leuZ</italic> have been shown to be dependent on RNase E for initial processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). However, when we visually inspected the sequence of the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> operon that encodes three tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup> in tandem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A), we noticed that there were no U residues immediately downstream of either the mature <italic>leuQ</italic> (<underline>CCA</underline>AAAACC) or <italic>leuP</italic> (<underline>CCA</underline>AACGAG) encoded tRNAs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). This observation was of particular interest, since all the currently mapped RNase E cleavage sites in tRNA precursors occur within A/U-rich sequences immediately downstream of the CCA determinants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). <fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Analysis of the processing of tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup>. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic presentation of the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> (A) and <italic>argX hisR leuT proM</italic> (B) operons (not drawn to scale). The leucine tRNA genes are shaded the same to reflect their identical nucleotide sequences. Relative positions of the oligonucleotide probes (a: LEUQ-UP, b: LEUQ, c: LEUQ-P, d: LEUP-V and e: LEUV-TER) used in the northern analysis are shown below the diagram. (<bold>B</bold>) Northern analysis of <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> operon. Total RNA (1 &#x003bc;g/lane) was separated on 6% PAGE, transferred to nylon membrane and probed as described in the Materials and Methods section. The autoradiograms shown were from the same blot probed sequentially with a, c and b. The genotypes of the strains used are noted against each lane. The RNA molecular weight (nts) size standards (Invitrogen) are shown to the left. The structures and the names for the processing intermediates of <italic>leuQPV</italic> transcript are shown. The bands labeled as XRTM, RTM, RT and pT on the b probed blot were identified using <italic>argX</italic> operon (<italic>argX hisR leuT proM</italic>) specific probes (data not shown) which represented additional processing intermediates of <italic>argX</italic> operon and were identical to the previous report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). Species RT and QP have very similar molecular weights. XRTM: <italic>argX hisR leuT proM</italic>, RTM: <italic>hisR leuT proM</italic>, RT: <italic>hisR leuT</italic> and pT: pre-<italic>leuT</italic>. RQ and PF are described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm917f5"/></fig></p><p>Since there are four loci for tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup> and one of them (<italic>leuT</italic>) is part of a different polycistronic tRNA operon (<italic>argX hisR leuT proM</italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B), we initially analyzed a northern blot using intergenic probes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A) to specifically identify the composition of the processing intermediates derived from the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcript. No transcripts were detected in either the wild-type or <italic>rne-1</italic> strains using probes a, c, d and e (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A and C, lanes 1&#x02013;2, 5&#x02013;6 and data not shown).</p><p>However, probes a, c and d hybridized to one or more high molecular weight intermediates in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lanes 3 and 7, data not shown), while probe e failed to detect any transcripts in all four genetic backgrounds tested (data not shown). Thus the largest species, labeled QPV in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C contained the intact 5&#x02032; leader region as well as the coding sequences of <italic>leuQ</italic>, <italic>leuP</italic> and <italic>leuV</italic> but not the 3&#x02032; downstream sequences. Likewise, the transcript labeled QP was missing the last tRNA (<italic>leuV</italic>) based on its hybridization to probes a&#x02013;c but not d (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lanes 3 and 7 and data not shown). Similarly, the transcripts labeled pQ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lane 3) missed the last two tRNAs (<italic>leuP</italic> and leuV), since they did not hybridize to probe c (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lane 7). Finally, the hybridization of probe a to all four bands (QPV, QP and pQ) suggested that all the intermediates retained the 5&#x02032; unprocessed sequence of the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> operon.</p><p>To determine the origin of QP and pQ bands, we also examined steady-state RNA isolated from an <italic>rnpA49 rne-1</italic> double mutant. While the amounts of the QPV transcript were comparable in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> and <italic>rnpA49 rne-1</italic> strains, the levels of the QP and pQ intermediates were reduced 2-fold in the double mutant compared to the <italic>rnpA49</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lanes 4 and 8). Quantitatively, the amount of the QP and pQ bands represented 27 &#x000b1; 3% of the total hybridization in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> strain compared to only 18 &#x000b1; 2% in the <italic>rnpA49 rne-1</italic> double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lanes 3, 4, 7 and 8), indicating the occurrence of inefficient RNase E cleavages in the intergenic regions of the QPV transcript in the absence of RNase P.</p><p>As mentioned above, there are four genes (<italic>leuQ</italic>, <italic>leuP</italic>, <italic>leuV</italic> and <italic>leuT</italic>) that encode tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup>. Since <italic>leuT</italic> is part of the <italic>argX hisR leuT proM</italic> operon that is dependent on RNase E for its processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), probe b (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A and B) offered the opportunity to both establish the importance of RNase P in the production of mature tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup> as well as providing an internal control to distinguish between RNase E- and RNase P-dependent processing.</p><p>As expected, probe b hybridized to mature tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup> in all four strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lanes 9&#x02013;12). In fact, several processing intermediates associated with the <italic>argX</italic> operon accumulated in the <italic>rne-1</italic> strain but were completely absent in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lane 10, XRTM, RTM and RT) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). On the other hand, the processing intermediates QPV, and pQ, which are part of the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> operon only accumulated in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lane 11) as was also observed in lanes 3 and 7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C). It should be noted that band RT (containing <italic>hisR leuT</italic>) from the <italic>argX</italic> operon and band QP (containing <italic>leuQ leuP</italic>) from the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> operon have identical molecular weights resulting in their overlap in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lanes 10&#x02013;11). Band RT was specifically identified by probing with a <italic>hisR</italic>-specific oligo (data not shown). The new smaller species in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> single mutant (pT, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B, lane 11) were tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup> precursors that were 10&#x02013;15 nt longer than the mature species, which were likely generated by RNase E cleavages upstream and downstream of <italic>leuT</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). This interpretation was supported by the fact that the intermediates XRTM, RTM and TM disappeared in the <italic>rnpA49 rne-1</italic> double mutant along with a concomitant increase in the full-length <italic>argX</italic> operon transcript (XRTM, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B, lane 12).</p><p>Not surprisingly, the PF (processed fraction) of tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup> only decreased to 0.53 in the <italic>rne-1</italic> strain, but dropped more than 5-fold in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lanes 11&#x02013;12) compared to the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lane 9). Similarly, the relative quantity (RQ) of the mature tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup> only decreased marginally in the <italic>rne-1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lane 10), but dropped dramatically in both <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C, lanes 11&#x02013;12). These results were consistent with the fact that three-fourth of the tRNA<sup>Leu1</sup> species were dependent on RNase P for maturation.</p><p>Since the half-life of the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript increased dramatically following inactivation of RNase P (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>), we performed a similar experiment to determine the half-life of the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcript. In this experiment, we used probe a (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A), since it hybridized to all the processing intermediates that were also detected by probes c and d (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A and C). As expected, no <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcript was detected in both the wild type and <italic>rne-1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A). In contrast, all the processing intermediates that were observed under steady-state conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C) were stabilized in both the <italic>rnpA49</italic> and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A and C). Interestingly, the QPV processing intermediate had a half-life of longer than 32 min in both strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A and C). In contrast, the levels of QP and pQ intermediates actually increased as a function of time in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A and C). In the <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> double mutant, the level of the QP intermediate was unaltered while pQ appeared to decay very slowly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). Furthermore, new decay intermediates (*) that were even smaller than the mature tRNA species accumulated over time in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A), but were absent in the <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> double mutant. <fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Decay of the processing intermediates of <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> operon. (<bold>A</bold>) Autoradiogram of northern analysis showing the decay of <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcripts (QPV, QP and pQ) in the wild type (MG1693), <italic>rne-1</italic> (SK5665), <italic>rnpA49</italic> (SK2525) and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> (SK2534) mutants. Total RNA (1 &#x003bc;g/lane) from different strains was isolated at times (minutes after rifampicin addition) indicated at the top of the blot and was separated on 6% PAGE, transferred to nylon membrane and probed with probe a (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). The RNA molecular weight (nts) size standards (Invitrogen) are shown to the left. Asterisk (*) indicates the break-down products in <italic>rnpA49</italic> mutant not present in <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> double mutant. Two northern blots (one for wild type and <italic>rne-1</italic> and another for <italic>rnpA49</italic> and <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic> strains) were run independently. (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold>) A graphical presentation of the amounts of QPV (open square: <italic>rnpA49</italic>,open triangle: <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic>), QP (inverted triangle: <italic>rnpA49</italic>, open diamond: <italic>rne-1 rnpA49</italic>) and pQ (open circle: <italic>rnpA49</italic>, +: <italic>rne1 rnpA49</italic>) in various genetic backgrounds. The band intensities in (A) were quantified with a PhosphorImager and the values (log of the percentage of transcript present compared to the 0 min time point) were plotted as a function of time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm917f6"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>PNPase and RNase II are involved in the removal of the terminator regions from the <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> precursor transcripts</title><p>Many tRNA transcripts are terminated in a Rho-independent fashion, which leads to the formation of a stem-loop structure with a very short single-stranded region at the 3&#x02032; terminus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Since the two major 3&#x02032; &#x02192; 5&#x02032; exonucleases in <italic>E. coli</italic> (PNPase and RNase II) are both inhibited by secondary structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>), this type of terminator sequence is generally thought to be removed endonucleolytically (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). However, both the <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> operons appear to be terminated in a Rho-dependent fashion since the downstream sequences do not contain any recognizable Rho-independent transcription terminator structures (data not shown). We hypothesized that this region would be susceptible to exonucleolytic degradation, explaining why we did not observe any hybridization with a probe specific for the sequences immediately downstream of the <italic>valW</italic> and <italic>leuV</italic> encoded CCA determinants in the experiments described above (probe d, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A; probe e, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A and data not shown).</p><p>Accordingly, we analyzed a northern blot of steady-state RNA isolated from strains that were deficient in PNPase, RNase II or a combination of PNPase, RNase II and RNase P using probes a, b and d for the <italic>valV valW</italic> operon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B, inactivation of PNPase (lanes 4 and 9), both PNPase and RNase P (lanes 3 and 8) or RNase II alone (CMA201/&#x00394;<italic>rnb</italic>, data not shown) was not sufficient to detect the downstream sequences. In contrast, the loss of both PNPase and RNase II resulted in the detection of a precursor (VWT) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B, lanes 1 and 6) that was approximately 35 nt larger than the VW1 species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B, lanes 2 and 3). Inactivation of RNase P along with PNPase and RNase II increased the level (2.5 &#x000b1; 0.1) of VWT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B, lanes 2 and 7). Surprisingly, probe a (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>A) did not hybridize to the VWT transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B, lanes 11&#x02013;12) suggesting that it was processed at the 5&#x02032; end by RNase E in a fashion similar to what occurred to generate the VW2 transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In addition, the ratio of VW1 to VW2 was significantly increased in strains that were deficient in both RNase P and one or more exonucleases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B, lanes 2&#x02013;3) compared to what was observed in the RNase P single mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, lanes 3 and 7). <fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Northern analysis of the <italic>valV valW</italic> operon in exonuclease deficient strains. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic represention of <italic>valV valW</italic> operon as described in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Autoradiograms of northern analysis. Total RNA (12 &#x003bc;g/lane) was separated on a 6% PAGE/8 M Urea gel, transferred to a nylon membrane and probed as described in the Materials and Methods section. The figure was composed from the same blot that was hybridized sequentially with probes b, d and a (A). The labeling efficiency of probe a was significantly lower than probe b (data not shown), resulting in detection of less VW1 by probe a. The genotypes of the strains used are listed above each lane. The names of each <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript (as explained in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B and the text) are indicated to the left and the corresponding graphical structures are indicated to the right.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm917f7"/></fig></p><p>Since the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcript has also been presumed to be terminated through a Rho-dependent mechanism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), we tested to determine if its downstream sequences were also removed by a combination of RNase II and PNPase. In fact, a high molecular weight species that was &#x0223c;40 nt longer than the QPV transcript (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>C) was observed in strains that were deficient in either both exonucleases (PNPase and RNase II, SK5726) or both exonucleases and RNase P (SK10451) (data not shown).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The data presented here demonstrate for the first time the existence of a tRNA maturation pathway in <italic>E. coli</italic> that does not require RNase E. Specifically, for tRNA transcripts such as <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> only the endonucleolytic activity of RNase P is necessary to generate pre-tRNAs whose 5&#x02032; termini are already mature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). The 3&#x02032; ends are subsequently processed exonucleolytically to produce functional tRNAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). Strong experimental support for this RNase E-independent maturation pathway is derived from the dramatic stabilization of polycistronic transcripts containing all the tRNAs in the absence of RNase P, but which are matured normally in the absence of RNase E (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Furthermore, while the half-lives of the <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcripts were greater than 32 min in an <italic>rnpA49</italic> single mutant, they were estimated to be less than 30 s (see Materials and Methods section) in both wild-type and <italic>rne-1</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), showing that this pathway is very efficient. <fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Model for RNase P-dependent maturation of <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA precursors. RNase P-dependent pathway. In wild-type cells, RNase P cleaves at the 5&#x02032; mature termini of both <italic>valV</italic> and <italic>valW</italic>. The removal of the Rho-dependent transcription terminator sequences is dependent on PNPase, RNase II and possibly other ribonucleases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). The extra nucleotides at the 3&#x02032; ends of both pre-tRNAs are removed by a combination of RNase T, RNase D, RNase PH, RNase BN and RNase II as suggested by the experiments of Li and Deutscher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). Alternatively, it is possible that the action of PNPase and RNase II in removal of the Rho-dependent terminator sequences is sufficient to generate the mature 3&#x02032; terminus for <italic>valW</italic>. In the absence of RNase P, the 5&#x02032; end is cleaved inefficiently by RNase E (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>), leading to the accumulation of a <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript with an unprocessed 5&#x02032; terminus (VW1, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B) and a slightly shorter transcript (VW2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B) generated by the RNase E cleavage. In the absence of both RNase P and RNase E only the VW1 transcript is observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). In the absence of RNase E alone, processing of this transcript occurs normally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm917f8"/></fig></p><p>Interestingly, it appears that the Rho-dependent transcription terminators associated with these operon transcripts are rapidly removed by a combination of PNPase and RNase II activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>, data not shown), since the polycistronic transcripts that accumulated in the <italic>rnpA49</italic> and <italic>rnpA49 rne-1</italic> mutants no longer contained these sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). However, even in a <italic>rnpA49 pnp-7 rnb-500</italic> strain (SK10451) most of the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcripts no longer contained the terminator sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>, lane 2). This observation may not be surprising since <italic>E. coli</italic> contains at least eight exoribonucleases that have considerable overlap in their functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>).</p><p>However, all of our strains were defective in RNase PH (<italic>rph-1</italic>) and the levels of the transcript containing the terminator (VWT, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>) in <italic>pnp rnb</italic> and <italic>pnp rnb rnr</italic> (RNase R) strains were identical (data not shown). Furthermore, it does not seem likely that RNase T, RNase D and RNase BN, all of which have limited substrate specificity, could account for this processing. In addition, the endonucleolytic removal of the terminator sequences by RNase E, in a fashion similar to what has been observed with Rho-independent transcription terminators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), was ruled out by the fact that an <italic>rne-1 rnpA49 pnp-7 rnb-500</italic> strain had identical levels of the VWT transcript as observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>, lane 2 (data not shown). Thus, we believe that there may be sufficient residual RNase II and/or PNPase activity in the <italic>pnp-7 rnb-500</italic> strains at the non-permissive temperature to account for the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>. In fact, we have previously shown that there is a significant level of residual PNPase activity in a <italic>pnp-7</italic> strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>).</p><p>Although 3&#x02032; &#x02192; 5&#x02032; exonucleolytic processing of the Rho-dependent terminator associated with the <italic>trp</italic> operon transcript has been predicted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>), this is the first direct demonstration of the involvement of both PNPase and RNase II in the removal of Rho-dependent transcription terminator sequences from the transcripts of tRNA operons, unlike the prediction of the Li and Deutscher model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), which invokes a cleavage by RNase E to remove these sequences. This, in fact, may be the mechanism by which the downstream sequences of all 13 tRNA transcripts terminated in a Rho-dependent fashion are removed. Clearly, the involvement of PNPase and RNase II provides a distinctly different approach for terminator removal than what has been observed for tRNA transcripts terminated in a Rho-independent fashion [(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>), Mohanty,B.K. and Kushner,S.R., unpublished data].</p><p>Since the data described above has demonstrated that there is more than one tRNA processing pathway in <italic>E. coli</italic>, the generally accepted model for tRNA processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) most likely only correctly describes the maturation of a subset of tRNA operons such as <italic>argX</italic> [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>)]. In fact, the RNase E cleavages that were observed here (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) only arose in the absence of RNase P, were not very efficient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>A), and occurred primarily in non-A/U-rich regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). In addition, in the case of the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript, the RNase E cleavages in the 5&#x02032; leader region were clearly a side reaction that resulted in a non-functional species. Similarly, for the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcripts some of the RNase E cleavages observed in the absence of RNase P generated products that were smaller than the mature tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A, *), suggesting that they may serve as a form of quality control to prevent the build up of the unprocessed transcripts.</p><p>Surprisingly, the ability of RNase E to cleave the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript appeared to be dependent on the presence of PNPase. For example, the amount of the VW2 species, which was generated by RNase E cleavages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), was significantly reduced in strains lacking PNPase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>, lanes 2&#x02013;3). This result suggests that the inefficient processing of the VW1 transcript in the absence of RNase P to generate VW2 requires the physical association of RNase E and PNPase, most probably through the multiprotein complex called the degradosome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39 B40 B41">39&#x02013;41</xref>).</p><p>The highly efficient endonucleolytic separation and maturation of the tRNA transcripts from operons such as <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> by RNase P raises many important questions. It is currently believed that the pre-tRNA substrates generated by endonucleolytic cleavages of tRNA precursors become the substrates for the RNase P holoenzyme whereby the enzyme contacts the T-stem and loop of the pre-tRNA substrate, while the catalytic domain interacts with the acceptor stem and cleavage site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>). In fact, the non-tRNA substrates for RNase P [tmRNA, precursors to 4.5S RNA, viral mRNAs, C4 antisense RNA from bacteriophages P1 and P7 and transient structures within riboswitches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44 B45 B46 B47 B48">44&#x02013;48</xref>)] very often closely resemble pre-tRNAs.</p><p>However, in the absence of initial RNase E cleavages within the <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcripts, it is not clear how RNase P recognizes these larger substrates. In fact, based on the secondary structures of the full-length transcripts that are predicted using the RNA-STAR program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>) (data not shown), it would appear that the RNase P cleavage sites at the mature 5&#x02032; ends of the individual tRNAs within the <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> transcripts may not correspond to known RNase P sites. Specifically, in the predicted equilibrium structures of both full-length transcripts, the RNase P cleavage sites fall within stem structures that should not be accessible to RNase P. Thus it is possible that the RNase P holoenzyme has greater flexibility in substrate recognition than previously envisioned. Alternatively, the maturation of multimeric tRNA substrates by RNase P may actually be coupled with transcription such that most of the precursors are cleaved prior to transcription termination. Interestingly, recent studies have suggested a role for the nuclear form of RNase P in transcription processing and regulation of tRNA gene expression in eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore, the notion that RNase P cannot act on tRNA substrates with long 3&#x02032; trailer sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>) needs to be reconsidered. In particular, if both operons are completely transcribed prior to any nucleolytic processing, the tRNA precursors will contain long 3&#x02032; trailer sequences. For example, the <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> operon has intergenic regions of 29&#x02013;34 nt with an observed size of over 300 nt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). Yet, the data presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> shows that the half-life of this transcript is less than 30 s in the wild-type strain, indicating that it is an excellent substrate for RNase P.</p><p>It should be noted that the data presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref> can also be interpreted to mean that most of the <italic>valV valW</italic> transcript is actually processed before transcription has been completed and that the full-length transcript only represents a small fraction of the total amount of <italic>valV</italic> and <italic>valW</italic> precursors that are transcribed. In this scenario, the failure to remove the terminator sequences generates a substrate that is resistant to RNase P cleavage such that the full-length transcript can be observed under steady-state conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>, lanes 1 and 6).</p><p>Finally, it is also worth revisiting the basis for why RNase P is essential for cell viability based on the results described above. It is currently thought that the enzyme is required to generate the mature 5&#x02032; ends for all tRNAs from any pre-tRNAs that contain extra nucleotides at their 5&#x02032; termini, since these may interfere with aminoacylation. However, <italic>in vitro</italic> studies indicate that the 5&#x02032; extension of yeast tRNA<sup>Asp</sup> does not interfere with recognition by aspartyl-tRNA synthetase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>). Furthermore, our recent observation that an <italic>E. coli</italic> mutant tRNA<sup>Leu2</sup> carrying an extra nucleotide (G) upstream of the mature 5&#x02032; end supports cell viability in a strain carrying a deletion of the chromosomally encoded <italic>leuU</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>) suggests that aminoacylation of pre-tRNAs with immature 5&#x02032; ends may not be inhibitory (Mohanty,B.K., Bar-Peled,L. and Kushner,S.R., unpublished data). Accordingly, in the absence of RNase P, RNase E processed pre-tRNAs containing extra nucleotides at their 5&#x02032; termini but with mature 3&#x02032; termini may still be chargeable. In contrast, for those tRNAs that are completely dependent on RNase P for their maturation (e.g. <italic>valV valW</italic> and <italic>leuQ leuP leuV</italic> and probably others), there is no alternative processing pathway to generate a functional tRNA. Thus the loss of cell viability may arise not only from a general defect in the maturation of all tRNAs, but also more likely from the loss of a subset of tRNAs that are dependent on RNase P for endonucleolytic processing.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>The authors wish to thank Liron Bar-Peled and Jamie Robinson for their assistance with strain constructions. This work was supported in part by a grant from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences (GM57220) to S.R.K. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by GM57220.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blattner</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Plunkett</surname><given-names>G.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Perna</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Burland</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Collado-Vides</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Glasner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rode</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The complete sequence of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>1453</fpage><lpage>1474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9278503</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutscher</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>3&#x02032; Exoribonucleolytic trimming is a common feature of the maturation of small, stable RNAs in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>2856</fpage><lpage>2861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9501180</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutscher</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of individual exoribonucleases in processing at the 3&#x02032; end of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> tRNA precursors</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>6064</fpage><lpage>6071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7509797</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutscher</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maturation pathways for <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA precursors: a random multienzyme process <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8756732</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirsebom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Soll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>RajBhandary</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Recent studies of RNase P</article-title><source>tRNA: Structure and Function</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology Press</publisher-name><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutscher</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNase E plays an essential role in the maturation of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> tRNA precursors</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11871663</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soderbom</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Svard</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirsebom</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNase E cleavage in the 5&#x02032; leader of a tRNA precursor</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081101</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ow</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Initiation of tRNA maturation by RNase E is essential for cell viability in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1102</fpage><lpage>1115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12000793</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deutscher</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Degradation of RNA in bacteria: comparison of mRNA and stable RNA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452296</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Belasco</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The function of RNase G in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> is constrained by its amino and carboxyl termini</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1205</fpage><lpage>1217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14763991</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rho-independent transcription terminators inhibit RNase P processing of the <italic>secG leuU</italic> and <italic>metT</italic> polycistronic transcripts in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><comment>in press</comment></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kole</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribonuclease P: an enzyme with an essential RNA component</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1977</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>3719</fpage><lpage>3721</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guerrier-Takada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pace</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RNA moiety of ribonuclease P is the catalytic subunit of the enzyme</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1983</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6197186</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gopalan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Vioque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNase P: variations and uses</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>6759</fpage><lpage>6762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11741968</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirsebom</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of mutations in the protein and RNA moieties of RNase P on the efficiency of suppression by various tRNA suppressors</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1988</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>879</fpage><lpage>888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2464697</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozeki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature sensitive mutants of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> for tRNA synthesis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1974</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10793671</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozeki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Precursor molecules of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> transfer RNAs accumulated in a temperature-sensitive mutant</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1975</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1099216</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alifano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivellini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Piscitelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Arraiano</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruni</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlomagno</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribonuclease E provides substrates for ribonuclease P-dependent processing of a polycistronic mRNA</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>1994</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>3021</fpage><lpage>3031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8001821</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of a single, temperature-sensitive mutation on global gene expression in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12702811</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ilgen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerik</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of large transfer ribonucleic acid precursors from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1976</year><volume>251</volume><fpage>922</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">765341</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-evolution of tRNA 3&#x02032; trailer sequences with 3&#x02032; processing enzymes in bacteria</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15811923</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schedl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Primakoff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutants of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> thermosensitive for the synthesis of transfer RNA</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1973</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>2091</fpage><lpage>2095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4579013</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrier-Takada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumelsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vioque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudock</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cleavage of RNA by RNase P</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of RNA</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>Orlando</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuven</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutscher</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNase PH is essential for tRNA processing and viability in RNase-deficient <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> cells</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1992</year><volume>267</volume><fpage>16015</fpage><lpage>16018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1644789</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deutscher</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exoribonucleases and their multiple roles in RNA metabolism</article-title><source>Prog. Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2001</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>105</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arraiano</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yancey</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stabilization of discrete mRNA breakdown products in <italic>ams pnp rnb</italic> multiple mutants of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>1988</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>4625</fpage><lpage>4633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2459106</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A conditional lethal mutation in an <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain with a longer chemical lifetime of mRNA</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1979</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">110942</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> demonstrates differential roles for polynucleotide phosphorylase and RNase II in mRNA abundance and decay</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14617186</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cairrao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpousis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Arraiano</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNase II levels change according to the growth conditions: characterization of <italic>gmr</italic>, a new <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> gene involved in the modulation of RNase II</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1550</fpage><lpage>1561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11260472</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piedade</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arraiano</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction and characterization of an absolute deletion of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ribonuclease II</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source><year>1995</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7758932</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polynucleotide phosphorylase and ribonuclease II are required for cell viability and mRNA turnover in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1986</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2417233</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Hara</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chekanova</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingle</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyadenylylation helps regulate mRNA decay in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>1807</fpage><lpage>1811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7534403</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritsch</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular cloning, a laboratory manual</source><year>1989</year><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Residual polyadenylation in poly(A) polymerase I (<italic>pcnB</italic>) mutants of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> does not result from the activity encoded by the <italic>f310</italic> gene</article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1109</fpage><lpage>1119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10594834</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spickler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackie</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Action of RNase II and polynucleotide phosphorylase against RNAs containing stem-loops of defined structure</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>2422</fpage><lpage>2427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10762241</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duester</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Campen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleotide sequence of an <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> tRNA (Leu 1) operon and identification of the transcription promotion signal</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1981</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2121</fpage><lpage>2139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6272226</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deutscher</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Promiscuous exoribonucleases of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>1993</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>4577</fpage><lpage>4583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8335617</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maturation of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> tryptophan operon mRNA: evidence for 3&#x02032; exonucleolytic processing after rho-dependent termination</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>1985</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1887</fpage><lpage>1891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2992951</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpousis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Houwe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehretsmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krisch</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copurification of <italic>E. coli</italic> RNAase E and PNPase: evidence for a specific association between two enzymes important in RNA processing and degradation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7510217</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Py</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Causton</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mudd</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A protein complex mediating mRNA degradation in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Mol. Microbiol.</source><year>1994</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7891559</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Py</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Krisch</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpousis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A DEAD-box RNA helicase in the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> RNA degradosome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8610017</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelke</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribonuclease P: the evolution of an ancient RNA enzyme</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Biochem. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16595295</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahler</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaye</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of substrate recognition by the ribonucleoprotein RNase P</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2002</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12431435</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mans</surname><given-names>RMW</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrier-Takada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pleij</surname><given-names>CWA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of RNase P from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> with pseudoknotted structures in viral RNAs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1990</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3479</fpage><lpage>3487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2194161</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlegl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Precursor of C4 antisense RNA of bacteriophages P1 and P7 is a substrate for RNase P of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>5822</fpage><lpage>5826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7597035</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peck-Miller</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of the processing of the precursor to 4.5S RNA, a naturally occurring substrate for RNase P from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>221</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1717693</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wesolowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrier-Takada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNase P cleaves transient structures in some riboswitches</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>11284</fpage><lpage>11289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16061811</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komine</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitabatake</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokigawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Inokuchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A tRNA-like structure is present in 10Sa RNA, a small stable RNA from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>9223</fpage><lpage>9227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7524073</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gultyaev</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>van Batenburg</surname><given-names>FHD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pleij</surname><given-names>CWA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The computer simulation of RNA folding pathways using a genetic algorithm</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7541471</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarrous</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human RNase P: a tRNA-processing enzyme and transcription factor</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>3519</fpage><lpage>3524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483522</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Asouli</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Krilovetzky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarrous</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for the catalytic ribonucleoprotein RNase P in RNA polymerase III transcription</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1621</fpage><lpage>1635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16778078</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perret</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Florentz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Giege</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient aminoacylation of a yeast transfer RNA<sup>Asp</sup> transcript with a 5&#x02032; extension</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1990</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2226785</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tokuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genes coding for SecG and Leu2-tRNA form an operon to give an unusual RNA comprising mRNA and a tRNA precursor</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>2005</year><volume>1729</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15951035</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 