<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkg789</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg789</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530443</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antizyme frameshifting as a functional probe of eukaryotic translational termination</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karamysheva</surname><given-names>Zemfira N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77b70">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77b70">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="gkg789fn2">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karamyshev</surname><given-names>Andrey L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77b70">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="gkg789fn3">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Koichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77b70">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yokogawa</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77b70">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>Kazuya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77b70">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Yoshikazu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77b70">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matsufuji</surname><given-names>Senya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77b70">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="gkg789fn1">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77b70"><label>1</label>Department of Biochemistry II, The Jikei University, School of Medicine, 3-25-8 Nishi-shinbashi, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105-8461, Japan, <label>2</label>Department of Basic Medical Sciences, Institute of Medical Science, University of Tokyo, 4-6-1 Shirokanedai, Minato-ku, Tokyo 108-8630, Japan and <label>3</label>Department of Biomolecular Science, Faculty of Engineering, Gifu University, Yanagido 1-1, Gifu 501-1193, Japan </aff><author-notes><fn id="gkg789fn1"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: &#x0002b;81 3 3433 1111; Fax: &#x0002b;81 3 3436 3897; Email: <email>senya@jikei.ac.jp</email></p></fn><fn id="gkg789fn2"><label>a</label><p>Present address: Zemfira N. Karamysheva, Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics, Texas A&#x00026;M University, College Station, TX 77843-2128, USA</p></fn><fn id="gkg789fn3"><label>a</label><p>Present address: Andrey L. Karamyshev, Department of Medical Biochemistry and Genetics, College of Medicine, Texas A&#x00026;M University System, Health Science Center, College Station, TX 77843-1114, USA</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2003</year></pub-date><volume>31</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>5949</fpage><lpage>5956</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nar.oupjournals.org/content/vol31/issue20/"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2003</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2003 Oxford University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2003</copyright-year><abstract><p>Translation termination in eukaryotes is mediated by the release factors eRF1 and eRF3, but mechanisms of the interplay between these factors are not fully understood, due partly to the difficulty of measuring termination on eukaryotic mRNAs. Here, we describe an <italic>in vitro</italic> system for the assay of termination using competition with programmed frameshifting at the recoding signal of mammalian antizyme. The efficiency of antizyme frameshifting in rabbit reticulocyte lysates was reduced by addition of recombinant rabbit eRF1 and eRF3 in a synergistic manner. Addition of suppressor tRNA to this assay system revealed competition with a third event, stop codon readthrough. Using these assays, we demonstrated that an eRF3 mutation at the GTPase domain repressed termination in a dominant negative fashion probably by binding to eRF1. The effect of the release factors and the suppressor tRNA showed that the stop codon at the antizyme frameshift site is relatively inefficient compared to either the natural termination signals at the end of protein coding sequences or the readthrough signal from a plant virus. The system affords a convenient assay for release factor activity and has provided some novel views of the mechanism of antizyme frameshifting.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes id="N0x99bdf10.0x9d77c30" notes-type="data_link"><p>DDBJ&#x0002f;EMBL&#x0002f;GenBank accession no. AB035256</p></notes></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The termination of translation occurs on ribosomes in response to one of the three stop codons, UAG, UGA or UAA. Extraribosomal proteins, the release factors, are essential components of this step (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c4">4</xref>). Both prokaryotic and eukaryotic release factors are composed of two classes, namely class-I and -II factors. Prokaryotes generally have two codon-specific class-I factors with overlapping specificity, RF1 (for UAG&#x0002f;UAA) and RF2 (for UGA&#x0002f;UAA), while eukaryotes and archaea have only one omnipotent factor, eRF1 and aRF1, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c2">2</xref>). A basic mechanism for the codon-specific recognition by the &#x02018;peptide anticodon&#x02019; of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> RF1 and RF2 has been proposed recently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c5">5</xref>). In addition, the crystal structure of eRF1 has been solved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c6">6</xref>) and a region defining stop codon recognition has been suggested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c10">10</xref>).</p><p>Class-II factors are RF3 and eRF3 in prokaryotes and eukaryotes, respectively, and are not found in small-genome bacteria or archaea. Class-II factors belong to the guanine nucleotide-binding protein superfamily and share a homology with other translation factors, such as EF1A, EF2 and eEF-1A. The termination of protein synthesis is achieved by the recognition of the stop codon in mRNA by class-I factors, which then trigger the hydrolysis of the ester bond linking the nascent polypeptide to peptidyl-tRNA on the ribosome. RF3 is not essential for bacterial cell growth and is known to recycle class-I factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c11">11</xref>). In contrast, eRF3 is an essential cell component, forms a stable complex with eRF1 and shares a stronger homology to bacterial EF1A rather than to EF2. It has therefore been proposed that eRF3 acts as a vehicle for eRF1, mimicking the carrier function of EF1A for tRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c12">12</xref>). However, the exact mechanism of action of eukaryotic release factors, in particular the role of eRF3 and GTP hydrolysis, remains unclear. In the literature, the <italic>in vitro</italic> eukaryotic polypeptide-release assay has been based on the classical Caskey&#x02019;s model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c13">13</xref>). In this system, release of formyl-&#x0005b;<sup>35</sup>S&#x0005d;methionine (f&#x0005b;<sup>35</sup>S&#x0005d;Met) from the ribosomal complex composed of f&#x0005b;<sup>35</sup>S&#x0005d;Met-tRNA<sub>f</sub><sup>Met</sup>, an initiator triplet (AUG) and a stop codon-containing tetranucleotide (i.e. UAAA, UAGA or UGAA) is measured upon the addition of release factors (eRF1 and eRF3). However, the lack of a convenient assay system of eukaryotic termination that is dependent on &#x02018;natural&#x02019; mRNA has been an obstacle to the functional study of the release factors.</p><p>A termination signal&#x02014;a stop codon with its flanking regions&#x02014;can be alternatively decoded in some genes causing translational frameshifting, readthrough or selenocysteine incorporation, referred to as &#x02018;recoding&#x02019; for <underline>re</underline>-programmed genetic de<underline>coding</underline> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c14">14</xref>). The association of recoding with termination may reflect the fact that termination is a relatively slow process compared to the elongation step (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c15">15</xref>). It has been shown that the efficiency of a stop signal is affected by its context and that the stop signal at the recoding site is often in an unfavorable context for efficient termination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c16">16</xref>). Each ribosome that reads a stop codon within a recoding site would select either a termination event or, alternatively, a recoding event. Therefore an increase in the frequency of one of these events should result in a decrease in the frequency of the other event. In the case of prokaryotic regulatory frameshifting of <italic>E.coli</italic> RF2 mRNA, an increase in the RF2 protein decreases the frameshift efficiency <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c17">17</xref>). A three way competition between termination, suppression and &#x0002b;1 frameshifting at the RF2 frameshift site was demonstrated by the addition of a suppressor tRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c18">18</xref>). In eukaryotes, addition of <italic>Xenopus</italic> eRF1 to the rabbit reticulocyte lysate translation system has been shown to reduce stop codon readthrough of a plant virus mRNA in the presence of suppressor tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c19">19</xref>). Thus, competition between termination and recoding could be utilized to measure the activities of release factors.</p><p>In the present study, we attempted to utilize translational frameshifting of mammalian antizyme to assay translation termination. Antizyme regulates the cellular level of polyamines (putrescine, spermidine and spermine) in a wide variety of eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c23">23</xref>). There are three members of the mammalian antizyme family, antizyme-1, 2 and 3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c23">23</xref>). The initiating open reading frame (ORF1) of antizyme-1 mRNA has a UGA at codon 68 where the majority of translating ribosomes terminate translation, while the rest of the ribosomes undergo a &#x0002b;1 frameshift event to decode UCC <underline>UGA</underline> U sequence (where the terminator of ORF1 is underlined) to serine-aspartate and continue elongation along the second open reading frame (ORF2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c26">26</xref>). Frameshifting is induced by polyamines and, in the presence of an optimal concentration of polyamines, the frameshift efficiency reaches &#x0003e;20&#x00025; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c26">26</xref>). A pseudoknot structure 3&#x02032; to the shift site and an upstream GC-rich sequence are <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements that stimulate the frameshifting event (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c27">27</xref>). For frameshifting to occur, the UGA codon must occupy the ribosomal A-site. Therefore the system represents a promising means by which translation termination can be measured. We examined the activities of homologous rabbit eRF1 and eRF3 in this assay system.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Cloning of rabbit eRF3</title><p>Rabbit eRF3 cDNA was cloned in this study by hybridization screening of the rabbit muscle &#x003bb;Zap II cDNA library (Stratagene) using human eRF3 (kindly provided by Dr S. Hoshino) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c28">28</xref>) as a probe. The hybridization and detection of positive clones were carried out with ECL kit (Amersham) according to the instructions. For positive clones, <italic>in vivo</italic> excision of the pBluescript phagemid from the &#x003bb;Zap II vector was carried out using ExAssist&#x0002f;SOLR system (Stratagene). A clone containing the longest insert (2203 bp) was sequenced on both strands with <italic>Taq</italic> DyeDeoxy terminator cycle sequencing kit (Applied Biosystems). The cDNA contained an open reading frame of 1767 bp where a part of the 5&#x02032; terminal sequence corresponding to the amino terminal 32 amino acid residues of human eRF3 (NP&#x0005f;060564) is missing. The coding sequence shares 86.4 and 88.6&#x00025; identity with human eRF3 on the nucleotide and the amino acid levels, respectively. The cDNA sequence has been deposited to DDBJ&#x0002f;EMBL&#x0002f;GenBank (accession number AB035256). It is known that the N-terminal part of the mammalian eRF3 sequence is functionally dispensable <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c29">29</xref>) and in fact, the cloned N-terminally truncated cDNA sequence was functionally active in the complementation test <italic>in vivo</italic> (see below). Hence we used this cDNA clone in further analysis.</p><p>The functional integrity of the rabbit eRF3 clones was tested by complementation of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae sup35</italic> (eRF3) mutant as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c30">30</xref>). Both untagged and a C-terminal His<sub>6</sub>-tagged form of eRF3 complemented the temperature-sensitive <italic>sup35</italic> mutation at 37&#x000b0;C to the same extent.</p><p>The site-directed mutant of rabbit eRF3 was prepared using Altered Sites II <italic>in vitro</italic> Mutagenesis System (Promega) with the corresponding oligonucleotides and the sequence was verified.</p></sec><sec><title>Expression and purification of rabbit eRF1 and eRF3</title><p>The untagged form of full-length rabbit eRF1 was overexpressed in <italic>E.coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) cells via pET-3(a) vector encoding the cDNA of full-length rabbit eRF1 (DDBJ&#x0002f;EMBL&#x0002f;GenBank accession number AB029089) as reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c31">31</xref>). Cells transformed with this construct were also transformed with an additional plasmid, pUBS520, encoding a tRNA<sup>Arg</sup> that is cognate to the rare arginine codons of <italic>E.coli</italic> (kindly provided by Dr R. Mattes) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c32">32</xref>). Synthesis of eRF1 was induced when the cell density at OD<sub>600</sub> reached 0.5 with 1 mM isopropylthio-&#x003b2;-<sc>d</sc>-galactoside (IPTG) for 4 h at 37&#x000b0;C. The soluble fraction of bacterial lysate (S100) was precipitated with ammonium sulphate (25&#x02013;50&#x00025;) and dialyzed against buffer A (50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, pH 7.8, 50 mM NaCl and 2 mM DTT). Next, chromatography by a Heparin Toyopearl column (Takara) using a linear gradient of 0.05&#x02013;1 M NaCl in buffer A was performed. After dialysis, eRF1 was further purified on a MonoQ column (Pharmacia) by FPLC using a linear gradient of 0.15&#x02013;1 M KCl in buffer A. Fractions containing eRF1 were combined, dialyzed against 50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, pH 7.5, 50 mM KCl, 2 mM DTT and 5&#x00025; glycerol, and frozen at &#x02013;80&#x000b0;C.</p><p>For rabbit eRF3 expression, <italic>E.coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) was transformed with a pET 30-a(&#x0002b;) vector expressing the eRF3 cDNA with a His<sub>6</sub>-tag at the C-terminus. The transformants were grown to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.5, induced with 0.1 mM IPTG and incubated at 25&#x000b0;C overnight. The recombinant eRF3 was purified from the soluble fraction of bacterial lysate by a Ni-NTA agarose column (Qiagen) using a linear gradient of 15&#x02013;250 mM imidasole in 50 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, pH 8.0, 300 mM NaCl and 1 mM DTT. After dialysis against 50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl, pH 7.8, 5 mM KCl and 1 mM DTT, eRF3 was then subjected to chromatography using a Heparin Toyopearl column under the same conditions as for eRF1.</p></sec><sec><title>Transcription and translation <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>The plasmid C3.UGA (referred to as C3NE in the reference) and its derivatives C3.UAG and C3.UAA were described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c26">26</xref>). Sense and antisense oligonucleotides of constructs containing readthrough or natural termination signals were annealed and cloned into the BstEII and KpnI sites of the pGB vector (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkg789tb1">1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c26">26</xref>). <italic>In vitro</italic> transcription and translation were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c26">26</xref>). Briefly, translation mixture (15 &#x000b5;l) contained 0.6 pmol of the mRNA, 15 &#x000b5;Ci of &#x0005b;<sup>35</sup>S&#x0005d;methionine (&#x0003e;1000 Ci&#x0002f;mmol, New England Nuclear) and 10.5 &#x000b5;l of ribonuclease-treated rabbit reticulocyte lysate (Promega). All of the translation reactions in this study were supplemented with 0.5 mM spermidine for optimal antizyme frameshifting. After translation reaction at 30&#x000b0;C for 45 min, the labeled products were separated by SDS&#x02013;PAGE on a 10&#x00025; acrylamide gel and quantified by scanning the dried gel with a BAS 2000 Image Analyzer (Fuji).</p></sec><sec><title>Suppressor tRNA</title><p>An artificial amber suppressor tRNA gene was prepared by modification of <italic>S.cerevisiae</italic> tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c33">33</xref>). It was overexpressed in <italic>E.coli</italic> and purified by ion-exchange column chromatography as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c34">34</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Exogenous eRF1 and eRF3 decrease antizyme frameshift efficiency in rabbit reticulocyte lysates</title><p>The antizyme frameshift assay was carried out in the rabbit reticulocyte lysate translation system using recombinant rabbit eRF1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c31">31</xref>) and eRF3 (cDNA cloned in this study) proteins. Translation was carried out with mRNAs carrying brome mosaic virus (BMV) coat gene fused to the rat antizyme-1 ORFs in the presence of &#x0005b;<sup>35</sup>S&#x0005d;methionine (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f1">1</xref>A) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c26">26</xref>). Frameshifting would yield the full-length product of 416 amino acids (45 450 Da), which is separated from the standard termination product of 257 amino acids (27 703 Da) by SDS&#x02013;PAGE (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f1">1</xref>B). The ratio of radioactivity between these two labeled products provides a measure of the frameshift efficiency.</p><p>The BMV coat-antizyme fusion mRNA directed frameshifting at an efficiency of &#x0223c;25&#x00025; in the reticulocyte lysate supplemented with 0.5 mM spermidine. The addition of increasing amounts of purified eRF1 decreased the frameshift efficiency in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f1">1</xref>B, lanes 1&#x02013;4 and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f2">2</xref>A). Next, purified eRF3 was added at a concentration of 100 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml alone or together with eRF1 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f1">1</xref>B, lanes 5&#x02013;8 and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f2">2</xref>A). Addition of eRF3 enhanced the inhibitory effect of eRF1 and lowered the effective dose of eRF1. In a control experiment, heat-denatured eRF1 and eRF3 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f1">1</xref>C) or purified recombinant green fluorescent protein (data not shown) did not affect antizyme frameshift efficiency. In the absence of exogenous spermidine, antizyme frameshift efficiency was 4.5 times less, but the effects of the addition of eRF1 and eRF3 was identical to those with spermidine (data not shown). These results indicate that in a competing system of translation events and antizyme frameshift events, eRF1 and eRF3 function synergistically to favor the termination events.</p></sec><sec><title>eRF1 and eRF3 affect frameshifting at all three stop codons</title><p>Although all of the known antizyme frameshift signals, from <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> to mammals, exclusively contain a UGA codon at their frameshift site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c22">22</xref>), it has been shown that experimental substitution of the UGA by either UAG or UAA only caused a mild decrease in the frameshift efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c27">27</xref>). We tested the effect of eRF1 and eRF3 on these mutant frameshift sites. Addition of eRF1 with or without eRF3 decreased the frameshift efficiency at either the UAG or UAA codon. The effect of eRF1 and eRF3 together was synergistic and showed a similar dose-dependent curve to that for the wild type mRNA (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f2">2</xref>B and C), confirming the omnipotency of codon recognition by eRF1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c19">19</xref>) and showing that eRF3 functions in a cooperative manner at all three stop codons by roughly the same extent.</p></sec><sec><title>Increased antizyme frameshifting by the G-domain variant of eRF3</title><p>It has been reported that eRF3 stimulates the activity of eRF1 in the presence of GTP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c29">29</xref>) and that eRF3 exhibits an eRF1- and ribosome-dependent GTPase activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c35">35</xref>). To test whether the inhibitory activity of eRF3 on antizyme frameshifting depends on its GTP&#x0002f;GDP binding ability, we substituted an essential amino acid residue within the G-domain. The lysine 216 (numbered as in the human eRF3) corresponds to a lysine residue located within the loop of the G1 domain, and its &#x003b5;-amino group forms hydrogen bonds with the &#x003b1;- and &#x003b2;-phosphates of GTP or GDP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c36">36</xref>). A mutation at the corresponding residue in <italic>E.coli</italic> RF3 resulted in a dominant lethal phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c37">37</xref>). A six-histidine (His<sub>6</sub>)-tagged rabbit eRF3 with a lysine 216 to glutamate mutation was purified and added to the antizyme frameshifting assay. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f3">3</xref>, addition of the mutant eRF3 alone at a concentration of 100 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml increased the antizyme frameshifting from 15 to 26&#x00025;. The increase could be reduced to the control level by the addition of 40 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml of purified eRF1. The opposite effect of the mutant eRF3 strongly suggests that the mutant eRF3 acts as a dominant negative inhibitor that retains eRF1-binding capacity (discussed below). This result also suggests that the effect of eRF3 to enhance termination is dependent on its GTPase activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Competition between frameshifting, readthrough and termination at the antizyme frameshift site</title><p>The termination assay was extended by adding a suppressor tRNA to the translation reaction so that termination, frameshifting and readthrough at the antizyme frameshift site could be monitored simultaneously. We used an amber suppressor tyrosine tRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c33">33</xref>) and coordinated the mRNA with the altered antizyme frameshift signal with UAG stop codon. Addition of the suppressor tRNA to the translation reaction reduced the amount of the frameshift and termination products, and concomitantly, two additional bands appeared between the frameshift and termination bands (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f4">4</xref>A). The size of the newly appeared small product (RT1) coincided to the calculated molecular mass (30 367 Da) yielded by UAG codon readthrough at the frameshift site (codon 258) followed by termination at the next in-frame UAG stop (codon 282). The other, larger, product (RT2) is likely to be caused by readthrough of both UAGs at codons 258 and 282, followed by termination at the next in-frame UAA at codon 299 (expected molecular mass 32 127 Da). The nucleotides 3&#x02032; to UAG at codon 282 and UAA at codon 299 are both &#x02018;C&#x02019;, and UAG-C is known to be an inefficient terminator (see below). The sum of intensities of the two readthrough bands (RT1 &#x0002b; RT2), as well as the RT2&#x0002f;RT1 ratio, was increased by the suppressor tRNA (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f4">4</xref>B). The decrease of the termination and frameshift products by the suppressor tRNA was almost proportional, unchanging the ratio of the frameshift to the termination products, that was 0.19 without the suppressor tRNA and 0.17 with 10 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml of the suppressor tRNA.</p><p>In the presence of 0.2 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml of the suppressor tRNA, &#x0223c;10&#x00025; of the frameshift product and 25&#x00025; of the readthrough product were observed. Under these conditions, we measured the effect of the release factors on the two recoding events. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f5">5</xref>, the efficiencies of frameshifting and readthrough were reduced by the addition of exogenous release factors in a similar manner. The results described in this section are consistent with a model that the three alternatives at the antizyme frameshift site, termination, frameshifting and readthrough, are in direct competition at the same instant.</p></sec><sec><title>Comparison of the strength of termination signal at the antizyme frameshift site and those in other contexts</title><p>During this study, we noticed that the effective concentrations of eRF1 to inhibit antizyme frameshifting was higher than for the stop-codon readthrough of the plant RNA virus (beet necrotic yellow vein virus, BNYVV) reported earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c19">19</xref>). We tested whether termination at the antizyme frameshift site is less efficient than those at the viral recoding signal or natural termination signals at the end of various protein coding regions. For this purpose, we first examined the effects of the suppressor tRNA in different termination contexts. Three UAG terminator signals from human genes encoding ornithine decarboxylase (ODC), autoantigen ribonucleoprotein La (La) and low-affinity IgG Fc receptor (FCRB) were chosen based on the diversity of their respective coding contexts. The stop codons of these genes, as well as 5&#x02013;9 flanking nucleotides on both sides, were inserted into the cloning site between two reporter genes &#x0005b;glutathione-<italic>S</italic>-transferase (GST) gene at the 5&#x02032; end and rabbit &#x003b2;-globin gene at the 3&#x02032; end&#x0005d; of the plasmid vector, pGB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c26">26</xref>). Thus, only when the insert directed readthrough, could the &#x003b2;-globin reporter be translated as a fusion with GST. The mRNAs were synthesized from the constructs and translated in the reticulocyte lysate in the absence or the presence of varying concentrations of the suppressor tRNA. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f6">6</xref>A, UAG in the antizyme frameshift context was not suppressed in the absence of suppressor tRNA, while the addition of the suppressor tRNA caused a marked increase in readthrough products. On the other hand, the BNYVV signal caused a significant level of readthrough even in the absence of suppressor tRNA, but was less sensitive to the suppressor tRNA than the antizyme signal. The &#x02018;true&#x02019; termination signals required even higher concentrations of the suppressor tRNA to be readthrough.</p><p>It has been reported that the identity of the base adjacent to the stop codon at the 3&#x02032; end is highly biased (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c38">38</xref>) and that it influences the efficiency of termination or suppression in experimental systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c41">41</xref>). For instance, UAG-A is a more efficient terminator than UAG-U or UAG-C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c41">41</xref>). The base adjacent to the stop codon at the 3&#x02032; end used in our experiments was &#x02018;U&#x02019; in the antizyme, La and FCRB termination signals, &#x02018;C&#x02019; in the BNYVV, and &#x02018;A&#x02019; in the ODC termination signal. We tested the effects of the suppressor tRNA for readthrough efficiency on derivatives of the ODC construct in which the base 3&#x02032; adjacent to the UAG codon was substituted by either C or U. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f6">6</xref>B, the effects of changing the 3&#x02032; adjacent base were much smaller than the differences for the dose&#x02013;responses between the recoding and termination contexts (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f6">6</xref>A). Therefore the termination efficiency of a stop codon is not merely determined by the 3&#x02032; base adjacent to the stop codon, but by a broader context.</p><p>We then compared the effects of the release factors on the recoding event at the stop codons of varying contexts by the addition of amber suppressor tRNA to translation reactions directed by the antizyme, BNYVV or ODC constructs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f7">7</xref>). The effects of the release factors were almost identical for frameshifting and readthrough in the context of the antizyme stop signal (with or without suppressor tRNA) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f7">7</xref>A&#x02013;C). The natural termination signal of ODC was much more sensitive to the release factors (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f7">7</xref>F) while readthrough of the BNYVV termination signal showed an intermediate sensitivity to the addition of release factors (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f7">7</xref>E). We also tested a UGA readthrough signal from an animal virus, Sindbis (SIND), which can be readthrough in the absence of exogenous suppressor tRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c43">43</xref>). The efficiency of stop codon readthrough in the SIND context was &#x0223c;7&#x00025;, and this was reduced by the addition of release factors to a similar extent to that of frameshifting or readthrough at the antizyme recoding site (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f7">7</xref>D).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>We developed an <italic>in vitro</italic> assay system to monitor the activity of eukaryotic release factors in translation termination by measuring the relative frequency of competing frameshift events at the antizyme termination signal. Ribosomes decoding along the antizyme frameshift site will either terminate translation at the UGA codon, or undergo a &#x0002b;1 frameshift event and continue elongation. Therefore reduction in frameshift events would correspond to an increase in translation termination activity, and vice versa. The relatively high occurrence of antizyme frameshifting in rabbit reticulocyte lysates provides a convenient, quantitative assay to monitor release factor activity. In this system, it is not necessary to supplement suppressor tRNA in the basic assays, and termination at all three stop codons can be quantified by simply changing the codon in the termination signal of the tester mRNA.</p><p>Using this system, we tested the activities of recombinant eRF1 and eRF3 of rabbit origin. Antizyme frameshifting was inhibited by eRF1 alone in a dose-dependent manner. Although addition of eRF3 alone caused only a marginal to mild inhibition, simultaneous addition of both factors synergistically inhibited antizyme frameshifting. Next we examined the effect of a mutant eRF3 at lysine 216, the residue known to be essential for guanine-nucleotide binding of G proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c36">36</xref>). The mutant eRF3 increased the frameshift efficiency when added alone and the effect was reversed by eRF1. It is known that the binding of eRF3 to eRF1 does not require the G domain, which is unlike prokaryotic RF3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c45">45</xref>). Therefore our result can be explained by assuming that the mutant eRF3 retains the eRF1-binding capacity and hinders eRF1 function by forming a non-functional eRF1&#x02013;eRF3 complex or by preventing an eRF1 exchange. However, other possibilities cannot be excluded at present since eRF3 function <italic>per se</italic> is not yet well understood. Further <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> analyses are necessary to uncover the reason for increased antizyme frameshifting by the G-domain variant of eRF3.</p><p>To analyze the relationship between the frameshift and termination events more precisely, we developed an additional assay method where frameshifting, stop codon readthrough and termination at the antizyme frameshift site can be measured with a single reporter system. This was achieved by the addition of an artificial amber suppressor tRNA as well as using the mutant antizyme frameshift signal with the UAG stop codon. Addition of increasing concentrations of the suppressor tRNA lowered both frameshifting and termination proportionally. In the presence of smaller concentrations of the suppressor tRNA, both of the frameshift and readthrough products were reduced by the release factors with a similar dose dependency. Thus, among three alternatives at the antizyme frameshift site, the forced increase of either readthrough or termination caused a concomitant decrease in the other two events. This is consistent with a model that the three events are in direct competition at the same instant of the translation cycle: i.e. the instant at which the A-site codon is recognized. The same conclusion has been drawn for <italic>E.coli</italic> RF2 frameshifting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c18">18</xref>).</p><p>Although it is widely accepted that eRF3 acts as a vehicle for eRF1 mimicking EF1A for tRNA, the timing of the GTP hydrolysis is still unclear and this model is not fully consistent with the results of molecular dissection studies of eRF1 and eRF3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c1">1</xref>). In addition, the discrepancy between the apparent dispensability <italic>in vitro</italic> and indispensability <italic>in vivo</italic> of eRF3 has led to the hypothesis that eRF3 has an alternative&#x0002f;additional function(s). Two possibilities have been hypothesized. First, by an analogy to prokaryotic RF3, eRF3 may be involved in recycling of the translational complex after the termination process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c46">46</xref>). Second, eRF3 could be involved in either increasing the accuracy of stop codon recognition or perhaps proofreading stop codon recognition by eRF1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c47">47</xref>). Given that termination and frameshifting are competing at the codon recognition step, our results suggest that the primary role of eRF3 is the enhancement of the stop codon recognition by eRF1 and that GTP hydrolysis is necessary before the completion of the codon recognition step. Unfortunately, the alternative possibilities could not be addressed with our system since the recycling event would occur after A-site codon recognition, and termination proofreading cannot be detected at the stop codon. Thus, these alternative events are not in competition with the antizyme frameshifting event used in this system.</p><p>The contexts around the stop codon are not random and the efficiency of translation termination is influenced by context in eukaryotes. For &#x02018;true&#x02019; termination signals, contexts are biased to preferable sequences for efficient termination and weak termination signals are often used at recoding sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c38">38</xref>). It has been demonstrated in mammalian systems that the nucleotide 3&#x02032; to the stop codon is a major determinant for the termination efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c41">41</xref>). By monitoring the effects of the addition of both suppressor tRNA and release factors, we demonstrated that the signal at the antizyme frameshift site is prone to less efficient termination, when compared to the natural termination signals of some protein coding sequences. Interestingly, the stop signal at the readthrough site of plant virus BNYVV (UAG-C) was much more efficient for termination than those in animal recoding site, antizyme (UGA-U) and Sindbis virus readthrough (UGA-U), even though the UAG-C was shown to be one of the most inefficient tetranucleotide terminators in mammalian cells by others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c41">41</xref>). Thus, consistent with previous observations in yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkg789c49">49</xref>), our results show that the termination efficiency is determined by a wider context. The antizyme mRNA context that circumvents termination at the shift site must be an important factor for efficient frameshifting and to address this issue further, precise mapping of <italic>cis</italic>-element(s) in the mRNA context should be performed.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig id="gkg789f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p> eRF1 and eRF3 decrease antizyme frameshift efficiency. (<bold>A</bold>) A diagram of the BMV coat-antizyme fusion constructs (C3.UGA) and the two possible products are shown. The termination product (Term) is produced by the standard termination at the end of ORF1 and the frameshift product (FS) is produced by frameshifting from ORF1 to ORF2 at the frameshift site. (<bold>B</bold>) C3.UGA mRNAs were translated in the rabbit reticulocyte lysate supplemented with 0.5 mM spermidine in the presence of increasing amounts of eRF1 with (&#x0002b;) or without (&#x02013;) 100 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml eRF3. The radiolabeled products were separated on SDS&#x02013;PAGE and visualized with a BAS 2000 Image Analyzer. (<bold>C</bold>) Control experiment with heat denatured eRF1 and eRF3. Samples were analyzed as in (B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg789f1"/></fig><fig id="gkg789f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p> Effects of eRF1 and eRF3 on the frameshift efficiency of antizyme frameshift signals with the UGA (<bold>A</bold>), UAG (<bold>B</bold>) or UAA (<bold>C</bold>) stop codon. C3.UGA mRNA and its derivatives containing the UAG (C3.UAG) or the UAA (C3.UAA) stop codon were translated as described in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f1">1</xref>B. Frameshift efficiencies were calculated from the relative radioactivity of the product bands as described in the text.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg789f2"/></fig><fig id="gkg789f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p> An eRF3 mutant at the G-domain facilitates antizyme frameshifting. The effect of wild type and mutant eRF3 on the frameshifting of C3.UGA mRNA was examined in the presence (or absence) of the indicated concentration of eRF1. The wild type and mutated eRF3 were added at 100 &#x000b5;g &#x0002f;ml and the assay was performed as described in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f1">1</xref>B.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg789f3"/></fig><fig id="gkg789f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p> Competition between frameshifting, readthrough and termination at the antizyme frameshift site in the presence of amber suppressor tRNA. (<bold>A</bold>) C3.UAG mRNA was translated in the reticulocyte lysate in the presence of varying concentrations of amber suppressor tRNA. Termination (Term), readthrough (RT) and frameshifting (FS) products were separated by SDS&#x02013;PAGE. (<bold>B</bold>) The amounts of the translated products were quantified as described in the text and the relative amount of each product was plotted as a percentage of the total.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg789f4"/></fig><fig id="gkg789f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p> Frameshifting and readthrough at antizyme frameshift site are reduced by eRF1 and eRF3 in the presence of amber suppressor tRNA. C3.UAG mRNA was translated in the reticulocyte lysate in the presence of 0.2 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml amber suppressor tRNA with and without 50 or 100 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml eRF1 and 100 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml eRF3. Termination, readthrough and frameshifting products were quantified as described in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkg789f4">4</xref> and plots represent the efficiency of readthrough (left) and frameshifting (right), respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg789f5"/></fig><fig id="gkg789f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p> Effect of amber suppressor tRNA on UAG readthrough in different contexts. (<bold>A</bold>) mRNAs were synthesized <italic>in vitro</italic> from C3.UAG as well as from the constructs with the BNYVV, ODC, FCRB and La recoding&#x0002f;termination contexts. These mRNAs were then translated in the reticulocyte lysate in the presence of increasing concentrations of amber-suppressor tRNA. (<bold>B</bold>) mRNAs from ODC termination contexts and its derivatives with either a C or a U base 3&#x02032; adjacent to the stop codon were translated under the same conditions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg789f6"/></fig><fig id="gkg789f7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p> Effects of the release factors on recoding in different contexts. mRNAs were synthesized <italic>in vitro</italic> and translated in the reticulocyte lysate in the absence or presence of increasing concentrations of eRF1 and in the presence of 100 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml of eRF3. The translation templates were: (<bold>A</bold>&#x02013;<bold>C</bold>) Antizyme with UAG stop codon, (<bold>D</bold>) SIND readthrough signal, (<bold>E</bold>) BNYVV readthrough signal and (<bold>F</bold>) ODC termination signal. Amber suppressor tRNA was added at the concentration of 0.2 (B and C) or 1 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml (E and F) whereas (A) and (D) were carried out in the absence of suppressor tRNA. Frameshift efficiency (A and B) or readthrough efficiency (C&#x02013;F) was determined and relative values against the efficiency in the absence of the release factors were indicated. The eRF1 concentrations are 0&#x02013;500 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml in (A)&#x02013;(D), and 0&#x02013;200 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml in (E) and (F).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkg789f7"/></fig><table-wrap id="gkg789tb1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Constructs containing natural readthrough or termination signals used in this study</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">Construct</th><th valign="top">Signal</th><th valign="top">Sequence<sup>a</sup></th><th valign="top">GenBank accession no.</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">SIND</td><td valign="top">Sindbis virus readthrough</td><td valign="top">CCAGT<underline>TGA</underline>CTAGACGCGTGCATGCG</td><td valign="top">J02363</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">BNYVV</td><td valign="top">BNYVV readthrough</td><td valign="top">CCGGACAA<underline>TAG</underline>CAATTAGC</td><td valign="top">X04197</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ODC</td><td valign="top">Human ornithine decarboxylase termination</td><td valign="top">ATGTG<underline>TAG</underline>ATAGCACT</td><td valign="top">M16650</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ODC-C</td><td valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td valign="top">ATGTG<underline>TAG</underline>CTAGCACT</td><td valign="top">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">ODC-T</td><td valign="top">&#x000a0;</td><td valign="top">ATGTG<underline>TAG</underline>TTAGCACT</td><td valign="top">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">La</td><td valign="top">Human autoantigen La termination</td><td valign="top">GAGACCAG<underline>TAG</underline>TTTAGTAA</td><td valign="top">J04205</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">FCRB</td><td valign="top">Human low-affinity IgG Fc receptor termination</td><td valign="top">GTATT<underline>TAG</underline>TCTCCATT</td><td valign="top">M28696</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>The stop codon is underlined.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><ack><sec><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>The authors thank S. Hoshino for providing human eRF3 clone, R. Mattes for pUBS520 plasmid and C. Crist for helping preparation of the manuscript. This work was supported in part by grants from the following: the Ministry of Education, Sports, Culture, Science and Technology of Japan (MEXT) to Y.N. and S.M.; the Human Frontier Science Program to Y.N.; the Basic Research for Innovation Biosciences Program of the Bio-oriented Technology Research Advancement Institution (BRAIN) to Y.N.; and the Organization for Pharmaceutical Safety and Research (OPSR) to Y.N. A.L.K. was a post-doctoral fellow of the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science and Z.N.K. was a research fellow of the Research for the Future Program of the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="gkg789c1"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, Ito,K. and Ehrenberg,M. (2000) Mimicry grasps reality in translation termination. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>101</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>352</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10830162</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c2"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kisselev</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name> and Buckingham,R.H. (2000) Translation termination comes of age. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>561</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>567</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11084369</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c3"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> and Ito,K. (2003) Making sense of mimic in translation termination. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12575998</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c4"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kisselev</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Ehrenberg,M. and Frolova,L. (2003) Termination of translation: interplay of m<italic>RNA</italic>, rRNAs and release factors? <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>182</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12514123</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c5"><label>5.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, Uno,M. and Nakamura,Y. (2000) A tripeptide &#x02018;anticodon&#x02019; deciphers stop codons in messenger RNA. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>403</volume>, <fpage>680</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>684</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688208</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c6"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, Mugnier,P., Das,A.K., Webb,H.M., Evans,D.R., Tuite,M.F., Hemmings,B.A. and Barford,D. (2000) The crystal structure of human eukaryotic release factor eRF1-Mechanism of stop codon recognition and peptidyl-tRNA hydrolysis. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>321</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10676813</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c7"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bertram</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, Bell,H.A., Ritchie,D.W., Fullerton,G. and Stansfield,I. (2000) Terminating eukaryote translation: domain 1 of release factor eRF1 functions in stop codon recognition. <source>RNA</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1247</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10999601</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c8"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, Frolova,L., Seit-Nebi,A., Karamyshev,A.L., Kisselev,L. and Nakamura,Y. (2002) Omnipotent decoding potential resides in eukaryotic translation termination factor eRF1 of variant-code organisms and is modulated by the interactions of amino acid sequences within the domain 1. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>99</volume>, <fpage>8494</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8499</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12084909</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c9"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, Blouin,C., Doolittle,W.F. and Roger,A.J. (2002) Convergence and constraint in eukaryotic release factor 1 (eRF1) domain 1: the evolution of stop codon specificity. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>532</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>544</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11788716</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c10"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Chavatte</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Kervestin,S., Favre,A. and Jean-Jean,O. (2003) Stop codon selection in eukaryotic translation termination: comparison of the discriminating potential between human and ciliate eRF1s. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1653</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12660170</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c11"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Freistroffer</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, Pavlov,M., MacDougall,J., Buckingham,R.H. and Ehrenberg,M. (1997) Release factor RF3 in <italic>E.coli</italic> accelerates the dissociation of release factors RF1 and RF2 from the ribosome in a GTP dependent manner. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>4126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9233821</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c12"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, Ito,K. and Isaksson,L.A. (1996) Emerging understanding of translation termination. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>87</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>150</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8861897</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c13"><label>13.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Caskey</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name>, Beaudet,A.L. and Tate,W.P. (1974) Mammalian release factor; <italic>in vitro</italic> assay and purification. <source>Methods Enzymol.</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4604721</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c14"><label>14.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Gesteland</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name> and Atkins,J.F. (1996) Recoding: dynamic reprogramming of translation. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>768</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8811194</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c15"><label>15.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Wolin</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name> and Walter,P. (1988) Ribosome pausing and stacking during translation of a eukaryotic mRNA. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>3559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3569</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2850168</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c16"><label>16.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name> and Mannering,S.A. (1996) Three, four or more: the translational stop signal at length. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8858577</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c17"><label>17.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Craigen</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name> and Caskey,C.T. (1986) Expression of peptide chain release factor 2 requires high-efficiency frameshift. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>322</volume>, <fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>275</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3736654</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c18"><label>18.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Adamski</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name>, Donly,B.C. and Tate,W.P. (1993) Competition between frameshifting, termination and suppression at the frameshift site in the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> release factor-2 mRNA. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>5074</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5078</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7504811</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c19"><label>19.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Drugeon</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, Jean-Jean,O., Frolova,L., Le Goff,X., Philippe,M., Kisselev,L. and Haenni,A.L. (1997) Eukaryotic release factor 1 (eRF1) abolishes readthrough and competes with suppressor tRNAs at all three termination codons in messenger RNA. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>2254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2258</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9171074</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c20"><label>20.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Murakami,Y. and Matsufuji,S. (1996) Ornithine decarboxylase antizyme: a novel type of regulatory protein. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8848835</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c21"><label>21.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>I.P.</given-names></name>, Matsufuji,S., Murakami,Y., Gesteland,R.F. and Atkins,J.F. (2000) Conservation of polyamine regulation by translational frameshifting from yeast to mammals. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1907</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1917</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10775274</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c22"><label>22.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>I.P.</given-names></name>, Gesteland,R.F. and Atkins,J.F. (2000) Antizyme expression: a subversion of triplet decoding, which is remarkably conserved by evolution, is a sensor for an autoregulatory circuit. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>3185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10954585</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c23"><label>23.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Coffino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> (2001) Regulation of cellular polyamines by antizyme. <source>Nature Rev. Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11265248</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c24"><label>24.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, Matsufuji,S. and Hayashi,S. (1992) Cloning and characterization of a rat gene encoding ornithine decarboxylase antizyme. <source>Gene</source>, <volume>113</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>197</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1572540</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c25"><label>25.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Rom</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> and Kahana,C. (1994) Polyamines regulate the expression of ornithine decarboxylase antizyme <italic>in vitro</italic> by inducing ribosomal frame-shifting. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>3959</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3963</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8171019</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c26"><label>26.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Matsufuji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Matsufuji,T., Miyazaki,Y., Murakami,Y., Atkins,J.F., Gesteland,R.F. and Hayashi,S. (1995) Autoregulatory frameshifting in decoding mammalian ornithine decarboxylase antizyme. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7813017</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c27"><label>27.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Matsufuji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Matsufuji,T., Wills,N.M., Gesteland,R.F. and Atkins,J.F. (1996) Reading two bases twice: mammalian antizyme frameshifting in yeast. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1360</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1370</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8635469</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c28"><label>28.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoshino</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Miyazawa,H., Enomoto,T., Hanaoka,F., Kikuchi,Y., Kikuchi,A. and Ui,M. (1989) A human homologue of the yeast GST1 gene codes for a GTP-binding protein and is expressed in a proliferation-dependent manner in mammalian cells. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>3807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3814</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2511002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c29"><label>29.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhouravleva</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, Frolova,L., Le Goff,X., Le Guellec,R., Inge-Vechtomov,S., Kisselev,L. and Philippe,M. (1995) Termination of translation in eukaryotes is governed by two interacting polypeptide chain release factors, eRF1 and eRF3. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>4065</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4072</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7664746</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c30"><label>30.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, Ebihara,K. and Nakamura,Y. (1998) The stretch of C-terminal acidic amino acids of translational release factor eRF1 is a primary binding site for eRF3 of fission yeast. <source>RNA</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>958</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>972</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9701287</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c31"><label>31.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Karamyshev</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name>, Karamysheva,Z.N., Ito,K., Matsufuji,S. and Nakamura,Y. (1999) Overexpression and purification of recombinant eRF1 proteins of rabbit and <italic>Tetrahymena thermophila</italic>. <source>Biochemistry</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>1391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1400</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10648963</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c32"><label>32.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Mattes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (2001) The production of improved tissue-type plasminogen activator in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. <source>Semin. Thromb. Hemost.</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>336</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11547355</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c33"><label>33.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Yokogawa,T., Fujii,I., Asahara,H., Inokuchi,H. and Nishikawa,K. (1998) Co-expression of yeast amber suppressor tRNA<sup>Tyr</sup> and tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: possibility to expand the genetic code. <source>J. Biochem.</source>, <volume>124</volume>, <fpage>1065</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1068</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9832608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c34"><label>34.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Yokogawa,T. and Nishikawa,K. (2001) Changing the amino acid specificity of yeast tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase by genetic engineering. <source>J. Biochem.</source>, <volume>130</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11530018</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c35"><label>35.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Frolova</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Le Goff,X., Zhouravleva,G., Davydova,E., Philippe,M. and Kisselev,L. (1996) Eukaryotic polypeptide chain release factor eRF3 is an eRF1- and ribosome-dependent guanosine triphosphatase. <source>RNA</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>341</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8634914</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c36"><label>36.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bourne</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name>, Sanders,D.A. and McCormick,F. (1991) The GTPase superfamily: conserved structure and molecular mechanism. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>349</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>127</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1898771</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c37"><label>37.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, Ito,K., Matsumura,K., Kawazu,Y. and Ebihara,K. (1995) Regulation of translation termination: conserved structural motifs in bacterial and eukaryotic polypeptide release factors. <source>Biochem. Cell Biol.</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>1113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8722028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c38"><label>38.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name>, Stockwell,P.A., Trotman,C.N. and Tate,W.P. (1990) Sequence analysis suggests that tetra-nucleotides signal the termination of protein synthesis in eukaryotes. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>6339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2123028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c39"><label>39.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, Phillips-Jones,M.K., Watson,F.J. and Hill,L.S. (1993) Codon context effects on nonsense suppression in human cells. <source>Biochem. Soc. Trans</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>846</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>851</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8132079</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c40"><label>40.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>McCaughan</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name>, Brown,C.M., Dalphin,M.E., Berry,M.J. and Tate,W.P. (1995) Translational termination efficiency in mammals is influenced by the base following the stop codon. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>92</volume>, <fpage>5431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7777525</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c41"><label>41.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Phillips-Jones</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name>, Hill,L.S., Atkinson,J. and Martin,R. (1995) Context effects on misreading and suppression at UAG codons in human cells. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>6593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6600</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8524224</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c42"><label>42.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and Rice,C.M. (1993) The signal for translational readthrough of a UGA codon in Sindbis virus RNA involves a single cytidine residue immediately downstream of the termination codon. <source>J. Virol.</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>5062</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5067</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8331741</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c43"><label>43.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> and Grimm,M. (2001) Misreading of termination codons in eukaryotes by natural nonsense suppressor tRNAs. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>4767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4782</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11726686</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c44"><label>44.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ebihara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> and Nakamura,Y. (1999) C-terminal interaction of translational release factors eRF1 and eRF3 of fission yeast: G-domain uncoupled binding and the role of conserved amino acids. <source>RNA</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>739</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>750</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10376874</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c45"><label>45.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Frolova</surname><given-names>L.Y.</given-names></name>, Merkulova,T.I. and Kisselev,L.L. (2000) Translation termination in eukaryotes: polypeptide release factor eRF1 is composed of functionally and structurally distinct domains. <source>RNA</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>390</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10744022</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c46"><label>46.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Pavlov</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name>, Freistroffer,D., MacDougall,J., Buckingham,R.H. and Ehrenberg,M. (1997) Fast recycling of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ribosomes requires both ribosome recycling factor (RRF) and release factor RF3. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>4134</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4141</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9233822</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c47"><label>47.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> and Ito,K. (1998) How protein reads the stop codon and terminates translation. <source>Genes Cells</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c48"><label>48.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, McClendon,V., Bonetti,B. and Bedwell,D.M. (1994) Premature translation termination mutations are efficiently suppressed in a highly conserved region of yeast Ste6p, a member of the ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter family. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>269</volume>, <fpage>17802</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17808</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7517933</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkg789c49"><label>49.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonetti</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, Fu,L., Moon,J. and Bedwell,D.M. (1995) The efficiency of translation termination is determined by a synergistic interplay between upstream and downstream sequences in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>251</volume>, <fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7650736</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 