<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PONE-RA-02877R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0002076</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Immunology/Autoimmunity</subject><subject>Immunology/Leukocyte Signaling and Gene Expression</subject><subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology/Type 1 Diabetes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>High Distribution of CD40 and TRAF2 in Th40 T Cell Rafts Leads to Preferential Survival of this Auto-Aggressive Population in Autoimmunity</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Autoaggressive T Cell Survival</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vaitaitis</surname><given-names>Gisela M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>David H.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>The Department of Medicine and Webb-Waring Institute, University of Colorado Denver, Denver, Colorado, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kanellopoulos</surname><given-names>Jean</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University Paris Sud, France</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>David.Wagner@uchsc.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: DW GV. Performed the experiments: GV. Analyzed the data: GV. Wrote the paper: GV.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e2076</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2008</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Vaitaitis, Wagner Jr. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>CD40&#x02013;CD154 interactions have proven critical in autoimmunity, with the identification of CD4<sup>lo</sup>CD40<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells (Th40 cells) as harboring an autoaggressive T cell population shedding new insights into those disease processes. Th40 cells are present at contained levels in non-autoimmune individuals but are significantly expanded in autoimmunity. Th40 cells are necessary and sufficient in transferring type 1 diabetes in mouse models. However, little is known about CD40 signaling in T cells and whether there are differences in that signaling and subsequent outcome depending on disease conditions. When CD40 is engaged, CD40 and TNF-receptor associated factors, TRAFs, become associated with lipid raft microdomains. Dysregulation of T cell homeostasis is emerging as a major contributor to autoimmune disease and thwarted apoptosis is key in breaking homeostasis.</p></sec><sec><title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title><p>Cells were sorted into CD4<sup>hi</sup> and CD4<sup>lo</sup> (Th40 cells) then treated and assayed either as whole or fractionated cell lysates. Protein expression was assayed by western blot and Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA-binding activity by electrophoretic mobility shifts. We demonstrate here that autoimmune NOD Th40 cells have drastically exaggerated expression of CD40 on a per-cell-basis compared to non-autoimmune BALB/c. Immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic>, untreated Th40 cells from NOD mice have high levels of CD40 and TRAF2 associated with the raft microdomain while Th40 cells from NOR and BALB/c mice do not. CD40 engagement of Th40 cells induces Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA-binding activity and anti-apoptotic Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expression in all three mouse strains. However, only in NOD Th40 cells is anti-apoptotic cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> induced which leads to preferential survival and proliferation. Importantly, CD40 engagement rescues NOD Th40 cells from Fas-induced death.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions/Significance</title><p>CD40 may act as a switch between life and death promoting signals and NOD Th40 cells are poised for survival via this switch. This may explain how they expand in autoimmunity to thwart T cell homeostasis.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The role of CD40&#x02013;CD154 interactions in autoimmune diseases <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Toubi1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Kobata1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref> including type I diabetes (T1D) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Vaitaitis1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Balasa1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>, collagen induced arthritis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Munroe1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Durie1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>, systemic lupus erythamotosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Quezada1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wang1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, and autoimmune thyroiditis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Yu1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>, has been well documented. CD40 (tnfrsf5) belongs to the TNF-receptor family and when CD40 is engaged it becomes associated with lipid rafts to interact with the adaptor molecules, TNF receptor associated factors (TRAFs), for downstream signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Xie1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. CD40 expression has traditionally been associated with B cells, dendritic cells and macrophages (antigen presenting cells, APC) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-vanKooten1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref> but has proven to be more ubiquitous and now has been described on T cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Munroe1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-vanKooten1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. In autoimmunity there is an expansion of a CD40-expressing T cell subset that also is characterized by its low surface-expression of CD4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid2">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>While the consequences of CD40 signals in APC have been extensively studied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-vanKooten1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Andrade1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Bishop1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref> little is known about the outcome of CD40 signals in T cells. Specifically, do differences exist in the signaling outcome between autoimmune and non-autoimmune conditions? We previously demonstrated that CD40 engagement of a CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>CD40<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cell clone, BDC2.5, induced rapid activation of Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA binding activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> as well as induction of RAG1 and RAG2 expression, the proteins necessary for TCR expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Vaitaitis1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. Recently it was shown that engagement of CD40 on T cells can serve a costimulatory function <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Munroe1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>. The CD4<sup>lo</sup>CD40<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells, which we termed Th40 cells, are detected in diabetic and prediabetic NOD mice as well as in non-autoimmune controls <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. Interestingly, the Th40 cell subset is greatly expanded under autoimmune conditions and is necessary and sufficient in diabetes transfers from the non-obese diabetic (NOD) mouse to NOD.<italic>scid</italic> animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. The expansion seen in autoimmune prone animals can be prevented by blocking CD40&#x02013;CD154 interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. While the identical subset is present in non-autoimmune subjects, it remains contained at lower percentages of total lymphocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Although the cause for peripheral T cell autoaggression in autoimmune disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Lafaille1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Liblau1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref> is not fully understood, dysregulation of T cell control is emerging as a major contributor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Sakaguchi1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Setoguchi1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>. Specifically, loss of homeostasis between regulatory T cells (T<sub>reg</sub>) and effector T cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Sakaguchi1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Setoguchi1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>, including potentially autoaggressive Th40 cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, is taking center stage. Homeostatic regulation of T cells is dependent on apoptosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Strasser1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Kroemer1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref> and thwarted apoptosis of peripheral effector T cells is a key element in autoimmunity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Strasser1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>. For example, mice deficient in Fas - FasL develop autoimmunity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Suda1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>. Events, such as engagement of death receptors ( e.g. Fas, TRAIL, TNF-R; i.e. extrinsic pathway) or loss of mitochondrial potential followed by release of cytochrome c (i.e. intrinsic pathway), can lead to apoptosis. The Bcl protein family (including anti-apoptotic Bcl-2 and Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> and pro-apoptotic Bax and Bak) is involved in pro- and anti-apoptotic events in the intrinsic pathway while cFLIP, a homolog of caspase-8 and FADD that can act as a caspase-8 decoy, is involved in the extrinsic pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Strasser1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Kroemer1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Thome1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Bortner1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>. cFLIP can be both pro- and anti-apoptotic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Boatright1">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref> but it can be cleaved to generate anti-apoptotic cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> that interacts with TRAF2 and induces Nf-&#x003ba;B activation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Kataoka1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>. The two apoptotic pathways also converge as it was shown that Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expression affects the extrinsic pathway partly by inducing cFLIP expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wang2">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Because we demonstrated a causal relationship of CD40&#x02013;CD154 interactions leading to expansion of potentially autoaggressive Th40 cells <italic>in vivo</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, we investigated whether CD40-signals directly to the T cell can be responsible for such an expansion. Therefore we compared CD40 expression and signaling outcomes between autoimmune and non-autoimmune conditions as well as between Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells within those conditions.</p><p>Here we show that Th40 cells from NOD, NOR and BALB/c mice have differences in CD40 protein expression levels as well as differences in CD40 and TRAF2 association with the raft microdomain. Immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic> NOD Th40 cells are poised for CD40 signaling by having high amounts of CD40 and TRAF2 associated with the raft microdomain and induce high levels of Nf-&#x003ba;B activation as well as anti-apoptotic cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> and Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> protein expression in response to CD40 engagement. CD40 engagement of NOD Th40 cells increases survival and induces proliferation. CD40 engagement also rescues those cells from Fas-induced death. CD40-induced cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> expression in NOD Th40 cells persists when Fas is simultaneously engaged. The same subsets from non-autoimmune NOR and BALB/c mice exhibit a difference in total levels of CD40 compared to each other but they both induce Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expression. However, neither NOR nor BALB/c T cells induce cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> expression or proliferate in response to CD40 engagement. Therefore it is possible that CD40, via cFLIP<sub>p43</sub>, acts as a switch between Fas-induced cell death and survival/proliferation of these cells in autoimmunity. The results, together with our previous report that <italic>in vivo</italic> blockade of CD40&#x02013;CD154 interaction in NOD prevents the expansion of potentially autoaggressive Th40 cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, suggest that a fundamental difference in CD40 expression and signaling leads to dysregulation of peripheral T cell control and may be a major cause for disease progression in autoimmunity.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Magnetic CD4 sort effectively purifies splenic cells into CD4<sup>lo</sup> (Th40 cells) and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells</title><p>We have previously purified CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells by flow cytometric sorting <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Vaitaitis1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. However, this method is costly and time consuming which lead us to develope a magnetic sort (detailed in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">methods</xref> section) that yielded CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells. We determined levels of T cell associated molecules in the CD4<sup>lo</sup> population. CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells from both NOD and BALB/c mice expressed CD4 and CD3 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s001">Figure S1A&#x02013;D</xref>). However, portions of those proteins were contained intracellularly (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s001">Figure S1A&#x02013;D</xref>). Additionally, CD4<sup>lo</sup> cells from both strains of mice expressed CD28 at similar mean fluorescence intensities as CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s001">Figure S1E</xref>). The CD4<sup>lo</sup> cells were further categorized as T cells by staining and RT-PCR for TCR. CD4<sup>lo</sup> cells from NOD and BALB/c mice exhibited expression of an array of both TCR&#x003b2; and TCR&#x003b1; molecules (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s002">Figure S2A and B</xref>). Additionally, CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells express IFN&#x003b3; when activated (data not shown).</p><p>To address the possibility of B cell contamination the B cell specific proteins CD19 and CD21 were stained on CD4<sup>lo</sup>, CD4<sup>hi</sup>, and depleted cells (MHCII<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>, CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>, and CD25<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> cells; removed by sorting). The CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cell populations exhibited very low B cell contamination (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s003">Figure S3A</xref>). As expected, the majority of the depleted cells (MHCII<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>CD25<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>) expressed CD19 and CD21 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s003">Figure S3A</xref>). We further determined levels of CD11b and CD11c which are mainly associated with monocytes/macrophages and dendritic cells, respectively, but have also been shown to be expressed by subsets of T cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Huleatt1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Kawakami1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>. A small portion of CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells from both NOD and BALB/c expressed CD11b (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s003">Figure S3B</xref>). In addition, when cultured in tissue culture flasks the CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells take on a morphology like that of T cell clones and the size of CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells, when activated, never increases like that of activated antigen presenting cells (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>NOD CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells express high levels of CD40</title><p>We have shown that CD4<sup>lo</sup>CD40<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells are expanded in autoimmune prone mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> as well as in human T1D patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid2">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>. Therefore we determined whether there is also a difference on a per-cell basis in CD40 expression in those cells comparing autoimmune prone NOD to non-autoimmune BALB/c and NOR mice. NOR mice are diabetes resistant but contain greater than 90&#x00025; of the NOD genome, including the unique IA<sup>g7</sup> MHCII <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Serreze1">&#x0005b;39&#x0005d;</xref>. Cells from NOD, NOR, and BALB/c mice were sorted into CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells. In immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic> CD4<sup>lo</sup> cells from NOD mice CD40 expression was 12-fold higher than that in the same subset from BALB/c mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g001">Figure 1A and C</xref>) and 2-fold higher than that of NOR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g001">Figure 1A&#x02013;C</xref>; note that the standard in the NOR experiment (B) is more intense than the standard in the NOD and BALB/c experiment (A)). CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from all three mouse strains expressed CD40 at a lower level than CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells but, by direct comparison, CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOD mice had higher CD40 levels than NOR and BALB/c CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells (about 2.5-fold; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g001">Figure 1A&#x02013;C</xref>). When CD40 was engaged for 20 hrs, both populations from NOD, BALB/c, and NOR mice induced an increase in CD40 expression demonstrating a positive feedback loop.</p><fig id="pone-0002076-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0002076.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>NOD Th40 cells express high levels of CD40 compared to BALB/c.</title><p>Immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic>, magnetically sorted Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from age matched 8&#x02013;12 week-old female NOD (euglycemic), BALB/c or NOR were either immediately lysed (Imm. <italic>ex-vivo</italic>) or cultured overnight in the absence (UN) or presence of CD40 engagement (CD40) then lysed. Whole cell extracts, 5 &#x000b5;g, were analyzed by western blot for CD40. As an internal standard for loading (std) the membranes were stripped and stained with coomassie blue and a representative band is shown. (A) Western blot for CD40 in Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOD and BALB/c. (B) Western blot for CD40 in Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOR. (C) Graph representing the data in A and B. Data in C are represented as mean&#x000b1;SEM from at least 3 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0002076.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>CD40 signals aid in survival of NOD Th40 cells <italic>in vitro</italic></title><p>Th40 cells are expanded in autoimmune mouse strains <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref> and that expansion is prevented in NOD mice by blocking CD40&#x02013;CD154 interactions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. Therefore we determined whether CD40 signals lead directly to increased survival of Th40 cells <italic>in vitro</italic> and whether there is a difference between autoimmune and non-autoimmune derivation of the Th40 cells.</p><p>Sorted Th40 cells (CD4<sup>lo</sup>) and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells, from spleens of NOD, NOR and BALB/c mice, were cultured in the absence or presence of CD40-, Fas- or (CD40&#x0002b;Fas)-engagement then absolute numbers of live cells were counted after 1, 2, and 3 days of culture. It was evident that CD40 engaged NOD Th40 cells, compared to untreated, survived more readily over 3 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). In fact, the number of cells doubled. In contrast there was no clear benefit of CD40 engagement in the same population from BALB/c mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). Th40 cells from NOR survived better, compared to untreated, when CD40 engaged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). However, the survival induced by CD40 declined with time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). When Fas was engaged on NOD Th40 cells, cell death was induced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Interestingly, if CD40 was engaged simultaneously with Fas, the Fas-induced death was thwarted, most prominently on day 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2A</xref>; p&#x0003c;0.001, t-test) persisting even 3 days after stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2A</xref>; p&#x0003c;0.05, t-test). Similarly, NOR Th40 cells were rescued from Fas induced death by CD40 engagement but the absolute number of cells from NOD mice that survived was 1.5 times greater than those from NOR mice after 3 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2A and C</xref>). The same type of rescue was not detected in BALB/c Th40 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). In NOD CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells, CD40 engagement led to somewhat increased survival (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2D</xref>). However, this survival was not accompanied by a drastic increase in the number of cells. While there was a CD40-induced rescue from Fas death in the NOD CD4<sup>hi</sup> population on day 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>; p&#x0003c;0.05, t-test), that rescue was not sustained on day 3 (p&#x0003e;0.6, t-test). BALB/c and NOR CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells did not preferentially survive in response to CD40 signals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Fig. 2E and F</xref>). These data demonstrate a crucial CD40 signaling difference, relative to cell survival, in the potentially autoaggressive Th40 cell population between autoimmune and non- autoimmune conditions.</p><fig id="pone-0002076-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0002076.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>CD40 engagement of NOD Th40 cells induces increased survival.</title><p>Sorted Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from age matched 8&#x02013;12 week-old female NOD (euglycemic), NOR or BALB/c were untreated (UN), CD40-crosslinked (CD40), Fas crosslinked (Fas) or (CD40&#x0002b;Fas)-crosslinked ((CD40&#x0002b;Fas)) for 1, 2 and 3 days. Absolute numbers of live cells were counted by trypan blue exclusion. (A) NOD CD4<sup>lo</sup>. (B) BALB/c CD4<sup>lo</sup>. (C) NOR CD4<sup>lo</sup>. (D) NOD CD4<sup>hi</sup>. (E) BALB/c CD4<sup>hi</sup>. (F) NOR CD4<sup>hi</sup>. Data are represented as mean&#x000b1;SEM from 3 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0002076.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Potentially autoaggressive Th40 cells from NOD proliferate in response to CD40 engagement</title><p>Because the NOD Th40 cells readily survived and nearly doubled in numbers in response to CD40 signals <italic>in vitro</italic>, we determined the effect of CD40 engagement on proliferation. Untreated NOD Th40 cells underwent minimal proliferation over 3 days in culture (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, UN). However, when cells were CD40 engaged for 3 days significant proliferation was seen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, CD40). When NOD Th40 cells were Fas engaged, the minimal proliferation seen in untreated cells was reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, compare UN and Fas). When CD40 was engaged simultaneously with Fas, NOD Th40 cells proliferated to the same extent as untreated cells but not to the extent seen with CD40 treatment alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). This demonstrates that although CD40 signals thwarted Fas-induced death, as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">figure 2</xref>, Fas signals ablated the proliferation seen in CD40 stimulated NOD Th40 cells. Unlike T cells from NOD mice, NOR and BALB/c Th40 cells did not proliferate in response to CD40 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g003">Fig. 3</xref>, compare UN and CD40). Additionally, CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOD, but not NOR and BALB/c mice, demonstrated some proliferation in response to CD40 engagement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g003">Fig. 3, CD40</xref>). However, this did not lead to a significant expansion of these cells as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">figure 2</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0002076-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0002076.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>CD40 engagement of NOD Th40 cells induces proliferation.</title><p>Sorted Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from age matched 8&#x02013;12 week-old female NOD (euglycemic), NOR or BALB/c were labelled with CFSE and were then untreated (UN), CD40-crosslinked (CD40), Fas-crosslinked (Fas) or (CD40&#x0002b;Fas)-crosslinked ((CD40&#x0002b;Fas)) for 1, 2 and 3 days. T cell proliferation was assessed by CFSE dilution on day 1 (filled histogram), day2 (solid line) and day 3 (dashed line) in FACS analysis on ungated cells. Percentages represent amount of cells that proliferated on day 3 and are represented as mean&#x000b1;SEM from 3 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0002076.g003"/></fig><p>These data demonstrate that CD40 engagement alone can drive not only survival but also expansion of the potentially autoaggressive Th40 cells in autoimmune NOD, but not in non-autoimmune NOR and BALB/c mice. These intrinsic differences relative to CD40, and now Fas, signaling suggest a mechanism to promote autoimmunity.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>CD40 and TRAF2 raft microdomain distribution is different between autoimmune and non-autoimmune Th40 cells</title><p>When CD40 is engaged on both B and T cells it becomes associated with lipid raft microdomains to interact with adaptor molecules, TRAFs, for downstream signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Munroe1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Xie1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. Therefore we determined whether CD40 became associated with the detergent-insoluble raft fraction in the Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOD, NOR, and BALB/c mice when CD40 was engaged. Strikingly, a large amount of CD40 was associated with the raft fraction in immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic> NOD Th40 cells compared to only a small amount in Th40 cells from NOR and BALB/c (insoluble fraction; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). When CD40 was engaged, this association increased slightly in NOD Th40 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). In immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic> CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOD and BALB/c mice, association of some CD40 with the raft fraction was observed while in the same subset from NOR mice CD40 was not detected in this fraction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). CD40 engagement of CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from both NOD and BALB/c mice sustained the association of CD40 with the raft fraction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). These data demonstrate that, given the immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic> data, NOD Th40 cells likely are CD40 engaged <italic>in vivo</italic>. Therefore these cells may be poised for survival and proliferation should they encounter death promoting signals such as Fas stimulation.</p><fig id="pone-0002076-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0002076.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic> NOD Th40 cells have CD40 and TRAF2 associated with rafts.</title><p>Sorted Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from age matched 8&#x02013;12 week-old female NOD (euglycemic), BALB/c or NOR were immediately lysed (Imm. <italic>ex-vivo</italic>) or untreated (UN), CD40-crosslinked (CD40), Fas-crosslinked (Fas) or (CD40&#x0002b;Fas)-crosslinked ((CD40&#x0002b;Fas)) for 5 hours then soluble (S) and insoluble (I) fractions were prepared. CD40 levels in Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> (A and B respectively) and TRAF2 levels in Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> (C and D respectively) were analyzed in western blots. CD40 was analyzed first then the membranes were stripped and TRAF2 was analyzed. As internal loading standard (std) membranes were stripped and stained with coomassie blue and a representative band of the same size from each membrane is shown. Data are representative of 3 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0002076.g004"/></fig><p>TRAFs, including TRAF2, function as CD40 signal adaptor molecules in both B and T cells and associate with lipid raft microdomains upon CD40 stimulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Munroe1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Xie1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Munroe2">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref>. Therefore we determined if TRAF2 was present in the raft fraction, setting the stage for CD40 signaling. TRAF2 was strongly associated with the raft fraction in NOD Th40 cells and remained associated during culture regardless of stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>). However, in NOR and BALB/c Th40 cells, only a small amount of TRAF2 was associated with the raft fraction immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>). In CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from all three mouse strains smaller amounts of TRAF2 associated with the raft fraction compared to that seen in the Th40 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g004">Fig. 4D compared to C</xref>). NOD CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells had higher amounts compared with NOR and BALB/c CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g004">Fig. 4D</xref>). This demonstrates that NOD Th40 cells have the signaling machinery necessary to transmit CD40 signals associated with the raft microdomain immediately <italic>ex-vivo</italic>. This could be due to the high availability of CD154 in autoimmunity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Toubi1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Solanilla1">&#x0005b;41&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Jinchuan1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref> that can constantly engage CD40 on these T cells.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>CD40 engagement induces increased, Nf-&#x003ba;B dependent, expression of Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> in Th40 cells but only NOD Th40 cells induce cFLIP<sub>p43</sub></title><p>Increased expression of anti-apoptotic factors such as Bcl-X<sub>L</sub>, which affects the intrinsic pathway, have been implicated in decreased apoptosis. Autoimmune diseases characteristically maintain T cells that are resistant to cell death <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Issazadeh1">&#x0005b;45&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-LamhamediCherradi1">&#x0005b;47&#x0005d;</xref>. Cleaved cFLIP (cFLIP<sub>p43</sub>) is protective in the extrinsic pathway and interacts with TRAF2 to induce Nf-&#x003ba;B activation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Kataoka1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>. Given that NOD Th40 cells readily survive in response to CD40 engagement we examined whether there were differences in Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> and cFLIP expression between Th40 cells from NOD, NOR and BALB/c mice.</p><p>A basal level of Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> was apparent in both NOD and BALB/c, but not in NOR, Th40 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Fig. 5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s004">Figure S4</xref>). CD40 engagement induced high Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> protein expression in NOD as well as NOR Th40 cells. In BALB/c Th40 cells more modest levels of Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> were induced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Fig. 5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s004">Figure S4</xref>). CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOD and NOR mice induced fairly high expression of Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> in response to CD40 engagement although not as high as those of the respective Th40 cell subsets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Fig. 5A and B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s004">Figure S4</xref>). Meanwhile, BALB/c CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells induced only low levels of Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Fig. 5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s004">Figure S4</xref>). Interestingly, the CD40-induced Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expression was sustained in both cell subsets from all three mouse strains even when Fas was engaged simultaneously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Fig. 5A and B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s004">Figure S4</xref>). Additionally, NOR CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells induced low levels of pro-apoptotic Bcl-X<sub>S</sub> in response to Fas engagement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Figure 5B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0002076-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0002076.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>CD40 engagement induces high Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> and cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> expression in NOD Th40 cells.</title><p>Sorted Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from age matched 8&#x02013;12 week-old female NOD (euglycemic), BALB/c or NOR were untreated (UN), CD40-crosslinked (CD40), Fas-crosslinked (Fas) or (CD40&#x0002b;Fas)-crosslinked (CD40&#x0002b;Fas) for 20 hours. Whole cell lysates from CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells (A and C) or CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells (B and D) were analyzed in western blot for Bcl-X or cFLIP. As internal loading standard (std), membranes were stripped and stained with coomassie blue and a representative band of the same size from each membrane is shown. Data are representative of 3 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0002076.g005"/></fig><p>When examining cFLIP levels, NOD Th40 cells exhibited a basal expression of cFLIP<sub>p43</sub>, the activated, protective form of cFLIP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). When CD40 engaged, NOD Th40 cells induced higher expression of cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> and this higher expression was sustained with simultaneous Fas engagement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). In NOR and BALB/c Th40 cells, however, only cFLIP<sub>L</sub> was expressed and none of the treatments induced cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). In CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOD, NOR and BALB/c mice, a low basal level of cFLIP<sub>L</sub> was observed but only in NOD CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells was cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> expression induced in response to CD40 engagement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">Figure 5D</xref>). The induced cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> expression was not sustained when Fas was simultaneously engaged.</p><p>The data demonstrate that CD40 successfully signals to both Th40 and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cell subsets in NOD, NOR, and BALB/c mice to induce Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expression. That induced expression appears independent of Fas signals. In the highest expressors, i.e. Th40 cells from NOD and NOR, Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expression appears to protect against Fas induced cell death. However, over time NOD Th40 cells appear to survive more readily (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g002">Figure 2</xref>) perhaps due to the high levels of induced cFLIPp<sub>43</sub>. In one of the moderate expressors of Bcl-X<sub>L</sub>, i.e. CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOD, CD40 engagement initially induces rescue from Fas death. However, with time and with CD40 induced cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> expression being all but thwarted when Fas was engaged simultaneously, the benefit is no longer there. NOR CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells are also moderate Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expressors but are not rescued from Fas death by CD40 engagement. This is perhaps due to that Bcl-X<sub>S</sub>, a pro-apoptotic protein, is induced by Fas engagement in the NOR CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells. Relative to proliferation it appears that only those cells capable of inducing cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> expression, i.e. NOD Th40 cells and to a lesser extent NOD CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells, are able to proliferate.</p><p>Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> and cFLIP expression are dependent on Nf-&#x003ba;B activation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Kreuz1">&#x0005b;48&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Khoshnan1">&#x0005b;49&#x0005d;</xref>. Since we have shown that CD40 engagement activates Nf-&#x003ba;B in a T cell clone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> we determined whether CD40 could induce Nf-&#x003ba;B activation in primary T cells as well. CD40 engagement induced Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA-binding activity in primary Th40 cells from both NOD and BALB/c mice although the induction was greater in NOD Th40 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). The CD40-induced Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA-binding activity in NOD Th40 cells was sustained when Fas was simultaneously engaged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). Interestingly, in BALB/c Th40 cells, Fas engagement blocked most of the CD40-induced Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA-binding activity. CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from both BALB/c and NOD mice demonstrated little or no Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA-binding activity in response to CD40 engagement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). When an Nf-&#x003ba;B inhibitor, BAY 11-7082 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Zhu1">&#x0005b;50&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Pierce1">&#x0005b;51&#x0005d;</xref>, was included during the different treatments all Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA-binding activity was abolished regardless of treatment and cell population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g006">Figure 6A</xref>, &#x0201c;&#x0002b;BAY&#x0201d;).</p><fig id="pone-0002076-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0002076.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>CD40 induces Nf-kB activation in Th40 cells and Nf-kB inhibition ablates CD40-induced Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> and cFLIP<sub>p43</sub>.</title><p>Sorted Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from age matched 8&#x02013;12 week-old female NOD (euglycemic) or BALB/c were untreated (UN), CD40-crosslinked (CD40), Fas crosslinked (Fas) or (CD40&#x0002b;Fas)-crosslinked ((CD40&#x0002b;Fas)) for 20 hours in the absence/presence of the Nf-kB inhibitor BAY 11-7082 (BAY). (A) Nuclear extracts were analyzed in EMSA for Nf-kB DNA-binding activity using a consensus Nf-kB oligonucleotide. As controls cold Nf-kB or AP1 oligonucleotides were used in competiotion reactions. Free oligonucleotide is not shown. Data represent 3 separate experiments. (B) Whole cell lysates from BAY 11-7082 treated NOD (B and D) or BALB/c (C and E) were analyzed in western blot for Bcl-X or cFLIP. As internal loading standard (std), membranes were stripped and stained with coomassie blue and a representative band of the same size from each membrane is shown. Data represent 3 separate experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0002076.g006"/></fig><p>We analyzed the levels of Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> and cFLIP in the presence of the Nf-kB inhibitor. In the presence of BAY 11-7082 neither cell population from NOD or BALB/c mice expressed Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g006">Figure 6B and C</xref>). Likewise, cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> expression was completely abolished in the presence of BAY 11-7082 while the long form of cFLIP, cFLIP<sub>L</sub>, was more readily expressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g006">Figure 6D and E</xref>). This indicates that Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA-binding activity is necessary for the expression of survival proteins in response to CD40 engagement. Additionally, given the strong expression of TRAF2 in the raft microdomain of NOD Th40 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g004">Figure 4</xref>), the possibility for interaction of induced cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> with TRAF2 and further activation of Nf-&#x003ba;B, as has been demonstrated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Kataoka1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>, arises.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Recently, reports have focused on the importance of T cell homeostasis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Sakaguchi1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Thornton1">&#x0005b;52&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Salomon1">&#x0005b;56&#x0005d;</xref> in protection against autoimmunity. Although the focus has been mainly on regulatory T cells, we have demonstrated the importance of the ratio of potentially autoaggressive Th40 cells to T<sub>reg</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. In fact, we determined that an intricate balance between T<sub>regs</sub> and potentially pathogenic Th40 cells must be maintained to prevent autoimmunity and this process is tightly associated with CD40 signaling <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid3">&#x0005b;57&#x0005d;</xref>. Autoimmune prone animals, and incidentally human T1D patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid2">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, have a substantial abundance of peripheral Th40 cells which are highly pathogenic in autoimmune conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. However, the disrupted homeostasis in autoimmune prone NOD mice can be prevented by blocking CD40&#x02013;CD154 interaction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Balasa1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>. In the present study we further define differences in this dyad by showing that not only are there differences in CD40 expression levels between autoimmune and non-autoimmune conditions but the microdomain distribution of CD40, as well as of the signaling adaptor molecule TRAF2, is different in the potentially autoaggressive Th40 cell subset. The CD40 signaling outcome is consequently different between autoimmune and non-autoimmune conditions. Clearly, with only the need for CD40 engagement, the Th40 cells from autoimmune prone NOD mice are poised for survival and proliferation via activation of Nf-&#x003ba;B DNA-binding activity and expression of high levels of anti-apoptotic proteins Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> and cFLIP<sub>p43</sub>.</p><p>A striking finding is that the CD40 engaged NOD and NOR Th40 cells could thwart Fas-induced death. However, only the NOD Th40 cells survived <underline>and</underline> proliferated. Therefore it is possible that CD40-induced Nf-&#x003ba;B activation could ultimately, via induction of Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expression and via decoy activity and further Nf-&#x003ba;B activation by cFLIP<sub>p43</sub>, keep the culprit autoaggressive Th40 cells resistant to death in autoimmunity and further allow expansion of this T cell subset. Interestingly, it was shown that NOR splenic T cells depleted of T<sub>reg</sub> transferred diabetes to NOD.scid recipients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid3">&#x0005b;57&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Ott1">&#x0005b;58&#x0005d;</xref> and we have recently transferred diabetes to NOD.scid recipients using NOR Th40 cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid3">&#x0005b;57&#x0005d;</xref>. Therefore it appears that NOD and NOR Th40 cells share the CD40 hyperexpression and pathogenic TCRs that predisposes them to become autoaggressive. However, the molecular environment in which they exist differs, as shown here, to favor CD40 signaling in NOD Th40 cells which poises them for survival and proliferation by constantly having CD40 and TRAF2 mobilized to the raft. Once the predisposed Th40 cells from NOR mice are transferred into the autoimmune environment, however, they are triggered to proliferate and become autoaggressive although at a much slower pace than the same subset from NOD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid3">&#x0005b;57&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>While the CD40 receptor on Th40 cells from non-autoimmune BALB/c mice is funtional, as demonstrated by the induction of Nf-kB activation as well as Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expression, it was not capable of induction of resistance to Fas death or of inducing proliferation. This demonstrates clear mechanistic differences relative to CD40-signaling in autoimmune versus non-autoimmune conditions. Additionally, it indicates that the CD40-signaling pathway that leads to cFLIP<sub>p43</sub> expression could be targeted to control the Th40 cells in autoimmunity.</p><p>Genetic linkage studies do not indicate CD40 as a candidate gene in autoimmunity. However, the present data demonstrate that conditions prevailing in autoimmunity lead to hyperexpression of CD40 on the potentially autoaggressive Th40 cell subset. This in turn leads to alterations in the signaling of CD40 and ultimately in life-and-death decisions in those cells. It is possible that a genetic deviation in a different gene leads to those conditions and that CD40 therefore by proxy is a culprit in autoimmune disease.</p><p>Intrinsic T<sub>reg</sub>, i.e. specifically described as CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>CD25<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>foxP3<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Sakaguchi1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Thornton1">&#x0005b;52&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Salomon1">&#x0005b;56&#x0005d;</xref>, which prevent autoimmune disease, are expanded in NOD mice only after blocking CD40&#x02013;CD154 interaction <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. This together with the present data suggests that homeostasis, specifically some maintained balance between T<sub>reg</sub> and potentially autoaggressive Th40 cells, can be CD40 regulated in autoimmune mice. Given the apparent hyperexpression of CD40 on Th40 cells and the increased availability of CD154 in autoimmune conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Toubi1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Solanilla1">&#x0005b;41&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Jinchuan1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>, homeostasis can readily be broken as has been demonstrated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Waid1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. The specific conditions leading to the observed differences are being studied and may hold clues to how to control the culprit T cells in autoimmunity and provide novel treatments and prevention of autoimmune disease.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Mice</title><p>NOD, NOR, and BALB/c mice from Jackson Laboratories, Bar Harbor, Maine, were maintained under pathogen-free conditions at the Webb-Waring Institute, University of Colorado HSC, IACUC-approved facility. The NOD colony consistently achieves &#x0003e;90&#x00025; diabetes in females by the age of 18 weeks. All experiments were carried out under IACUC-approved protocol number 55802006(04)1E.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Antibodies and reagents</title><p>Anti-CD40 (sc-975) and anti-Bcl- X<sub>L/S</sub> (sc-634) were from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc., Santa Cruz, California, and anti-cFLIP (F9800) from Sigma, St. Louis, MO. Biotinylated anti-Fas (Jo-2) was from BD Biosciences, San Diego, CA. Biotinylated anti-CD40 antibodies (1C10 and 4F11) were produced in-house. Biotinylated anti-Fas and anti-CD40 (1C10 and 4F11 always used together) antibodies were used at 5 &#x000b5;g/ml each followed by 1.0 &#x000b5;g/ml streptavidin to crosslink. NF-&#x003ba;B blocker, BAY 11-7082, was from BIOMOL Research Laboratories, Inc., Plymouth Meeting, PA, and was used at 10 &#x000b5;M. Biotinylated anti-CD25 (7D4) and anti-CD4 (GK1.5) were produced in-house. Anti-CD8-, anti-MHCII-, and streptavidin-conjugated magnetic microbeads were from Miltenyi Biotec Inc., Auburn, California.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>T cell purification and cell culture</title><p>Spleens from age matched female 8&#x02013;12 week old NOD, NOR and BALB/c mice were homogenized in red blood cell lysis buffer (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, Missouri) then pelleted. The cell pellet was resuspended in 1 ml (per original spleen) PBS containing 2&#x00025; BSA and 2 mM EDTA. This buffer was used in all incubations and washes. Biotin-anti-CD25, 1 &#x000b5;g/&#x000b5;l, was added at 20 &#x000b5;l/spleen and incubated, rocking, for 15 minutes at room temperature. Streptavidin-, anti-CD8-, and anti-MHCII-microbeads were added at 20, 40, and 40 &#x000b5;l/spleen, respectively, and then incubated another 15 minutes. Cells were washed once with 10 ml buffer then sorted in &#x0201c;DepleteS&#x0201d; (slow-flow) mode using an autoMACS&#x02122; magnetic cell sorter (Miltenyi Biotec Inc., Auburn, California). Depleted cells (CD25<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup>MHCII<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) were labeled with biotin-anti-CD4, 1 &#x000b5;g/&#x000b5;l, at 40 &#x000b5;l/spleen for 15 minutes then washed once as above. Streptavidin-microbeads, 40 &#x000b5;l/spleen, were added, incubated for another 15 minutes then cells were washed once. Cells were sorted in &#x0201c;Possel&#x0201d; (fast-flow) in autoMACS&#x02122;. Magnetically positive cells were considered CD4<sup>hi</sup> and magnetically negative cells were considered Th40 cells (CD4<sup>lo</sup>CD40<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>). (While Th40 cells are magnetically CD4-negative they do express CD4, predominantly intracellularly, CD3 and TCR (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s001">Figure S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0002076.s002">Figure S2</xref>).) Cells were cultured in DMEM containing 10&#x00025; fetal calf serum and 50 &#x000b5;M &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol. Cells were CD40- and/or Fas-crosslinked using 5 &#x000b5;g/ml each of biotinylated 1C10&#x0002b;4F11 and/or Fas, respectively, followed by 1.0 &#x000b5;g/ml of streptavidin to crosslink.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>T cell survival and proliferation assays</title><p>T cells were purified as described above then cultured in the absence/presence of CD40 crosslinking. After 1, 2, and 3 days live cells were counted by trypan blue exclusion to determine the survival rate. For proliferation assays the cells were labelled with CFSE, 5 &#x000b5;M, crosslinked as above and assayed after 1, 2, and 3 days on a FACSCalibur flowcytometer (BD Biosciences, San Diego, CA) for CFSE dilution.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>EMSA</title><p>Nuclear protein was prepared and assayed as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Wagner2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> on T cells that were purified and cultured as above. For the binding reaction 1.5 &#x000b5;g of nuclear protein was used with a radiolabeled NF-&#x003ba;B consensus oligonucleotide (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI).</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Western blot</title><p>Preparation of detergent-insoluble microdomains (rafts) from equal numbers of Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells from NOD, NOR, and BALB/c was done as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Munroe1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>. Briefly, 1.9&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup> cells were lysed in 50 &#x000b5;l Brij-58 buffer and insoluble matter pelleted. The pellet was then solubilized in 50 &#x000b5;l octylglucopyranoside buffer. The resulting fractions were analyzed in western blots for CD40 and TRAF2 expression (10 &#x000b5;l/lane). Preparation of whole cell lysates from Th40 cells and CD4<sup>hi</sup> cells was done by lysis in buffer (1&#x00025; Triton X-100, 150 mM NaCl, 20 mM Tris, pH 7.5, 2 mM EDTA, 1 &#x000b5;g/ml each aprotinin and leupeptin, 0.4 mM PMSF, 0.4 mM sodium-ortho-vanadate, 0.5 mM DTT) for 10 minutes at room temperature then insoluble debris was pelleted. Bcl-X and cFLIP levels were analyzed by western blot, 10 &#x000b5;g protein/lane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0002076-Vaitaitis1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. As internal loading standard, membranes were stripped and stained with Coomassie Blue R-250. Analysis of band intensities was done with Kodak 1D densitometry analysis software (Eastman Kodak Company, Rochester, New York).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0002076.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>CD4<sup>lo</sup> cells express T cell associated proteins CD4, CD3 and CD28. NOD and BALB/c splenic cells were magnetically sorted into CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> populations as detailed in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">methods</xref> section. (A) CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> cells were either stained immediately after sort (black lines) or cultured overnight then stained for CD4 (dashed lines). Grey-shaded histogram is isotype control. (Staining after overnight culture was done because the CD4-molecule on the CD4<sup>hi</sup> cells was somewhat blocked for stain by the antibody used for sort (GK1.5). It is known that the antibody used for staining here (H129.19; CyChrome-conjugated from BD Bioscience) competes with the GK1.5 antibody.) Percentages on the left represent the amount of cells staining in the CD4-low range (M1) and on the right the amount of cells staining in the CD4-high range (M2) after overnight culture. Events were ungated. (B) Western blot for CD4 on whole cell extracts (10 ug/lane) from CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> cells was performed on cells immediately after sort using CD4 antibody (sc-1140) from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc. As a loading control membranes were stripped and coomassie blue stained and a representative band is shown (std). (C) CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> cells were stained immediately after sort for CD3-&#x003b5; (145.2C11; CyChrome-conjugated from BD Bioscience; black line). Grey-shaded histogram is isotype control. Percentages on the left represent the amount of cells staining in the CD3-low range (M1) and on the right the amount of cells staining in the CD3-high range (M2). Events were ungated. (D) Western blot for CD3, using CD3 antibody (sc-1127) from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, performed as above. (E) CD4<sup>lo</sup> (black line) and CD4<sup>hi</sup> (dashed line) cells were stained for CD28 (37.51; PE-conjugated from eBioscience) immediately after sort. Grey-shaded histogram is isotype control. Percentages represent the amount of cells staining in M1. Events were ungated.</p><p>(0.53 MB PPT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0002076.s001.ppt" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-powerpoint"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0002076.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>CD4<sup>lo</sup> cells express T cell receptor &#x003b1; and &#x003b2;. NOD and BALB/c splenic cells were magnetically sorted into CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> populations as detailed in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">methods</xref> section. (A) CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> cells were stained immediately after sort for TCR&#x003b2; (H57-597; CyChrome-conjugated from BD Bioscience; black line). Grey-shaded histogram is isotype control. Percentages on the left represent the amount of cells staining in the TCR-low range (M1) and on the right the amount of cells staining in the TCR-high range (M2). Events were ungated. (B) RT-PCR was performed on RNA from CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> cells from NOD and BALB/c using TCR V&#x003b1; specific primers (Blish, C. A., B. J. Gallay, et al. (1999). J Immunol 162(6): 3131&#x02013;40) or TCR V&#x003b2; specific primers (DiLorenzo, T. P., R. T. Graser, et al. (1998). Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 95(21): 12538&#x02013;43). Each lane had cDNA-starting-material equivalent to 750 cells.</p><p>(4.68 MB PPT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0002076.s002.ppt" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-powerpoint"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0002076.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells are not contaminated by B cells and a portion of the CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells express CD11b. NOD and BALB/c splenic cells were magnetically sorted into CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> populations as detailed in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">methods</xref> section. The non-CD4 cells (MHCII<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>CD25<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>) initially depleted in the sort were kept for staining. (A) CD4<sup>lo</sup>, CD4<sup>hi</sup> and MHCII<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>CD25<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> cells were stained for CD21 and CD19 (eBio8D9 and MB19-1; PE- and PE-Cy5-conjugated, respectively, from eBioscience). Percentages represent cells staining in upper right quadrant. Events were ungated. (B) CD4<sup>lo</sup> T cells from NOD and BALB/c were stained for CD11c and CD11b (N418 and M1/70; FITC- and PE-conjugated respectively.) Percentages represent cells staining in upper left quadrant. Events were ungated. Quadrants in A and B were set based on isotype controls.</p><p>(0.26 MB PPT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0002076.s003.ppt" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-powerpoint"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0002076.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>Bcl-X<sub>L</sub> expression in CD4<sup>lo</sup> and CD4<sup>hi</sup> T cells. Graph representing the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0002076-g005">figure 5A and B</xref>. Data are represented as mean&#x000b1;SEM from 3 separate experiments.</p><p>(0.07 MB PPT)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0002076.s004.ppt" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-powerpoint"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0002076-Toubi1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toubi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoenfeld</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The role of CD40-CD154 interactions in autoimmunity and the benefit of disrupting this pathway.</article-title><source>Autoimmunity</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15621572</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Kobata1"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Azuma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okumura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Role of costimulatory molecules in autoimmunity.</article-title><source>Rev Immunogenet</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11324695</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Vaitaitis1"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaitaitis</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haskins</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Cutting edge: CD40-induced expression of recombination activating gene (RAG) 1 and RAG2: a mechanism for the generation of autoaggressive T cells in the periphery.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>170</volume><fpage>3455</fpage><lpage>3459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12646605</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Waid1"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waid</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaitaitis</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Peripheral CD4loCD40&#x0002b; auto-aggressive T cell expansion during insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus.</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>1488</fpage><lpage>1497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15114683</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Balasa1"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balasa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Krahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Patstone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>CD40 ligand-CD40 interactions are necessary for the initiation of insulitis and diabetes in nonobese diabetic mice.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>159</volume><fpage>4620</fpage><lpage>4627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9379064</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Munroe1"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munroe</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A costimulatory function for T cell CD40.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>178</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17202327</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Durie1"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durie</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Foy</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aruffo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledbetter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Prevention of collagen-induced arthritis with an antibody to gp39, the ligand for CD40.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>261</volume><fpage>1328</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7689748</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Quezada1"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quezada</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adeyi</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schned</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Noelle</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Distinct mechanisms of action of anti-CD154 in early versus late treatment of murine lupus nephritis.</article-title><source>Arthritis Rheum</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>2541</fpage><lpage>2554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13130474</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Wang1"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Mechanism of action of combined short-term CTLA4Ig and anti-CD40 ligand in murine systemic lupus erythematosus.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>168</volume><fpage>2046</fpage><lpage>2053</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11823542</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Yu1"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Medling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Braley-Mullen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Characteristics of inflammatory cells in spontaneous autoimmune thyroiditis of NOD.H-2h4 mice.</article-title><source>J Autoimmun</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11221995</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Xie1"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hostager</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Munroe</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Cooperation between TNF receptor-associated factors 1 and 2 in CD40 signaling.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>176</volume><fpage>5388</fpage><lpage>5400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16622006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-vanKooten1"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Kooten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Banchereau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>CD40&#x02013;CD40 ligand.</article-title><source>J Leukoc Biol</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10647992</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Cooper1"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Cutting Edge: TCR revision occurs in germinal centers.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>173</volume><fpage>6532</fpage><lpage>6536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15557142</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Bourgeois1"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourgeois</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanchot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>A role for CD40 expression on CD8&#x0002b; T cells in the generation of CD8&#x0002b; T cell memory.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>297</volume><fpage>2060</fpage><lpage>2063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242444</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Wagner1"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Increased expression of CD40 on thymocytes and peripheral T cells in autoimmunity: a mechanism for acquiring changes in the peripheral T cell receptor repertoire.</article-title><source>Int J Mol Med</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10425271</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Wagner2"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Vaitaitis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobbs</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Expression of CD40 identifies a unique pathogenic T cell population in type 1 diabetes.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>3782</fpage><lpage>3787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11891296</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Waid2"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waid</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaitaitis</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennock</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A Unique T Cell Subset Described as CD4loCD40&#x0002b; T cells (TCD40) in Human Type 1 Diabetes.</article-title><source>Clin Immunol</source><volume>124</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17560173</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Andrade1"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wessendarp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Portillo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>TNF receptor-associated factor 6-dependent CD40 signaling primes macrophages to acquire antimicrobial activity in response to TNF-alpha.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>175</volume><fpage>6014</fpage><lpage>6021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16237096</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Benson1"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hostager</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Rapid CD40-mediated rescue from CD95-induced apoptosis requires TNFR-associated factor-6 and PI3K.</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>2535</fpage><lpage>2543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16897814</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Bishop1"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hostager</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>The CD40-CD154 interaction in B cell-T cell liaisons.</article-title><source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12787567</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Lafaille1"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lafaille</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>The role of helper T cell subsets in autoimmune diseases.</article-title><source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9754708</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Seetharaman1"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seetharaman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabozny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boothby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Essential role of T cell NF-kappa B activation in collagen-induced arthritis.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>163</volume><fpage>1577</fpage><lpage>1583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10415062</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Haskins1"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haskins</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McDuffie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Acceleration of diabetes in young NOD mice with a CD4&#x0002b; islet-specific T cell clone.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>249</volume><fpage>1433</fpage><lpage>1436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2205920</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Santamaria1"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santamaria</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Kinetic evolution of a diabetogenic CD8&#x0002b; T cell response.</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><volume>1005</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14679043</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Liblau1"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liblau</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Santamaria</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Autoreactive CD8 T cells in organ-specific autoimmunity: emerging targets for therapeutic intervention.</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12150886</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Sakaguchi1"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Naturally arising Foxp3-expressing CD25&#x0002b;CD4&#x0002b; regulatory T cells in immunological tolerance to self and non-self.</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15785760</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Setoguchi1"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Setoguchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Homeostatic maintenance of natural Foxp3(&#x0002b;) CD25(&#x0002b;) CD4(&#x0002b;) regulatory T cells by interleukin (IL)-2 and induction of autoimmune disease by IL-2 neutralization.</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><volume>201</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753206</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Strasser1"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The role of BH3-only proteins in the immune system.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15719025</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Kroemer1"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kroemer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Caspase-independent cell death.</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16015365</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Suda1"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Why do defects in the Fas-Fas ligand system cause autoimmunity?</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>S97</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9440553</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Thome1"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thome</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschopp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Regulation of lymphocyte proliferation and death by FLIP.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11905814</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Bortner1"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bortner</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cidlowski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Cellular mechanisms for the repression of apoptosis.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11807173</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Boatright1"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boatright</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Deis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Denault</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherlin</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvesen</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Activation of caspases-8 and -10 by FLIP(L).</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><volume>382</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15209560</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Kataoka1"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschopp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>N-terminal fragment of c-FLIP(L) processed by caspase 8 specifically interacts with TRAF2 and induces activation of the NF-kappaB signaling pathway.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>2627</fpage><lpage>2636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15024054</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Wang2"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Bcl-XL disrupts death-inducing signal complex formation in plasma membrane induced by hypoxia/reoxygenation.</article-title><source>Faseb J</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1826</fpage><lpage>1833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15576486</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Huleatt1"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huleatt</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefrancois</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Antigen-driven induction of CD11c on intestinal intraepithelial lymphocytes and CD8&#x0002b; T cells in vivo.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>154</volume><fpage>5684</fpage><lpage>5693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7751620</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Christensen1"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreasen</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>CD11b expression as a marker to distinguish between recently activated effector CD8(&#x0002b;) T cells and memory cells.</article-title><source>Int Immunol</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11282998</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Kawakami1"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Teruya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudeken</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonamine</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Mac1 discriminates unusual CD4-CD8- double-negative T cells bearing alpha beta antigen receptor from conventional ones with either CD4 or CD8 in murine lung.</article-title><source>Immunol Lett</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7590910</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Serreze1"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serreze</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Prochazka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reifsnyder</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridgett</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leiter</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Use of recombinant congenic and congenic strains of NOD mice to identify a new insulin-dependent diabetes resistance gene.</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><volume>180</volume><fpage>1553</fpage><lpage>1558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7931087</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Munroe2"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munroe</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Role of tumor necrosis factor (TNF) receptor-associated factor 2 (TRAF2) in distinct and overlapping CD40 and TNF receptor 2/CD120b-mediated B lymphocyte activation.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>53222</fpage><lpage>53231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15485859</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Solanilla1"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solanilla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Viallard</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Contin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosset</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Platelet-associated CD154 in immune thrombocytopenic purpura.</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15191945</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Harding1"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommerfield</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Twomey</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Newby</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Increased CD40 ligand and platelet-monocyte aggregates in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus.</article-title><source>Atherosclerosis</source><volume>176</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15380455</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Varo1"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Libby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuzzo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Italiano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Doria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Elevated release of sCD40L from platelets of diabetic patients by thrombin, glucose and advanced glycation end products.</article-title><source>Diab Vasc Dis Res</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16308911</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Jinchuan1"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jinchuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zonggui</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jinming</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiantao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Upregulation of CD40&#x02013;CD40 ligand system in patients with diabetes mellitus.</article-title><source>Clin Chim Acta</source><volume>339</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14687897</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Issazadeh1"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Issazadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitnis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandraker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Role of passive T-cell death in chronic experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis.</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>1109</fpage><lpage>1116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10772655</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Nakamura1"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Migita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawabe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Expression of CD40/CD40 ligand and Bcl-2 family proteins in labial salivary glands of patients with Sjogren's syndrome.</article-title><source>Lab Invest</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10092062</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-LamhamediCherradi1"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamhamedi-Cherradi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eloy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluteau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Resistance of T-cells to apoptosis in autoimmune diabetic (NOD) mice is increased early in life and is associated with dysregulated expression of Bcl-x.</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9498651</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Kreuz1"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreuz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegmund</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheurich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wajant</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>NF-kappaB inducers upregulate cFLIP, a cycloheximide-sensitive inhibitor of death receptor signaling.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>3964</fpage><lpage>3973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11359904</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Khoshnan1"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khoshnan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tindell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Laux</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>The NF-kappa B cascade is important in Bcl-xL expression and for the anti-apoptotic effects of the CD28 receptor in primary human CD4&#x0002b; lymphocytes.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>165</volume><fpage>1743</fpage><lpage>1754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10925251</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Zhu1"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnuson</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>CD40 signaling in B cells regulates the expression of the Pim-1 kinase via the NF-kappa B pathway.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>168</volume><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11777968</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Pierce1"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenleber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jesmok</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Novel inhibitors of cytokine-induced IkappaBalpha phosphorylation and endothelial cell adhesion molecule expression show anti-inflammatory effects in vivo.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>272</volume><fpage>21096</fpage><lpage>21103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9261113</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Thornton1"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shevach</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Suppressor effector function of CD4&#x0002b;CD25&#x0002b; immunoregulatory T cells is antigen nonspecific.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>164</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10605010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Gregori1"><label>53</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Giarratana</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Smiroldo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Uskokovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adorini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>A 1alpha,25-dihydroxyvitamin D(3) analog enhances regulatory T-cells and arrests autoimmune diabetes in NOD mice.</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11978632</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Lepault1"><label>54</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lepault</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnerault</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Characterization of peripheral regulatory CD4&#x0002b; T cells that prevent diabetes onset in nonobese diabetic mice.</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>164</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10605017</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Adorini1"><label>55</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adorini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Tolerogenic Dendritic Cells Induced by Vitamin D Receptor Ligands Enhance Regulatory T Cells Inhibiting Autoimmune Diabetes.</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><volume>987</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12727648</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Salomon1"><label>56</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenschow</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashourian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>B7/CD28 costimulation is essential for the homeostasis of the CD4&#x0002b;CD25&#x0002b; immunoregulatory T cells that control autoimmune diabetes.</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10795741</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Waid3"><label>57</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waid</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaitaitis</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennock</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>DH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><year>in press</year><article-title>Disruption of the homeostatic balance between autoaggressive (CD4&#x0002b;CD40&#x0002b;) and regulatory (CD4&#x0002b;CD25&#x0002b;FoxP3&#x0002b;) T cells promotes diabetes.</article-title><source>J Leukoc Biol</source></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0002076-Ott1"><label>58</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tary-Lehmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>CD4&#x0002b;CD25&#x0002b; regulatory T cells control the progression from periinsulitis to destructive insulitis in murine autoimmune diabetes.</article-title><source>Cell Immunol</source><volume>235</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16122720</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work was supported by grants from National Institutes of Health (grant # DK07501), the American Diabetes Association, the Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation and the Kleberg Foundation.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article> 