<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PONE-RA-05065R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003175</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subject>Biophysics</subject><subject>Ophthalmology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Interaction of C-Terminal Truncated Human &#x003b1;A-Crystallins with Target Proteins</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">&#x003b1;-Crystallin-Interactions</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumarasamy</surname><given-names>Anbarasu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>Edathara C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Department of Biochemistry &#x00026; Molecular Biology, University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences, Little Rock, Arkansas, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>Ashley I.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Mental Health Research Institute of Victoria, Australia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>ecabraham@uams.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AK EA. Performed the experiments: AK. Analyzed the data: AK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AK. Wrote the paper: AK.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e3175</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Kumarasamy et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Significant portion of &#x003b1;A-crystallin in human lenses exists as C-terminal residues cleaved at residues 172, 168, and 162. Chaperone activity, determined with alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) and &#x003b2;L-crystallin as target proteins, was increased in &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> and decreased in &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>. The purpose of this study was to show whether the absence of the C-terminal residues influences protein-protein interactions with target proteins.</p></sec><sec><title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title><p>Our hypothesis is that the chaperone-target protein binding kinetics, otherwise termed subunit exchange rates, are expected to reflect the changes in chaperone activity. To study this, we have relied on fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET) utilizing amine specific and cysteine specific fluorescent probes. The subunit exchange rate (k) for ADH and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> was nearly the same as that of ADH and &#x003b1;A-wt, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> had lower and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> had the lowest k values. When &#x003b2;L-crystallin was used as the target protein, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> had slightly higher k value than &#x003b1;A-wt and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> had lower k values. As expected from earlier studies, the chaperone activity of &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> was slightly better than that of &#x003b1;A-wt, the chaperone activity of &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> was similar to that of &#x003b1;A-wt and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> had substantially decreased chaperone activity.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions/Significance</title><p>Cleavage of eleven C-terminal residues including Arg-163 and the C-terminal flexible arm significantly affects the interaction with target proteins. The predominantly hydrophilic flexible arm appears to be needed to keep the chaperone-target protein complex soluble.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The major proteins in the vertebrate eye lens are &#x003b1;-, &#x003b2;-, and &#x003b3;-crystallins the predominant one being the &#x003b1;-crystallin. &#x003b1;-Crystallin consists of two nearly homologous subunits, namely, &#x003b1;A- and &#x003b1;B-crystallins and both having a molecular mass of 20 kDa in the monomer form and contain 173 and 175 amino acid residues respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-VanDerOuderra1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-DeJong1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. Both &#x003b1;A- and &#x003b1;B-crystallins belong to the class of small heat shock proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Ingolia1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref> and function as molecular chaperones having the ability to prevent aggregation of partially unfolded proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Horwitz1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Rao1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. The model structure of &#x003b1;-crystallin consists of a globular N-terminal domain and a C-terminal domain containing an exposed C-terminal arm rich in hydrophilic amino acids, whereas the C-terminal stretch of 80&#x02013;100 residues known as the &#x02018;&#x003b1;-crystallin/sHsp domain&#x02019; are highly conserved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Wistow1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>C-terminal cleavage of &#x003b1;A-crystallin at residues 162, 168, and 172 has been reported earlier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Takemoto1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Thampi1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. The major post-translational modification which occurs in human &#x003b1;A-crystallin is the loss of the C-terminal serine residue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Takemoto1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Takemoto2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Thampi1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. Enhanced cleavage of the C-terminal residue of &#x003b1;A-crystallin in diabetic human lenses has been reported in our earlier study, the average level of the truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallin increased from 30&#x00025; to 50&#x00025; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Thampi1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. Aziz <italic>et al</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> have recently reported modification in the oligomeric structure and chaperone function of the various truncated human &#x003b1;A-crystallins. Interestingly, the truncated &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> exhibited significant increase in its oligomeric size as well as chaperone activity. The oligomeric size of &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> was similar to that of &#x003b1;A-wild type (&#x003b1;A-wt) whereas the chaperone activity was moderately decreased. &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>, on the other hand, showed substantial decrease in the oligomeric size as well as the chaperone activity. If indeed chaperone to target protein binding is an essential step for &#x003b1;A-crystallin to operate as a molecular chaperone, characterization of the interaction of the truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins with target proteins should show why their chaperone function is altered as a result of the truncation. In this study, we have used fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET) to study chaperone - target protein interaction using ADH and &#x003b2;L-crystallin, two widely used target proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Shroff1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, and recombinant &#x003b1;A-wt and C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Levels of fluorescence labeling of human &#x003b1;A-wt, C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins and the target proteins</title><p>The level of subunit exchange between two different proteins was determined by FRET. In order to determine the <italic>in vitro</italic> FRET level two fluorescent dyes with overlapping fluorescence spectra are necessary. SITS and LYI are widely used fluorescent dyes with spectral overlaps and safe from structural alterations due to fluorescent tags <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Bera1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Ghahghghaei1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>. So, in the present study the amine specific fluorescent probe SITS was attached to human &#x003b1;A-wt and the C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins and the cysteine specific LYI fluorescent probe was attached to the target proteins ADH and &#x003b2;L-crystallin. The level of labeling was determined spectrophotometrically using molar extinction coefficients of 47,000 mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at 336 nm for SITS and 11,000 mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at 426 nm for LYI. The level of labeling was about 0.8, 1.12, 1.17, 1.04 and 7.1 and 1.56 moles for &#x003b1;A-wt, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub>, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>, ADH and &#x003b2;L-crystallin respectively. Differences in the level of labeling of the two different fluorophores were taken into account while computing the data.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Subunit exchange between labeled &#x003b1;A-crystallins and the target protein ADH</title><p>The interaction between the SITS -labeled human &#x003b1;A-wt and the C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins and the LYI- labeled target protein ADH was initiated by mixing equimolar concentration of the proteins in 20 mM MOPS buffer with 100 mM NaCl and 10 mM EDTA at 37&#x000b0;C. EDTA was used for unfolding ADH so that &#x003b1;A-crystallin will bind to ADH under the same condition as used for the chaperone assay. The rate of subunit exchange with ADH was determined by FRET analysis. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g001">Figure 1</xref> shows the fluorescence spectra showing the time dependent decrease in SITS emission intensity at 426 nm and a concomitant increase in LYI fluorescence at 515 nm. After 30 min at 37&#x000b0;C, there was no remarkable change in the emission intensity at 515 nm due to the achievement of stable equilibrium (data not shown). The fluorescence emission spectra illustrate that the highest increase in the acceptor spectrum at 515 nm was observed in &#x003b1;A-wt when compared to the C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). We have calculated the rate of subunit exchange from the increase in acceptor fluorescence intensity after taking into account differences in the levels of tagging of the various proteins by the probes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g002">Figure 2A</xref> shows the plot of Ft/ F0 of LYI at 515 nm as a function of time, where Ft and F0 are the emission intensities at time t and zero respectively. The rate constant was obtained by fitting the data to the exponential function Ft/F0&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;A1&#x0002b;A2 e-kt, where A1 and A2 are constants and k is the rate constant for subunit exchange. The increase in the relative fluorescence intensity at 515 nm is due to fluorescence resonance energy transfer from donor SITS-labeled human &#x003b1;A-wt and C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins' fluorophore to the acceptor LYI-labeled ADH during the interaction. The maximum relative fluorescence intensity was seen with &#x003b1;A-wt whereas &#x003b1;A <sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> had lower fluorescence intensity, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> showed further decrease in the fluorescence intensity, and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> showed the lowest. The subunit exchange rates or the k values are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0003175-t001">Table 1</xref> which is in agreement with the above observation. For instance, &#x003b1;A-wt had the highest k value (2.073) whereas the k values of &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub>, and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>, respectively, were 6, 24, and 43&#x00025; lower. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g002">Figure 2B</xref> illustrates the decrease in the relative fluorescence at 426 nm when the fluorescence resonance energy is transferred to the acceptor target protein. The rate constant (k) values (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0003175-t001">Table 1</xref>) were higher when collected and calculated at donor energy (at 426 nm) than when calculated at acceptor energy (at 515 nm). This is believed to be was due to fluorescence quenching because no direct transfer of fluorescence energy occurs where there is no sufficient contact between the residues carrying the two probes. The amount of loss due to quenching is comparatively lower in both &#x003b1;A-wt and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> than in &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>.</p><fig id="pone-0003175-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003175.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Time &#x02013;dependent spectral changes in the emission spectra of SITS-labeled &#x003b1;A- crystallins interacting with LYI- labeled ADH.</title><p>The emission spectra of fluorescence- labeled &#x003b1;A crystallin excited at 336 nm were recorded at every 2 min intervals at 0, 2,4,6,8,10,12,14,16,18,20,22,24,26,28 and 30 minutes after mixing of SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A - wt and its C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub>, and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> with LYI &#x02013; labeled ADH in 1&#x02236;1 ratio, with a final protein concentration of 1 mg/ml at 37&#x000b0;C. The decrease in fluorescence intensity at 426 nm of SITS- labeled &#x003b1;A- crystallins and concomitant increase in fluorescence intensity at 515 nm of LYI- labeled ADH is indicative of energy transfer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003175.g001"/></fig><fig id="pone-0003175-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003175.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>A: Relative fluorescence intensity at 515 nm due to subunit exchange of SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A-crystallins with LYI &#x02013; labeled ADH.</title><p>Time &#x02013; dependent increase in acceptor fluorescence emission intensity is due to subunit exchange as evident from energy transfer from the SITS &#x02013; labeled protein to the LYI &#x02013; labeled protein. SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A wt (&#x02666;), &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>(&#x025aa;), &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> (&#x025b4;) and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> (&#x02022;) was incubated with LYI &#x02013; labeled ADH. Each curve was analyzed with the best curve fit of the data to the exponential function F<sub>t</sub>/F<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;A<sub>1</sub>&#x0002b;A<sub>2</sub> e<sup>&#x02212;kt</sup>. B: Relative fluorescence intensity at 426 nm due to subunit exchange of SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A-crystallins with LYI &#x02013; labeled ADH. Time &#x02013; dependent decrease in donor fluorescence emission intensity is due to subunit exchange as evident from energy transfer from the SITS &#x02013; labeled protein to the LYI &#x02013; labeled protein. SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A wt (&#x02666;), &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>(&#x025aa;), &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> (&#x025b4;) and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> (&#x02022;) was incubated with LYI &#x02013; labeled ADH. Each curve was analyzed with the best curve fit of the data to the exponential decay function F<sub>t</sub>/F<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;A<sub>1</sub>&#x0002b;A<sub>2</sub> e<sup>&#x02212;kt</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003175.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0003175-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003175.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Subunit exchange rate constant (k) of &#x003b1;A-wt and its C-terminal truncated forms interacting with ADH when increase and decrease respectively (Mean&#x000b1;SE).</title></caption><graphic id="pone-0003175-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0003175.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0003175-t001-1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crystallin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit exchange rate constant at 515 nm (&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> S<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit exchange rate constant at 426 nm (&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> S<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;A wt&#x0002b;ADH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.073&#x000b1;0.169</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.035&#x000b1;0.373</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>&#x0002b;ADH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.947&#x000b1;0.149</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.549&#x000b1;0.327</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub>&#x0002b;ADH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.585&#x000b1;0.112</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.170&#x000b1;0.462</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>&#x0002b;ADH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.190&#x000b1;0.111</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.737&#x000b1;0.403</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Subunit exchange between &#x003b1;A-crystallins and the target protein &#x003b2;L-crystallin</title><p>The interaction between the SITS- labeled human &#x003b1;A-wt and the C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins and the LYI- labeled target protein &#x003b2;L-crystallin was initiated by mixing equimolar concentration of the proteins in 20 mM MOPS buffer with 100 mM NaCl at 62&#x000b0;C. Higher temperature was necessary to unfold &#x003b2;L-crystallin. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g003">Figure 3</xref> shows the fluorescence spectra and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g004">Figure 4A and 4B</xref> show the increase and decrease in relative fluorescence intensity or Ft/F0 at 515 nm and 426 nm, respectively as a function of time. The k values which reflect the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g004">Figure 4A and 4B</xref> were summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0003175-t002">Table 2</xref>. Interestingly, the acceptor gain rate constant (k) value for &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> was maximal at 2.422 and it was about 8&#x00025; higher than the value for &#x003b1;A-wt and about 41&#x00025; higher than the values for &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>. The same trend was noticed in donor k values determined at 426 nm also. The C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> was maximal at 6.391 which was about 24&#x00025; higher than that of &#x003b1;A-wt and 34&#x00025; and 54&#x00025; higher than those of &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> respectively. As mentioned above, here also at the time of energy transfer from donor fluorophore to the acceptor fluorophore some energy loss was noticed. The amount of energy lost was about 54&#x02013;66&#x00025;. The subunit exchange rate constant (k) values clearly showed that in &#x003b1;A-crystallin and the counterparts with ADH at both emission intensities (at 426 &#x00026; 515 nm) the &#x003b1;A-wt showed the highest interaction compared to the C-terminally truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins and among the C-terminally truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> showed higher k value followed by &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> in that order. However, the subunit exchange rate constant (k) values in &#x003b1;A-crystallin and counterparts with &#x003b2;L crystallin were higher in &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> followed by &#x003b1;A-wt, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>. Nevertheless, the loss of energy (due to quenching) was least in &#x003b1;A-wt with both target proteins (ADH &#x00026; &#x003b2;L crystallin) followed by &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>.</p><fig id="pone-0003175-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003175.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Time &#x02013;dependent spectral changes in the emission spectra of the SITS-labeled &#x003b1;A- crystallins interacting with LYI- labeled &#x003b2;L- crystallin.</title><p>The emission spectra of fluorescence- labeled &#x003b1;A crystallin excited at 336 nm were recorded at every 2 min intervals at 0, 2,4,6,8,10,12,14,16,18,20,22,24,26,28 and 30 minutes after mixing of SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A - wt and C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins with LYI &#x02013; labeled &#x003b2;L- crystallin in a 1&#x02236;1 ratio, with a final protein concentration of 1 mg/ml at 62&#x000b0;C. The decrease in fluorescence intensity at 426 nm of SITS-labeled &#x003b1;A- crystallins and concomitant increase in fluorescence intensity at 515 nm of LYI- labeled ADH is indicative of energy transfer due to exchange of subunits between the two labeled proteins.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003175.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone-0003175-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003175.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>A: Relative fluorescence intensity at 515 nm of SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A-crystallins interacting with LYI &#x02013; labeled &#x003b2;L- crystallin.</title><p>Time &#x02013; dependent increase in acceptor fluorescence in emission intensity is due to subunit exchange. Increase in the relative fluorescence intensity at 515 nm is due to energy transfer from the SITS &#x02013; labeled protein to the LYI &#x02013; labeled protein. SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A- wt (&#x02666;), &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>(&#x025aa;), &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> (&#x025b4;) and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> (&#x02022;) were incubated with LYI &#x02013; labeled &#x003b2;L- crystallin. Each curve was analyzed with the best curve fit of the data to the exponential function F<sub>t</sub>/F<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;A<sub>1</sub>&#x0002b;A<sub>2</sub> e<sup>&#x02212;kt</sup>. B: Relative fluorescence intensity at 426 nm of SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A-crystallins interacting with LYI &#x02013; labeled &#x003b2;L- crystallin. Time &#x02013; dependent decrease in donor fluorescence in emission intensity is due to subunit exchange. Decrease in the relative fluorescence intensity at 426 nm is due to energy transfer from the SITS &#x02013; labeled protein to the LYI &#x02013; labeled protein. SITS &#x02013; labeled &#x003b1;A- wt (&#x02666;), &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>(&#x025aa;), &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> (&#x025b4;) and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> (&#x02022;) were incubated with LYI &#x02013; labeled &#x003b2;L- crystallin. Each curve was analyzed with the best curve fit of the data to the exponential function F<sub>t</sub>/F<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;A<sub>1</sub>&#x0002b;A<sub>2</sub> e<sup>&#x02212;kt</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003175.g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0003175-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003175.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Subunit exchange rate constant (k) of &#x003b1;A-wt and its C-terminal truncated forms interacting with &#x003b2;L-crystallin when increase and decrease respectively (Mean&#x000b1;SE).</title></caption><graphic id="pone-0003175-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0003175.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0003175-t002-2"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crystallin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit exchange rate constant at 515 nm (&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> S<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit exchange rate constant at 426 nm (&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> S<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;A wt&#x0002b;&#x003b2;L-crystallin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.233&#x000b1;0.010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.826&#x000b1;0.876</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>&#x0002b;&#x003b2;L-crystallin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.422&#x000b1;0.039</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.391&#x000b1;0.501</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub>&#x0002b;&#x003b2;L-crystallin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.419&#x000b1;0.008</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.183&#x000b1;0.287</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>&#x0002b;&#x003b2;L-crystallin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.435&#x000b1;0.004</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.462&#x000b1;0.267</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Chaperone activity of &#x003b1;A-wt and the C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins</title><p>Although the chaperone activity of the truncated human &#x003b1;A-crystallins were reported earlier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> the chaperone activity assay was repeated in the present study using the ratio of 1&#x02236;1 which is the same ratio as used in the FRET analysis. With ADH as the target protein, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> showed about 18&#x00025; better chaperone activity than &#x003b1;A-wt, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> had nearly the same chaperone activity as &#x003b1;A-wt and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> showed nearly 80&#x00025; loss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). With &#x003b2;L-crystallin as the protein, both &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> showed normal chaperone activity whereas &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> showed nearly 60&#x00025; loss in chaperone activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g006">Fig. 6</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0003175-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003175.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Effect of C-terminal truncation of &#x003b1;A-crystallin on its chaperone activity as measured with ADH as the target protein.</title><p>The chaperone activity of &#x003b1;A-wt (&#x025aa;) and C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>,(&#x025b4;) &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> (&#x02022;) and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> (&#x02212;) ADH alone (&#x02666;) determined with ADH as the target protein at 1&#x02236;1 ratio (0.14 mg/ml) denatured with EDTA at 37&#x000b0;C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003175.g005"/></fig><fig id="pone-0003175-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0003175.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Effect of C-terminal truncation of &#x003b1;A-wt on its chaperone activity as measured with &#x003b2;L-crystallin as the target protein.</title><p>The chaperone activity of &#x003b1;A-wt (&#x025aa;) and C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>,(&#x025b4;) &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> (&#x02022;) and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> (&#x02212;) &#x003b2;L-crystallin alone (&#x02666;) determined with ADH as the target protein at 1&#x02236;1 ratio (0.14 mg/ml) at 62&#x000b0;C.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0003175.g006"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s3"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Fluorescence probes</title><p>Lucifer yellow iodoacetamide (LYI) and 4-acetamido-4&#x02032;-isothiocyanatostilbene-2,-2&#x02032;-disulfonic acid (SITS) were obtained from Molecular Probes (Eugene, OR, USA). Alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) and &#x003b2;L-crystallin were purchased form Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Cloning, site-directed mutagenesis, expression and purification of human &#x003b1;A-crystallin wild type (&#x003b1;A-wt), and C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins</title><p>Cloning of human &#x003b1;A-crystallin and subsequent subcloning into the pET-23d(&#x0002b;) expression vector has been described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Shroff2">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>. To generate the different C-terminally truncated human &#x003b1;A-crystallins lacking 1 (&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>), 5 (&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub>), and 11(&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>) residues, stop codons were introduced at desired sites as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. The pET-23d(&#x0002b;) expression vector harboring DNA constructs of human &#x003b1;A-wt and C-terminally truncated &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub>, and &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> were expressed in BL21 (DE3) PLysS <italic>E. coli</italic> cells. The expressed proteins were purified by Sephacryl S-300 HR size exclusion chromatography, the peak fractions collected were concentrated and repurified by molecular sieve HPLC using a 600 mm&#x000d7;7.8 mm BIOSEP-SEC 4000 column (Phenomenex). The purity of the protein preparations was examined by sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) according to Laemmli <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Laemmli1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Labeling of human &#x003b1;A-wt, C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins and target proteins ADH and &#x003b2;L-crystallin with fluorescence probes</title><p>Labeling of &#x003b1;A-crystallin and C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins with SITS and the target proteins ADH and &#x003b2;L-crystallin with LYI was done as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Ghahghghaei1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Shroff2">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>. Briefly, 10 fold excess of solid SITS was added to 1 ml of a protein solution (3 mg/ml) in 20 mM MOPS buffer containing 100 mM NaCl (pH 7.9) and the reaction was allowed to proceed for about 16 h at room temperature (25&#x000b0;C) in the dark. The unlabeled fluorescent dye was removed from the fluorescently labeled protein on a Sephadex G-25 column equilibrated with 20 mM MOPS buffer containing 100 mM NaCl (pH 7.9). Elution was performed with the same buffer, pooled and concentrated. LYI-labeled protein was prepared as described above with the same buffer in 20 fold excess of the reagent. The extent of labeling was determined spectrophotometrically using molar extinction coefficients of 47,000 mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at 336 nm for SITS and 11,000 mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at 426 nm for LYI and corrected for the contribution of the dye at 280 nm.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Measurement of the rate of subunit exchange among &#x003b1;A-crystallins and the target proteins</title><p>The rate of subunit exchange was measured by the method of fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET). The subunit exchange reaction was initiated by mixing equal amounts (0.5 mg/ml) of SITS -labeled &#x003b1;A-wt and C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins (&#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> &#x00026; &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub>) with the same amount of LYI-labeled target proteins: 1)ADH in 20 mM MOPS buffer containing 100 mM NaCl and 10 mM EDTA (pH 7.9) at 37&#x000b0;C and 2) &#x003b2;L-crystallin in 20 mM MOPS buffer containing 100 mM NaCl (pH 7.9) at 62&#x000b0;C. The fluorescence emission spectra were obtained with Shimadzu RF-5301PC spectrofluorophotometer (Columbia, MD) at an excitation wavelength of 336 nm. Decrease in SITS emission intensity at 426 nm and increase in LYI emission intensity at 515 nm were recorded at every 2 min intervals and the subunit exchange rate constant (k) was calculated by curve fitting an exponential function F<sub>t</sub>/ F<sub>0</sub>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;A<sub>1</sub>&#x0002b;A<sub>2</sub> e<sup>&#x02212;kt</sup> where A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>2</sub> are constants and k is the rate constant for subunit exchange.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Determination of Chaperone activity</title><p>The ability of &#x003b1;A-wt and the C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins to prevent the extent of EDTA induced aggregation of ADH and thermal aggregation of &#x003b2;L-crystallin was determined as described before <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Shroff1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>. &#x003b1;A-wt and the C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins were mixed with equal amounts of target proteins (1&#x02236;1 ratio) at a total concentration of 0.14 mg/ml. ADH was induced to unfold with 10 mM EDTA in 50 mM PBS buffer (pH 7.9) at 37&#x000b0;C and the &#x003b2;L-crystallin unfolding was thermally induced at 62&#x000b0;C. The extent of aggregation was measured by monitoring the light scattering at 360 nm using Shimadzu UV 160 spectrophotometer equipped with a temperature regulated cell holder.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>We have shown earlier that cleavage of 1, 5, and 11 C-terminal residues affects or improves chaperone activity depending on the number of residues cleaved and the chaperone assay system <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. Chaperone activity of the truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins can vary by two major factors: accessibility to the chaperone sites which are responsible for the chaperoning process or due to enhanced or decreased affinity to the substrate which is being unfolded. The present study focused on the latter aspect by studying the binding of the wild-type and the truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins with the putative target proteins. The data show that the binding kinetics (k value) reflect the chaperone activity differences with the exception that &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> showed higher chaperone activity, but, lower k value. Thus, we can conclude that the binding affinity to target proteins does not always concur with the chaperone activity data. However, it is noteworthy that all the three truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins have shown decreased target protein binding.</p><p>In an earlier study, we have determined the oligomeric size, secondary and tertiary structures and chaperone activity of recombinant human &#x003b1;A-wt and the various C-terminal truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub>, which is the major form of the truncated human &#x003b1;A-crystallin, had a molecular mass of 866 kDa as compared to 702 kDa for &#x003b1;A-wt, when the molecular mass was determined by dynamic light scattering. The chaperone activity of &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> was higher than that of &#x003b1;A-wt, when ADH, insulin and &#x003b2;L-crystallin were used as target proteins and the &#x003b1;A-crystallin : target protein ratio varied between 1&#x02236;1 and 1&#x02236;20. In this study, we have used equal amounts of &#x003b1;-crystallin and target protein, ie, 1&#x02236;1 ratio, in all the assays to avoid artificially exaggerated differences between &#x003b1;A-wt and the truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g005">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g006">6</xref>, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> had slightly better chaperone activity than &#x003b1;A-wt, which confirms our previous observation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. However, &#x003b1;A-crystallin-target protein binding studies gave conflicting results. For instance, the relative fluorescence intensity due to FRET and the k values were lower in &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g002">Figs. 2</xref> &#x00026; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g004">4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0003175-t001">Tables 1</xref> &#x00026; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0003175-t002">2</xref>). Both the present study and the earlier study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> have shown &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> having nearly the same chaperone activity as &#x003b1;A-wt. however, the FRET studies gave contradicting results as the relative fluorescence intensity as well as the k values were significantly lower (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g002">Figs. 2</xref> &#x00026; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g004">4</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0003175-t001">Tables 1</xref> &#x00026; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0003175-t002">2</xref>). With both the ADH and the &#x003b2;L-crystallin target protein methods, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> showed the lowest chaperone activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g005">Figs. 5</xref> &#x00026; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0003175-g006">6</xref>) as shown earlier. Interestingly, &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> also showed the lowest level of relative fluorescence intensity and k value during FRET studies. Thus, the cleavage of 11 C-terminal residues of &#x003b1;A-crystallin, which is known to affect its secondary and tertiary structures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>, severely affects its binding to target proteins which in turn affect its ability to function as a molecular chaperone.</p><p>By using FRET analysis, we have recently investigated the effect of cleavage of the C-terminal residues of human &#x003b1;A-crystallin on subunit exchange with &#x003b1;B-crystallin forming heteroaggregates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Shroff2">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>. The subunit exchange rate or the k value for &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> interacting with &#x003b1;B-wt was decreased by 50&#x00025; compared to &#x003b1;A-wt interacting with &#x003b1;B-wt. Likewise, the k value was decreased 40&#x00025; when &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;168</sub> interacted with &#x003b1;B-wt, whereas interaction of &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> with &#x003b1;B-wt showed 84&#x00025; decrease in the k value. Thus, cleaving 11 residues including lysine-163 had shown the most effect. The importance of lysine-163 in maintaining the oligomeric structure of &#x003b1;A-crystallin has been demonstrated in a recent study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Rajan1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. In fact, in &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;162</sub> the secondary and tertiary structures were significantly altered and the molecular mass was substantially decreased <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Aziz1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. Such changes affect binding to &#x003b1;B-crystallin and heterooligomerization <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0003175-Shroff2">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref> and also seem to affect binding to target proteins decreasing the chaperone activity.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0003175-VanDerOuderra1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Der Ouderra</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloemendal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1973</year><article-title>The amino- acid sequence of the alphaA2 chain of bovine alpha-crystallin.</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4770792</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-VanDerOuderra2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Der Ouderra</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilderink</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloemendal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1974</year><article-title>The amino-acid sequence of the alphaB2 chain of bovine alpha-crystallin.</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4477528</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-DeJong1"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Terwindt</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloemendal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>1975</year><article-title>The amino-acid sequence of the A chain of human alpha-crystallin.</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>58</volume><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">817940</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Ingolia1"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingolia</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1982</year><article-title>Four small Drosophila heat shock proteins are related to each other and to mammalian &#x003b1;-crystallin.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>2360</fpage><lpage>2364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6285380</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Horwitz1"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>&#x003b1;-Crystallin can function as a molecular chaperone.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>10449</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1438232</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Wang1"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>The chaperone activity of bovine alpha-crystallin. Interaction with other lens crystallins in native and denatured states.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>269</volume><fpage>13601</fpage><lpage>13608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7909809</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Rao1"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name><name><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zigler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Evidence that alpha-crystallin prevents non-specific protein aggregation in the intact eye lens.</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1245</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8541324</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Wistow1"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wistow</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>Domain structure and evolution in &#x003b1;-crystallins and small heat shock proteins.</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3972098</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Takemoto1"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Identification of the <italic>in vivo</italic> truncation sites at the C-terminal region of alpha-A-crystallin from aged bovine and human lens.</article-title><source>Curr Eye Res</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8529423</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Lund1"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Modifications of the water-insoluble human lens alpha-crystallins.</article-title><source>Exp Eye Res</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9068373</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Colvis1"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colvis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Posttranslational modification of human &#x003b1;A-crystallin: correlation with electrophoretic migration.</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><volume>397</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11795889</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Ma1"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampi</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Age-related changes in human lens crystallins identified by HPLC and mass spectrometry.</article-title><source>Exp Eye Res</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9702175</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Miesbauer1"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miesbauer</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Posttranslational modifications of water-soluble human lens crystallins from young adults.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>269</volume><fpage>12494</fpage><lpage>12502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8175657</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Takemoto2"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takemoto</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Quantitation of specific cleavage sites at the C-terminal region of alpha-A-crystallin from human lenses of different age.</article-title><source>Exp Eye Res</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9533852</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Thampi1"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thampi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Enhanced C-terminal truncation of alphaA- and alphaB-crystallins in diabetic lenses.</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><volume>43</volume><fpage>3265</fpage><lpage>3272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12356833</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Aziz1"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Santhoshkumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Cleavage of the C-terminal serine of human &#x003b1;A-crystallin produces &#x003b1;A<sub>1&#x02013;172</sub> with increased chaperone activity and oligomeric size.</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>2510</fpage><lpage>2519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17279772</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Shroff1"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherian-Shaw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Substituted hydrophobic and hydrophilic residues at methionine-68 influence the chaperone-like function of &#x003b1;B-crystallin.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biochem</source><volume>220</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11451372</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Bera1"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The &#x003b1;A-crystallin R116C mutant has a higher affinity for forming heteroaggregates with &#x003b1;B-crystallin.</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11772029</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Kallur1"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kallur</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>C-Terminal truncation affects subunit exchange of human &#x003b1;A-crystallin with &#x003b1;B-crystallin.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biochem</source><volume>308</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17909943</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Ghahghghaei1"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghahghghaei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rekas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The effect of dextran on subunit exchange of the molecular chaperone &#x003b1;A-crystallin.</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1774</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17118727</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Shroff2"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherian-Shaw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Mutation of R116C results in highly oligomerized &#x003b1;A-crystallin with modified structure and defective chaperone-like function.</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>1420</fpage><lpage>1426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10684623</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Laemmli1"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laemmli</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name></person-group><year>1970</year><article-title>Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>227</volume><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5432063</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0003175-Rajan1"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrashekar</surname></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Role of arginine-163 and the <sup>163</sup> REEK <sup>166</sup> motiff in the oligomerization truncated &#x003b1;A-crystallins.</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>15684</fpage><lpage>15691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17176090</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>EY11352 from the National Institutes of Health.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article> 