<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jem</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20072660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20072660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18794338</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject><subj-group><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>PSGL-1 engagement by E-selectin signals through Src kinase Fgr and ITAM adapters DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; to induce slow leukocyte rolling</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zarbock</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1d839c0N0x395eb50">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abram</surname><given-names>Clare L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hundt</surname><given-names>Matthias</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>Amnon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lowell</surname><given-names>Clifford A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>Klaus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1d839c0N0x395eb50">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1d839c0N0x395eb50">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1d839c0N0x395eb50"><label>1</label>Robert M. Berne Cardiovascular Research Center, <label>2</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Molecular Physiology and Biological Physics, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA 22908</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Anesthesiology and Intensive Care Medicine, University of M&#x000fc;nster, D-48149 M&#x000fc;nster, Germany</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA 94143</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>La Jolla Institute for Allergy and Immunology, La Jolla, CA 92037</aff><author-notes><fn><p>CORRESPONDENCE Klaus Ley: <email>klaus@liai.org</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>205</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2339</fpage><lpage>2347</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2008 Zarbock et al.</copyright-statement><license><p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/misc/terms.shtml">http://www.jem.org/misc/terms.shtml</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ext-link>).</p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="jem2052339.pdf"/><abstract><p>E-selectin binding to P-selectin glycoprotein ligand-1 (PSGL-1) can activate the &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrin lymphocyte function-associated antigen-1 by signaling through spleen tyrosine kinase (Syk). This signaling is independent of G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub>-protein&#x02013;coupled receptors, results in slow rolling, and promotes neutrophil recruitment to sites of inflammation. However, the signaling pathways linking E-selectin engagement of PSGL-1 to Syk activation are unknown. To test the role of Src family kinases and immunoreceptor tyrosine-based activating motif (ITAM)&#x02013;containing adaptor proteins, we used different gene-deficient mice in flow chamber, intravital microscopy, and peritonitis studies. E-selectin&#x02013;mediated phosphorylation of Syk and slow rolling was abolished in neutrophils from <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> or <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. Neutrophils from <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice lacking both DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; were incapable of sustaining slow neutrophil rolling on E-selectin and intercellular adhesion molecule-1 and were unable to phosphorylate Syk and p38 MAPK. This defect was confirmed in vivo by using mixed chimeric mice. G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub>-independent neutrophil recruitment into the inflamed peritoneal cavity was sharply suppressed in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. Our data demonstrate that an ITAM-dependent pathway involving the Src-family kinase Fgr and the ITAM-containing adaptor proteins DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; is involved in the initial signaling events downstream of PSGL-1 that are required to initiate neutrophil slow rolling.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>Abbreviations used: GST, glutathione S-transferase; ICAM-1, intercellular adhesion molecule-1; ITAM, immunoreceptor tyrosine-based activating motif; PSGL-1, P-selectin glycoprotein ligand-1; Syk, spleen tyrosine kinase; TREM, triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><p>The first three steps of the neutrophil adhesion cascade&#x02014;capture, rolling, and slow rolling&#x02014;require selectins and their counter receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref>). These steps are mediated by endothelial P- and E-selectin, which both bind to P-selectin glycoprotein ligand-1 (PSGL-1) on neutrophils. In venules of the cremaster muscle, the rolling velocity of leukocytes on P-selectin is 40 &#x003bc;m/s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref>), whereas under inflammatory conditions (e.g., when endothelium is activated by TNF-&#x003b1;), E-selectin mediates slower rolling (3&#x02013;7 &#x003bc;m/s) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). Recently, it has been shown that P-selectin binding to PSGL-1 can induce Nef-associated factor 1&#x02013;dependent downstream signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>). Disruption of this signal transduction pathway leads to reduced leukocyte adhesion in vivo and reduced leukocyte recruitment into the peritoneal cavity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>). E-selectin engagement of PSGL-1 can also induce downstream signaling, inducing tyrosine phosphorylation of p38 MAP kinase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>), spleen tyrosine kinase (Syk) phosphorylation, and slow rolling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). Antibody cross-linking of PSGL-1 has been shown to induce association of its cytoplasmic tail with ezrin and moesin and activation of Syk and transcription factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>).</p><p>Neutrophils express the &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrins LFA-1 (&#x003b1;<sub>L</sub>&#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>) and macrophage antigen (Mac)-1 (&#x003b1;<sub>M</sub>&#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>), which regulate the rolling velocity of leukocytes in inflamed microvessels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref>). Neutrophils perfused through flow chambers coated with E-selectin plus intercellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1) roll much more slowly than on E-selectin alone, and this slow rolling is LFA-1 dependent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). LFA-1 can undergo partial activation to an intermediate affinity state or full activation to a high affinity state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>). Allosteric inhibitors that stabilize LFA-1 in the extended conformation associated with intermediate affinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref>) still allow LFA-1&#x02013;dependent slow rolling on E-selectin plus ICAM-1, but block chemokine-triggered firm adhesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). The physiological behavior of LFA-1 in the extended conformation is similar to that of its isolated I domain, which also supports rolling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>).</p><p>Stimulation of immunoreceptors (TCR, B cell receptor, and FcR) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>), growth factor receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref>), cytokine receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref>), G-protein&#x02013;linked receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref>), and integrins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>) can activate Src-family kinases. Binding of P-selectin to PSGL-1 on isolated human neutrophils cells can also activate Src-family kinases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>). These Src tyrosine kinases share a high degree of structural homology and possess three major domains: an Src homology 3 (SH3) domain, an SH2 domain, and the tyrosine kinase (SH1) domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>). The Src-family kinases Lyn, Hck, and Fgr are expressed in neutrophils and are involved in several signaling pathways by promoting phosphorylation of downstream effectors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>).</p><p>The cytoplasmic tyrosine kinase Syk is expressed in hematopoietic cells and contains tandem SH2 domains and a C-terminal kinase domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>). Syk is absolutely required in myeloid cells and platelets for downstream signaling after activation of receptors involved in innate immunity, such as Fc receptors and platelet glycoprotein (GP) VI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>). The related kinase Zap-70 is required for adaptive immune responses triggered by B cell and T cell receptors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>). After engagement of the respective cell surface receptors, Syk is activated by docking to phosphorylated tyrosine residues within immunoreceptor tyrosine-based activation motifs (ITAMs) that contain the characteristic amino acid sequence YxxL/Ix<sub>6-8</sub>YxxL/I, where x represents any amino acid. Neutrophils express several ITAM-containing adaptor molecules, including ezrin, moesin, radixin, DAP12, and FcR&#x003b3; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref>). Ezrin and moesin have previously been shown to directly interact with the cytoplasmic tail of PSGL-1 and act as linkers between Syk and PSGL-1 cross-linked by antibodies in the human promyeloid cell line HL-60 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>). After stimulation of human neutrophils with chemoattractants, moesin and PSGL-1 are colocalized in the uropod of migrating cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref>).</p><p>DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; have short extracellular domains of 21 and 5 amino acids, respectively, and no specific extracellular binding ligands are known. Cysteine residues in the extracellular regions of these adaptor proteins allow their expression as disulfide-linked homodimers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref>). A charged aspartic acid residue present in the transmembrane domain of DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; mediates their association with ligand-binding receptors such as Fc&#x003b3;RIII, Fc&#x003b5;R, and GP VI. The association of DAP12 or FcR&#x003b3; with specific ligand binding receptors is required for initiation of intracellular signaling.</p><p>DAP12 is expressed in neutrophils, mast cells, natural killer cells, monocytes, and dendritic cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref>). Triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells (TREM)-1, TREM-2, myeloid DAP12-associating lectin-1, and signal-regulatory protein &#x003b2; are surface receptors associated with DAP12 in myeloid cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref>). Engagement of the DAP12-associated receptor TREM-1 on neutrophils and monocytes leads to cell activation and subsequent secretion of proinflammatory cytokines and chemokines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>).</p><p>The &#x003b3; chain (FcR&#x003b3;) of immunoglobulin Fc receptors is an essential component of the high-affinity receptor for IgE (Fc&#x003b5;RI), expressed by mast cells and basophils, the low-affinity receptor for IgG (Fc&#x003b3;RIII, CD16), and is associated with the high-affinity receptor for IgG (Fc&#x003b3;RI, CD64) and the TCR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref>). FcR&#x003b3; is essential for receptor assembly and provides the ITAM domain necessary for signal transduction. Elimination of FcR&#x003b3; results in immunocompromised mice showing reduced phagocytosis, defects in macrophage and NK cell&#x02013;mediated cytotoxicity, osteopetrosis, and defective mast cell&#x02013;mediated allergic responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref>).</p><p>Engagement of &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrins by ligands leads to outside-in signaling that promotes leukocyte adhesion, degranulation, and proliferation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>). A recent study showed that DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; are involved in outside-in signaling through &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrins in neutrophils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>). In this signaling pathway, DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; have a partially redundant function, and elimination of both molecules is necessary to abolish signaling transduction and superoxide production after integrin engagement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>).</p><p>It is well established that Src-family kinases and ITAM-containing adaptor proteins are involved in Syk activation during integrin and immunoreceptor signaling. The present study was designed to test whether Src-family kinases and ITAM-containing adaptor proteins DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; are also required for Syk activation and slow rolling of neutrophils after E-selectin engagement of PSGL-1. Using in vitro phosphorylation assays in neutrophils, ex vivo flow chamber assays, and in vivo inflammation experiments with several gene-targeted mouse strains, we find that the Src-family kinase Fgr is involved with DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; in initiating the signaling events downstream of PSGL-1 that are required for activation of neutrophil slow rolling.</p><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Src family kinases are involved in E-selectin&#x02013;mediated rolling</title><p>Binding of P-selectin to PSGL-1 induces Src kinase&#x02013;dependent phosphorylation of downstream molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>). To test whether Src kinases are involved in E-selectin&#x02013;mediated slow rolling, we investigated the rolling velocity of neutrophils from mice pretreated with the Src-family kinase inhibitor (PP2) or an inactive control (PP3) in an autoperfused flow chamber. In this system, neutrophils can be investigated in native whole blood, without any isolation procedure that might activate the cells and alter their ability to regulate rolling velocity. As previously shown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>), the rolling velocity of WT neutrophils rolling in autoperfused flow chambers coated with E-selectin plus ICAM-1 is significantly reduced compared with E-selectin alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). Pretreatment of mice with PP2 did not influence the rolling velocity of neutrophils on E-selectin, but the decrease of rolling velocity on E-selectin plus ICAM-1 was almost completely abolished after Src-family kinase blockade (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1 A</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Src-family kinases are involved in slow rolling after E-selectin engagement.</bold> (A) Rolling velocities of neutrophils from WT mice treated with a specific Src-family kinase inhibitor (PP2) or inactive control (PP3) in E-selectin and E-selectin/ICAM-1&#x02013;coated autoperfused flow chamber experiments (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3). The wall shear stress in all flow chamber experiments was 5&#x02013;6 dynes/cm<sup>2</sup>. (B) Mixed chimeric mice were generated by injecting bone marrow cells from LysM-GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> WT mice and <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice into lethally irradiated WT mice. Rolling velocities of 111 GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> (WT, filled circle) and 111 GFP<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, open square) leukocytes in inflamed cremaster muscle venules of mixed chimeric mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 4) treated with PTx and a monoclonal blocking antibody against P-selectin presented as cumulative histogram. (inset) Mean &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>&#x00023;</sup>, P &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052339f01"></graphic></fig><p>To confirm our flow chamber data in vivo, we conducted intravital microscopy in mixed chimeric mice. <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> triple knockout mice lack all three neutrophil Src-family kinases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref>). Lethally irradiated WT mice received bone marrow cells from WT LysM-GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>) and GFP-negative <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice mixed in a ratio of 1:1. Leukocyte rolling was analyzed in TNF-&#x003b1;&#x02013;treated venules of the cremaster muscle after blocking P-selectin (to limit our observations to E-selectin) and G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub>-signaling (to block chemokine signaling). In this system, gene-targeted leukocytes can be compared side-by-side with leukocytes from WT mice under the same hemodynamic conditions in the same venules. The measured mean blood flow velocity and the calculated wall shear rates in these venules were 3.2 &#x000b1; 0.2 mm/s and 2,000 &#x000b1; 200 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively. Under these conditions, mean rolling velocity (V<sub>avg</sub>) of <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> leukocytes in vivo was 7.3 &#x000b1; 0.3 &#x003bc;m/s (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1 B</xref>), almost twice that of LysM-GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> control cells (V<sub>avg</sub> &#x0003d; 4.4 &#x000b1; 0.1 &#x003bc;m/s; P &#x0003c; 0.05). The high rolling velocity seen in <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> leukocytes is equal to the rolling velocity of leukocytes seen in WT mice after antibody blockade of both &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrins, Mac-1 and LFA-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). These findings suggest that Src-family kinases participate in &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrin activation and subsequent slow rolling after E-selectin engagement.</p></sec><sec><title>Elimination of the Src family kinase Fgr abolishes E-selectin&#x02013;mediated slow rolling</title><p>It is known that the Src-family kinases have a considerable redundancy and that elimination of more than one kinase is often necessary to impair downstream signaling and subsequent biological activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>). To test whether such a redundancy exists in the signaling pathways triggered by PSGL-1 engagement with E-selectin, we investigated the rolling velocity of WT, <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, <italic>lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, and <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> neutrophils using the autoperfused flow chamber described int the previous section. The rolling velocity of neutrophils from WT mice and gene-deficient mice on E-selectin alone was similar (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 A</xref>). As expected, neutrophils from WT mice showed a reduction of the rolling velocity on E-selectin plus ICAM-1 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 A</xref>). However, <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> neutrophils failed to reduce their rolling velocity on E-selectin plus ICAM-1 compared with WT neutrophils (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 A</xref>). This rolling velocity was not further increased in <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> triple knockout mice, and <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> or <italic>lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice showed no rolling defect.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><bold>Fgr is required for E-selectin&#x02013;mediated slow rolling.</bold> (A) Carotid cannulas were placed in WT mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3), <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3), <italic>lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3), <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3), and <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3) and connected to autoperfused flow chambers. The wall shear stress in all flow chamber experiments was 5&#x02013;6 dynes/cm<sup>2</sup>. Mean rolling velocity of neutrophils on E-selectin (left) and E-selectin/ICAM-1 (right) presented as mean &#x000b1; SEM (B) Mixed chimeric mice were generated by injecting bone marrow cells from LysM-GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> WT mice and <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice into lethally irradiated WT mice. Cumulative histogram of rolling velocity of 121 GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> (WT, filled circle) and 121 GFP<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, open diamond) leukocytes in inflamed cremaster muscle venules of mixed chimeric mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 4) treated with PTx and a monoclonal blocking P-selectin antibody. (inset) Mean &#x000b1; SEM <sup>&#x00023;</sup>P &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052339f02"></graphic></fig><p>Mixed chimeric mice, generated with bone marrow from LysM-GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> mice and <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, showed that the rolling velocity of <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> leukocytes was significantly increased (7.8 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;m/s, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 B</xref>) compared with leukocytes from WT mice (4.5 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;m/s, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2 B</xref>). Collectively, these data show that Fgr, but not Hck or Lyn, is required for slow rolling triggered by PSGL-1 engagement.</p></sec><sec><title>DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; are involved in E-selectin&#x02013;induced slow rolling</title><p>To address whether ITAM-containing adaptor proteins are involved in E-selectin&#x02013;dependent rolling, we investigated the rolling velocity of neutrophils from DAP12-deficient mice (<italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>), FcR&#x003b3;-deficient mice (<italic>Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>), double mutant mice (<italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>), and WT mice using the whole-blood autoperfused flow chamber. Elimination of either FcR&#x003b3; or DAP12 alone slightly increased rolling velocity on E-selectin plus ICAM-1 compared with neutrophils from WT mice (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 A</xref>). The rolling velocity on E-selectin plus ICAM-1 of neutrophils lacking both adaptor molecules was significantly increased compared with neutrophils from WT mice, and was similar to the rolling velocity on E-selectin alone (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 A</xref>). These data suggest that the two ITAM-containing adaptor proteins, DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3;, have a partially redundant function. When both are eliminated, E-selectin&#x02013;dependent slow rolling is abolished.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><bold>The ITAM domain-containing adapters DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; are involved in E-selectin&#x02013;mediated slow rolling in vitro and in vivo.</bold> (A) Carotid cannulas were placed in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (upsidedown triangle, <italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3), <italic>Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (square, <italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3), <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (triangle, <italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3), and WT mice (filled circle, <italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 5) and connected to autoperfused flow chambers. The wall shear stress in all flow chamber experiments was 5&#x02013;6 dynes/cm<sup>2</sup>. Average rolling velocity of neutrophils on E-selectin (left) and E-selectin and ICAM-1 (right) presented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. (B) Mixed chimeric mice were generated by injecting bone marrow cells from LysM-GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> WT mice and <italic>Tyrob<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, mixed at a 1:1 ratio, into lethally irradiated WT mice. Cumulative histogram of rolling velocities of 150 GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> (WT, filled circle) and 150 GFP<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (<italic>Tyrob<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, open triangle) leukocytes in inflamed cremaster muscle venules of mixed chimeric mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 4) treated with PTx and a monoclonal blocking P-selectin antibody (RB40.34; Video 1). (inset) Mean &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>&#x00023;</sup>, P &#x0003c; 0.05. Video 1 is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20072660/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20072660/DC1</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052339f03"></graphic></fig><p>To investigate the role of the ITAM-containing adaptor proteins DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; in E-selectin&#x02013;dependent slow rolling in vivo, we generated mixed chimeric mice by injecting bone marrow cells from LysM-GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> mice and <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice into lethally irradiated WT mice and performed intravital microscopy. As before, we blocked P-selectin and G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub>-coupled signaling to more clearly address the E-selectin pathway of neutrophil activation. In TNF-&#x003b1;&#x02013;induced inflamed postcapillary venules, the rolling velocity of <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> leukocytes was 8.4 &#x000b1; 0.4 &#x003bc;m/s (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3 B</xref> and Video 1, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20072660/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20072660/DC1</ext-link>), which is significantly higher than LysM-GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> control cells (4.3 &#x000b1; 0.2 &#x003bc;m/s; P &#x0003c; 0.05). These findings show that &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrin activation after E-selectin engagement is defective in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> leukocytes.</p></sec><sec><title>G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub>-independent neutrophil recruitment is defective in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice</title><p>Neutrophil recruitment into the peritoneal cavity after thioglycollate injection is promoted by E-selectin&#x02013; and chemokine-dependent pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref>). To investigate the physiological importance of DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; in a model of acute inflammation, neutrophil recruitment in thioglycollate-induced peritonitis was investigated in WT, <italic>Fcrg</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, and <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> F<italic>crg</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>mice with or without PTx treatment to block G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub>-signaling. Consistent with previous data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref>), pretreatment with PTx reduced neutrophil recruitment to WT peritoneum 8 h after thioglycollate injection by &#x0223c;50% (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). In the presence of intact GPCR signaling, <italic>Fcrg</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>, <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, and <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice showed no major defect in neutrophil recruitment into the peritoneal cavity 8 h after thioglycollate injection. This is reminiscent of the phenotype of <italic>Syk<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> neutrophils in bone marrow chimeras after induction of thioglycollate peritonitis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref>). Blocking of G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub> signaling by PTx reduced neutrophil recruitment in <italic>Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> and <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> single knockout mice by &#x0223c;50%. However, treating <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> double knockout mice with PTx almost completely abolished neutrophil recruitment into the peritoneal cavity after thioglycollate injection.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><bold>G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub>-independent neutrophil recruitment drastically reduced in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice.</bold> Neutrophil influx into the peritoneal cavity 8 h after 1 ml injection of 4% thioglycollate into WT mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 4), <italic>Fcrg</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3), <italic>Tyrobp</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 7), and <italic>Tyrobp</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> F<italic>crg</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 7). The same groups were also analyzed after pretreatment with 4 &#x003bc;g PTx i.v. (&#x0002b;PTx; WT mice &#x0002b; PTx [<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 5], <italic>Fcrg</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice &#x0002b; PTx [<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 4], <italic>Tyrobp</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice &#x0002b; PTx [<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 7], and <italic>Tyrobp</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> F<italic>crg</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice &#x0002b; PTx [<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 5]). Number of mice indicated above each bar. Total numbers of neutrophils in the peritoneal lavage fluid determined by flow cytometry and hemocytometer count. <sup>&#x00023;</sup>, P &#x0003c; 0.05 from all groups by analysis of variance and Newman-Keuls post-hoc test. &#x0002a;, P &#x0003c; 0.05 compared with WT by Student's <italic>t</italic> test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052339f04"></graphic></fig></sec><sec><title>PSGL-1 signals through Fgr, DAP12, FcR&#x003b3;, and Syk</title><p>Engagement of PSGL-1 can activate Src-family kinases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>) and the tyrosine kinase Syk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>). However, because Syk cannot directly interact with the cytoplasmatic tail of PSGL-1, ITAM-containing adaptor molecules are necessary for this interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>). During immunoreceptor and integrin signaling, Src-family kinases phosphorylate ITAM-containing adaptor proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>). This leads to activation of Syk, which in turn induces further downstream signaling. Consequently, we tested whether downstream signaling of PSGL-1 after E-selectin engagement required Fgr, DAP12, and FcR&#x003b3;. Stimulation of WT neutrophils with E-selectin under shear stress conditions induced phosphorylation of the tyrosine in the catalytic domain of Fgr in a time-dependent manner (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5 A</xref>). E-selectin engagement also activated Hck (Fig. S1 A, available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20072660/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20072660/DC1</ext-link>), but did not induce tyrosine phosphorylation of Lyn (Fig. S1B). As <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice showed an abolished E-selectin&#x02013;mediated slow rolling, we speculated that these ITAM-containing adaptor molecules are phosphorylated after E-selectin stimulation. To investigate DAP12 phosphorylation, we used a glutathione S-transferase (GST) fusion protein with the tandem SH2 domains of Syk (GST-Syk-[SH2]2) to pull down tyrosine-phosphorylated proteins. Bound proteins were immunoblotted with a phosphospecific DAP12 antibody. Stimulation of neutrophils with E-selectin for 10 min led to an increase in DAP12 phosphorylation (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5 B</xref>). To investigate whether Fgr is involved in phosphorylation of the tyrosine residues in the ITAM domains, we stimulated WT and <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> neutrophils with E-selectin. Elimination of Fgr almost completely abolished DAP12 phosphorylation after stimulation with E-selectin (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5 C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><bold>PSGL-1 signals through Fgr, DAP12, FcR&#x003b3;, and Syk.</bold> Bone marrow&#x02013;derived neutrophils were plated on uncoated (unstimulated) or E-selectin&#x02013;coated wells for the indicated time, and then lysates were prepared. (A) Lysates were immunoprecipitated with anti-Fgr, followed by immunoblotting (IB) with a phosphospecific Src antibody that recognizes the tyrosine in the catalytic domain of Fgr (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3). (B and C) Lysates were incubated with GST&#x02013;Syk&#x02013;(SH2)<sub>2</sub> fusion protein (ppt), and bound proteins were immunoblotted with a phosphospecific DAP12 antibody (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3) or (D and E) immunoprecipitated with anti-Syk followed (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 3) by immunoblotting (IB) for phosphotyrosine (PY) or Syk or ERK as a loading control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052339f05"></graphic></fig><p>Phosphorylation of downstream effectors was abolished in neutrophils pretreated with an Src-family kinase inhibitor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>). To investigate whether only Fgr is responsible for signaling downstream of PSGL-1, we measured Syk phosphorylation in bone marrow&#x02013;derived neutrophils from WT mice and <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. Plating neutrophils on immobilized recombinant E-selectin under shear stress conditions for 10 min induced phosphorylation of Syk in neutrophils from WT, <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, and <italic>lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> (Fig. S1 C), but not <italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, neutrophils (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5 D</xref>). To directly demonstrate that DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; are also involved in this signaling pathway, we investigated Syk phosphorylation in unstimulated and stimulated neutrophils from WT mice and <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. In contrast to stimulated WT neutrophils, no Syk phosphorylation was detectable in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> neutrophils after stimulation (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5 E</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Elimination of DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; abolishes E-selectin&#x02013;dependent downstream signaling in neutrophils</title><p>p38 MAPK is phosphorylated after E-selectin engagement and is involved in neutrophil slow rolling and adhesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref>). Pharmacological inhibition of p38 MAPK reduces slow rolling on E-selectin plus ICAM-1 through unknown mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref>). Consistent with this functional role, WT neutrophils incubated with immobilized E-selectin show significant induction of p38 MAPK phosphorylation that peaked at 10 min (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6, A and B</xref>). <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> neutrophils failed to phosphorylate p38 MAPK after stimulation with E-selectin (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6 C</xref>). In contrast, phosphorylation of p38 MAPK was normal in <italic>Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> or <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> neutrophils (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6 C</xref>). These data suggest that ITAM domains provided either by DAP12 or FcR&#x003b3; are sufficient for downstream signaling after E-selectin engagement.</p><fig position="float" id="fig6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><bold>Elimination of DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; abolishes E-selectin-mediated downstream signaling in neutrophils.</bold> (A and B) Bone marrow&#x02013;derived neutrophils from WT mice were plated on uncoated (unstimulated) or E-selectin&#x02013;coated plates for the indicated times, after which lysates were prepared and immunoblotted with antibody to phosphorylated p38 MAPK (phospho-p38) or total p38 (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 2). Data in B normalized to phospho-p38 in unstimulated WT neutrophils (<italic>n</italic> &#x0003d; 2). (C) Immunoblot analysis of total cell lysates generated from bone marrow&#x02013;derived neutrophils of WT mice, <italic>Fcrg</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, <italic>Tyrobp</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, and <italic>Tyrobp</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> F<italic>crg</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with antibody to phosphorylated p38 MAPK (phospho-p38) or total p38 (total p38). This was confirmed in four additional experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jem2052339f06"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Several prior studies have shown that engagement of selectin receptors on neutrophils can activate Src-family kinases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>), induce Syk phosphorylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>), integrin activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>), slow rolling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>), and adhesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref>). However, the proximal signaling pathway between PSGL-1 and Syk was still unknown. In this study, we demonstrate that the Src-family kinase Fgr was indispensable for PSGL-1&#x02013;dependent Syk activation and slow neutrophil rolling in vitro and in vivo. After E-selectin engagement, Fgr was activated and ITAM-containing adaptor proteins became phosphorylated and subsequently associated with Syk. Eliminating both DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; blocked this signaling pathway, and G&#x003b1;<sub>i</sub>-independent neutrophil recruitment into the peritoneal cavity was defective in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, confirming the physiological relevance of this signaling pathway.</p><p>The PSGL-1&#x02013;Fgr&#x02013;DAP12&#x02013;FcR&#x003b3; pathway has striking similarities to the immunoreceptor and integrin outside-in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>) signaling pathways. However, there are also significant differences. Elimination of only one Src-family kinase does not affect &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrin&#x02013;dependent neutrophil functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>) or the inflammatory response in an endotoxic shock model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref>). At least two Src-family kinases must be eliminated to reduce &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrin&#x02013;dependent neutrophil adhesion and superoxide production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref>). However, such a redundancy does not exist in the E-selectin&#x02013;mediated signaling pathway. Elimination of Fgr abolishes downstream signaling, including Syk phosphorylation and slow neutrophil rolling. This study is one of the few examples demonstrating a specific and nonredundant function for a Src-family kinase. In most other signaling pathways studied, one Src-family kinase may be dominant (such as Src in &#x003b2;<sub>3</sub> integrin signaling in osteoclasts or Lyn in inhibitory signaling in B lymphocytes), or there may be no apparent kinase selectivity (such as in integrin signaling). The specific role of Fgr in neutrophil PSGL-1 signaling is unique and provides a potential explanation for the evolution of this individual member of the Src kinase family.</p><p>Another difference between PSGL-1 and immunoreceptor or integrin signaling is the strength of the signal. E-selectin engagement of PSGL-1 induces downstream signaling and leads to partial activation of &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> integrins on the leukocyte surface, resulting in slow rolling on ICAM-1. In the autoperfused flow chamber, this activation is insufficient to cause arrest. This suggests that signaling through PSGL-1 is weak compared with other immunoreceptor pathways such as TREM1, which can induce firm adhesion, and even activation, of effector functions like cytokine production and degranulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>).</p><p>A study with isolated human neutrophils showed that P-selectin engagement of PSGL-1 induced Lyn and Hck activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref>). However, this study may be complicated by the ligands used. Piccardoni et al. stimulated neutrophils with either fixed platelets or a P-selectin&#x02013;IgG chimera containing an Fc portion that does not rule out the possibility that the signal was induced by outside-in integrin signaling or engagement of Fc receptors. In our in vitro assay, we can exclude signaling through engagement of Fc receptors, because neutrophils from <italic>Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, which cannot signal through Fc receptors, show the same phosphorylation pattern of p38 as WT mice. Together with the present study, these data suggest that engagement of E- or P-selectin may activate different Src-family kinases.</p><p>Although Fgr is activated after E-selectin engagement of PSGL-1, the mechanism of this interaction remains unknown. It is tempting to speculate that phosphatases like CD45 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref>) and/or kinases like Csk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">42</xref>) may be involved in this process. Csk phosphorylates tyrosine 527 near the C-terminus of Fgr, which blocks Fgr activation. CD45 is a plausible candidate phosphatase that may dephosphorylate Y527 and activate Fgr (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref>). Indeed, elimination of phosphatases is associated with a proinflammatory phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">42</xref>). Further detailed studies are needed to determine how Fgr is activated after E-selectin engagement of PSGL-1.</p><p>The tyrosine kinase Syk cannot directly interact with the cytoplasmatic tail of PSGL-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>). In HL-60 cells, the ITAM-containing adaptor proteins ezrin and moesin can act as linkers between the two molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>). In this study, we demonstrate that the ITAM-containing adaptor proteins DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; provide alternative linkers, and eliminating both adaptor proteins abolishes E-selectin&#x02013;mediated downstream signaling and slow rolling. This suggests that the ITAM domains of ezrin and moesin cannot substitute for DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3;. One likely explanation for this is that ITAM-containing adaptor molecules may be compartmentalized in the neutrophil, with one set (DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3;) promoting slow rolling and another (ezrin and moesin) involved in directing PSGL-1 to the uropod of migrating cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref>). Compartmentalization of multimolecular signaling complexes is known to be important for linking different signals at the appropriate time and location to specific signaling cascades in the cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref>). Both FcR&#x003b3; and DAP12 associate with many cell surface receptors in various hematopoietic cell types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>). However, PSGL-1, unlike TREM-1, myeloid DAP12-associating lectin-1, and signal-regulatory protein &#x003b2;, does not contain a basic amino acid in its transmembrane domain. Therefore, the interaction between DAP12 or FcR&#x003b3; and PSGL-1 may be indirect. Other transmembrane proteins may be involved in linking PSGL-1 to DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3;. The finding that PSGL-1 resides in lipid rafts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">46</xref>) may bring it into close enough proximity to allow productive interactions with DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3;.</p><p>Our data suggest that DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; are partially redundant in slow rolling after PSGL-1 engagement by E-selectin. However, they seem to be fully redundant for p38 MAPK phosphorylation, because the phosphorylation level is indistinguishable in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> or <italic>Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> neutrophils, but completely absent in double knockouts. This raises the possibility that more than one signaling pathway may be involved in LFA-1 activation after PSGL-1 binding to E-selectin. The p38 MAPK-dependent arm of the pathway may require only one ITAM domain-containing species, DAP12 or FcR&#x003b3;, whereas another arm of the pathway may require both, resulting in partial loss of slow rolling function in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> or <italic>Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice.</p><p>The reduction of neutrophil recruitment in <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice after blocking GPCR signaling is quantitatively similar to the reduction seen in PTx-treated <italic>syk<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> chimeric mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). This suggests that eliminating DAP12 and FcR&#x003b3; is as effective in blocking neutrophil recruitment as eliminating Syk. Like <italic>syk<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> chimeric mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>) or E-selectin&#x02013;deficient (<italic>Sele<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>) mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref>), <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice show defective neutrophil recruitment to the inflamed peritoneum when chemokine receptor signaling is blocked. These data demonstrate the physiological relevance of the E-selectin&#x02013;mediated PSGL-1 pathway in vivo. The new mechanistic insights we provide here suggest that Syk, DAP12, and FcR&#x003b3; may be therapeutic targets for antiinflammatory therapy. The specific role of Fgr suggests that specific Fgr inhibitors that do not block Lyn or Hck could be devised that may specifically block E-selectin&#x02013;dependent neutrophil activation, perhaps without compromising host defense.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec disp-level="3"><title>Animals and bone marrow chimeras.</title><p>8&#x02013;12-wk-old C57BL/6 mice (The Jackson Laboratory), DAP12 (<italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref>), FcR&#x003b3; (<italic>Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref>), <italic>Tyrobp<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>), Fgr (<italic>fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref>), Lyn (<italic>lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">49</xref>), Hck (<italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref>), Hck/Lyn/Fgr (<italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> fgr<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>)</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref>), and Syk (<italic>syk<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>) mice were housed in a specific pathogen&#x02013;free facility. The Animal Care and Use Committees of the University of Virginia, the La Jolla Institute for Allergy and Immunology, and the University of California at San Francisco approved all animal experiments. Chimeric mice were generated by performing bone marrow transplantation, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref>). In brief, bone marrow cells isolated from Lys-M-GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref>) and gene-deficient mice were mixed 1:1, and 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> unfractionated cells were injected intravenously into lethally irradiated mice. Experiments were performed 6&#x02013;8 wk after bone marrow transplantation.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Intravital microscopy.</title><p>2 h before cremaster muscle exteriorization, mice received 4 &#x003bc;g PTx i.v. (Sigma-Aldrich) and 500 ng TNF-&#x003b1; intrascrotally (R&#x00026;D Systems). Mice were anesthetized with an i.p. injection of 125 mg/kg ketamine hydrochloride (Sanofi), 0.025 mg/kg atropine sulfate (Fujisawa), and 12.5 mg/kg xylazine (TranquiVed; Phoenix Scientific) and placed on a heating pad. The cremaster muscle was prepared as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">51</xref>). Postcapillary venules with a diameter between 20 and 40 &#x003bc;m were recorded using an intravital microscope (Axioskop, SW 40/0.75 objective; Carl Zeiss, Inc.) through a digital camera (sensicam qe; Cooke Corporation). Blood flow centerline velocity was measured using a dual-photodiode sensor system (CircuSoft Instrumentation).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Blood-perfused microflow chamber.</title><p>Autoperfused flow chambers were used to investigate the rolling velocity of neutrophils, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref>). Rectangular glass capillaries (20 &#x000d7; 200 &#x003bc;m) were coated either with 30 &#x003bc;g/ml E-selectin (R&#x00026;D Systems) alone or in combination with 15 &#x003bc;g/ml ICAM-1 (R&#x00026;D Systems) for 2 h and blocked with 10% casein (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Each capillary was connected to a PE 10 catheter (Becton Dickinson) inserted into a mouse carotid artery. Wall shear stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref>) was controlled by hydrostatic pressure applied to the downstream side of the flow chamber. One representative field of view was recorded for 1 min using an SW40/0.75 objective and a charge-coupled device camera (VE-1000CD; Dage-MTI).</p><p>In some experiments, mice were pretreated with the specific Src-family kinase inhibitor PP2 (10 &#x003bc;g/kg, i.v., 30 min before the experiments, Calbiochem) or the inactive control (PP3).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Engagement of PSGL-1 with E-selectin.</title><p>For biochemical assays, 15-mm Petri dishes were coated with 3 &#x003bc;g/ml E-selectin for 2 h and blocked with casein. Bone marrow neutrophils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref>) were suspended in PBS (containing 1 mM each CaCl<sub>2</sub> and MgCl<sub>2</sub>) and incubated at 65 rpm for 10 min at 37&#x000b0;C. Neutrophils were lysed with RIPA buffer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>). Lysates were boiled with sample buffer or incubated with protein A&#x02013;coated magnetic beads (Miltenyi Biotec) and rabbit anti-Syk (N-19; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) antibody for 30 min on ice and separated using a magnet (Miltenyi Biotec). Beads were washed four times and bound proteins were eluted by adding boiling sample buffer. To test DAP12 phosphorylation, GST-Syk-(SH2)2 was coupled to glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads (GE Healthcare), as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>).</p><p>Cell lysates and immunoprecipitates were run on 10% SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted using antibodies against phosphotyrosine (4G10; Millipore), p38 MAP kinase (3D7), and phospho-p38 MAP kinase (both from Cell Signaling Technology), developed using GE Healthcare's ECL system, and analyzed by ImageJ (National Institutes of Health).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Peritonitis model.</title><p>Peritonitis was induced by injecting sterile 4% thioglycollate i.p. (Sigma-Aldrich) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref>). Some mice received 4 &#x003bc;g PTx i.v. 2 h before thioglycollate injection. After 8 h, mice were killed, the peritoneal cavity was rinsed with 10 ml PBS (containing 2 mM EDTA), and the number of leukocytes was counted. Neutrophils were detected by flow cytometry (FACSCalibur; BD Biosciences) based on expression of CD45 (clone 30-F11), 7/4 (clone 7/4; both from BD Biosciences), and GR-1 (clone RB6-8C5).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Statistics.</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed with SPSS (version 14.0, Chicago, IL) and included one-way analysis of variance, Student-Newman-Keuls test, and Student's <italic>t</italic> test where appropriate. All data are presented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. P &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Online supplemental material.</title><p>Fig. S1 shows Src and Syk phosphorylation by E-selectin engagement in <italic>hck<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> and <italic>lyn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. Video 1 shows intravital microscopy of an inflamed cremaster muscle venule of a mixed chimeric mouse treated with PTx and a monoclonal blocking P-selectin antibody (GFP<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>, WT leukocytes; GFP<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, <italic>Tyrob<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> Fcrg<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> leukocytes). The online version of this article is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20072660/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20072660/DC1</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>[Supplemental Material Index]</title></caption><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20072660_index.html"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20072660_1.html"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20072660_JEM_20072660_FS1.jpg"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="jem.20072660_JEM_20072660_FS1-01.jpg"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="jem.20072660_2.html"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="quicktime" xlink:href="jem.20072660_JEM_20072660_V1.mov"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was supported by grants from Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (AZ 428/2-1 and 428/3-1 to A. Zarbock) and from the National Institutes of Health (NIH HL73361 to K. Ley and AI065495 to C.A. Lowell).</p><p>The authors have no conflicting financial interests.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal">Butcher, E.C. <year>1991</year>. Leukocyte-endothelial cell recognition: three (or more) steps to specificity and diversity. <source>Cell.</source><volume>67</volume>:<fpage>1033</fpage>&#x02013;1036.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1760836</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal">Springer, T.A. <year>1994</year>. Traffic signals for lymphocyte recirculation and leukocyte emigration: the multistep paradigm. <source>Cell.</source><volume>76</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;314.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7507411</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ley, K., C. Laudanna, M.I. Cybulsky, and S. Nourshargh. <year>2007</year>. Getting to the site of inflammation: the leukocyte adhesion cascade updated. <source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><volume>7</volume>:<fpage>678</fpage>&#x02013;689.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17717539</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal">Jung, U., D.C. Bullard, T.F. Tedder, and K. Ley. <year>1996</year>. Velocity differences between L- and P-selectin-dependent neutrophil rolling in venules of mouse cremaster muscle in vivo. <source>Am. J. Physiol.</source><volume>271</volume>:<fpage>H2740</fpage>&#x02013;H2747.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8997339</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kunkel, E.J., and K. Ley. <year>1996</year>. Distinct phenotype of E-selectin-deficient mice. E-selectin is required for slow leukocyte rolling in vivo. <source>Circ. Res.</source><volume>79</volume>:<fpage>1196</fpage>&#x02013;1204.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8943958</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal">Zarbock, A., C.A. Lowell, and K. Ley. <year>2007</year>. Spleen tyrosine kinase Syk is necessary for E-selectin-induced alpha(L)beta(2) integrin-mediated rolling on intercellular adhesion molecule-1. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>26</volume>:<fpage>773</fpage>&#x02013;783.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17543554</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal">Wang, H.B., J.T. Wang, L. Zhang, Z.H. Geng, W.L. Xu, T. Xu, Y. Huo, X. Zhu, E.F. Plow, M. Chen, and J.G. Geng. <year>2007</year>. P-selectin primes leukocyte integrin activation during inflammation. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source><volume>8</volume>:<fpage>882</fpage>&#x02013;892.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17632516</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal">Hentzen, E., D. McDonough, L. McIntire, C.W. Smith, H.L. Goldsmith, and S.I. Simon. <year>2002</year>. Hydrodynamic shear and tethering through E-selectin signals phosphorylation of p38 MAP kinase and adhesion of human neutrophils. <source>Ann. Biomed. Eng.</source><volume>30</volume>:<fpage>987</fpage>&#x02013;1001.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12449760</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal">Simon, S.I., Y. Hu, D. Vestweber, and C.W. Smith. <year>2000</year>. Neutrophil tethering on E-selectin activates beta 2 integrin binding to ICAM-1 through a mitogen-activated protein kinase signal transduction pathway. <source>J. Immunol.</source><volume>164</volume>:<fpage>4348</fpage>&#x02013;4358.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10754335</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal">Urzainqui, A., J.M. Serrador, F. Viedma, M. Yanez-Mo, A. Rodriguez, A.L. Corbi, J.L. Alonso-Lebrero, A. Luque, M. Deckert, J. Vazquez, and F. Sanchez-Madrid. <year>2002</year>. ITAM-based interaction of ERM proteins with Syk mediates signaling by the leukocyte adhesion receptor PSGL-1. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>17</volume>:<fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;412.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12387735</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal">Dunne, J.L., C.M. Ballantyne, A.L. Beaudet, and K. Ley. <year>2002</year>. Control of leukocyte rolling velocity in TNF-alpha-induced inflammation by LFA-1 and Mac-1. <source>Blood.</source><volume>99</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>&#x02013;341.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11756189</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal">Salas, A., M. Shimaoka, A.N. Kogan, C. Harwood, U.H. von Andrian, and T.A. Springer. <year>2004</year>. Rolling adhesion through an extended conformation of integrin alphaLbeta2 and relation to alpha I and beta I-like domain interaction. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>20</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;406.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084269</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal">Shimaoka, M., A. Salas, W. Yang, G. Weitz-Schmidt, and T.A. Springer. <year>2003</year>. Small molecule integrin antagonists that bind to the beta2 subunit I-like domain and activate signals in one direction and block them in the other. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>19</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;402.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14499114</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal">Knorr, R., and M.L. Dustin. <year>1997</year>. The lymphocyte function&#x02013;associated antigen 1 I domain is a transient binding module for intercellular adhesion molecule (ICAM)-1 and ICAM-3 in hydrodynamic flow. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source><volume>186</volume>:<fpage>719</fpage>&#x02013;730.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9271587</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal">Burkhardt, A.L., M. Brunswick, J.B. Bolen, and J.J. Mond. <year>1991</year>. Anti-immunoglobulin stimulation of B lymphocytes activates src-related protein-tyrosine kinases. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source><volume>88</volume>:<fpage>7410</fpage>&#x02013;7414.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1714601</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal">Parsons, J.T., and S.J. Parsons. <year>1997</year>. Src family protein tyrosine kinases: cooperating with growth factor and adhesion signaling pathways. <source>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol.</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;192.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9069259</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal">Hallek, M., C. Neumann, M. Schaffer, S. Danhauser-Riedl, N. von Bubnoff, G. de Vos, B.J. Druker, K. Yasukawa, J.D. Griffin, and B. Emmerich. <year>1997</year>. Signal transduction of interleukin-6 involves tyrosine phosphorylation of multiple cytosolic proteins and activation of Src-family kinases Fyn, Hck, and Lyn in multiple myeloma cell lines. <source>Exp. Hematol.</source><volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1367</fpage>&#x02013;1377.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9406996</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ma, Y.C., J. Huang, S. Ali, W. Lowry, and X.Y. Huang. <year>2000</year>. Src tyrosine kinase is a novel direct effector of G proteins. <source>Cell.</source><volume>102</volume>:<fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;646.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11007482</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lowell, C.A., and G. Berton. <year>1999</year>. Integrin signal transduction in myeloid leukocytes. <source>J. Leukoc. Biol.</source><volume>65</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;320.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10080533</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal">Thomas, S.M., and J.S. Brugge. <year>1997</year>. Cellular functions regulated by Src family kinases. <source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source><volume>13</volume>:<fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;609.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442882</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal">Abram, C.L., and C.A. Lowell. <year>2007</year>. Convergence of immunoreceptor and integrin signaling. <source>Immunol. Rev.</source><volume>218</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;44.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17624942</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal">Fodor, S., Z. Jakus, and A. Mocsai. <year>2006</year>. ITAM-based signaling beyond the adaptive immune response. <source>Immunol. Lett.</source><volume>104</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;37.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16332394</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal">Humphrey, M.B., L.L. Lanier, and M.C. Nakamura. <year>2005</year>. Role of ITAM-containing adapter proteins and their receptors in the immune system and bone. <source>Immunol. Rev.</source><volume>208</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;65.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16313340</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal">Alonso-Lebrero, J.L., J.M. Serrador, C. Dominguez-Jimenez, O. Barreiro, A. Luque, M.A. del Pozo, K. Snapp, G. Kansas, R. Schwartz-Albiez, H. Furthmayr, et al. <year>2000</year>. Polarization and interaction of adhesion molecules P-selectin glycoprotein ligand 1 and intercellular adhesion molecule 3 with moesin and ezrin in myeloid cells. <source>Blood.</source><volume>95</volume>:<fpage>2413</fpage>&#x02013;2419.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10733515</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lanier, L.L., and A.B. Bakker. <year>2000</year>. The ITAM-bearing transmembrane adaptor DAP12 in lymphoid and myeloid cell function. <source>Immunol. Today.</source><volume>21</volume>:<fpage>611</fpage>&#x02013;614.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114420</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lanier, L.L., B. Corliss, J. Wu, and J.H. Phillips. <year>1998</year>. Association of DAP12 with activating CD94/NKG2C NK cell receptors. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>8</volume>:<fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;701.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9655483</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal">Dietrich, J., M. Cella, M. Seiffert, H.J. Buhring, and M. Colonna. <year>2000</year>. Cutting edge: signal-regulatory protein beta 1 is a DAP12-associated activating receptor expressed in myeloid cells. <source>J. Immunol.</source><volume>164</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;12.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10604985</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal">Bakker, A.B., E. Baker, G.R. Sutherland, J.H. Phillips, and L.L. Lanier. <year>1999</year>. Myeloid DAP12-associating lectin (MDL)-1 is a cell surface receptor involved in the activation of myeloid cells. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source><volume>96</volume>:<fpage>9792</fpage>&#x02013;9796.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10449773</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal">Bouchon, A., J. Dietrich, and M. Colonna. <year>2000</year>. Cutting edge: inflammatory responses can be triggered by TREM-1, a novel receptor expressed on neutrophils and monocytes. <source>J. Immunol.</source><volume>164</volume>:<fpage>4991</fpage>&#x02013;4995.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10799849</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal">Mina-Osorio, P., and E. Ortega. <year>2004</year>. Signal regulators in FcR-mediated activation of leukocytes? <source>Trends Immunol.</source><volume>25</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;535.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15364055</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal">Takai, T., M. Li, D. Sylvestre, R. Clynes, and J.V. Ravetch. <year>1994</year>. FcR gamma chain deletion results in pleiotrophic effector cell defects. <source>Cell.</source><volume>76</volume>:<fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;529.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8313472</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal">Mocsai, A., C.L. Abram, Z. Jakus, Y. Hu, L.L. Lanier, and C.A. Lowell. <year>2006</year>. Integrin signaling in neutrophils and macrophages uses adaptors containing immunoreceptor tyrosine-based activation motifs. <source>Nat. Immunol.</source><volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1326</fpage>&#x02013;1333.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17086186</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal">Meng, F., and C.A. Lowell. <year>1997</year>. Lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced macrophage activation and signal transduction in the absence of Src-family kinases Hck, Fgr, and Lyn. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source><volume>185</volume>:<fpage>1661</fpage>&#x02013;1670.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9151903</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal">Faust, N., F. Varas, L.M. Kelly, S. Heck, and T. Graf. <year>2000</year>. Insertion of enhanced green fluorescent protein into the lysozyme gene creates mice with green fluorescent granulocytes and macrophages. <source>Blood.</source><volume>96</volume>:<fpage>719</fpage>&#x02013;726.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10887140</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal">Smith, M.L., T.S. Olson, and K. Ley. <year>2004</year>. CXCR2- and E-selectin&#x02013;induced neutrophil arrest during inflammation in vivo. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source><volume>200</volume>:<fpage>935</fpage>&#x02013;939.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466624</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal">Mocsai, A., M. Zhou, F. Meng, V.L. Tybulewicz, and C.A. Lowell. <year>2002</year>. Syk is required for integrin signaling in neutrophils. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>16</volume>:<fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;558.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11970878</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal">Chesnutt, B.C., D.F. Smith, N.A. Raffler, M.L. Smith, E.J. White, and K. Ley. <year>2006</year>. Induction of LFA-1-dependent neutrophil rolling on ICAM-1 by engagement of E-selectin. <source>Microcirculation.</source><volume>13</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;109.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16459323</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal">Piccardoni, P., R. Sideri, S. Manarini, A. Piccoli, N. Martelli, G. de Gaetano, C. Cerletti, and V. Evangelista. <year>2001</year>. Platelet/polymorphonuclear leukocyte adhesion: a new role for SRC kinases in Mac-1 adhesive function triggered by P-selectin. <source>Blood.</source><volume>98</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;116.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11418469</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lowell, C.A., L. Fumagalli, and G. Berton. <year>1996</year>. Deficiency of Src family kinases p59/61hck and p58c-fgr results in defective adhesion-dependent neutrophil functions. <source>J. Cell Biol.</source><volume>133</volume>:<fpage>895</fpage>&#x02013;910.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8666673</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lowell, C.A., and G. Berton. <year>1998</year>. Resistance to endotoxic shock and reduced neutrophil migration in mice deficient for the Src-family kinases Hck and Fgr. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source><volume>95</volume>:<fpage>7580</fpage>&#x02013;7584.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9636192</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kishihara, K., J. Penninger, V.A. Wallace, T.M. Kundig, K. Kawai, A. Wakeham, E. Timms, K. Pfeffer, P.S. Ohashi, M.L. Thomas, et al. <year>1993</year>. Normal B lymphocyte development but impaired T cell maturation in CD45-exon6 protein tyrosine phosphatase-deficient mice. <source>Cell.</source><volume>74</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;156.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8334701</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal">Thomas, R.M., C. Schmedt, M. Novelli, B.K. Choi, J. Skok, A. Tarakhovsky, and J. Roes. <year>2004</year>. C-terminal SRC kinase controls acute inflammation and granulocyte adhesion. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>20</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;191.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14975240</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal">Mustelin, T., T. Vang, and N. Bottini. <year>2005</year>. Protein tyrosine phosphatases and the immune response. <source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><volume>5</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;57.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15630428</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal">Leo, A., J. Wienands, G. Baier, V. Horejsi, and B. Schraven. <year>2002</year>. Adapters in lymphocyte signaling. <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source><volume>109</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;309.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11827988</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal">Bezman, N., and G.A. Koretzky. <year>2007</year>. Compartmentalization of ITAM and integrin signaling by adapter molecules. <source>Immunol. Rev.</source><volume>218</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;28.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17624941</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal">Abbal, C., M. Lambelet, D. Bertaggia, C. Gerbex, M. Martinez, A. Arcaro, M. Schapira, and O. Spertini. <year>2006</year>. Lipid raft adhesion receptors and Syk regulate selectin-dependent rolling under flow conditions. <source>Blood.</source><volume>108</volume>:<fpage>3352</fpage>&#x02013;3359.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16849645</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal">Bakker, A.B., R.M. Hoek, A. Cerwenka, B. Blom, L. Lucian, T. McNeil, R. Murray, L.H. Phillips, J.D. Sedgwick, and L.L. Lanier. <year>2000</year>. DAP12-deficient mice fail to develop autoimmunity due to impaired antigen priming. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>13</volume>:<fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;353.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11021532</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lowell, C.A., P. Soriano, and H.E. Varmus. <year>1994</year>. Functional overlap in the src gene family: inactivation of hck and fgr impairs natural immunity. <source>Genes Dev.</source><volume>8</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;398.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8125254</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal">Chan, V.W., F. Meng, P. Soriano, A.L. DeFranco, and C.A. Lowell. <year>1997</year>. Characterization of the B lymphocyte populations in Lyn-deficient mice and the role of Lyn in signal initiation and down-regulation. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>7</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9252121</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="journal">Zarbock, A., K. Singbartl, and K. Ley. <year>2006</year>. Complete reversal of acid-induced acute lung injury by blocking of platelet-neutrophil aggregation. <source>J. Clin. Invest.</source><volume>116</volume>:<fpage>3211</fpage>&#x02013;3219.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17143330</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ley, K., D.C. Bullard, M.L. Arbones, R. Bosse, D. Vestweber, T.F. Tedder, and A.L. Beaudet. <year>1995</year>. Sequential contribution of L- and P-selectin to leukocyte rolling in vivo. <source>J. Exp. Med.</source><volume>181</volume>:<fpage>669</fpage>&#x02013;675.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7530761</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="journal">Smith, D.F., T.L. Deem, A.C. Bruce, J. Reutershan, D. Wu, and K. Ley. <year>2006</year>. Leukocyte phosphoinositide-3 kinase &#x0007b;gamma&#x0007d; is required for chemokine-induced, sustained adhesion under flow in vivo. <source>J. Leukoc. Biol.</source><volume>80</volume>:<fpage>1491</fpage>&#x02013;1499.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16997858</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53</label><citation citation-type="journal">Stark, M.A., Y. Huo, T.L. Burcin, M.A. Morris, T.S. Olson, and K. Ley. <year>2005</year>. Phagocytosis of apoptotic neutrophils regulates granulopoiesis via IL-23 and IL-17. <source>Immunity.</source><volume>22</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;294.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15780986</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 