<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Physiol Renal Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ajprenal</journal-id><journal-title>American Journal of Physiology - Renal Physiology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0363-6127</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1522-1466</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Physiological Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">F-90258-2008</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajprenal.90258.2008</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18632794</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Human H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase a4 subunit mutations causing renal tubular acidosis reveal a role for interaction with phosphofructokinase-1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Ya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blake-Palmer</surname><given-names>Katherine G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sorrell</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Javid</surname><given-names>Babak</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>Katherine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Aiwu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Simon H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qamar</surname><given-names>Seema</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karet</surname><given-names>Fiona E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">6</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x3cccbb0N0x1d602c8">Departments of <label>1</label>Medical Genetics, <label>2</label>Medicine, <label>4</label>Hematology, and <label>6</label>Division of Renal Medicine, Cambridge University, Cambridge; <label>3</label>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University College London, London, United Kingdom; and <label>5</label>Department of Biological Sciences, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, Louisiana</aff><author-notes><fn><p>Address for reprint requests and other correspondence: F. E. Karet, Cambridge Institute for Medical Research, Addenbrooke's Hospital Box 139, Cambridge, CB2 0XY, UK (e-mail: <email>fek1000&#x00040;cam.ac.uk</email>)</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>10</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 12 months and 0 days and was based on the copyright element. --><volume>295</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>F950</fpage><lpage>F958</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008, American Physiological Society</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.the-aps.org/publications/journals/funding_addendum_policy.htm">www.the-aps.org/publications/journals/funding_addendum_policy.htm</ext-link>.</p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zh201008000950.pdf"/><abstract><p>The vacuolar-type ATPase (H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase) is a ubiquitously expressed multisubunit pump whose regulation is poorly understood. Its membrane-integral a-subunit is involved in proton translocation and in humans has four forms, a1&#x02013;a4. This study investigated two naturally occurring point mutations in a4's COOH terminus that cause recessive distal renal tubular acidosis (dRTA), R807Q and G820R. Both lie within a domain that binds the glycolytic enzyme phosphofructokinase-1 (PFK-1). We recreated these disease mutations in yeast to investigate effects on protein expression, H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase assembly, targeting and activity, and performed in vitro PFK-1 binding and activity studies of mammalian proteins. Mammalian studies revealed complete loss of binding between the COOH terminus of a4 containing the G-to-R mutant and PFK-1, without affecting PFK-1's catalytic activity. In yeast expression studies, protein levels, H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase assembly, and targeting of this mutant were all preserved. However, severe (78&#x00025;) loss of proton transport but less decrease in ATPase activity (36&#x00025;) were observed in mutant vacuoles, suggesting a requirement for the a-subunit/PFK-1 binding to couple these two functions. This role for PFK in H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase function was supported by similar functional losses and uncoupling ratio between the two proton pump domains observed in vacuoles from a <italic>PFK</italic>-null strain, which was also unable to grow at alkaline pH. In contrast, the R-to-Q mutation dramatically reduced a-subunit production, abolishing H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase function completely. Thus in the context of dRTA, stability and function of the metabolon composed of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase and glycolytic components can be compromised by either loss of required PFK-1 binding (G820R) or loss of pump protein (R807Q).</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>kidney</kwd><kwd>proton pump</kwd><kwd>yeast</kwd><kwd>glycolysis</kwd><kwd>acidosis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn><p>The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. The article must therefore be hereby marked &#x0201c;<italic>advertisement</italic>&#x0201d; in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><p><sc>transporting epithelia</sc> of the distal nephron contain a group of cells known as &#x003b1;-intercalated cells (&#x003b1;-ICs), which express a high density of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPases on their apical plasma membranes. These cells are responsible for urine acidification in response to acidosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r14">14</xref>). Proper &#x003b1;-IC function is important not only for the maintenance of bodily acid-base homeostasis, but also for maintaining calcium solubility in urine and its stability in bone. Functional failure of &#x003b1;-ICs results in metabolic acidosis, which together with nephrocalcinosis and rickets are cardinal features of distal renal tubular acidosis (dRTA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r1">1</xref>).</p><p>In addition to their vital function in the kidney, H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPases pump protons across the plasma membranes of other cell types, such as osteoclasts and cells that line the epididymis and vas deferens, as well as being essential for acidification of many intracellular compartments in eukaryotic cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r55">55</xref>).</p><p>H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPases from fungi, plants, and animals are structurally very similar, consisting of two major functional domains known as V<sub>1</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r55">55</xref>). The V<sub>1</sub> domain, comprised of eight different subunits (A-H), is responsible for ATP hydrolysis. The V<sub>0</sub> domain contains at least five different subunits (a, c, c'', d, and e) and transports protons across the membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r55">55</xref>). This proton pumping requires both structural and functional coupling of the V<sub>1</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> domains. Assembly of the V<sub>1</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> subcomplexes into the holoenzyme is completed in the ER, the pump then being targeted to the required destination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r40">40</xref>). In yeast cells lacking a V<sub>1</sub> domain, the V<sub>0</sub> domain can still be assembled and targeted onto the vacuolar membrane. Conversely, if the V<sub>0</sub> domain is absent, the V<sub>1</sub> domain is assembled, but cannot be attached onto the membrane (reviewed in Ref. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r55">55</xref>). In addition, free V<sub>1</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> domains lack MgATP hydrolytic and proton transport activity, respectively, indicating a requirement for coupling of V<sub>1</sub> to V<sub>0</sub> for normal pump function.</p><p>Yeast studies demonstrated that disruption of genes encoding any one subunit of the H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase leads to a defect of vacuolar acidification, due to failure of either pump assembly or functional coupling between V<sub>1</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r59">59</xref>). These deletion strains exhibit a conditional growth phenotype (Vma<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) whereby they can only grow at acidic pH, and not at neutral or higher pH, nor in the presence of high levels of extracellular divalent cations, nor in media containing only nonfermentable sources of carbon (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r55">55</xref>).</p><p>The H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase a-subunit, a component of the V<sub>0</sub> domain, comprises a large NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal hydrophilic half, several transmembrane helices, and a small soluble COOH-terminal tail (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r47">47</xref>). Unlike all other subunits in yeast, two different a-subunit paralogs have been identified, Vph1p and Stv1p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r39">39</xref>). Vph1p resides in the vacuole, and yeast studies suggest that its COOH-terminal tail is critical not only for proton pumping, but also for stability of Vph1p, and assembly, targeting, and activity of the pump (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r44">44</xref>). In contrast, Stv1p resides in the Golgi. Both paralogs must be absent for yeast to exhibit the conditional (Vma<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r39">39</xref>).</p><p>In both mouse and humans, four different a-subunit paralogs (a1-a4) exist. Of these, a4 is expressed predominantly in the kidney, being located apically in &#x003b1;-ICs and subapically in the proximal tubule (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r51">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r53">53</xref>). Defects in the genes encoding a4, the osteoclast-enriched a3, and endosomal a2 subunits are associated with recessively inherited dRTA (rdRTA), infantile malignant osteopetrosis, and cutis laxa, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r52">52</xref>), underscoring the functional importance of this subunit in kidney, bone, and skin.</p><p>The gene encoding a4 was identified as the second causative gene for rdRTA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r52">52</xref>), the first encoding B1, another renal H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase subunit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r22">22</xref>). A wide variety of homozygous mutations have been reported, most of which are predicted to disrupt the encoded protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r58">58</xref>). Only a few missense mutations have been described, two of which, R807Q and G820R, affect residues in the COOH terminus within a domain of the a-subunit that we previously reported is responsible for binding to PFK-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r57">57</xref>).</p><p>To date, no laboratory has been able to achieve stable epithelial cell expression of the mammalian a-subunit; so to ascertain disease-causing mechanisms in these forms of rdRTA, we turned to yeast to investigate their effects on protein expression, H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase assembly/targeting, and enzyme activity, together with the relationship between the a-subunit/PFK-1 interaction and H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase function.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec disp-level="3"><title>Strain and plasmid construction.</title><p>KEBY9, a <italic>stv1&#x00394;</italic>/<italic>vph1&#x00394;</italic> double deletion strain of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r23">23</xref>), was used for transformation of plasmid constructs. The coding regions of <italic>VPH1</italic> or <italic>STV1</italic> and their 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; UTRs amplified in-house by PCR were separately cloned into the low-copy (CEN) plasmid pRS316 to create constructs pKGB1 and pKEB4, respectively. Site-directed mutagenesis using the QuikChange Mutagenesis Kit (Stratagene) was performed using pKGB1 as template; base substitutions were separately introduced into codon 799 (CGT&#x02192;CAA) or codon 812 (GGT&#x02192;CGT), resulting in the single amino acid changes R&#x02192;Q (pKGB1-R799Q) or G&#x02192;R (pKGB1-G812R), respectively. All constructs were sequence-verified before use.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Yeast complementation assay.</title><p>KEBY9 cells were transformed with either pKGB1-R799Q, pKGB1-G812R, pKGB1, or empty vector as control, followed by selection on SD-U medium. Colonies were resuspended in 30 &#x003bc;l of H<sub>2</sub>O, which was then serially diluted and 5 &#x003bc;l of each dilution was pipetted onto YPD buffered to either pH 5, 7.5, or 7 with 100 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Cell growth was scored following incubation at 25, 30, or 37&#x000b0;C for 3 days. Each assay was performed twice.</p><p>For experiments using the <italic>PFK</italic>-null yeast strain (<italic>&#x00394;pfk1:: LEU2.&#x00394;pfk2::URA2</italic>, gift of E. Boles, Frankfurt), 2&#x00025; ethanol &#x0002b; 0.2&#x00025; glucose replaced 2&#x00025; glucose in the media, to provide a suitable carbon source while avoiding spontaneous H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase disassembly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">21</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Whole cell lysates and isolation of vacuolar membrane vesicles.</title><p>Yeast cells were grown to OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.8 in SD-U medium at 30&#x000b0;C. Whole cell lysates were prepared using YeastBuster Protein Extraction Reagent (Novagen).</p><p>Vacuolar membrane vesicles were isolated essentially as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">48</xref>) with minor modifications: after growth in SD-U at 30&#x000b0;C to OD<sub>600</sub> of 1&#x02013;2, cells resuspended in 50 mM Tris&#x000b7;HCl, pH 9.5, containing 10 mM DTT were incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 30 min. Cells were spheroplasted at 30&#x000b0;C for 90 min in 1.2 M sorbitol, 50 mM K<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> (pH 7.4), 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1&#x00025; glucose, and 3.6 mg/ml zymolyase 100T. Spheroplasts were lyzed and vacuoles were purified by flotation on a discontinuous Ficoll 400 gradient. Purified vacuoles were resuspended in TE, pH 7.4, containing 1 mM PMSF and 1 &#x003bc;g/ml leupeptin.</p><p>Whole cell lysate and vacuole samples were analyzed by Western blot using mouse monoclonal antibodies 10D7 (&#x003b1;-Vph1p) and 8B1 (&#x003b1;-Vma1p, the yeast V<sub>1</sub> domain's A subunit; Molecular Probes). Data were quantified densitometrically using ChemiImager V5.5 software.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Immunofluorescence microscopy.</title><p>Spheroplasting, fixation, and mounting of yeast cells were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r48">48</xref>). Following blocking for 1 h with 1&#x00025; normal goat serum in PBS/BSA (5 mg/ml), cells were incubated first with rabbit polyclonal &#x003b1;-Vph1p antibody (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r18">18</xref>) (gift of T. Stevens to K. Bowers) at room temperature (RT) for 2.5 h, then biotin-conjugated goat &#x003b1;-rabbit (Jackson Immuno Research) secondary for 1 h, followed by 1 h with streptavidin-conjugated fluorescein, DTAF (Jackson ImmunoResearch). Slides were mounted in Vectashield Mounting Medium with DAPI (Vector Labs). All images were collected with a Zeiss Axiovert 200M microscope.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase functional assays.</title><p>Bafilomycin-sensitive ATPase activity of yeast vacuoles was measured as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r13">13</xref>). Three micrograms of vacuoles were added into 1 ml of assay mixture &#x0005b;50 mM KCl, 50 mM Tris, pH 8.0, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.2 mM NADH, 1 mM phosphoenolpyruvate, 2 mM MgATP (pH 7.4), 10&#x02013;11 U/ml lactate dehydrogenase, and 12&#x02013;13 U/ml of pyruvate kinase (Sigma)&#x0005d; at 25&#x000b0;C. The corresponding decrease in absorbance of NADH at 340 nm was monitored for 4 min, with and without the addition of 0.3 &#x003bc;M H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase inhibitor bafilomycin A using a UV-1601 spectrophotometer.</p><p>ATP-dependent proton transport activity of yeast vacuole samples was measured using fluorescence quenching of acridine orange (Sigma) by 3&#x02013;4 &#x003bc;g vacuoles in buffer &#x0005b;20 mM Mops/Tris, pH 7, 150 mM KCl, 4 &#x003bc;M acridine orange, 1 mM Mg/ATP, with and without bafilomycin A (0.3 &#x003bc;M)&#x0005d; and corrected for mass, as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r43">43</xref>).</p><p>These H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase functional properties were measured in triplicate in each of two separate vacuole preparations. For each type of assay, comparison of wild-type (WT) with mutant activities was made by taking WT levels as 100&#x00025;.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Peptide synthesis.</title><p>Peptides corresponding to the coding sequences of the last 45 residues of WT human a4 (a4C-WT; <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) or a4C containing G820R (a4C-GR) with acetylated NH<sub>2</sub> termini were synthesized and HPLC-purified by CovalAb UK (Cambridge, UK).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Expression and purification of PFK-1.</title><p>PCR-amplified and sequence-verified cDNA encoding full-length rabbit muscle-type PFK-1 was cloned into pET5a plasmid and expressed in the <italic>PFK</italic>-deficient <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain DF1020 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r7">7</xref>), which was modified by lysogenization with lambda (DE3) prophage (Novagen) at 30&#x000b0;C for 6 h. Cells were lysed by sonication and PFK-1 was purified first through a Cibacron blue 3GA-agarose column (Sigma) and then by ammonium sulfate precipitation and finally by an HiTrap Q HP anion exchange column (Amersham Biosciences). Purity, specificity, and activity of the recombinant PFK-1 were analyzed by SDS-PAGE, Western blot using a goat polyclonal anti-PFK-1 antibody (Chemicon Europe), and enzyme activity assays, respectively (Supplementary <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), before use (the online version of this article contains supplemental data).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Surface plasmon resonance analysis.</title><p>Binding affinity analysis was performed on a BIAcore 2000 biosensor system (Pharmacia Biosensor AB) using surface plasmon resonance (SPR) measurements. A carboxymethylated CM5 sensor chip was activated with a 1:1 mixture of 0.4 M <italic>N</italic>-ethyl-<italic>N</italic>&#x02032;-(3-dimethylaminopropyl) carbodiimide and 0.1 M <italic>N</italic>-hydroxysuccinimide. Recombinant rabbit muscle-type PFK-1 (60 &#x003bc;g/ml in 10 mM NaOAc, pH 5) was then immobilized on the sensor chip by amine-coupling according to the manufacturer's instructions. Unreacted sites were blocked with 1 M ethanolamine/HCl (pH 8). Control flow cells were activated and blocked in the absence of PFK-1. Flow cells were routinely equilibrated with running buffer (PBS, 0.005&#x00025; surfactant P20). Each synthetic a4C peptide was diluted in this buffer and allowed to interact with the sensor surface by a 180-s injection. Five to one hundred seventy five micromolar each a4C peptide was injected, each at a flow rate of 10 &#x003bc;l/min at 25&#x000b0;C. Data from duplicate assays were modelled for binding equilibria using Origin (OriginLab software).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Circular dichroism spectroscopy.</title><p>Secondary structures of a4C peptides were analyzed with far-UV circular dichroism (CD) spectroscopy. Spectra were measured using a Jasco J-810 spectropolarimeter at 25&#x000b0;C. Each peptide was dissolved in 20 mM phosphate buffer (pH 7) to a final concentration of 25 or 50 &#x003bc;M before being transferred into a measuring cuvette (cell length 0.2 mm). Wavelength scans were collected in 0.2-nm decrements from 260 to 180 nm with a 1-nm bandwidth and a 2-s time constant at 50 nm/min. Ten scanning spectra were averaged for each sample. Estimates of secondary structural components were obtained using CDNN (version 2.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r3">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>PFK-1 activity assay.</title><p>PFK-1 activity measurements were conducted by coupling the reaction catalyzed by PFK-1 to oxidation of NADH and monitoring the corresponding decrease in absorbance at 340 nm at 25&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r31">31</xref>). Reaction mixtures contained 50 mM Tris&#x000b7;HCl, pH 8, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM DTT, 0.2 mM NADH, 40 &#x003bc;g/ml aldolase, 2 &#x003bc;l/ml triosephosphate isomerase &#x0002b; glycerophosphate dehydrogenase readymade mixture (Roche), 10 &#x003bc;g/ml recombinant rabbit muscle-type PFK-1, 1 mM ATP, and 0.0275 to 0.305 mM fructose-6-phosphate (F6P). To investigate the potential effects of a4C on PFK-1 activity, each a4C peptide was preincubated with PFK-1 for 2 h at RT before inclusion in the reaction mixture. Each peptide was assayed on three different occasions. Kinetic data were analyzed using Origin.</p></sec><sec disp-level="3"><title>Coimmunoprecipitation.</title><p>Thirty-five micrograms of the vacuoles isolated as above from KEBY9 cells transformed with <italic>VPH1</italic>-containing plasmid were resuspended in binding buffer (TBS, 1&#x00025; NP40, 10&#x00025; glycerol) and incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C with 20 &#x003bc;l of 13D-11 monoclonal antibody (Molecular Probes) against Vma2p, the B subunit of the V<sub>1</sub> domain. Antibody was omitted in parallel control experiments. After 1-h incubation with &#x003b1;-mouse IgG-agarose beads (Sigma), the immunoprecipitates were washed three times with <italic>buffer A</italic> (TBS, 1&#x00025; NP40, 5 mM NaN<sub>3</sub>); three times with <italic>buffer A</italic> plus 500 mM NaCl; and finally three times with <italic>buffer A</italic>. Bound proteins were eluted from beads in SDS sample buffer (0.18 M Tris&#x000b7;HCl, pH 6.8, 5.14&#x00025; SDS, 18&#x00025; glycerol, 0.3 M DTT, 0.006&#x00025; bromophenol blue) at 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min and supernatants were subjected to SDS-PAGE. Western blot was performed with an antibody against yeast Pfk (gift of J. Heinisch, Osnabr&#x000fc;eck) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r17">17</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>The <italic>ATP6V0A4</italic> mutations investigated in this study were previously reported as homozygous alterations in two different patients diagnosed with rdRTA: G820R in patient 5-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r52">52</xref>) and R807Q in patient 70-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r56">56</xref>) (Supplementary Table 1). They presented at 11 and 2 mo of age, respectively, with normal anion gap metabolic acidosis and inappropriately alkaline urine, fulfilling diagnostic criteria. Following the original report, audiometry at age 9 in patient 5-1 revealed no evidence of hearing loss, whereas by this age, severe loss was present in patient 70-1 who is now profoundly deaf.</p><p>We wished to express human a4 in the <italic>vph1&#x00394;</italic>/<italic>stv1&#x00394;</italic> double deletion yeast strain KEBY9, in which expression of either Vph1p or Stv1p restores growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r39">39</xref>). For initial validation of a yeast model, we coimmunoprecipitated the vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase and Pfk from KEBY9 reconstituted with Vph1p, to confirm that the two are associated in yeast as well as in mammalian tissue (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref>), observing a band of the correct size for yeast Pfk in the &#x0002b; lane only. Unfortunately, WT human a4 constructs in two different vectors could not complement KEBY9 growth under several conditions (Supplementary <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Instead, we took advantage of the high homology of this region across species (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref>) and recreated the mutations R799Q and G812R in conserved residues of Vph1p for these studies. Compared with WT Vph1p transformants, yeast cells carrying the R799Q mutant could not rescue the deletion phenotype (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>A</italic></xref>). However, cells containing the G812R mutant protein showed no obvious difference in growth compared with WT under all conditions tested, indicating complementation. Using whole cell lysates of each sample, Western blot using &#x003b1;-Vph1p antibody demonstrated that the level of G812R mutant protein was comparable to WT Vph1p (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>B</italic></xref>). In contrast, an 86&#x00025; reduction of R799Q mutant protein was observed, in keeping with the complementation results.</p><p>To test the effect of the mutations on assembly and targeting of the H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase, isolated vacuoles were first analyzed by Western blot using &#x003b1;-Vph1p and &#x003b1;-Vma1p antibodies, to identify a V<sub>0</sub> and a V<sub>1</sub> component, respectively. As shown in <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>C</italic></xref>, G812R mutant vacuoles showed levels of both Vph1p and Vma1p comparable to WT cells, suggesting that this mutation does not impair assembly or vacuolar targeting of the intact H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase, for which both V<sub>1</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> domains must be present. The reduced level of Vph1p observed in R799Q mutant vacuoles was similar to those found in the whole cell preparation but was still accompanied by Vma1p, suggesting that the small amount of mutant R799Q protein produced is capable of being assembled and targeted onto vacuolar membranes.</p><p>Concomitant immunocytochemistry showed that similar to WT Vph1p (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <italic>A&#x02013;C</italic>), the G812R mutant was expressed and localized at the vacuolar membrane (<italic>E</italic> and <italic>F</italic>) in almost every cell (<italic>D</italic>), further confirming normal expression and targeting of these mutant pumps. Predictably, the majority of R799Q mutant cells showed almost no Vph1p staining (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3<italic>G</italic></xref>). However, a small population of cells did show some vacuolar membrane localization of mutant Vph1p (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <italic>H</italic> and <italic>I</italic>), in good agreement with data in <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>C</italic></xref>.</p><p>We next investigated both ATPase and proton translocation activity of R799Q or G812R mutant pumps. As expected from the low protein levels, the R799Q mutation led to almost complete loss of both bafilomycin-sensitive ATPase and proton transport activity, indicating a lethal effect of this mutation on H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase function (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). In marked contrast, the G812R mutant lost 36 &#x000b1; 5&#x00025; of WT levels of bafilomycin-sensitive ATPase activity, but a much greater fraction of proton transport (78 &#x000b1; 4&#x00025;). The significant difference between these (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003d; 0.023 by <italic>t</italic>-test) is indicative that this mutation leads to loss of the required functional coupling between proton transport (V<sub>0</sub>) and ATP hydrolysis (V<sub>1</sub>), but preserves enough proton translocation to permit yeast cell growth at alkaline pH. Interestingly, the severe loss of proton translocation observed for this mutant is similar to that reported in an earlier study of a3 and a4 subunit mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r44">44</xref>) but there, ATPase activity was also severely impaired. The authors used a different yeast strain, in which Vph1p but not Stv1p was deleted, and this difference is one feature that may account for differing results.</p><p>In the face of preserved expression, assembly, and targeting of this mutant H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase, we hypothesized that the functional uncoupling and severe reduction in pump activity engendered by the G to R substitution might result from disruption of the a4/PFK-1 interaction. To test this, we expressed, purified, and confirmed the enzymatic activity of full-length rabbit muscle-type PFK-1 (Supplementary <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), synthesized WT and mutant peptides corresponding to the last 45 amino acids of human a4 (a4C-WT and a4C-GR), and then performed SPR analysis using the BIAcore system.</p><p>BIAcore measurements are expressed in resonance units (RU) proportional to the concentration of immobilized protein. <xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>C</italic>, displays sensorgrams of a4C-WT (<italic>top</italic>) or a4C-GR mutant peptide (<italic>bottom</italic>) binding to PFK-1 and <xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, shows the corresponding binding curves. The <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> value for a4C-WT/PFK-1 interaction was 29.4 &#x000b1; 6.2 &#x003bc;M. A similar value was obtained using rabbit liver-type PFK-1 (Sigma) in place of the recombinant muscle-type PFK-1 (data not shown). However, the <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> value for a4C-GR/PFK-1 interaction could not be generated due to extremely low affinity, indicating severe disruption of binding.</p><p>We then asked whether this disruption might be explained by secondary structural alteration in a4C-GR. The CD spectra of both WT and mutant a4C peptides exhibit the two large negative bands &#x0223c;208 and 222 nm suggestive of mainly &#x003b1;-helical structure in solution. <xref rid="f6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref> shows data for 50 &#x003bc;M peptides; data for 25 &#x003bc;M analysis were not different. A rightward shift was evident in the a4C-GR mutant spectrum, and spectral analysis using the program CDNN suggested an increase in random coils of almost 50&#x00025;, with a concomitantly decreased &#x003b1;-helical content in the mutant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>), indicating some loss of regular structure.</p><p>To exclude a direct effect of the a4C-GR peptide on enzyme activity of PFK-1, we measured the comparative activity of PFK-1 in phosphorylating F6P with and without inclusion of WT or mutant a4C. a4C-WT peptides ranging between 3 and 50 &#x003bc;M were initially preincubated with PFK-1 and then incorporated into a reaction mixture containing an excess of F6P; similar activity levels were found (Supplementary <xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Thereafter, experiments employing 6 &#x003bc;M a4C with varying amounts of F6P generated saturation curves and kinetic parameters that best fitted the first-order Michaelis-Menten equation (<xref rid="f7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). Specific activity and <italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub> values for a4C peptide-bound PFK-1 were not significantly different from that of free PFK-1 alone (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.45), confirming that neither WT nor mutant a4C peptide affected PFK-1's catalytic ability.</p><p>Finally, to confirm the role of PFK in proton pump regulation, we employed a <italic>Saccharomyces</italic> strain lacking this enzyme. Yeast Pfk is a hetero-octamer containing two subunits, &#x003b1; and &#x003b2;, encoded by <italic>PFK</italic>-1 and -2, respectively. The <italic>Pfk1/Pfk2</italic> null strain requires a nonfermentable carbon source such as ethanol for growth. In the presence of both ethanol and a small amount of glucose (to prevent H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase disassembly), <xref rid="f8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8<italic>A</italic></xref> demonstrates that like yeast lacking both proton pump a-subunits, the absence of Pfk imposes a pH-conditional growth phenotype whereby growth cannot proceed at raised pH, indicating defective vacuolar function. Second (<xref rid="f8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8<italic>B</italic></xref>), vacuoles isolated from this strain behaved similarly to those from the G812R mutant strain, demonstrating similar loss of bafilomycin-sensitive ATPase activity (39 &#x000b1; 1&#x00025;) compared with WT <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, with again a much more severe accompanying proton translocation loss (83 &#x000b1; 2&#x00025;), confirming Pfk's role as a cofactor for proton pump function and necessary mediator of functional coupling between V<sub>1</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> domains.</p></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPases form complexes with glycolytic enzymes; we previously identified an interaction between the COOH-terminal tail of the human a-subunit and PFK-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r57">57</xref>), and the E subunit has been found to interact with aldolase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r35">35</xref>). Since the integrity of proton pump function is dependent on the presence of glucose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">21</xref>), these observations provided a potential regulatory mechanism for H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase in higher eukaryotes, and highlight the functional importance of the a-subunit's COOH terminus. By seeking insight into mechanisms of disease caused by the two known disease-causing mutations (R807Q and G820R) in the COOH terminus of a4, we here established an important role for PFK-1 in the proton pump complex.</p><p>Both R807 and G820 are highly conserved across species, and both lie within a region that is similarly highly conserved. While the R799Q mutation in the yeast model resulted in loss of protein and therefore function, which is commonly found in recessive disease, the mechanism underlying rdRTA associated with the G820R substitution is the more complex, affecting neither stability of the encoded protein nor assembly and targeting efficiency of the H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase. Instead, the observed significant reductions in both ATP hydrolysis and more importantly, proton translocation, were associated with a dramatically lowered binding affinity between the mutant a-subunit tail and PFK-1, such that the interaction was too weak to generate kinetic data. This disruption of binding could have resulted from the change of the residue's charge and/or from the change in secondary structure of the a4C region as suggested by CD spectroscopy analysis.</p><p>Coupling of proton transport and ATP hydrolysis (subserved by V<sub>0</sub> and V<sub>1</sub> domains, respectively) is essential for normal overall function of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPases. Intrinsic subunits from both domains (namely A, C, H, a, and d) have been reported to play a role in this functional coupling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r50">50</xref>). Although changes in coupling efficiency are recognized as an important mechanism for regulating H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase activity, being affected by nonprotein factors such as ATP, trypsin, or NaN<sub>3</sub>, the normal intracellular signals controlling coupling remain unclear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r11">11</xref>). Our finding of a role for PFK, a known pump-associated protein, provides new insight into the regulation of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase activity.</p><p>Having confirmed that in yeast, as in humans, the H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase and PFK are associated, we have gone on to demonstrate that the Pfk-null yeast vacuoles behave similarly to the G812R mutant strain, with much more severe impairment of proton transport than of ATPase activity, showing the necessity of this glycolytic enzyme for functional coupling of the different domains of the pump and supporting the concept that loss of function and uncoupling caused by the G812R substitution are directly associated with loss of binding of PFK-1 to a4C-GR. It is notable that whereas sufficient proton pump activity was present to permit rescue of the conditional growth phenotype in G812R mutant yeast, complete absence of Pfk did not permit growth under these conditions. This is consistent with previous studies demonstrating that a mutant strain with as little as 20&#x00025; preservation of WT pump activity is sufficient to rescue the growth phenotype, whereas less than 20&#x00025; of WT activity would display a Vma<sup>&#x02212;</sup> phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r37">37</xref>). In addition, complete absence of the glycolytic component may exert a greater overall metabolic derangement, for example an alternative carbon source to glucose must be provided to permit any growth at all.</p><p>Evidence supporting the involvement of glycolysis in regulation of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase function is not limited to our findings. Aldolase (the next enzyme down the glycolytic pathway) interacts with the H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase via the E-subunit, but the mechanism is different, affecting assembly of V<sub>1</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> domains rather than their functional coupling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r36">36</xref>). Earlier assessment of proton transport in the isolated turtle urinary bladder showed that it could be driven by the energy from both aerobic and anaerobic glycolysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r54">54</xref>). Also, investigation of the effect of glucose on the reversible assembly of the V<sub>1</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> domains of the pump complex in yeast suggested not only coupling between H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase activity and glycolysis, but also that further glucose metabolism is required, since accumulation of glucose-6-phosphate was insufficient to maintain or induce pump assembly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r46">46</xref>). Thus there are several means by which PFK-1 may function as an indirect regulator of the proton pump.</p><p>During glycolysis, PFK-1 catalyzes the phosphorylation of F6P by MgATP to form fructose 1,6-bisphosphate and MgADP. Its activity is allosterically controlled by several activators and inhibitors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r8">8</xref>). The active sites identified for substrate binding and allosteric regulation involve residues mainly located in the NH<sub>2</sub>-terminal half of PFK-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r60">60</xref>), whereas the binding region for the a-subunit that we identified is at the COOH-terminal end of PFK-1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r57">57</xref>). By comparison with the bacterial crystal structure, we could assume a priori that binding of a4 to PFK-1 would not affect its enzyme catalytic activities, and indeed, activity was not adversely affected by a4C. Thus we could exclude the possibility that abolishing the a4C/PFK-1 interaction exerts a direct effect on PFK-1 activity leading to secondary loss of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase function.</p><p>Extrapolating between species does require some caution, and while we would have preferred to perform these studies in an epithelial system, no group has successfully established stable expression of mammalian a-subunits. In our studies, we utilized human constructs wherever possible, for example in the SPR and PFK enzymatic assays. The <italic>vph1&#x00394;</italic>/<italic>stv1&#x00394;</italic> mutant yeast strain is, however, a useful tool for the study of the a-subunit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r39">39</xref>), as it can be rescued by restoration of either gene back into the double deletion strain, where it reassembles with the other subunits to reform functional H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPases. Thus transformation with WT or mutants of Vph1p alone, which normally resides in the vacuole, provides an effective cellular model.</p><p>Our results for R807Q are in good agreement with the data obtained from a yeast mutagenesis study that employed different substitutions of this residue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r24">24</xref>), in which changing the Arg to Leu, Ala, or Lys resulted in variable functional effects: dramatic destabilization of Vph1p, or a severe defect in assembly and activity of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase, or inactivated the pump without affecting assembly. In contrast, the earlier report of mutagenesis correlating to G820R in a yeast model noted above suggested a more severe decrement in ATPase activity than we observed, but similar compromise of proton translocation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r44">44</xref>). Despite overall more severe functional compromise reported there, the mutant strains were still able to grow at alkaline pH in both studies. Possible reasons for the difference include methodological variations (for example, temperature, inhibitor, or buffer components) as well as the strain difference mentioned earlier. We ensured that the linear phase of enzyme activity was assessed at constant temperature, using reagents and equipment frequently in use and validated, and obtained similar and highly reproducible results in all assays.</p><p>We were interested to consider the effects on vacuolar ATPase function of replenishing the PFK-null strain with a variant lacking the COOH-terminal domain that interacts with a4C. However, it has already been reported that such constructs result in only poor levels of protein expression, which would make interpretation impossible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r9">9</xref>). Importantly, it has been previously demonstrated that the pump spontaneously disassembles when no glucose is present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r21">21</xref>); thus for our assays, we were careful to include a small amount of glucose in the media in addition to the ethanol required by this null strain, to avoid confounding results.</p><p>Considering the phenotypic consequences of the two mutations in the patients themselves, the patient carrying two copies of the R807Q mutation has been much more severely affected than the child who is homozygous for G820R, with a younger age at diagnosis, more severe acidosis, and significant deafness. This difference is reflected in the differing effects of the mutations, since the R799Q mutation did not generate sufficient protein for any significant functional activity, whereas the G812R mutant was able to do so. Interestingly, despite its extremely low levels, almost all of the R799Q mutant produced appeared at the vacuolar membrane, implying this mutation per se does not affect assembly and targeting of the H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase, but rather protein stability with an overall ablative effect on the pump. Thus this Arg residue is critical for stable expression of the a-subunit and therefore its function.</p><p>Hearing impairment is highly variable among those carrying destructive recessive mutations in a4, but the basis of the apparent redundancy of a4 function in the inner ear in some patients is not clear. The child with predicted complete loss of a4 function due to R807Q is severely hearing impaired, whereas hearing is at present preserved in the patient with the G820R change, who is now 17. In addition, her alkali requirement has progressively diminished as she has reached teenage. A formal dietary assessment has not been carried out to determine whether the difference can be accounted for by diet or by the milder course of her disease. Previous mutagenesis studies of different subunits of yeast H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase demonstrate that growth can be observed if a reassembled mutant H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase enzyme has as little as 20&#x00025; of WT activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r37">37</xref>), and since the milder mutant retained about this level of function in vitro, we can conclude that this level of activity is sufficient to maintain inner ear fluid pH homeostasis, but not to acidify the urine adequately, at least during childhood. In addition, this particular patient may yet lose hearing in young adulthood, in common with others with reported <italic>ATP6V0A4</italic> mutation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r56">56</xref>).</p><p>In summary, these data demonstrate an important role for PFK-1 in normal proton pump function, that loss of a-subunit/PFK-1 interaction is likely to decrease the stability of the &#x0201c;metabolon&#x0201d; formed by various H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase subunits (notably E and a) and glycolytic components (aldolase and PFK-1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="r57">57</xref>), and also that differing mechanisms for rdRTA underlie these point mutations in a4.</p></sec><sec><title>GRANTS</title><p>This study was funded by the Wellcome Trust. B. Javid was a Medical Research Council Training Fellow.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>[Supplemental Figures and Tables]</title></caption><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="90258.2008_index.html"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="90258.2008_1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank W. Li, M. Eichner-Techau, E. Norgett (all CIMR), and J. Bason (Dunn Human Nutrition Unit) for technical assistance, and A. Nayir and J. Rodriguez-Soriano for referring patients 5-1 and 70-1.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Batlle</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, Sehy JT, Roseman MK, Arruda JA, Kurtzman NA. Clinical and pathophysiologic spectrum of acquired distal renal tubular acidosis. <source>Kidney Int</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;396, <year>1981</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6795380</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Beauwens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, Al-Awqati Q. Active H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> transport in the turtle urinary bladder. Coupling of transport to glucose oxidation. <source>J Gen Physiol</source><volume>68</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>&#x02013;439, <year>1976</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11270</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bohm</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, Muhr R, Jaenicke R. Quantitative analysis of protein far UV circular dichroism spectra by neural networks. <source>Protein Eng</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;195, <year>1992</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1409538</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, Brown D. New insights into the regulation of V-ATPase-dependent proton secretion. <source>Am J Physiol Renal Physiol</source><volume>292</volume>: <fpage>F1</fpage>&#x02013;F10, <year>2007</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032935</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, Lui B, Gluck S, Sabolic I. A plasma membrane proton ATPase in specialized cells of rat epididymis. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source><volume>263</volume>: <fpage>C913</fpage>&#x02013;C916, <year>1992</year>.</citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Crider</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, Andersen P, White AE, Zhou Z, Li X, Mattsson JP, Lundberg L, Keeling DJ, Xie XS, Stone DK, Peng SB. Subunit G of the vacuolar proton pump. Molecular characterization and functional expression. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>272</volume>: <fpage>10721</fpage>&#x02013;10728, <year>1997</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9099722</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Daldal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> Molecular cloning of the gene for phosphofructokinase-2 of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and the nature of a mutation, pfkB1, causing a high level of the enzyme. <source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>168</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;305, <year>1983</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6310120</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Dunaway</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> A review of animal phosphofructokinase isozymes with an emphasis on their physiological role. <source>Mol Cell Biochem</source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;91, <year>1983</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6306441</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Edelmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, Kirchberger J, Heinisch JJ, Kopperschlager G. C-terminal modification of 6-phosphofructo-1-kinase from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> and its influence on enzyme structure and activity. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>295</volume>: <fpage>992</fpage>&#x02013;999, <year>2002</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12127994</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Foe</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, Kemp RG. Properties of phospho and dephospho forms of muscle phosphofructokinase. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>257</volume>: <fpage>6368</fpage>&#x02013;6372, <year>1982</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6210694</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Forgac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> Structure, mechanism and regulation of the clathrin-coated vesicle and yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPases. <source>J Exp Biol</source><volume>203</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;80, <year>2000</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10600675</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Frattini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, Orchard PJ, Sobacchi C, Giliani S, Abinun M, Mattsson JP, Keeling DJ, Andersson AK, Wallbrandt P, Zecca L, Notarangelo LD, Vezzoni P, Villa A. Defects in TCIRG1 subunit of the vacuolar proton pump are responsible for a subset of human autosomal recessive osteopetrosis. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>25</volume>: <fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;346, <year>2000</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10888887</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Gledhill</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, Walker JE. Inhibition sites in F1-ATPase from bovine heart mitochondria. <source>Biochem J</source><volume>386</volume>: <fpage>591</fpage>&#x02013;598, <year>2005</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15537385</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Gluck</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> The structure and biochemistry of the vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> ATPase in proximal and distal urinary acidification. <source>J Bioenerg Biomembr</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;359, <year>1992</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1400280</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, Hill KJ, Stevens TH. Assembly of the yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase occurs in the endoplasmic reticulum and requires a Vma12p/Vma22p assembly complex. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>142</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;49, <year>1998</year>.</citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, Powell B, Stevens TH. Composition and assembly of the yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase complex. <source>J Exp Biol</source><volume>203</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;70, <year>2000</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10600674</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Heinisch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> Construction and physiological characterization of mutants disrupted in the phosphofructokinase genes of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>Curr Genet</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;234, <year>1986</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2965996</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, Stevens TH. Vma21p is a yeast membrane protein retained in the endoplasmic reticulum by a di-lysine motif and is required for the assembly of the vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase complex. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1039</fpage>&#x02013;1050, <year>1994</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7841520</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, Hirata R, Umemoto N, Ohya Y, Takatsuki A, Stevens TH, Anraku Y. VMA13 encodes a 54-kDa vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase subunit required for activity but not assembly of the enzyme complex in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>268</volume>: <fpage>18286</fpage>&#x02013;18292, <year>1993</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8349704</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, Stevens TH. VMA12 encodes a yeast endoplasmic reticulum protein required for vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase assembly. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>272</volume>: <fpage>25928</fpage>&#x02013;25934, <year>1997</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9325326</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, Parra KJ. Assembly and regulation of the yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase. <source>J Exp Biol</source><volume>203</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;87, <year>2000</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10600676</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Karet</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>, Finberg KE, Nelson RD, Nayir A, Mocan H, Sanjad SA, Rodriguez-Soriano J, Santos F, Cremers CW, Di Pietro A, Hoffbrand BI, Winiarski J, Bakkaloglu A, Ozen S, Dusunsel R, Goodyer P, Hulton SA, Wu DK, Skvorak AB, Morton CC, Cunningham MJ, Jha V, Lifton RP. Mutations in the gene encoding B1 subunit of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase cause renal tubular acidosis with sensorineural deafness. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>21</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;90, <year>1999</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9916796</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawasaki-Nishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, Bowers K, Nishi T, Forgac M, Stevens TH. The amino-terminal domain of the vacuolar proton-translocating ATPase a subunit controls targeting and in vivo dissociation, and the carboxyl-terminal domain affects coupling of proton transport and ATP hydrolysis. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>276</volume>: <fpage>47411</fpage>&#x02013;47420, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11592965</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kawasaki-Nishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, Nishi T, Forgac M. Arg-735 of the 100-kDa subunit a of the yeast V-ATPase is essential for proton translocation. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>98</volume>: <fpage>12397</fpage>&#x02013;12402, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11592980</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, Fox RW, Latshaw SP. Amino acid sequence at the citrate allosteric site of rabbit muscle phosphofructokinase. <source>Biochemistry</source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>3443</fpage>&#x02013;3446, <year>1987</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2958083</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kemp</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, Gunasekera D. Evolution of the allosteric ligand sites of mammalian phosphofructo-1-kinase. <source>Biochemistry</source><volume>41</volume>: <fpage>9426</fpage>&#x02013;9430, <year>2002</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12135364</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kornak</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, Reynders E, Dimopoulou A, van Reeuwijk J, Fischer B, Rajab A, Budde B, Nurnberg P, Foulquier F, Lefeber D, Urban Z, Gruenewald S, Annaert W, Brunner HG, van Bokhoven H, Wevers R, Morava E, Matthijs G, Van Maldergem L, Mundlos S. Impaired glycosylation and cutis laxa caused by mutations in the vesicular H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase subunit ATP6V0A2. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>40</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;34, <year>2008</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18157129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kornak</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, Schulz A, Friedrich W, Uhlhaas S, Kremens B, Voit T, Hasan C, Bode U, Jentsch TJ, Kubisch C. Mutations in the a3 subunit of the vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase cause infantile malignant osteopetrosis. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>2059</fpage>&#x02013;2063, <year>2000</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10942435</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>, Manolson MF, Forgac M. Function of the COOH-terminal domain of Vph1p in activity and assembly of the yeast V-ATPase. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>273</volume>: <fpage>6717</fpage>&#x02013;6723, <year>1998</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9506970</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>, Nishi T, Forgac M. Transmembrane topography of the 100-kDa a subunit (Vph1p) of the yeast vacuolar proton-translocating ATPase. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>274</volume>: <fpage>14655</fpage>&#x02013;14661, <year>1999</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10329659</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, Zhu X, Byrnes M, Nelson JW, Chang SH. Site-directed mutagenesis of rabbit muscle phosphofructokinase cDNA. Mutations at glutamine 200 affect the allosteric properties of the enzyme. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>268</volume>: <fpage>24599</fpage>&#x02013;24606, <year>1993</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8227018</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, Rivera D, Ru W, Gunasekera D, Kemp RG. Identification of allosteric sites in rabbit phosphofructo-1-kinase. <source>Biochemistry</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>16407</fpage>&#x02013;16412, <year>1999</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10587466</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, Kane PM. Mutational analysis of the catalytic subunit of the yeast vacuolar proton-translocating ATPase. <source>Biochemistry</source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>10938</fpage>&#x02013;10948, <year>1996</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8718887</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, Ammar D, Ives H, Albrecht F, Gluck SL. Physical interaction between aldolase and vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase is essential for the assembly and activity of the proton pump. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>282</volume>: <fpage>24495</fpage>&#x02013;24503, <year>2007</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17576770</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, Holliday LS, Zhang L, Dunn WA Jr, Gluck SL. Interaction between aldolase and vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase: evidence for direct coupling of glycolysis to the ATP-hydrolyzing proton pump. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>276</volume>: <fpage>30407</fpage>&#x02013;30413, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11399750</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, Sautin YY, Holliday LS, Gluck SL. The glycolytic enzyme aldolase mediates assembly, expression, and activity of vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume>: <fpage>8732</fpage>&#x02013;8739, <year>2004</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14672945</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>MacLeod</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, Vasilyeva E, Baleja JD, Forgac M. Mutational analysis of the nucleotide binding sites of the yeast vacuolar proton-translocating ATPase. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>273</volume>: <fpage>150</fpage>&#x02013;156, <year>1998</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9417059</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Manolson</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, Proteau D, Preston RA, Stenbit A, Roberts BT, Hoyt MA, Preuss D, Mulholland J, Botstein D, Jones EW. The VPH1 gene encodes a 95-kDa integral membrane polypeptide required for in vivo assembly and activity of the yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>267</volume>: <fpage>14294</fpage>&#x02013;14303, <year>1992</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1385813</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Manolson</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, Wu B, Proteau D, Taillon BE, Roberts BT, Hoyt MA, Jones EW. STV1 gene encodes functional homologue of 95-kDa yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase subunit Vph1p. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>269</volume>: <fpage>14064</fpage>&#x02013;14074, <year>1994</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7514599</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, Forgac M. Assembly of the peripheral domain of the bovine vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-adenosine triphosphatase. <source>J Cell Physiol</source><volume>156</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;42, <year>1993</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8314860</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, Nelson N. Disruption of genes encoding subunits of yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase causes conditional lethality. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>87</volume>: <fpage>3503</fpage>&#x02013;3507, <year>1990</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2139726</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, Kawasaki-Nishi S, Forgac M. Expression and function of the mouse V-ATPase d subunit isoforms. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>278</volume>: <fpage>46396</fpage>&#x02013;46402, <year>2003</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963731</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Noumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, Beltran C, Nelson H, Nelson N. Mutational analysis of yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>88</volume>: <fpage>1938</fpage>&#x02013;1942, <year>1991</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1825730</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ochotny</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, Van Vliet A, Chan N, Yao Y, Morel M, Kartner N, von Schroeder HP, Heersche JN, Manolson MF. Effects of human a3 and a4 mutations that result in osteopetrosis and distal renal tubular acidosis on yeast V-ATPase expression and activity. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>281</volume>: <fpage>26102</fpage>&#x02013;26111, <year>2006</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16840787</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r45"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, Murata Y, Namba M, Yoshimizu T, Toyomura T, Yamamoto A, Sun-Wada GH, Hamasaki N, Wada Y, Futai M. a4, a unique kidney-specific isoform of mouse vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase subunit a. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>276</volume>: <fpage>40050</fpage>&#x02013;40054, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11498539</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r46"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, Kane PM. Reversible association between the V1 and V0 domains of yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase is an unconventional glucose-induced effect. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>18</volume>: <fpage>7064</fpage>&#x02013;7074, <year>1998</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9819393</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r47"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Perin</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, Fried VA, Stone DK, Xie XS, Sudhof TC. Structure of the 116-kDa polypeptide of the clathrin-coated vesicle/synaptic vesicle proton pump. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>266</volume>: <fpage>3877</fpage>&#x02013;3881, <year>1991</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1704894</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r48"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, Raymond CK, Yamashiro CT, Stevens TH. Methods for studying the yeast vacuole. <source>Methods Enzymol</source><volume>194</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>&#x02013;661, <year>1991</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1706462</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r49"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Sambade</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, Kane PM. The yeast V-ATPase contains a subunit homologous to the M. sexta and bovine e subunits that is essential for function. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume>: <fpage>17361</fpage>&#x02013;17365, <year>2004</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14970230</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r50"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, Nishi T, Kawasaki-Nishi S, Forgac M. Mutational analysis of the nonhomologous region of subunit A of the yeast V-ATPase. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>278</volume>: <fpage>12985</fpage>&#x02013;12991, <year>2003</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12569096</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r51"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, Finberg KE, Wagner CA, Lifton RP, Devonald MA, Su Y, Karet FE. Molecular cloning and characterization of <italic>Atp6n1b</italic>: a novel fourth murine vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase a-subunit gene. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>276</volume>: <fpage>42382</fpage>&#x02013;42388, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11495928</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r52"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, Skaug J, Choate KA, Nayir A, Bakkaloglu A, Ozen S, Hulton SA, Sanjad SA, Al-Sabban EA, Lifton RP, Scherer SW, Karet FE. Mutations in <italic>ATP6N1B</italic>, encoding a new kidney vacuolar proton pump 116-kD subunit, cause recessive distal renal tubular acidosis with preserved hearing. <source>Nat Genet</source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;75, <year>2000</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10973252</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r53"><label>53</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Stehberger</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, Schulz N, Finberg KE, Karet FE, Giebisch G, Lifton RP, Geibel JP, Wagner CA. Localization and regulation of the ATP6V0A4 (a4) vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase subunit defective in an inherited form of distal renal tubular acidosis. <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source><volume>14</volume>: <fpage>3027</fpage>&#x02013;3038, <year>2003</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14638902</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r54"><label>54</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, Husted RF, Mueller A, Beauwens R. Coupling between H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> transport and anaerobic glycolysis in turtle urinary bladder: effect of inhibitors of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> ATPase. <source>J Membr Biol</source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;34, <year>1981</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6264081</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r55"><label>55</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, Forgac M. Structure, function and regulation of the vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>779</fpage>&#x02013;808, <year>1997</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442887</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r56"><label>56</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, Borthwick KJ, Bavalia C, Eady N, Fritz DM, Rungroj N, Giersch AB, Morton CC, Axon PR, Akil I, Al-Sabban EA, Baguley DM, Bianca S, Bakkaloglu A, Bircan Z, Chauveau D, Clermont MJ, Guala A, Hulton SA, Kroes H, Li Volti G, Mir S, Mocan H, Nayir A, Ozen S, Rodriguez Soriano J, Sanjad SA, Tasic V, Taylor CM, Topaloglu R, Smith AN, Karet FE. Novel <italic>ATP6V1B1</italic> and <italic>ATP6V0A4</italic> mutations in autosomal recessive distal renal tubular acidosis with new evidence for hearing loss. <source>J Med Genet</source><volume>39</volume>: <fpage>796</fpage>&#x02013;803, <year>2002</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12414817</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r57"><label>57</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, Zhou A, Al-Lamki RS, Karet FE. The a-subunit of the V-type H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase interacts with phosphofructokinase-1 in humans. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>278</volume>: <fpage>20013</fpage>&#x02013;20018, <year>2003</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12649290</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r58"><label>58</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Vargas-Poussou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, Houillier P, Le Pottier N, Strompf L, Loirat C, Baudouin V, Macher MA, Dechaux M, Ulinski T, Nobili F, Eckart P, Novo R, Cailliez M, Salomon R, Nivet H, Cochat P, Tack I, Fargeot A, Bouissou F, Kesler GR, Lorotte S, Godefroid N, Layet V, Morin G, Jeunemaitre X, Blanchard A. Genetic investigation of autosomal recessive distal renal tubular acidosis: evidence for early sensorineural hearing loss associated with mutations in the <italic>ATP6V0A4</italic> gene. <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1437</fpage>&#x02013;1443, <year>2006</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16611712</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r59"><label>59</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Whyteside</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, Gibson L, Scott M, Finbow ME. Assembly of the yeast vacuolar H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>-ATPase and ATP hydrolysis occurs in the absence of subunit c''. <source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>579</volume>: <fpage>2981</fpage>&#x02013;2985, <year>2005</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15907326</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="r60"><label>60</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, Kemp RG. Identification of interactions that stabilize the transition state in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> phosphofructo-1-kinase. <source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>269</volume>: <fpage>18475</fpage>&#x02013;18479, <year>1994</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8034595</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-wrap><fig position="float" id="f1"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Confirmation of yeast H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase/Pfk interaction and comparison of a-subunit COOH-terminal sequences. <italic>A</italic>: Co-IP of H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase and Pfk from vacuoles of KEBY9 (a-subunit double deletion) yeast transformed with Vph1p. IP: (&#x0002b;) or (&#x02212;) indicates inclusion or omission of &#x003b1;-Vma2p; IB: &#x003b1;-Pfk. A single band corresponding to yeast Pfk is seen in the (&#x0002b;) lane only. <italic>B</italic>: amino acid sequences of the COOH termini from human and yeast orthologs and paralogs are aligned. Residues at the start and end of this domain are numbered. The highly conserved first 17 amino acids are highlighted in gray. Conserved Arg (807 in a4 or 799 in Vph1p) and Gly (820 in a4 or 812 in Vph1p) residues are boxed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh20090852610001"></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="f2"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Effect of R799Q and G812R mutations on yeast growth, Vph1p expression, H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase assembly, and targeting. <italic>A</italic>: KEBY9 yeast cells were transformed with relevant constructs containing one of either <italic>VPH1-</italic>R799Q (R&#x0003e;Q), <italic>VPH1-</italic>G812R (G&#x0003e;R), <italic>VPH1</italic> (Vph1p), or empty vector. Images are of 30&#x000b0;C cultures. Functional complementation was observed from the G812R mutant at a level comparable to wild-type (WT) Vph1p, but not by the R799Q mutant. Yeast whole cell lysates (<italic>B</italic>) or vacuolar membrane vesicles (<italic>C</italic>) isolated from cells expressing WT or mutant forms of Vph1p, or control KEBY9 cells (&#x00394;/&#x00394;), were analyzed by Western blot using antibodies against Vph1p and/or Vma1p, densitometrically quantified, and expressed relative to WT (100&#x00025;) &#x000b1; SE. <italic>B</italic>: whole cell lysate showed expression of both mutants, with G812R at WT levels and R799Q severely reduced. <italic>C</italic>: relative amounts of each mutant present on the vacuolar membranes mirrored that seen for whole cells. Both V<sub>0</sub> and V<sub>1</sub> subunits (Vph1p and Vma1p) were present in G812R and R799Q mutant vacuoles, indicating that each was capable of assembly and targeting (<italic>top</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh20090852610002"></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="f3"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Indirect immunofluorescence examination of Vph1p expression and targeting. KEBY9 cells transformed with plasmid carrying either WT or mutant <italic>VPH1</italic> were fixed, spheroplasted, and stained with polyclonal &#x003b1;-Vph1p antibody (green). To observe vacuoles, differential interference contrast (DIC) images were collected (<italic>right</italic>, <italic>C</italic>, <italic>F</italic>, <italic>I</italic>, <italic>L</italic>). DAPI-labeled nuclei are blue. <italic>Left</italic>: expression of R799Q (<italic>G</italic>) is much lower than WT (<italic>A</italic>) and G812R (<italic>D</italic>), consistent with Western blot data in <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>. At higher magnification (<italic>middle</italic>), images (<italic>B</italic>, <italic>E</italic>, <italic>H</italic>) confirm that both mutant proteins can reach the vacuolar membrane. Control KEBY9 cells (&#x00394;/&#x00394;) show no Vph1p (<italic>J</italic>, <italic>K</italic>). Scale bars &#x0003d; 3 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh20090852610003"></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="f4"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Effects of R799Q and G812R mutations on H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase activity. Bafilomycin-sensitive ATPase activity and rate of ATP-dependent proton transport in vacuolar membrane vesicles isolated from cells expressing WT or mutant forms of Vph1p are shown as percentages of WT levels &#x000b1; SE. The specific activity of bafilomycin-sensitive ATPase activity of vacuoles containing WT-Vph1p was 1.02 &#x000b1; 0.09 &#x003bc;mol ATP hydrolyzed&#x000b7;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000b7;mg protein<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Approximately 70&#x00025; of the ATPase activity of WT vacuoles was bafilomycin sensitive. Experiments were performed in triplicate in each of 2 preparations per strain. Supplementary <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> shows representative proton translocation traces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh20090852610004"></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="f5"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Surface plasmon resonance (SPR) assay of a4C/PFK-1 interaction. Synthetic human a4C peptides in the range 5&#x02013;175 &#x003bc;M were analyzed for binding to immobilized rabbit PFK-1. Representative sensorgrams are displayed at left (<italic>A</italic>, <italic>C</italic>) and show amount of bound a4C-WT or a4C-GR (RU) over time. <italic>B</italic> and <italic>D</italic>: binding curves reveal saturable kinetics for the a4C-WT/PFK-1 interaction (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> &#x0003d; 29.4 &#x000b1; 6.2 &#x003bc;M), whereas a4C-GR and PFK-1 interacted too weakly to permit calculation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh20090852610005"></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="f6"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Far-UV circular dichroism (CD) spectra of a4C-WT and a4C-GR. Each is the average of 10 spectra at 50 &#x003bc;M. Spectral shifts were the same for 25 &#x003bc;M peptides. The G820R spectrum is <italic>right</italic>-shifted compared with WT, suggesting a change in secondary structure. See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref> for structural modelling.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh20090852610006"></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="f7"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>PFK-1 activity assays. Enzyme activity was assayed with and without a4C-WT or a4C-GR. These peptides did not affect activity. Representative curves shown are means of triplicate replicates in 1 of 3 experiments. Curves fitted first-order kinetics (Origin software). See <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref> for kinetic parameters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh20090852610007"></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="f8"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p>H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase functional disruption in PFK-null yeast. Similar to the strain lacking H<sup>&#x0002b;</sup>ATPase a-subunits, acid-dependent growth is exhibited (<italic>A</italic>), and bafilomycin-sensitive ATPase activity and proton translocation rates are impaired in <italic>PFK</italic>-null yeast (<italic>B</italic>), confirming that Pfk is essential for normal proton pump function.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zh20090852610008"></graphic></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Percentage of secondary structure elements present in a4 COOH-terminal 45 amino acids, estimated from 10 CD spectra using CDNN software</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Peptides</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">a4C-WT</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">a4C-GR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x003b1;-Helix</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">41&#x00025;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">33&#x00025;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x003b2;-Sheet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">12&#x00025;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">16&#x00025;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">&#x003b2;-Turn</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">16&#x00025;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">16&#x00025;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">Random Coil</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">26&#x00025;</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="char" char="." valign="top">38&#x00025;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>WT, wild-type.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Steady-state kinetic parameters for PFK-1 &#x000b1; WT or mutant a4C peptides</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Proteins</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>K</italic><sub>m</sub>(F6P, mM)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="bottom"><italic>V</italic><sub>max</sub>, mol/min</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PFK-1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">0.16&#x000b1;0.03</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">2.61&#x000b1;0.19</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PFK-1 &#x0002b; a4C-WT</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">0.13&#x000b1;0.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">2.42&#x000b1;0.15</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="left" valign="top">PFK-1 &#x0002b; a4C-GR</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">0.11&#x000b1;0.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1" align="center" valign="top">2.28&#x000b1;0.13</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Data are means &#x000b1; SE of 3 assays. No significant differences were found.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-wrap></article> 