<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mmi</journal-id><journal-title>Molecular Microbiology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0950-382X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1365-2958</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2008.06431.x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> mutants specifically impaired for replication fork reversal</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Le Masson</surname><given-names>Marie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baharoglu</surname><given-names>Zeynep</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;dicte</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>CNRS, Centre de G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique Mol&#x000e9;culaire</institution><addr-line>UPR 2167, Gif-sur-Yvette, F-91198, France</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Universit&#x000e9; Paris-Sud</institution><addr-line>Orsay, F-91405, France</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Universit&#x000e9; Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris 6</institution><addr-line>Paris, F-75005, France</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*For correspondence. E-mail <email>benedicte.michel@cgm.cnrs-gif.fr</email>; Tel. (+33) 1 69 82 32 29; Fax (+33) 1 69 82 31 40.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></date></history><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2008 The Authors Journal compilation &#x000a9; 2008 Blackwell Publishing Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><p>Re-use of this article is permitted in accordance with the Creative Commons Deed, Attribution 2.5, which does not permit commercial exploitation.</p></license><abstract><p>Replication fork reversal (RFR) is a reaction that takes place in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> at replication forks arrested by the inactivation of a replication protein. Fork reversal involves the annealing of the leading and lagging strand ends; it results in the formation of a Holliday junction adjacent to DNA double-strand end, both of which are processed by recombination enzymes. In several replication mutants, replication fork reversal is catalysed by the RuvAB complex, originally characterized for its role in the last steps of homologous recombination, branch migration and resolution of Holliday junctions. We present here the isolation and characterization of <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> single mutants that are impaired for RFR at forks arrested by the inactivation of polymerase III, while they remain capable of homologous recombination. The positions of the mutations in the proteins and the genetic properties of the mutants suggest that the mutations affect DNA binding, RuvA&#x02013;RuvB interaction and/or RuvB-helicase activity. These results show that a partial RuvA or RuvB defect affects primarily RFR, implying that RFR is a more demanding reaction than Holliday junction resolution.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Chromosome replication is not a continuous process but can be impaired by obstacles or by the inactivation of a replication protein. Replication arrest can have dramatic consequences and replication defects are now recognized as a major source of genomic instability in all organisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">Michel, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">Branzei and Foiani, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">Lambert <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">Tourriere and Pasero, 2007</xref>). Consequently, restart of inactivated replication forks while limiting DNA damage and DNA recombination is a crucial process. It is now clear that a large diversity of enzymes will cooperate to rescue inactivated replication forks, depending on the cause of replication arrest. In <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, in spite of the existence of a well-characterized multiprotein replication restart system, most often inactivated replication forks do not simply restart. A large panel of different reactions can take place prior to restart, which are determined by the cause of replication inactivation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">Michel <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">2007</xref>). A second important point is that recombination proteins are involved in all the reactions that were observed to take place prior to replication restart. Recombination proteins act on their normal substrates, double-strand DNA ends, single-strand DNA gaps or Holliday junctions (HJs), which are made at blocked forks, and they also act directly on replication forks, catalysing specific novel reactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>).</p><p>In several replication mutants, a specific reaction takes place prior to replication restart, called replication fork reversal (RFR; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Seigneur <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">Michel <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Forks are reversed by the annealing of the leading and lagging strand ends, which results in the formation of an HJ adjacent to a DNA double-strand end. This DNA double-strand end is processed by RecBCD, the enzyme that initiates recombinational repair of DNA double-strand breaks in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">Kowalczykowski, 2000</xref>). RecBCD is an exonuclease-recombinase and, at reversed forks, it either degrades the double-strand end or promotes its re-integration into the homologous chromosome by RecA-dependent recombination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1A</xref>, pathway B). HJs are resolved in <italic>E. coli</italic> by the RuvABC complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">Yamada <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). RuvA and RuvB form a complex composed of one or two tetramers of RuvA associated with two hexamers of RuvB; this complex has been extensively characterized for its property of branch migration of HJs formed during homologous recombination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">West, 1997</xref>). Associated with the endonuclease RuvC, it promotes HJ resolution. At reversed forks and in the absence of RecBC, resolution by RuvABC of the HJ formed by RFR leads to fork breakage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1A</xref>, pathway E). Cells lacking RecBC are therefore used to assay RFR by measuring RuvABC-dependent fork breakage after replication inactivation.</p><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>A. Model for replication fork reversal in a <italic>dnaEts</italic> mutant (adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). In the first step (A), the replication fork is arrested by inactivation of DnaE (the catalytic subunit of Pol III). RuvAB catalyses the annealing of leading and lagging strand ends, i.e. fork reversal. The reversed fork forms a four-arm structure (Holliday junction, HJ; two alternative representations of this structure are shown, open X and parallel stacked X). RecBC is essential for resetting of the fork, either by RecA-dependent homologous recombination (B&#x02013;C) or by DNA degradation (B&#x02013;D). In the absence of RecBCD (E), resolution of the HJ causes chromosome linearization. Continuous lines: parental chromosome strands. Dashed lines: newly synthesized strands. Circle: RuvAB. Incised circle: RecBCD.</p><p>B.Model of RuvAB action at blocked forks. In the first step, RuvA binds to the fork and drives the assembly of a RuvB hexamer on the template strands (a tetramer of RuvA is drawn, although an octamer may be required to convert the fork into an HJ). The translocase action of this RuvB hexamer pulls the leading and lagging strands into the RuvA complex (direction of migration of DNA is indicated by arrows) and results in the formation of an HJ. This HJ is bound by a second RuvB hexamer forming a <italic>bona fide</italic> branch migration complex. HJ resolution by RuvC results in a cleaved replication fork.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mmi0070-0537-f1"/></fig><p>The first step of RFR is the conversion of a three-arm fork structure into an HJ. This step is catalysed by different means in different replication mutants. It requires RecA in one mutant, the <italic>dnaBts</italic> mutant affected for the replicative helicase DnaB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">Seigneur <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>), whereas it is catalysed by RuvAB in <italic>dnaEts</italic> and <italic>holD</italic> mutants, affected for two different subunits of the main <italic>E. coli</italic> polymerase Pol III (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>) [DnaE is the Pol III catalytic subunit and HolD is a subunit of the clamp loader complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">O'Donnell, 2006</xref>)]. The occurrence of RuvAB-catalysed RFR implies that RuvAB recognizes blocked replication forks and is able to convert them into HJs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1B</xref>). In order to characterize the action of RuvAB on its two different targets, HJs and replication forks, we screened for dissociation-of-function <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants that are specifically affected for RFR. We recently reported the isolation and characterization of two <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants that are fully proficient for homologous recombination but are unable to reverse <italic>dnaEts</italic>-blocked forks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). These mutants were obtained by PCR mutagenesis and carry multiple mutations. In the present work, we used an <italic>in vivo</italic> mutagenesis approach and isolated four single <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants and four single <italic>ruvB</italic> mutants which present a dissociation-of-function phenotype. Genetic characterization of these mutants shows that RFR-deficient <italic>ruvA</italic> or <italic>ruvB</italic> alleles encode partially impaired RuvAB complexes, supporting the idea that RFR is more demanding than recombination intermediates resolution.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Isolation of Rec<sup><italic>+</italic></sup>/RFR-deficient mutants</title><p>In order to mutate the <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> genes, the pGB-ruvAB plasmid was introduced into a <italic>mutD5</italic> mutator strain. <italic>mutD</italic>, also called <italic>dnaQ</italic>, encodes the proofreading subunit of Pol III. In its absence, lack of proofreading during DNA synthesis increases the rate of replication errors 10<sup>4</sup>-fold (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Schaaper, 1993</xref>). Plasmids encoding a Rec<sup>+</sup>/RFR-deficient RuvAB complex were selected in a <italic>dnaEts</italic> context. The <italic>dnaE486ts</italic> mutant is killed at 42&#x000b0;C by the inactivation of the Pol III catalytic subunit DnaE. It grows at the semi-permissive temperature 37&#x000b0;C, but the impaired Pol III then leads to the formation of SOS-inducing gaps and arrested-restarting replication forks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Grompone <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Lestini and Michel, 2007</xref>). Consequently, <italic>dnaEts</italic> cells are killed at 37&#x000b0;C by <italic>ruvAB</italic> inactivation because of unresolved HJs made by RecFOR-dependent gap repair, and they are also killed when <italic>recB</italic> is inactivated because of the occurrence of RFR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). The <italic>dnaEts ruvAB recBCts</italic> mutant, in which both <italic>ruvAB</italic> and <italic>recBC</italic> are inactive at 37&#x000b0;C, does not grow at 37&#x000b0;C because of <italic>ruvAB</italic> inactivation, but remains non-viable when <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> wild-type genes are introduced because RuvAB then catalyses RFR and RecBC is inactive. The only way to make a <italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic> mutant viable at 37&#x000b0;C is to introduce <italic>ruvAB</italic> alleles that resolve HJs but do not catalyse RFR. To select such alleles, pGB-ruvAB plasmids extracted from six different <italic>mutD5</italic> clones were introduced in <italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic> competent cells at 37&#x000b0;C. <italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic> [pGB-RuvAB] transformants were obtained, and, in order to ascertain that the plasmids present in these clones carry <italic>ruvAB</italic> genes that were able to resolve HJs, we tested their ability to suppress the UV sensitivity of a <italic>ruvAB</italic> null mutant (this UV sensitivity results from the HJ resolution defect; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">Donaldson <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). Twenty-six plasmids that improved <italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic> viability at 37&#x000b0;C were introduced into a <italic>ruvAB</italic> mutant; seven of them carried a mutation in <italic>ruvA</italic> and/or <italic>ruvB</italic> but still fully suppressed the sensitivity of a <italic>ruvAB</italic> mutant to UV irradiation. One carried a <italic>ruvA</italic> mutation (V28G), five carried a <italic>ruvB</italic> mutation (A22V, Y184H, A250T, P220S and P111L) and one carried two mutations, one in <italic>ruvA</italic> and one in <italic>ruvB</italic> (<italic>ruvA</italic>-T120N <italic>ruvB</italic>-P220S). The positions of the mutations in the <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> genes are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>, and the UV resistance that they confer is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3A and B</xref>. The same protocol was applied to a pGB-ruvA plasmid, yielding two plasmids that allow <italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvA100</italic> growth at 37&#x000b0;C and confer UV resistance to a <italic>ruvA100</italic> mutant. Each of these two plasmids carried a <italic>ruvA</italic> mutation (V164I and P114S; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Figs 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3C</xref>).</p><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Positions of <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> mutations in the primary sequence.</p><p>A.RuvA: Full and dashed lines indicate the positions of the two helix&#x02013;turn&#x02013;helix motifs in domain II and of the disordered segment that separates domains II and III respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Nishino <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>). Domains I (1&#x02013;64), II (65&#x02013;140) and III (156&#x02013;203) are not indicated. Mutations that impair RFR are in red with the replacing amino acid indicated above the sequence. The mutation T120N that suppresses the <italic>ruvB</italic> P220S mutant defect is in blue. Separation-of-function mutations previously isolated (N79D N100D and H29R K129E F140S) are underlined.</p><p>B.RuvB: Full lines indicate the AAA motifs, and the dashed lines indicate the &#x003b2;-hairpin loop known to interact with RuvA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Iwasaki <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). Mutations are in red with the replacing amino acid indicated above the sequence.</p><p>C.Three-dimensional ribbon structure of a RuvA tetramer viewed at the DNA binding face. Three monomers are in grey and one is in purple. Mutations that affect RFR are shown as yellow spheres and the T120N-suppressing mutation is shown as a pink sphere.</p><p>D.Three-dimensional ribbon structure of a RuvB monomer (pink) bound to ADP (blue). Mutations that impair RFR are shown as blue spheres.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mmi0070-0537-f2"/></fig><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> mutants suppress the UV sensitivity of <italic>ruvAB</italic> or <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants.</p><p>A&#x02013;C. Suppression in <italic>ruv</italic> mutants. Appropriate dilutions of exponentially growing JJC 2907 (<italic>ruvA</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>, A and B) or JJC2971 (<italic>ruvA100</italic>, C) containing different plasmids were plated on LB spectinomycin, UV-irradiated and incubated overnight. Ratios of cfu on irradiated versus non-irradiated plates were calculated. Average of at least three values and standard deviations are shown.</p><p>D&#x02013;F. Suppression in <italic>ruv recR</italic> mutants. Same experiments with JJC4447 (<italic>ruvA</italic>::Tn<italic>10 recR</italic>; D and E) or JJC3375 (<italic>ruvA100 recR</italic>; F<italic>)</italic>.</p><p>G&#x02013;I. Suppression in <italic>ruv recG</italic> mutants. Same experiments in <italic>ruvA</italic>::Tn<italic>10 recG</italic> (G and H) or <italic>ruvA100 recG</italic>(I) cells.</p><p>A, D and G. Closed diamonds: pGB2; open squares, dashed line: pGB-ruvAB (RuvA<sup>+</sup> RuvB<sup>+</sup>); closed circles: pGB-RuvA<sup>+</sup>-RuvB-A250T; closed triangles: pGB-RuvA<sup>+</sup>-RuvB-P220S; closed squares: pGB-RuvA<sup>+</sup>-RuvB-Y184H; stars: pGB-RuvA<sup>+</sup>-RuvB-A22V.</p><p>B, E and H. Closed diamonds: pGB2; open squares, dashed line: pGB-ruvAB; closed triangles: pGB-RuvA-I89N-RuvB<sup>+</sup> closed squares pGB-RuvA-V28G-RuvB<sup>+</sup> stars: pGB-RuvA-T120N-RuvB-P220S.</p><p>C, F and I. Closed diamonds: pGB2; open squares, dashed line: pGB-ruvA (pGB-RuvA<sup>+</sup>); closed triangles: pGB-RuvA-V164I; stars: pGB-RuvA-P114S.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mmi0070-0537-f3"/></fig><p>In another experiment, because we were concerned that the first screen was too stringent, pGB-ruvAB plasmids extracted from <italic>mutD5</italic> clones were also introduced in a <italic>dnaEts recBCts lexAind ruvA</italic> mutant. By preventing SOS induction, the <italic>lexAind</italic> mutation improves the viability of the <italic>dnaEts</italic> mutant at semi-permissive temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Grompone <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). Actually, more transformants were obtained in the <italic>lexAind</italic> context than in the LexA<sup>+</sup><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvA</italic> mutant (ratio of transformants at 37&#x000b0;C versus 30&#x000b0;C of about 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> instead of 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>). These transformants were pooled for plasmid extractions and a genetic test that allows a direct selection of Rec<sup>+</sup> plasmids was used to identify such plasmids in these extracts. The <italic>dnaNts ruvAB</italic> mutant, impaired for the Pol III clamp, is killed at semi-permissive temperature by unresolved RecFOR-dependent recombination events. Plasmids extracted at 37&#x000b0;C from 12 pools of <italic>dnaEts recB ruvA lexAind</italic> [pGB-ruvAB] transformants were introduced into the <italic>dnaNts ruvAB</italic> mutant at 37&#x000b0;C. Only one pool of plasmids, and only one plasmid in this pool, yielded <italic>dnaNts ruvAB</italic> clones able to propagate at 37&#x000b0;C, suggesting that the <italic>lexAind</italic> context provided a lot of fully inactivated <italic>ruvAB</italic> mutants. The only plasmid that allowed growth of <italic>dnaNts ruvAB</italic> cells at 37&#x000b0;C also suppressed the UV sensitivity of a <italic>ruvAB</italic> mutant. The <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> genes on this Rec<sup>+</sup> plasmid were sequenced, showing a mutation in <italic>ruvA</italic> (I89N, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Figs 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">3B</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Mutant alleles are deficient or affected for RFR</title><p>In order to ascertain that the <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> mutant alleles that do not kill a <italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic> mutant at 37&#x000b0;C are indeed deficient for RFR, the purified pGB-ruv(AB)m plasmids were re-introduced in the <italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic> mutant and fork breakage was measured by pulse field gel electrophoresis [PFGE, pGB-ruv(AB)m stands for the seven pGB-ruvAB plasmids with a mutation in <italic>ruvA</italic>, <italic>ruvB</italic> or both]. Briefly, the chromosomes were labelled by growing cells in <sup>3</sup>H-Thy-containing medium; cells were lysed in agarose plugs and run on pulse field gel (PFG). As only the linear DNA can enter PFG, the proportion of linear DNA <italic>in vivo</italic> was calculated as the ratio of DNA that enters gels versus total DNA in each migration lane. A high proportion of linear DNA is observed with <italic>dnaEts recBCts</italic> cells, owing to RuvAB-catalysed RFR and RuvABC resolution of the resulting HJ (60%, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Grompone <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). The proportion of linear DNA is strongly decreased by <italic>ruvAB</italic> inactivation, which prevents fork reversal in the <italic>dnaEts</italic> mutant (10%, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">Grompone <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Introduction of wild-type <italic>ruvAB</italic> genes on pGB-ruvAB plasmid restores a high level of fork breakage, and introduction of the different pGB-ruv(AB)m alleles leads to variable levels of fork breakage (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). The <italic>ruvB</italic>-P111L mutant was clearly capable of fork reversal and was not studied further (70% fork breakage, data not shown). Two <italic>ruvB</italic> mutations (<italic>ruvB</italic>-A22V and <italic>ruvB</italic>-A250T) and one <italic>ruvA</italic> mutation (<italic>ruvA</italic>-V28G) affected RFR partially (40&#x02013;45% linear DNA). RFR was strongly decreased by the <italic>ruvB</italic>-Y184H mutation (23% linear DNA) and completely abolished by the <italic>ruvA</italic>-I89N and the <italic>ruvB</italic>-P220S mutations (about 10% linear DNA). Interestingly, the presence of the <italic>ruvA</italic>-T120N mutation restored fork breakage when combined with <italic>ruvB</italic>-P220S. This double mutant was obtained independently from the <italic>ruvB</italic>-P220S single mutant, raising the possibility that this <italic>ruvB</italic> mutation aroused twice independently and was, in one case, later compensated by the <italic>ruvA</italic>-T120N mutation.</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> isolated alleles decrease fork breakage.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relevant genotype</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmid</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% linear DNA (<italic>n</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 &#x000b1; 2.9 (8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-RuvAB</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 &#x000b1; 5.8 (8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-RuvA<sup>+</sup>-<italic>ruvB-</italic>P220S</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3 &#x000b1; 2.4 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-RuvA<sup>+</sup>-<italic>ruvB</italic>-Y184H</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 &#x000b1; 2.3 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-RuvA<sup>+</sup>-<italic>ruvB</italic>-A22V</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 &#x000b1; 4.7 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-RuvA<sup>+</sup>-<italic>ruvB</italic>-A250T</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 &#x000b1; 6.3 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-<italic>ruvA</italic>-I89N-RuvB<sup>+</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 &#x000b1; 2.2 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-<italic>ruvA</italic>-V28G-RuvB<sup>+</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 &#x000b1; 4.3 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvAB</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-<italic>ruvA</italic>-T120N<italic>-ruvB</italic>-P220S</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5 &#x000b1; 2.8 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3723</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvA100</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 &#x000b1; 1.5 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3723</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvA100</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-RuvA</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3 &#x000b1; 3.2 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3723</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvA100</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-<italic>ruvA</italic>-V164I</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 &#x000b1; 3.4 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3723</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvA100</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-<italic>ruvA</italic>-P114S</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 &#x000b1; 6.1 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3723</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvA100</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-<italic>ruvA</italic>-V164I-RuvB<sup>+</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.6 &#x000b1; 1.5 (3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3723</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvA100</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-<italic>ruvA</italic>-P114S-RuvB<sup>+</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.4 &#x000b1; 3.3 (3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>n</italic> is the number of independent experiments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Similarly, fork breakage was measured in <italic>dnaEts recBCts ruvA100</italic> cells carrying pGB-ruvAm mutant plasmids. For both pGB-ruvAm mutants, RFR remained strongly decreased, although not fully abolished (27&#x02013;31% fork breakage, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> genes form an operon, with <italic>ruvB</italic> downstream of <italic>ruvA</italic>. <italic>ruvB</italic> expression is prevented by the <italic>ruvA60</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic> mutation used here (called here <italic>ruvAB</italic>, it is not complemented by the expression of <italic>ruvA</italic> only, data not shown), whereas the Cm<sup>R</sup> insertion in the <italic>ruvA100</italic> allele affects but does not prevent the expression of the downstream <italic>ruvB</italic> gene (called here <italic>ruvA</italic>, it is complemented by the expression of <italic>ruvA</italic> only, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). The two <italic>ruvA</italic> dissociation-of-function mutants previously characterized (N79D N100D and H29R K129E F140S) affect RuvA&#x02013;RuvB interactions <italic>in vitro</italic>, and were only deficient when <italic>ruvB</italic> was expressed downstream of the <italic>ruvA100</italic> allele, as they became proficient for RFR when <italic>ruvB</italic> was coexpressed with the <italic>ruvA</italic> mutant allele, from the plasmid or from the chromosome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). In order to test whether coexpression of <italic>ruvB</italic> suppresses the RFR defect of <italic>ruvA</italic>-V164I and <italic>ruvA</italic>-P114S mutants, these <italic>ruvA</italic> mutations were introduced by site-directed mutagenesis on the pGB-ruvAB plasmid. Fork breakage in <italic>dnaEts recB ruvAB</italic> cells was shown to be restored to a high level in the presence of the pGB-ruvAm-ruvB<sup>+</sup> plasmids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). This result indicates that the two RFR-deficient <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants isolated on a plasmid that does not carry <italic>ruvB</italic> become capable of RFR if the level of RuvB protein is increased.</p><p>Altogether, we have identified four <italic>ruvA</italic> and four <italic>ruvB</italic> mutations that impair or abolish RFR. For the two <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants isolated on a plasmid that does not carry <italic>ruvB</italic>, RFR is only decreased if RuvB is expressed from the chromosome locus downstream of the <italic>ruvA100</italic> mutation. Interestingly, a <italic>ruvB</italic> mutation (P220S) was isolated twice, once alone where it prevents RFR, and once combined with a <italic>ruvA</italic> mutation that restores RFR.</p></sec><sec><title>The RFR-deficient mutants complement the UV sensitivity of <italic>ruvA(B)</italic> mutant</title><p>All RFR mutants restore full resistance to UV irradiation in <italic>ruvAB</italic> or <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3A&#x02013;C</xref>). As the role of RuvAB post UV irradiation is the resolution of recombination intermediates, the resistance to UV irradiation is a strong indication that these <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> alleles are capable of HJ resolution <italic>in vivo</italic>. We further tested the recombination proficiency of these alleles in combination with other recombination mutations and by other assays.</p><p>The UV sensitivity due to <italic>ruvAB</italic> inactivation is synergistic with the inactivation of <italic>recFOR</italic>, which prevents gap repair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>, pGB2-containing strains). All pGB-ruv(AB)m plasmids suppressed the <italic>ruvAB</italic> defect in a <italic>ruvAB recR</italic> double mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3D and E</xref>). Similarly, the two pGB-ruvAm plasmids suppressed the <italic>ruvA100</italic> repair defect in a <italic>ruvA100 recR</italic> mutant, to the same extent as pGB-ruvA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3F</xref>). In conclusion, these experiments show that all <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> mutations isolated do not affect the capacity of RuvAB to resolve HJs during recombinational repair of UV DNA lesions, in <italic>recR</italic> as well as in Rec<sup>+</sup> contexts.</p><p>Residual recombination proficiency in <italic>ruv</italic> null mutants depends on the integrity of the <italic>recG</italic> gene, which encodes a helicase capable of HJ branch migration <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Lloyd, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">Whitby and Lloyd, 1998</xref>). The <italic>recG</italic> mutation was introduced by P1 transduction in <italic>ruvAB</italic> cells containing pGB-ruv(AB)m and in <italic>ruvA100</italic> cells containing pGB-ruvAm. First, the presence of these plasmids suppressed the poor viability of <italic>ruvAB recG</italic> and <italic>ruvA recG</italic> double mutants (data not shown). Second, compared with the <italic>ruv recG</italic> double mutant that carries the vector (pGB2), all plasmids suppressed most or all the UV sensitivity of <italic>ruvA recG</italic>, or <italic>ruvAB recG</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3G and H</xref>). Only a residual UV sensitivity was observed with some plasmids (<italic>ruvB</italic>-A250T, <italic>ruvB</italic>-P220S and <italic>ruvA</italic>-I89N).</p><p>Both pGB-ruvA-P114S and pGB-ruvA-V164I suppressed the UV sensitivity of <italic>ruvA100 recG</italic> cells as efficiently as pGB-ruvA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3I</xref>). It was observed that <italic>ruvA100 recG</italic> [pGB-ruvA] cells were significantly more UV-sensitive than <italic>ruvAB recG</italic> [pGB-ruvAB] (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3G&#x02013;I</xref>); the <italic>ruvA100 recG</italic> [pGB-ruvA] defect results from the limiting amount of RuvB in this mutant as it was fully suppressed by pGB-ruvAB wild type, and by the plasmids expressing RuvB together with <italic>ruvA</italic>-P114S or <italic>ruvA</italic>-V164I (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Some, but not all RFR-deficient mutants complement the mitomycin C sensitivity of <italic>ruvA(B)</italic> mutant</title><p>Mitomycin C is a DNA-damaging agent that introduces a variety of lesions, including interstrand cross-links and base monoadducts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">Keller <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). These DNA lesions are in part repaired by homologous recombination, rendering <italic>ruvAB</italic> mutants sensitive to mitomycin C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">Shurvinton and Lloyd, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). In our experimental conditions, the <italic>ruvAB</italic> mutant was 10- to 20-fold more sensitive to mitomycin C than the wild-type strain (not shown) or than the <italic>ruvAB</italic> mutant carrying pGB-ruvAB<sup>+</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4A</xref>). Two <italic>ruvB</italic> (A22V, Y184H) and one <italic>ruvA</italic> (A28G) mutant alleles suppressed the mitomycin C sensitivity of the <italic>ruvAB</italic> null mutant as efficiently as the <italic>ruvAB</italic> wild-type gene, RuvB-A22V, RuvB-Y184H and RuvA-A28G. One <italic>ruvB</italic> and one <italic>ruvA</italic> mutant alleles did not suppress the mitomycin C sensitivity of the <italic>ruvAB</italic> mutant: <italic>ruvB</italic>-A250T and <italic>ruvA</italic>-I89N (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4A</xref>). For unknown reasons, results with <italic>ruvB</italic>-P220S and with the <italic>ruvA</italic>-T120N <italic>ruvB</italic>-P220S double mutant were highly variable and could not be interpreted (six independent experiments, data not shown). These results confirm that certain mutants are fully recombination proficient and indicate that two of them, although they fully suppress the UV sensitivity of <italic>ruvAB</italic> null mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>), have retained some recombination deficiency in mitomycin C-treated cells.</p><fig id="fig04" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Most <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> mutants alleles suppress the mitomycin C sensitivity of <italic>ruvAB</italic> or <italic>ruvA</italic> null mutants. Exponentially growing JJC 2907 (<italic>ruvA</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>, A) or JJC 2971 (<italic>ruvA100</italic>, B) containing different plasmids was treated with 2 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mitomycin C for 90 min, plated on LB spectinomycin and incubated overnight. Ratios of colony-forming units (cfu) in treated versus untreated cultures are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mmi0070-0537-f4"/></fig><p>The <italic>ruvA100</italic> mutant is 100-fold more sensitive to mitomycin C than the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4B</xref>). For unknown reasons, <italic>ruvA100</italic> [pGB2] cells were about 10-fold more sensitive to UV irradiation and to mitomycin C treatment than <italic>ruvAB</italic> [pGB2] cells, suggesting that RuvB expressed downstream of the <italic>ruvA100</italic> allele might affect HJ resolution in the absence of RuvA. We tested the capacity of <italic>ruvA</italic> single mutants to suppress the repair defect of the <italic>ruvA100</italic> mutant and observed that the two <italic>ruvA</italic>-V164I and <italic>ruvA</italic>-P114S mutations conferred a nearly wild-type level of survival to mitomycin C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4B</xref>); therefore, these alleles are able to promote HJ resolution during the recombinational repair of mitomycin C DNA lesions.</p></sec><sec><title>The RFR-deficient mutants complement the conjugational recombination defect of a <italic>ruvA(B) recG</italic> double mutant</title><p>Homologous recombination on non-damaged DNA was tested by measuring Hfr conjugation efficiency. During Hfr conjugation, the chromosome of the donor cell is introduced in the recipient cell and ex-conjugants are obtained when the incoming chromosome recombines with the homologous sequence in the recipient chromosome. Hfr conjugation efficiency is only weakly affected by the inactivation of <italic>ruvAB</italic>, but nearly completely abolished in a <italic>ruvAB recG</italic> double mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">Lloyd, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). We compared Hfr conjugation efficiencies using as recipient cells <italic>ruvAB recG</italic> double mutants that contain either the pGB2 vector, or pGB-ruvAB, or one of the pGB-ruv(AB)m plasmid. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5A</xref>, the pGB-ruv(AB)m plasmids restored Hfr conjugational recombination. Similarly, Hfr conjugation was also restored in <italic>ruvA100 recG</italic> cells by the two pGB-ruvAm plasmids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5B</xref>). Altogether, these experiments show that the <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> mutant alleles that decrease or abolish RFR in the <italic>dnaEts</italic> mutant are not significantly affected for homologous recombination of intact DNA.</p><fig id="fig05" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> mutants suppress the conjugational recombination defect of <italic>ruvAB</italic> or <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants in a <italic>recG</italic> context. Exponentially growing cells were mixed with a His<sup>+</sup> Hfr donor for 25 min, plated on Kan (A) or Cm (B) minimal medium plates devoid of histidine and incubated for 48 h. Ratios of His<sup>+</sup> versus total recipient cfu are shown. Recipient: (A) <italic>ruvA::</italic>Tn<italic>10 recG</italic>::<italic>kan</italic><sup>R</sup>, (B) <italic>ruvA100 recG</italic>::<italic>kan</italic><sup>R</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mmi0070-0537-f5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The <italic>ruvAB</italic> mutants are capable of preventing RusA action</title><p>The <italic>rusA</italic> gene belongs to a cryptic prophage and encodes an HJ resolvase. This promoter-less gene is not expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic>, unless it is activated by the insertion of an upstream functional promoter, as in the <italic>rus-1</italic> allele (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Mandal <italic>et al</italic>., 1993</xref>). The <italic>rus-1</italic> mutation suppresses the recombinational defects of <italic>ruvAB</italic> and <italic>ruvABC</italic> mutants, but RusA cannot act in a <italic>ruvB</italic> or <italic>ruvC</italic> mutant, owing to RuvA or RuvAB masking the HJ. Therefore, the capacity of RuvA alleles to recognize and bind HJs <italic>in vivo</italic> can be deduced from their capacity to prevent RusA action. pGB-ruv(AB)m and pGB-ruvAm plasmids were introduced into a <italic>ruvABC rus-1</italic> mutant and UV sensitivity was measured. As expected, in the presence of the vector pGB2, <italic>ruvAB rus-1</italic> cells were UV-resistant because of RusA-catalysed HJ resolution. None of the <italic>ruvB</italic> mutations prevented RuvA from sequestering the HJ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6A</xref>). In contrast, with the exception of the <italic>ruvA</italic>-I89N mutant, all mutant <italic>ruvA</italic> alleles had retained the property of preventing RusA-mediated resolution, as they all rendered <italic>ruvABC rus-1</italic> cells sensitive to UV irradiation, similar to the wild-type RuvA protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6B and C</xref>). These results indicate that the <italic>ruvA</italic>-I89N mutation affects RuvA binding to HJs <italic>in vivo</italic>, while all other mutants bind HJs efficiently enough to prevent RusA action.</p><fig id="fig06" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>All plasmids but pGB-RuvA-I89N-RuvB<sup>+</sup> prevent resolution of HJ by RusA. Same experiments as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref> with JJC2761 (<italic>ruvABC::cm rus-1</italic>). Symbols are as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="mmi0070-0537-f6"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In this work we isolated several <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> mutant alleles that are much more affected for RFR than for homologous recombination. This work shows that mutations in various domains of RuvA or in RuvB separate the fork reversal function of RuvAB from its function as an HJ branch migration and resolution enzyme, suggesting that there are several ways of separating these two functions. The phenotypes of the different mutants are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of the phenotypes of <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> RFR-deficient alleles.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UV<sup>R</sup> in wt and <italic>recR</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UV<sup>R</sup> in <italic>recG</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UV<sup>R</sup> in <italic>rus-1</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMC<sup>R</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hfr in <italic>recG</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fork breakage</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-ruvAB<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ruvB-P220S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weakly S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ruvB-Y184H</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ruvB-A22V</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ruvB-A250T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weakly S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ruvA-I89N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weakly S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ruvA-V28G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ruvB-P220S ruvA-T120N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pGB-ruvA<sup>+</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ruvA-V164I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ruvA-P114S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>MMC: mitomycin C; Hfr: Hfr conjugation; Fork breakage: percentage of linear DNA in a <italic>dnaEts recB ruvA(B)</italic> background (cf. <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). R: resistant; S: sensitive.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>RuvA is composed of three domains. Domains I [amino acids (AA) 1&#x02013;64] and II (AA 65&#x02013;140) are involved in DNA binding while domain III (AA 155&#x02013;203) is involved in RuvB binding. Domains II and III are separated by an unstructured flexible linker of 15 amino acids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Nishino <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">Rafferty <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">Ariyoshi <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Yamada <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). The two <italic>ruvA</italic> separation-of-function mutants isolated previously were multiple mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>). Both mutant proteins were shown to bind HJ <italic>in vitro</italic> fairly well, but to be defective for octamerization (binding of two RuvA tetramers that sandwich a junction) and for binding to DNA fork structures. In addition, the triple mutant, H29R K129E F140S, was significantly affected for RuvB-helicase stimulation. These <italic>ruvA</italic> mutations were isolated on a plasmid that carries only <italic>ruvA</italic>, with <italic>ruvB</italic> expressed downstream of <italic>ruvA100</italic> in the chromosome. The <italic>ruvA</italic>-V164I and <italic>ruvA</italic>-P114S mutations were isolated here on the same plasmid and, as observed for the two previously characterized mutants, their RFR defect is suppressed when RuvB expression is increased (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>, plasmids pGB-<italic>ruvA</italic>-V164I-RuvB<sup>+</sup> and pGB-<italic>ruvA</italic>-P114S-RuvB<sup>+</sup>). This observation suggests that these mutants suffer from a defect in RuvA&#x02013;RuvB interactions, which has detectable consequences only when RuvB is in a limiting amount. The <italic>ruvA</italic>-V164I mutation lies within RuvA domain III, which interacts with RuvB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>), and two mutations (L167A and L170A) within the same alpha helix as V164 (alpha 7) were previously shown to abolish RuvB activity <italic>in vivo</italic> (these two mutants are deficient for homologous recombination) without affecting RuvA binding to HJs <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">Nishino <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>). <italic>ruvA</italic>-P114S is just before the flexible linker that separates domains II and III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>). In support of the idea that this mutation also affects RuvB activation, the T120N mutation, only six amino acids distant from P114S, suppresses the RFR defect of the <italic>ruvB</italic>-P220S mutant. The helix from amino acids 118&#x02013;130 is involved in interactions between two RuvA tetramers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">Roe <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">Privezentzev <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Fujiwara <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Our observations suggest that mutations in this helix&#x02013;turn&#x02013;helix region of RuvA domain II also affect RuvA&#x02013;RuvB interactions. Actually, a <italic>Thermus thermophilus ruvA</italic> mutant impaired for octamerization forms complexes in which a RuvA tetramer is flanked by two RuvB hexamers on an HJ, but these complexes exhibit impaired branch migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Fujiwara <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">Mayanagi <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). In conclusion, the phenotypes of the P114S and V164I mutants suggest that impairing RuvA&#x02013;RuvB interactions is sufficient to significantly decrease RFR without any detectable effect on homologous recombination. This observation supports a model in which RuvA&#x02013;RuvB interactions are crucial for the stability and/or the action of RuvAB at forks.</p><p>Two other <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants were isolated on plasmids that carry both <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic>. In contrast with the two <italic>ruvA</italic> mutants suppressed by RuvB coexpression, they both map in the N-terminal half of the RuvA protein, in proximity to the DNA, at positions 28 and 89 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2C</xref>). The V28G mutation is adjacent to one of the mutations in the previously isolated triple mutant (H29R). This mutant is partially impaired for RFR, as fork breakage is only down to 42%, and is fully recombination proficient in all assays. Although the RuvA-V28G remains fully capable of preventing RusA action, given the position of the V28 and H29 residues on the tri-dimensional structure of RuvA, close to the crossing strands at the junction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2C</xref>), it is likely that these mutations affect DNA contacts. The I89N mutation is in a helix&#x02013;turn&#x02013;helix motif, between the N79D and N100D mutations previously shown to prevent octamerization and fork binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). The position of the mutation in the protein and the <italic>in vitro</italic> properties of the N79D N100D double mutant suggest that the primary defects conferred by the I89N mutation might also be DNA binding and RuvA octamerization. Accordingly, even when coexpressed with RuvB, this mutant is unable to prevent RusA action <italic>in vivo</italic>, an observation that suggests either that one face of the HJ remains accessible to RusA within the RuvA-I89N&#x02013;HJ complex, or that RuvA-I89N easily dissociates from HJs. The I89N mutation has dramatic consequences, as it causes a drastic drop of fork breakage (8%), and shows sign of a slight recombination defect: it is slightly affected in the <italic>recG</italic> context for UV repair and remains sensitive to mitomycin C. This recombinational repair defect might reflect impairment of branch migration through certain DNA lesions. It is noteworthy that this mutant was isolated in the <italic>lexAind</italic> context, in a screen that yielded a lot of recombination-deficient (presumably null) mutants. Nevertheless, the <italic>ruvA</italic>-I89N mutant is recombination-proficient on intact DNA (Hfr conjugation) and in UV-irradiated cells, in which it only weakly needs RecG. The minor defects in HJ resolution cannot be the cause of the very low level of fork breakage, and the properties of this mutant support the idea that strong DNA binding, and possibly octamer formation, is needed for RuvA action at forks, logically because several DNA strands are missing in a RuvA&#x02013;fork complex compared with a RuvA&#x02013;HJ complex, and because octamerization, as in <italic>T. thermophilus</italic>, may stimulate RuvB activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">Fujiwara <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>).</p><p>Four <italic>ruvB</italic> mutants were isolated in this work. The RuvB protein is composed of three domains (N, M and C), which form a crescent-like architecture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Putnam <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">Yamada <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">Ohnishi <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). The N and M domains are involved in ATP binding and hydrolysis and adopt the canonical fold of AAA+ family proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">Ogura and Wilkinson, 2001</xref>). The N domain also contains a protruding &#x003b2;-hairpin (L135&#x02013;L152) which interacts with RuvA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">Han <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). The <italic>ruvB</italic>-A250T mutation lies in domain C (T241 to terminus), adjacent to a conserved leucine. It is the only mutant which is only partially affected for fork breakage and shows a slight recombination deficiency by all assays, except UV sensitivity in Rec<sup>+</sup> and RecR contexts. It is conceivable that for this mutant the decrease in fork breakage results from the impairment for HJ resolution. The other three <italic>ruvB</italic> mutants behave as dissociation-of-function mutants, as they are much more strongly affected for RFR than for homologous recombination. They are all in the N or M domains of RuvB, adjacent or within one of the AAA conserved motifs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>). The Ala22 residue, changed here to a valine, is not conserved in other bacterial RuvB proteins but is adjacent to the first conserved AAA motif. Changing the nearby Arg24 to cysteine or histidine inactivates the protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Iwasaki <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). The Tyr184 residue, mutated here to histidine, is invariant in all bacterial RuvB proteins, within the AAA motif 8, and part of the ATP binding site (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Iwasaki <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Putnam <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). The Y184A mutation inactivates RuvB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Iwasaki <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). The Pro220 residue, changed here to a serine, is nearly invariant and also part of the ATP binding site, within the conserved sensor 2 motif of AAA proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Iwasaki <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">Putnam <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). Changing either of the flanking T219 or R221 residues to an alanine largely or fully inactivate RuvB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">Iwasaki <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). It is surprising that the T184H and P220S mutations only very slightly affect homologous recombination. Given their positions in the protein, close to the ATP binding site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>), these three <italic>ruvB</italic> mutations are likely to impair ATP binding or hydrolysis, suggesting that full RuvB ATPase activity is more essential for RFR than for homologous recombination, an observation in agreement with a model in which only one RuvB hexamer is present at forks. Interestingly, the P220S mutation is fully suppressed by the RuvA T120N mutation. It suggests that the alpha 6 helix of RuvA (AA 118&#x02013;129) could be involved in long-range communications between RuvA, RuvB and DNA. This helix is part of the helix&#x02013;turn&#x02013;helix motif and is involved in contacts between two RuvA tetramers, while the suppressed <italic>ruvB</italic> P220S mutation is in one of the ATPase sensor motifs. It is tempting to speculate that coupling of ATP hydrolysis and branch migration involves interactions through the tetramerization helix of RuvA (T120) when bound to DNA, and the ATP sensing of RuvB (P220) and DNA.</p><p>In conclusion, this work shows that there are multiple ways of decreasing the activity of the RuvAB complex so that it remains capable of producing recombinant molecules with a normal or close to normal efficiency, while being largely or fully inactivated for its capacity to reverse blocked forks.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Experimental procedures</title><sec><title>Strains and plasmids</title><p>Strains are described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>. Mutations were introduced by P1 transduction. For the construction of plasmid-containing strains, the plasmids were introduced at the last step by transformation of CaCl<sub>2</sub> competent cells. A different protocol was used for the <italic>ruv recG</italic> double mutants. As these mutants are very sick and therefore difficult to make competent, plasmid-containing <italic>ruv recG</italic> double mutants were constructed from plasmid-containing <italic>ruv</italic> single mutants, by P1 transduction of the <italic>recG253</italic>::<italic>kan</italic> mutation. Fresh <italic>recG</italic> transductants were constructed for each independent experiment. Antibiotics were used at the following concentration: spectinomycin (Spc) 60 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, chloramphenicol (Cm) 20 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, kanamycin (Kan) 50 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, tetracycline (Tet) 15 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The presence of the <italic>mutD5</italic> mutation was tested by measuring the ratio of Rif<sup>R</sup> spontaneous mutants in overnight cultures (about 10E<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> in the <italic>mutD5</italic> mutant versus 10E<sup>&#x02212;8</sup> in the wild-type strain, using rifampicin 50 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Sequencing of <italic>ruvA</italic> and <italic>ruvB</italic> genes in plasmids was performed using &#x02018;Genetic Analyser&#x02019; 3100 (Applied Biosystem) automatic sequencer. The <italic>ruvA ruvB</italic> operon was amplified with oligonucleotides pGB1: CGAAGTAATCGCAACATCCGC and pGBa: CAATATGTGTCCCGACCCTAG. These oligonucleotides were also used for sequencing as well as the following ones: ruvA: GCTTCCTAGGGGCCCTTAA and CTTCCGGCAAAGTGGTACC; ruvB: GTCCCGCTCGCTAAAACGAG, GCGGCCTGGAAGTGGTTAGT, CGTCGGTGGTGCTATGTGCG and ACGAGCAACTTCCAGCGCGC.</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Strains.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relevant genotype</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Construction or reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild type</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">As AB1157 but <italic>hsdR</italic> Thr<sup>+</sup> Pro<sup>+</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC145</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hfr PK19-PO66 &#x00394;-(<italic>gpt-lac</italic>) <italic>supE44 srlC::</italic>Tn<italic>10 thi1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGSC6813 Genetic Stock Center</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC720</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>mutD5</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">Schaaper (1993)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC944</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>recG263</italic>::kan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3793 = CF3324 in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Mandal <italic>et al</italic>. (1993)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC1193</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>recR252</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>kan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2211</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sfiA11 recB270ts recC271ts dnaE486ts zae3095</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>kan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Lestini and Michel (2007)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2434</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sfiA11 dnaN159ts zid501</italic>::<italic>Tn</italic>10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Lestini and Michel (2007)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2761</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sfiA11</italic>&#x00394;<italic>ruvABC::Cm rus-1</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>. (2006)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2818</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sfiA11 dnaE486ts zae3095</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>kan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">Flores <italic>et al</italic>. (2005)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2880</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sfiA11 recB270ts recC271ts dnaE486ts zae3095</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>kan <italic>ruvA60</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2211 * P1 JJC 2907</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2907</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ruvA60</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC40 * P1 N2057 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">Shurvinton <italic>et al</italic>. (1984)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2971</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>ruvA100::</italic>Cm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3192</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sfiA11 dnaN59ts zid</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>&#x00394;<italic>ruvA100::</italic>Cm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2434 * P1 JJC2971</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3207</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>ruvA100::</italic>Cm &#x00394;<italic>recG263</italic>::kan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3297</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sfiA11 dnaE486ts zae3095</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>kan <italic>lexAind mal</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>&#x00394;<italic>recB</italic>::<italic>Ap</italic>&#x00394;<italic>ruvA100::</italic>Cm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2818 * P1 <italic>lexAind mal</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>* P1 JJC2971 * P1 &#x00394;<italic>recB</italic>::<italic>Ap</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3375</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>ruvA100::</italic>Cm <italic>recR</italic>::kan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC3723</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sfiA11 recB270ts recC271ts dnaE486ts zae3095</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>kan &#x00394;<italic>ruvA100::</italic>Cm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>. (2008)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC4447</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ruvA60</italic>::Tn<italic>10 recR252</italic>::Tn<italic>10</italic>kan</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JJC2907 * P1 JJC1193</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>UV and mitomycin C resistance tests</title><p>UV irradiation was performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>). For mitomycin C treatment, cells were grown at 37&#x000b0;C in LB to an OD<sub>650</sub> = 0.5, mitomycin C was added to the culture at a final concentration of 2 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and incubation continued at 37&#x000b0;C for 90 min. An untreated culture was used as control. Appropriate dilutions were plated on LB plates and incubated overnight at 37&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">Baharoglu <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Ratios of colony-forming units (cfu) of mitomycin C-treated over cfu of untreated cells were calculated.</p></sec><sec><title>Conjugation</title><p>Conjugations were performed as described using JJC145 as Hfr donor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">Lestini and Michel, 2007</xref>). Donor and recipient cells were mixed for 25 min. Selective medium was M9 minimal medium supplemented with leucine, proline, threonine and arginine (2% final concentration each), and 10 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> Cm for <italic>ruvA100 recG</italic>::Kan recipient cells, 10 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> Kan for <italic>ruvA60</italic>::Tn<italic>10 recG</italic>::Kan recipient cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Measurement of linear DNA by PFGE</title><p>Quantification of pulsed field gels was performed using <italic>in vivo</italic><sup>3</sup>H-thymidine labelled chromosomes as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">Seigneur <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr Irina Tsaneva and Dr Mireille B&#x000e9;termier for very helpful reading of the manuscript. We thank Maud Silvain and Liliane Troussard for DNA sequencing. Z.B. is supported by the ACI Biologie Cellulaire Moleculaire et Structurale 04 5 481. Work in B.M. laboratory is supported by ACI BMCS 04 5 481, ANR-05-BLAN-0204-01, FRM INE 2005110527.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ariyoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the Holliday junction DNA in complex with a single RuvA tetramer</article-title><source>Proc Nat Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>8257</fpage><lpage>8262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10890893</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baharoglu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Petranovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RuvAB is essential for replication forks reversal in certain replication mutants</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16424908</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baharoglu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Masson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsaneva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>ruvA</italic> mutants that resolve Holliday junctions but do not reverse replication forks</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e1000012</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18369438</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Branzei</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Foiani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interplay of replication checkpoints and repair proteins at stalled replication forks</article-title><source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>994</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17382606</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Courcelle</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Courcelle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RuvABC is required to resolve Holliday junctions that accumulate following replication on damaged templates in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>28811</fpage><lpage>28821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16895921</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A fork-clearing role for UvrD</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1664</fpage><lpage>1675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16135232</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayanagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional significance of octameric RuvA for a branch migration complex from <italic>Thermus thermophilus</italic></article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2008</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18068124</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grompone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Seigneur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication fork reversal in DNA polymerase III mutants of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: a role for the beta clamp</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1331</fpage><lpage>1339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12028381</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayanagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A unique beta-hairpin protruding from AAA+ ATPase domain of RuvB motor protein is involved in the interaction with RuvA DNA recognition protein for branch migration of Holliday junctions</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>35024</fpage><lpage>35028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11427534</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutational analysis of the functional motifs of RuvB, an AAA+ class helicase and motor protein for Holliday junction branch migration</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10844644</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>OverbeckCarrick</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival and induction of SOS in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> treated with cisplatin, UV-irradiation, or mitomycin C are dependent on the function of the RecBC and RecFOR pathways of homologous recombination</article-title><source>Mutat Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>486</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11356333</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kowalczykowski</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Initiation of genetic recombination and recombination-dependent replication</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10754547</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Froget</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arrested replication fork processing: interplay between checkpoints and recombination</article-title><source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1042</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17412649</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lestini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UvrD controls the access of recombination proteins to blocked replication forks</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>3804</fpage><lpage>3814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17641684</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conjugational recombination in resolvase-deficient <italic>ruvC</italic> mutants of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 depends on <italic>recG</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1991</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>5414</fpage><lpage>5418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1653210</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahdi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharples</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resolution of Holliday intermediates in recombination and DNA repair &#x02013; indirect suppression of <italic>ruvA</italic>, <italic>ruvB</italic>, and <italic>ruvC</italic> mutations</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1993</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>4325</fpage><lpage>4334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8331065</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayanagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron microscopic single particle analysis of a tetrameric RuvA/RuvB/Holliday junction DNA complex</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2008</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17981150</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication fork arrest and DNA recombination</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10754549</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grompone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bidnenko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple pathways process stalled replication forks</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>12783</fpage><lpage>12788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15328417</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Boubakri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Baharoglu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemasson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lestini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recombination proteins and rescue of arrested replication forks</article-title><source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>980</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17395553</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishino</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ariyoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analyses of the domain structure in the Holliday junction binding protein RuvA</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>1998</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9493263</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replisome architecture and dynamics in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>10653</fpage><lpage>10656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16421093</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AAA+ superfamily ATPases: common structure &#x02013; diverse function</article-title><source>Genes Cells</source><year>2001</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11473577</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure&#x02013;function analysis of the three domains of RuvB DNA motor protein</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>30504</fpage><lpage>30510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15972826</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Privezentzev</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigala</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsaneva</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of RuvA octamerization for RuvAB function <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>3365</fpage><lpage>3375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15556943</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clancy</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuruta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetmur</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tainer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and mechanism of the RuvB Holliday junction branch migration motor</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>311</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11478862</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rafferty</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingleston</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Artymiuk</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharples</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural similarities between <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> RuvA protein and other DNA-binding proteins and a mutational analysis of its binding to the Holliday junction</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9571037</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsaneva</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearl</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of an octameric RuvA&#x02013;Holliday junction complex</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9774974</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaaper</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Base selection, proofreading, and mismatch repair during DNA replication in <italic>Escherichia-coli</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>23762</fpage><lpage>23765</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8226906</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seigneur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bidnenko</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RuvAB acts at arrested replication forks</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9814711</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seigneur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RuvABC-dependent double-strand breaks in <italic>dnaBts</italic> mutants require RecA</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069680</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shurvinton</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Damage to DNA induces expression of the <italic>ruv</italic> gene of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1982</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7045590</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shurvinton</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Attfield</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis and molecular cloning of the <italic>Escherichia coli ruv</italic> gene</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1984</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6328219</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tourriere</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maintenance of fork integrity at damaged DNA and natural pause sites</article-title><source>DNA Repair (Amst)</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>900</fpage><lpage>913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17379579</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Processing of recombination intermediates by the RuvABC proteins</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442895</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitby</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting Holliday junctions by the RecG branch migration protein of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>19729</fpage><lpage>19739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9677403</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohnishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of the RuvA&#x02013;RuvB complex: a structural basis for the Holliday junction migrating motor machinery</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12408833</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="b38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ariyoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional structural views of branch migration and resolution in DNA homologous recombination</article-title><source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15093826</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 