<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn1023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkn1023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19151091</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>RNA</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mechanistic characterization of the sulfur-relay system for eukaryotic 2-thiouridine biogenesis at tRNA wobble positions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Noma</surname><given-names>Akiko</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>Yuriko</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Tsutomu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Chemistry and Biotechnology, Graduate School of Engineering, University of Tokyo, Bldg. 7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113-8656, Japan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+81 3 5841 8752</phone>; Fax: <fax>+81 3 3816 0106</fax>; Email: <email>ts@chembio.t.u-tokyo.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><!--For NAR both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>37</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1335</fpage><lpage>1352</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2009 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The wobble modification in tRNAs, 5-methoxycarbonylmethyl-2-thiouridine (mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U), is required for the proper decoding of NNR codons in eukaryotes. The 2-thio group confers conformational rigidity of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U by largely fixing the C3&#x02032;-<italic>endo</italic> ribose puckering, ensuring stable and accurate codon&#x02013;anticodon pairing. We have identified five genes in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, <italic>YIL008w</italic> (<italic>URM1</italic>), <italic>YHR111w</italic> (<italic>UBA4</italic>), <italic>YOR251c</italic> (<italic>TUM1)</italic>, <italic>YNL119w</italic> (<italic>NCS2</italic>) and <italic>YGL211w</italic> (<italic>NCS6</italic>), that are required for 2-thiolation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. An <italic>in vitro</italic> sulfur transfer experiment revealed that Tum1p stimulated the cysteine desulfurase of Nfs1p, and accepted persulfide sulfurs from Nfs1p. <italic>URM1</italic> is a ubiquitin-related modifier, and <italic>UBA4</italic> is an E1-like enzyme involved in protein urmylation. The carboxy-terminus of Urm1p was activated as an acyl-adenylate (-COAMP), then thiocarboxylated (-COSH) by Uba4p. The activated thiocarboxylate can be utilized in the subsequent reactions for 2-thiouridine formation, mediated by Ncs2p/Ncs6p. We could successfully reconstitute the 2-thiouridine formation <italic>in vitro</italic> using recombinant proteins. This study revealed that 2-thiouridine formation shares a pathway and chemical reactions with protein urmylation. The sulfur-flow of eukaryotic 2-thiouridine formation is distinct mechanism from the bacterial sulfur-relay system which is based on the persulfide chemistry.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Post-transcriptional RNA modifications are characteristic structural feature of RNA molecules. RNA modifications play critical roles in various aspects of RNA molecules, including biogenesis, metabolism, structural stability and functions. To date, more than 100 species of RNA modifications have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). The majority of these modifications have been identified and characterized in tRNA molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2 B3 B4">2&#x02013;4</xref>). In the region of the tRNA anticodon in particular, various modified nucleosides with diverse chemical structures have been found at the anticodon first (wobble) position 34, and at position 37 3&#x02032;-adjacent to the anticodon. The wobble modifications play pivotal roles in deciphering genetic codes that are mediated by the precise codon&#x02013;anticodon interactions at the ribosomal A-site. The wobble base of the tRNAs for Glu, Gln and Lys are universally modified to 5-methyl-2-thiouridine derivatives (xm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U), such as 5-methylaminomethyl-2-thiouridine (mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U) and 5-carboxymethyl-2-thiouridine (cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U) in bacterial tRNAs, 5-taurinomethyl-2-thiouridine (&#x003c4;m<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U) in mammalian mitochondrial tRNAs and 5-methoxycarbonylmethyl-2-thiouridine (mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U) in cytoplasmic tRNAs in eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). It is known that the conformation of xm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U is largely fixed in the C3&#x02032;-<italic>endo</italic> form of its ribose puckering, since the large van der Waals&#x02019; radius of the 2-thio group causes a steric repulsion with its 2&#x02032; OH group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>). The xm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U modification base-pairs preferentially with purine and prevents misreading of near cognate codons ending in pyrimidine due to this conformational rigidity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>). It is known that the 2-thio group of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U is required for efficient codon recognition on the ribosome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>). In addition, the 2-thio group of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> acts as the identifying element for specific recognition by glutaminyl-tRNA synthetase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>). Lack of xm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U modification in the mutant mitochondrial tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> from myoclonus epilepsy associated with ragged-red fibers (MERRF), results in a marked defect in whole mitochondrial translation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Thus, the 2-thio modification xm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U plays a critical role in protein synthesis. <fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Chemical structure of 5-methoxycarmonylmethyl-2-thiouridene (mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U) and secondary structure of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup>. (<bold>A</bold>) Chemical structures of mcm<sup>5</sup>U and mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. 2-thiolation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U utilizes cysteine and ATP as substrates. (<bold>B</bold>) Secondary structure of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> with modified nucleosides: 5-methoxycarmonylmethyl-2-thiouridine (mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U), pseudouridine (&#x003a8;), dihydrouridine (D), 5-methylcytidine (m<sup>5</sup>C) and 5-methyluridine (m<sup>5</sup>U). Arrows indicate the sites for RNase T<sub>1</sub> cleavage needed to produce the anticodon-containing fragment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn1023f1"/></fig></p><p>It is known that sulfur is an essential element for all living organisms. In fact, sulfur occurs in all the major classes of biomolecules, such as Fe/S clusters (iron/sulfur clusters or ISCs) in proteins, enzyme cofactors such as thiamine, biotine and molybdopterin, and thionucleosides in tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11 B12 B13">11&#x02013;13</xref>). The trafficking and delivery of sulfur to these molecules remains to be elucidated. Cysteine desulfurases have been shown to play a key role in the generation of sulfur-containing metabolites. In eubacteria, IscS is a widely distributed cysteine desulfurase that catalyzes the desulfuration of L-cysteine using pyridoxal-5&#x02032;-phosphate (PLP) as a cofactor to generate cysteine persulfide (IscS-S-SH) by transferring the sulfur atom from the L-cysteine to the active-site cysteine residue of IscS. The resultant persulfide can be utilized by subsequent reactions in various sulfur pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>). In fact, it is known that IscS is required for the generation of several thionucleosides in bacterial tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>). The biogenesis of 2-thiouridine in tRNAs requires a complicated sulfur-transfer system that involves multiple sulfur mediators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). We previously identified five sulfur mediators, named as TusA, B, C, D and E, which are involved in a bucket-brigade transfer of the persulfide responsible for 2-thiolation of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Efficient 2-thiouridine formation <italic>in vitro</italic> could be reconstituted with recombinant proteins of IscS, TusA, the TusBCD complex, TusE and MnmA. TusA directly interacts with IscS, and stimulates its desulfurase activity. TusA accepts the persulfide sulfur from IscS, and transfers the sulfur to TusD in the TusBCD complex. TusE can interact with TusBCD and accepts the sulfur from TusD. TusE also interacts with MnmA, a thiouridylase responsible for 2-thiouridine formation, and transfers the persulfide to it. MnmA activates the C2-position of the uracil base at the wobble position of the tRNA by forming an acyl-adenylated intermediate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). Then, nucleophilic attack by the persulfide sulfur on the activated carbon generates a thiocarbonyl group by releasing the AMP. The crystal structure of the MnmA&#x02013;tRNA complex clearly revealed snapshots of 2-thiouridine formation via the acyl-adenylated intermediate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). These studies indicated that the biogenesis of 2-thiouridine in <italic>E. coli</italic> utilizes persulfide chemistry and proceeds through a complex sulfur-relay system by multiple sulfur mediators that select and facilitate specific sulfur flow to 2-thiouridine from various cellular sulfur pathways.</p><p>In the yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, the cysteine desulfurase <italic>NFS1</italic> is essential for the biogenesis of the 2-thiouridines in both mitochondrial and cytoplasmic tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Since <italic>NFS1</italic> not only functions as a direct supplier of persulfide to thionucleosides, but also provides a sulfur atom to the Fe/S cluster formation, it was uncertain whether biogenesis of the Fe/S cluster is required for 2-thiouridine formation. Since three components of the cytosolic Fe/S protein assembly (CIA) apparatus (Cfd1, Nbp35 and Cia1), and two scaffold proteins (Isu1 and Isu2), for the mitochondrial ISC machinery, were required for 2-thiolation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in cytoplasmic tRNAs, but not for 2-thiolation of cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in mitochondrial tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>), cytoplasmic 2-thiouridine formation essentially requires a protein containing an Fe/S cluster, while mitochondrial 2-thiouridine formation is an independent reaction from the biogenesis of the Fe/S cluster. We previously showed that <italic>MTU1</italic>, which is the eukaryotic homolog of <italic>mnmA</italic>, is a mitochondria-specific 2-thiouridylase responsible for the generation of cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in yeast and &#x003c4;m<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). As no homologs of bacterial Tus-proteins have been identified in eukaryotes, unidentified sulfur mediators might be involved in connecting the specific sulfur-flow between <italic>NFS1</italic> and <italic>MTU1</italic> in mitochondria.</p><p>In the case of cytoplasmic 2-thiouridine formation, it was reported that deletion of <italic>TUC1</italic>/<italic>NCS6</italic>/<italic>YGL211</italic> resulted in the loss of the 2-thio group of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Recently, in nematode and fission yeast, Ctu1, a homolog of TUC1, was shown to be involved in the 2-thiouridine formation of cytoplasmic tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Ctu1 forms a functional complex with Ctu2. These results indicate that the Ctu1-Ctu2 complex is a putative enzyme for the formation of 2-thiouridine. Although <italic>in vitro</italic> 2-thiouridine formation could be partially reconstituted using the immunoprecipitated Ctu1&#x02013;Ctu2 complex and Nfs1p, the activity was quite low, indicating that there are still components missing from the pathway. The proteins mediating the transfer of the activated sulfur from the cysteine residue to the 2-thio group of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in cytoplasmic tRNAs, and the mechanism by which this is achieved, remain unclear.</p><p>To elucidate a sulfur-flow system for cytoplasmic 2-thiouridine formation, we searched for the genes responsible for 2-thiolation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in cytoplasmic tRNAs using a genome-wide screen of uncharacterized genes in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. The screen employed a reverse genetic approach combined with mass spectrometry, which we called &#x02018;ribonucleome&#x02019; analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). This analysis utilizes a series of gene-deletion strains of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (or <italic>E. coli</italic>). The total RNA extracted from each strain is analyzed by liquid chromatography/mass spectrometry (LC/MS) to determine whether a particular gene deletion leads to the absence of a specific modified nucleoside, thereby permitting us to identify the enzyme or protein responsible for this modification. The ribonucleome analysis enables us to identify not only the enzyme genes directly responsible for RNA modifications, but also genes that encode non-enzymatic proteins necessary for the biosynthesis of RNA modifications. These include carriers of the metabolic substrates used for RNA modifications and partner proteins needed for RNA recognition. In fact, using this approach, we previously identified <italic>tilS</italic> for lysidine formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>), <italic>tusA-E</italic> for 2-thiouridine formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) and <italic>tmcA</italic> for <italic>N</italic><sup>4</sup>-acetyl-cytidine formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>) in <italic>E. coli</italic>. In <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, <italic>TYW1-4</italic> for wybutosine synthesis were identified and characterized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). In this study, we have used ribonucleome analysis to identify five genes that are required for 2-thiouridine formation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. Biochemical characterization revealed that eukaryotic 2-thiouridine formation occurs through a chemical reaction related to ubiquitination, the sulfur-flow of which employs a different system from the bacterial sulfur-relay system which is based on the persulfide chemistry.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Strains, media and plasmids</title><p><italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> wild-type strain and deletion strains were obtained from EUROSCARF: the BY4742 (<italic>Mat &#x003b1;; his3&#x00394;1; leu2&#x00394;0; lys2&#x00394;0; ura3&#x00394;0</italic>) series of strains&#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> (<italic>YIL008w::kanMX4</italic>), &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> (<italic>YHR111w::kanMX4</italic>), &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> (<italic>YOR251c::kanMX4</italic>), &#x00394;<italic>NCS2</italic> (<italic>YNL119w::kanMX4</italic>), &#x00394;<italic>NCS6</italic> (<italic>YGL211w::kanMX4</italic>), &#x00394;<italic>ELP4</italic> (<italic>YPL101w::kanMX4</italic>), &#x00394;<italic>TRM9</italic> (<italic>YML014w::kanMX4</italic>) and &#x00394;<italic>THI4</italic> (<italic>YGR144w::kanMX4</italic>). YSC3869-9518112 (Y258; <italic>Mat a; pep4</italic><italic>&#x00394;</italic><italic>3</italic>; <italic>his4&#x00394;580; ura3&#x00394;53; leu2&#x00394;3;/pYOR251c</italic>) for expression of recombinant Tum1p, and YSC1178-7500542 for TAP tagged Ncs6p were obtained from OpenBiosystems.</p><p>Strains were grown in rich medium YPD (2% peptone, 1% yeast extract and 2% glucose) or in synthetic complete medium SC [0.67% yeast nitrogen base (YNB) without amino acids, 0.5% casamino acid and 2% glucose] supplemented with auxotrophic nutrients as specified. Thiamine-deficient medium was prepared by mixing YNB without amino acids, ammonium sulfate and thiamine, 0.5% ammonium sulfate, 2% glucose supplemented by auxotrophic nutrients as specified. For control experiments this medium was supplemented with 0.4 &#x000b5;g/ml thiamine hydrochloride. The plasmid pET15b-YCL017c (pNFS1) was kindly provided by Dr Roland Lill (University of Marburg) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>), and was transformed into Rosetta(DE3)(Invitrogen) for expression of Nfs1p. pURM1 was constructed by inserting His-tag at the N-terminus and a TAA stop codon into the C terminus of the <italic>URM1</italic> ORF of the BG1805-amp plasmid obtained from the yeast ORF collection of the <italic>E. coli</italic> strain YSC3867-9521287 (OpenBiosystems). pURM1 was introduced into the &#x00394;<italic>PEP4</italic> strain (BY4741; <italic>Mat a; his3&#x00394;1; leu2&#x00394;0; met15&#x00394;0; ura3&#x00394;0; pep4::kanMX4</italic>) for expression of Urm1p. The ORF of UBA4 (YHR111w) was PCR-amplified from <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> genomic DNA with primers bearing BamHI and NotI sites, and was then integrated into the same sites of pETDuet-1 (Invitrogen) to construct pETDuet/UBA4. pETDuet/UBA4 was introduced into Rosetta(DE3) for expression of Uba4p. For site-directed mutagenesis and complementation test, pUBA4 was constructed by inserting a TAG stop codon at the C-terminus of the UBA4 ORF of the BG1805-amp plasmid obtained from the yeast ORF collection of the <italic>E. coli</italic> strain YSC3867-9523618 (OpenBiosystems). pTUM1 was a series of BG1805-amp plasmids obtained from the yeast ORF <italic>E. coli</italic> strain YSC3867-9523911 (OpenBiosystems). pNCS2 and pNCS6 were obtained from the yeast ORF <italic>E. coli</italic> strains YSC3867-9519368 and YSC3867-98812192, respectively (OpenBiosystems).</p></sec><sec><title>Ribonucleome analysis</title><p>The basic procedure was carried out as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). Yeast strains were grown in 5 ml of YPD in 24-well format deep-well plates at 30&#x000b0;C for 8&#x02013;10 h and cells were harvested during log phase growth (OD<sub>660</sub> = 1.5&#x02013;2.0). Cell pellets were resuspended in 500 &#x003bc;l of lysis buffer [20 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>]. Then it was added by neutralized phenol/chloroform (500 &#x003bc;l/100 &#x003bc;l), and shaken for 3 h at room temperature, to extract the RNA fraction. The extracted RNA was then precipitated twice with 2-propanol and ethanol. The total RNA samples were dissolved in 100 &#x003bc;l of ddH<sub>2</sub>O and stored at &#x02013;20&#x000b0;C until use. To analyze RNA nucleosides, total RNA (20 &#x003bc;g) obtained from each strain was digested to nucleosides with nuclease P1 (Yamasa) and bacterial alkaline phosphatase (BAP.C75, Takara) for 3 h at 37&#x000b0;C, and analyzed by LC/MS using ion trap mass spectrometry as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) with slight modifications. Nucleosides were separated by an ODS reverse-phase column (Intertsil ODS3 5 &#x003bc;m, 2.1 &#x000d7; 250 mm, GL Science) using an HP1100 liquid chromatography system (Agilent). The solvent consisted of 0.1% acetonitrile in 5 mM NH<sub>4</sub>OAc (pH 5.3) (Solvent A) and 60% acetonitrile in H<sub>2</sub>O (Solvent B) in the following gradients: 1&#x02013;35% B in 0&#x02013;35 min, 35&#x02013;99% B in 35&#x02013;40 min, 99% B in 40&#x02013;50 min, 0.99&#x02013;1% B in 50&#x02013;50.1 min and 1% B in 50.1&#x02013;60 min. The chromatographic effluent was directly conducted to the electrospray ionization (ESI) source to ionize the separated nucleosides, which were analyzed on a LCQ DUO ion trap mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The mass spectrometer was operated with a spray voltage of 5 kV and a capillary temperature of 245&#x000b0;C. The sheath gas flow rate was 95 arb, auxiliary gas flow rate was 5 arb. Positive ions were scanned over an m/z range of 103 to 900.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation and purification of individual tRNAs from yeast</title><p>Yeast strains were grown in 2 L of YPD medium and harvested during late-log phase growth (OD<sub>660</sub> = 1.5&#x02013;2.0). Total RNA was extracted as described above, to obtain about 700 A<sub>260</sub> units. To isolate individual tRNAs, we employed the chaplet column chlomatography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>) and the reciprocal circulating chromatography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). The 3&#x02032;-biotinylated DNA probes complementary to yeast cytoplasmic tRNAs used in this study are 5&#x02032;-ctccgatacggggagtcgaaccccggtctc-3&#x02032; for tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> and 5&#x02032;-ctcctcatagggggctcgaacccctgacat-3&#x02032; for tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup>. As appropriate, the isolated tRNAs were further purified by denaturing polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis.</p></sec><sec><title>Mass spectrometry of tRNA</title><p>A detailed description of tRNA analysis by mass spectrometry was described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). The purified tRNA (24 ng each) was digested at 37&#x000b0;C for 1 h, then heated at 55&#x000b0;C for 10 min in 10 &#x000b5;l of a reaction mixture containing 10 mM ammonium acetate (pH 5.3) and 5 U/&#x000b5;l of RNase T<sub>1</sub> (Epicentre). After digestion, 10 &#x003bc;l of 0.1 M triethylamine-acetate (TEAA) (pH 7.0) was added to the reaction mixture. To analyze the limited quantity of RNA fragments, we employed a system of capillary LC nano ESI/mass spectrometry consisting of a tandem quadrupole time-of-flight (QqTOF) mass spectrometer (QSTAR&#x000ae; XL, Applied Biosystems) equipped with nanoelectrospray ionization sources (NANOSPRAY II), and a splitless nanoflow HPLC system (DiNa, KYA Technologies) equipped with a nano injection valve (Nanovolume Valve,Valco Instruments). Twelve nanograms of the digested tRNA were loaded onto a nano-LC trap column (C18, &#x003a6;0.5 &#x000d7; 0.1 mm) and desalted, by 0.1 M TEAA (pH 7.0). The RNA fragments were eluted from the trap column, directly injected into a C18 capillary column (HiQ Sil; 3 um C18, 100A pore size; &#x003a6;0.15 &#x000d7; 50 mm, KYA Technologies) and chromatographed at a flow rate of 500 nl/min in a linear gradient of 0&#x02013;80% B for 40 min. The solvent system consisted of 0.4 M 1,1,1,3,3,3-hexafluoro-2-propanol (HFIP) (pH 7.0, adjusted with triethylamine) (Solvent A) and 0.4 M HFIP in 50% methanol (Solvent B). The chromatographic eluent was sprayed from an energized sprayer tip attached to the capillary column. Ions were scanned with a negative polarity mode over an m/z range of 600 to 2000 throughout the separation. The parameters for the QSTAR used in this analysis were: spray voltage, &#x02013;2.0 kV; curtain gas, 15; accumulation time, 1 s.</p></sec><sec><title>APM&#x02013;polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis/northern blotting</title><p>The presence of thiouridine in tRNAs was analyzed by the retardation of electrophoretic mobility on polyacrylamide gels containing 0.02 mg/ml (<italic>N</italic>-acryloylamino)phenyl]mercuric chloride (APM) (kindly provided by Dr Naoki Shigi of AIST). The procedure was originally developed by Igloi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Total RNA (0.05 A<sub>260</sub> units) was separated by PAGE containing APM and blotted onto Hybond N<sup>+</sup> membranes (GE Healthcare). Individual tRNAs were detected by northern blotting with 5&#x02032; <sup>32</sup>P-labeled oligonucleotide probes as follows: 5&#x02032;-ctccgatacggggagtcgaaccccg-3&#x02032; for tRNA<sup>Glu</sup>, 5&#x02032;-ctcctcatagggggctcgaacccct-3&#x02032; for tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup> and 5&#x02032;-tgagaatagctggagttgaaccaag-3&#x02032; for mt tRNA<sup>Lys</sup>. Following hybridization, membranes were washed, dried and then exposed to a phosphor-imaging plate. The radioactivity was visualized by an FLA-7000 imaging analyzer (Fuji Film).</p></sec><sec><title>Expression and purification of the recombinant proteins</title><p>The yeast strains expressing hexahistidine-tagged Urm1p and Tum1p were grown at 30&#x000b0;C in 300 ml of YPD. The expression of the recombinant proteins was induced by 2% galactose. After cultivation for 20 h, cells were harvested and washed with ddH<sub>2</sub>O, and then resuspended in the lysis buffer [20 mM HEPES-KOH (pH 7.6), 10 mM KOAc, 2 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT) and a protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche)] and disrupted by four passages through the French press (Thermo Fischer Scientific). The cell lysate was cleared by ultracentrifugation with 100 000 <italic>g</italic> for 1.5 h at 4&#x000b0;C. The supernatant of the lysate was passed through a His-Trap chelating HP column (GE Healthcare) to purify the His-tagged protein using an AKTA purifier chromatography system (GE Healthcare) according to the manufacturer's instruction. Briefly, the column was equilibrated with wash buffer [50 mM HEPES-KOH (pH 7.6), 100 mM KCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 7 mM &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol and a protease inhibitor cocktail], and then the supernatant was loaded onto the column and washed with 25&#x02013;50 ml of the wash buffer. The His-tagged proteins were eluted from the column with a linear-gradient of imidazole (50&#x02013;450 mM) in the wash buffer. The eluted fractions were analyzed by SDS&#x02013;PAGE. The fractions containing the recombinant proteins were pooled and dialyzed against a buffer containing 20 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.6), 4 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 55 mM NaCl and 1 mM DTT. Urm1p was further purified by anion-exchange chromatography using a Mono Q (GE healthcare) column. His-tagged Nfs1p and Uba4p were recombinantly expressed in the <italic>E. coli</italic> strain Rosetta(DE3). The expression of these recombinant proteins was induced by 2% lactose. The <italic>E. coli</italic> cells, grown for 20 h at 18&#x000b0;C for Nfs1p (or 25&#x000b0;C for Uba4p), were harvested and resuspended in lysis buffer, and lyzed by sonication. The lysate was cleared by ultracentrifugation at 4&#x000b0;C and 100 000 <italic>g</italic> for 1.5 h. The His-tagged proteins were purified by the AKTA purifier chromatography system using a His-Trap chelating HP column (GE Healthcare) as described above.</p></sec><sec><title>Site-directed mutagenesis</title><p>Site-directed mutagenesis of <italic>URM1</italic>, <italic>UBA4</italic> and <italic>TUM1</italic> was carried out on the plasmids pURM1, pUBA4 and pTUM1 by QuikChange<sup>TM</sup> Site-Directed Mutagenesis (Stratagene) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Introduced mutations were confirmed by DNA sequencing. The following pairs of oligonucleotides were used to create each mutantion:</p><p>5&#x02032;-ttacttcaacattacattaaaacccagctttctt-3&#x02032;and 5&#x02032;-aagaaagctgggttttaatgtaatgttgaagtaa-3&#x02032; for pURM1 &#x00394;GG, 5&#x02032;-aaatgccgtgacctcttcccaagaaggcggtgtga-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-tcacaccgccttcttgggaagaggtcacggcattt-3&#x02032; for pUBA4 C225S, 5&#x02032;-aaatgccgtgacctctgcccaagaaggcggtgtga-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-tcacaccgccttcttgggcagaggtcacggcattt-3&#x02032; for pUBA4 C225A, 5&#x02032;-taatatagtgattctttcccgctacggtaacgact-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-agtcgttaccgtagcgggaaagaatcactatatta-3&#x02032; for pUBA4 C397S, 5&#x02032;-accaactatttgctcttctggaactggcgtttcag-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-ctgaaacgccagttccagaagagcaaatagttggt-3&#x02032; for pTUM1 C259S, 5&#x02032;-accaactatttgctctgctggaactggcgtttcag-3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032;-ctgaaacgccagttccagcagagcaaatagttggt-3&#x02032; for pTUM1 C259A.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> sulfur transfer experiments</title><p>Sulfur transfer from Nfs1p to Tum1p was performed as follows: a 10 &#x000b5;l reaction mixture consisting of 50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 12 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 20 &#x000b5;M pyridoxal 5&#x02032;-phosphate (PLP), 0.4 mM DTT, 0.1 mM [<sup>35</sup>S] cysteine (370 MBq/mmol), 25 pmol of Nfs1p and 2.5&#x02013;60.2 pmol of Tum1p was incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 30 min. In the case of sulfur transfer from Nfs1p to Urm1p, a 10 &#x000b5;l reaction mixture consisting of 50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 12 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 20 &#x000b5;M PLP, 0.4 mM DTT, 0.1 mM [<sup>35</sup>S]cysteine (370 MBq/mmol) with or without 2 mM ATP and recombinant proteins (50 pmol of Urm1p and 25 pmol each of Nfs1p, Tum1p and Uba4p) was incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 30 min. Following the reaction, the reaction mixture was mixed with the sample loading solution for SDS&#x02013;PAGE to give a final concentration of 4% glycerol, 25 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 6.8), 1% SDS, and 0.0015% bromophenol blue. SDS&#x02013;PAGE was performed on a 9% acrylamide gel. The gel was dried and exposed on a phosphor-imaging plate, and the radioactivity was visualized by an FLA-7000 imager (Fuji Film).</p><p>To characterize the thiocarboxylation of Urm1p by mass spectrometry, 0.1% trifluoroacetic acid (TFA) was added to the reaction mixture following sulfur transfer from Nfs1p to Urm1p to adjust the reaction mixture to pH 3. It was then subjected to capillary LC nano ESI/mass spectrometry as described above. The reaction mixture containing 10 pmol of Urm1p was loaded onto a trap-column packed with C4 reverse-phase resin to be desalted with 0.1% TFA, then directly injected into a C4 capillary column (HiQ Sil, 5um C4, 100 &#x000c5; poresize; &#x003a6;0.15 &#x000d7; 50 mm, KYA Technologies) and chromatographed at a flow rate of 500 nl/min in a linear gradient of 0&#x02013;80% Solvent B for 30 min. The solvent system consisted of 0.1% formic acid and 2% acetonitrile (Solvent A) and 0.1% formic acid and 70% acetonitrile (Solvent B). The applied voltage on the sprayer was set +2.2 kV to generate a nanoelectrospray. TOF MS and product ion spectra were acquired on positive mode using the information-dependent data acquisition (IDA) of the Analyst QS software (Applied Biosystems). Mass ranges for TOF MS and MS/MS were set to 400&#x02013;2000 and 200&#x02013;2000, respectively. The collision energy was set at +40 to decompose the acyl adenylated Urm1p (-COAMP). To reconstruct the zero-charge deconvoluted spectra from the raw data, the Bayesian protein reconstruct tool in the Bioanalyst software (Applied Biosystems) was used.</p></sec><sec><title>Pulling down TAP-tagged Ncs6p by IgG beads</title><p>The yeast strain expressing TAP-tagged Ncs6p was cultivated in 1 L of YPD at 30&#x000b0;C (until OD<sub>660</sub> = 0.7) and washed with ddH<sub>2</sub>O, and then resuspended in lysis buffer. The cells were disrupted by three passages through a homogenizer an EmulsiFlex C-3 (AVESTIN). The lysate was cleared by ultracentrifugation at 100 000 <italic>g</italic> and 4&#x000b0;C for 1.5 h. The lysate was mixed with IgG beads (Sigma), and incubated for 2 h at 4&#x000b0;C. The beads were washed twice with IPP300 buffer [25 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 8.0), 300 mM NaCl, 0.1% NP-40, 1% Empigen BB(Fluka), 1 mM DTT and protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche)], washed twice with IPP150 buffer [25 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 8.0), 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% NP-40, 1% Empigen BB(Fluka), 1 mM DTT and a protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche)], and washed once with a buffer consisting of 50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 50 mM KCl, 12 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. Finally, the beads were washed once with T buffer [50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 50 mM KCl, 12 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 20 &#x000b5;M PLP, 1 mM cysteine and 5 mM ATP] and then suspended in T buffer. As a negative control, we prepared IgG beads which were passed through the cell lysate of the wild-type strain, and treated with the same procedure as used in pulling down Ncs6p.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> 2-thiouridine formation</title><p>The isolated tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup> from the &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> strain was dephosphorylated by bacterial alkaline phosphatase (BAP.A19, Takara), and labeled at its 5&#x02032; terminus with [&#x003b3;-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP (111 TBq/mmol) by T4 polynucleotide kinase (Toyobo). The end-labeled tRNA was then purified by 10% denaturing PAGE. Formation of 2-thiouridine formation was carried out as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) with following modifications: the reaction mixture (20 &#x000b5;l) consisting of 50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 12 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 20 &#x000b5;M PLP, 1 mM cysteine, 2 mM ATP, 0.1 mM DTT and 50 pmol of Urm1p and 25 pmol each of Nfs1p, Tum1p and Uba4p and 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P-labeled tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup> (50 000 cpm) was incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 60 min in the presence or absence of the TAP-tagged Ncs6p trapped on the IgG beads. Reaction mixtures without ATP or with IgG beads which were passed through the wild-type cell lysate tRNA were employed as negative controls for 2-thiouridine formation. After the reaction, tRNAs were recovered by ISOGEN (Wako), ethanol-precipitated and dissolved by APM&#x02013;PAGE as described above. The gels were exposed on a phosphor-imaging plate and analyzed by FLA-7000 imager (Fuji Film).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Genome-wide identification of genes responsible for 2-thiouridine formation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U by the ribonucleome analysis</title><p>To identify the genes responsible for 2-thiouridine formation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, we performed ribonucleome analysis, a genome-wide reverse genetic approach combined with mass spectrometry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>). Since 2-thiouridine is a non-essential RNA modification, the complete set of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> deletion strains (4829) serves as a parent population for this analysis. To reduce the size of the starting population, we selected 3482 genes that have orthologs in <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic>, because <italic>S. pombe</italic> tRNAs possess mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. Next, we chose 767 genes which are described as proteins of unknown function, and proteins with weak similarity to known functions in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (CYGD: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mips.gsf.de/genre/proj/yeast">http://mips.gsf.de/genre/proj/yeast</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>). We then started the ribonucleome analysis using this population. In the mass chromatogram (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A), mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U was detected as a proton adduct form (MH<sup>+</sup>; m/z 333) with its base fragment (BH<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup>; m/z 201) in wild-type cells. mcm<sup>5</sup>U (MH<sup>+</sup>; m/z 317) with its base fragment (BH<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup>; m/z 185), which is a precursor form of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, could also be detected in wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). Among the 767 selected deletion mutants, we identified four deletion strains, <italic>YHR111w(UBA4), YNL119w(NCS2), YGL211w(NCS6)</italic> and <italic>YOR251c</italic>, in which mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U was absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A, upper panels), while levels of its precursor mcm<sup>5</sup>U were increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A, lower panels), demonstrating that these genes are specifically involved in 2-thiolation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. We have renamed <italic>YOR251c</italic> as tRNA-<underline>t</underline>hio<underline>u</underline>ridine <underline>m</underline>odification protein <underline>1</underline> (<italic>TUM1</italic>). <italic>NCS2</italic> is an orthologous protein of Ctu2 in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> and fission yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). Although it was reported that <italic>NCS6</italic>/<italic>TUC1</italic> is responsible for 2-thiouridine formation by comparative genomic approach in 2007 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>), we have independently identified the same gene in this analysis. It was reported that <italic>UBA4, NCS2</italic> and <italic>NCS6</italic> are essential in the <italic>&#x00394;CLA4</italic> strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>), and that their deletion affects the protein urmylation, which is a ubiquitin-like conjugation pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). <italic>UBA4</italic> encodes a paralog of a ubiquitin-activating enzyme (E1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). In fact, <italic>UBA4</italic> was shown to function as an E1-like enzyme for <italic>URM1</italic>, which is an ubiquitin-related modifier involved in protein urmylation. We therefore analyzed the total nucleosides of &#x00394;<italic>YIL008w</italic>(<italic>URM1</italic>) and found that <italic>URM1</italic> is also responsible for 2-thiolation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A). <fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Mass spectrometric analyses of total nucleosides and purified tRNAs<sup>Glu</sup> from <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> wild-type and mutant cells. (<bold>A</bold>) LC/MS analyses of total nucleosides from strains of wild-type (WT), &#x00394;<italic>YOR251c</italic> (<italic>TUM1</italic>), &#x00394;<italic>YHR111w</italic> (<italic>UBA4</italic>), &#x00394;<italic>YIL008w</italic> (<italic>URM1</italic>), &#x00394;<italic>YNL119w</italic> (<italic>NCS2</italic>) and &#x00394;<italic>YGL211w</italic> (<italic>NCS6</italic>). The upper panels show the merged mass chromatograms detecting MH<sup>+</sup> (m/z 333) and BH<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> (m/z 201) of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. The lower panels show the mass chromatograms detecting MH<sup>+</sup> (m/z 317) and BH<sub>2</sub><sup>+</sup> (m/z 185) of mcm<sup>5</sup>U. Arrows in the upper panels indicate the retention time for mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. (<bold>B</bold>) LC/MS fragment analyses of RNase T<sub>1</sub>-digested tRNAs<sup>Glu</sup> obtained from wild-type strains: &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>NCS2</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>NCS6</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>TRM9</italic>. A graph on the top-right represents the mass spectrum for the anticodon-containing fragment (CUmcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>UUCACCGp) (Figure 1B) from the wild-type strain. Charge states of multiply charged ions are indicated in parentheses. Other graphs describe the mass chromatograms shown by triply charged ions of anticodon-containing fragments bearing mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (m/z 1458.17, red line), mcm<sup>5</sup>U (m/z 1450.18, black line), ncm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (m/z 1450.67, green line) and ncm<sup>5</sup>U (m/z 1443.18, blue line). The RNA sequence including the wobble modification is indicated on each graph.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn1023f2"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Analyses of individual tRNAs isolated from a series of the knockout strains</title><p>To confirm the absence of the 2-thio group of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U at the wobble position of individual tRNAs, we isolated individual tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> from each of <italic>&#x00394;URM1</italic>, <italic>&#x00394;UBA4</italic>, <italic>&#x00394;TUM1</italic>, <italic>&#x00394;NCS2</italic> and <italic>&#x00394;NCS6</italic> strains. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, the anticodon-containing fragments of the isolated tRNAs<sup>Glu</sup> were analyzed by LC/MS (RNaseT<sub>1</sub> mapping). In the wild-type tRNA<sup>Glu</sup>, the anticodon-containing RNA fragment with mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U modification (CUmcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>UUCACCGp, MW 2918.344), produced by RNase T<sub>1</sub> digestion was clearly observed as doubly-charged (m/z 1458.277), triply-charged (m/z 971.856) and quadruply-charged (m/z 728.586) ions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, top left panel). The same RNA fragment in tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> isolated from the &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>NCS2</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>NCS6</italic> strains weighed 2902.367 Da (detected as m/z 1450.183, 966.455 and 724.591 for doubly- to quadruply charged ions), which is the mass of a fragment composed of mcm<sup>5</sup>U instead of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. Very recently, it has been reported that 5-carboxymethyluridine (cm<sup>5</sup>U) was detected as a modification intermediate in &#x00394;<italic>NCS2</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>NCS6</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>). However, no such intermediate could be observed in the isolated tRNAs in our analysis. In the case of the &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> strain, the mass of a fragment with a fully modified mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U was also detected as a minor product (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B, as shown in red).</p><p>Next, we also employed APM&#x02013;PAGE/northern blotting to detect thiolated tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B) from each of the knockout strains. In the wild-type cells, a large fraction of the tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> migrates slowly on the PAGE in the presence of APM due to a specific interaction between the thiocarbonyl group of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and the APM in the gel. No retarded band for tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> from &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>NCS2</italic> was observed, showing that no thiouridine formation occurred in these strains. The thiouridine in these deletion strains was partially or completely restored by the introduction of a plasmid encoding <italic>URM1</italic>, <italic>UBA4</italic> or <italic>NCS2</italic>. With respect to <italic>NCS6</italic>, we failed to restore 2-thiouridine formation in the &#x00394;<italic>NCS6</italic> strain, by introduction of a plasmid encoding <italic>NCS6</italic>, for unknown reasons (data not shown). In the case of &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic>, the large fraction of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> lacked 2-thiouridine, but the small fraction of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> remained 2-thiolated. This result is consistent with the LC/MS analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). Thus, although <italic>TUM1</italic> is not essential for thiolation, it is a major component involved in this pathway.</p><p>As it is known that <italic>NFS1</italic> is involved in the biogenesis of the 2-thiouridines in both mitochondrial and cytoplasmic tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>), we investigated whether these genes affect mitochondrial 2-thiouridine formation. We employed APM&#x02013;PAGE/northern blotting to detect thiolated mitochondrial tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> from each of the five knockout strains, and found that none of these genes affected the retarded bands of mitochondrial tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> on the APM gel (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkn1023/DC1">Supplementary Figure 1</ext-link>). The data demonstrated that <italic>URM1</italic>, <italic>UBA4</italic>, <italic>TUM1</italic>, <italic>NCS2</italic> and <italic>NCS6</italic> are specific to cytoplasmic 2-thiouridine formation.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>TUM1</italic> is a sulfur mediator stimulating the desulfurase activity of <italic>NFS1</italic></title><p><italic>NFS1</italic> is a cysteine desulfurase that accepts a sulfur atom from a cysteine to form a persulfide group using PLP as a cofactor. This activated sulfur is considered to be a direct substrate for 2-thiouridine formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). According to the sequence alignment of <italic>TUM1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A), <italic>TUM1</italic> contains two rhodanese-like domains in the N-terminal and C-terminal regions, respectively. Rhodaneses are widespread sulfur carrier proteins that catalyze the transfer of sulfur atoms from thiosulfate to cyanide <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). It is known that a conserved cysteine residue in the active-site loop of rhodanese plays a key role in substrate recognition and catalytic activity. <italic>TUM1</italic> has one conserved cysteine residue (Cys259) in the C-terminal rhodanese-like domain (RLD) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). To clarify the functional importance of Cys259 in thiouridine formation, plasmids expressing wild type <italic>TUM1</italic> and its mutants, in which Cys259 was replaced with Ser (pTUM1 C259S) or Ala (pTUM1 C259A), were introduced in a &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> strain to test for complementation activity of these mutations. We performed APM&#x02013;PAGE/northern blotting to estimate 2-thiouridine formation. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, the reduced level of 2-thiolated tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> in the &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> strain was restored by the introduction of wild-type <italic>TUM1</italic>. Compared with the &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> strain, no enhancement for 2-thiouridine formation could be observed when <italic>TUM1</italic> with a C259S or C259A mutation was introduced. This result revealed that Cys259 in the C-terminal RLD of <italic>TUM1</italic> is critical for enhancing 2-thiouridine formation. <fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Sequence alignments of <italic>TUM1</italic>, <italic>UBA4</italic> and <italic>URM1</italic>. Each protein is aligned with its homologs. Multiple alignment of each sequence was carried out by Clustal X analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>) and displayed using the Genedoc multiple sequence alignment editor. White letters in black boxes represent amino-acid residues identical in all species, while white letters in gray boxes represent residues with &#x0223c;80% homology. Black letters in gray boxes represent restudies with &#x0223c;60% homology. (<bold>A</bold>) Sequence alignment of <italic>TUM1</italic> with its homologs. Two conserved rhodanese domains are underlined. The conserved C259 is indicated. (<bold>B</bold>) Sequence alignment of <italic>UBA4</italic> with its homologs and <italic>E. coli ThiF</italic> and <italic>MoeB</italic>. The boxed regions are the ATP-binding motif (GxGxxG) and the metal-binding motif (CxxC, CxxCG). The conserved C225 and C397 are indicated. The rhodanese-like domain in the C-terminal region is underlined. (<bold>C</bold>) Sequence alignment of <italic>URM1</italic> with its homologs and <italic>E. coli ThiS</italic> and <italic>MoaD</italic>. The conserved C-terminal GG motif is boxed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn1023f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>APM Northern analyses of thiolation-status of tRNAs in mutant strains and transformants. (<bold>A</bold>) APM northern analyses of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> in the s<sup>2</sup>U-deficient strains by introducing a series of mutant plasmids. Total RNA from each strain was resolved by denaturing polyacrylamide-gel electrophoresis in the presence (upper panels) or absence (lower panels) of APM. 2-thiolated tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> in each strain was detected as a shifted band only in the presence of APM, by northern blotting. Lanes 1 to 12 correspond to wild-tye (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> harboring pURM1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> harboring pURM1&#x00394;GG (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> harboring pUBA4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> harboring pUBA4 C225S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> harboring pUBA4 C225A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> harboring pUBA4 C397S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>),&#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> harboring pTUM1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> harboring pTUM1 C259S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> harboring pTUM1 C259A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>), &#x00394;<italic>NCS2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>) and &#x00394;<italic>NCS2</italic> harboring pNCS2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>), respectively. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of the thiolation-status of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> by APM/northern analyses. The fraction of the retarded band in the total intensity of the bands was calculated. Data are shown as values &#x000b1; SD and reflect the average of four independent experiments. (<bold>C</bold>) APM/northern analyses of tRNAs<sup>Lys</sup> from wild-type, &#x00394;<italic>TRM9</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>ELP4</italic>, &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic>. The right panel represents a mass chromatogram shown by triply charged ions of the anticodon-containing fragments of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> isolated from &#x00394;<italic>ELP4</italic>. The unmodified fragment (m/z 1414.18, black line) and the s<sup>2</sup>U-containing fragment (m/z 1422.16, gray line) are specifically detected.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn1023f4"/></fig></p><p>Next, we tested whether Tum1p accepts a sulfur atom from Nfs1p using an <italic>in vitro</italic> sulfur transfer experiment. Recombinant Nfs1p and Tum1p were mixed and incubated with [<sup>35</sup>S] cysteine and immediately electrophoresed without a reducing agent and boiling. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A, Nfs1p alone was slightly labeled by [<sup>35</sup>S] sulfur due to its intrinsic desulfurase activity (lane 1), while Tum1p alone was also labeled by [<sup>35</sup>S] sulfur due to its rhodanese activity (lane 2). When they were mixed, both Nfs1p and Tum1p were significantly labeled by [<sup>35</sup>S] sulfur. As the [<sup>35</sup>S] labeled sulfur was readily dissociated from Nfs1p and Tum1p by DTT treatment (data not shown), Nfs1p and Tum1p carried the sulfur atoms as a persulfide form. The labeling efficiency of Nfs1p was enhanced significantly in the presence of increasing amounts of Tum1p. Concomitantly, the activated sulfur of Nfs1p was efficiently transferred to Tum1p (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). This result suggested that the desulfurase activity of Nfs1p was enhanced in the presence of Tum1p, then the activated sulfur of Nfs1p was specifically transferred to Tum1p. Thus, Tum1p is a persulfide mediator as well as an activator for Nfs1p. The catalytic Cys259 in the RLD of Tum1p is likely to be the site for the persulfide formation. <fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><italic>In vitro</italic> sulfur transfer from Nfs1p to Tum1p and Uba4p. (<bold>A</bold>) Sulfur transfer from Nfs1p to Tum1p. The gel was stained with Coomassie brilliant blue (CBB) (upper panel) and [<sup>35</sup>S] radioactivity was visualized on a phosphor-imaging plate (lower panel). Lane 1, Nfs1p (25 pmol); lane 2, Tum1p (25 pmol); lane 3, Nfs1p (25 pmol) and Tum1p (25 pmol), lanes 4&#x02013;9, Nfs1p (25 pmol) and Tum1p (2.5, 5, 12.5, 25, 37.5, 50 pmol). (<bold>B</bold>) Sulfur transfer from Nfs1p to Uba4p. The gel was stained with Coomassie brilliant blue (CBB) (upper panel) and [<sup>35</sup>S] radioactivity was visualized on a phosphor-imaging plate (lower panel). Lane 1, Nfs1p (25 pmol); lane 2, Uba4p (25 pmol); lane 3, Nfs1p (25 pmol) and Uba4p (25 pmol), lanes 4&#x02013;9, Nfs1p (25 pmol) and Uba4p (2.5, 5, 12.5, 25, 37.5, 50 pmol).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn1023f5"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Rhodanese domain of <italic>UBA4</italic> acts as a persulfide carrier</title><p>It is known that <italic>UBA4</italic> also contains an RLD in the C-terminal region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). According to the sequence alignment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B), <italic>UBA4</italic> has a highly conserved cysteine residue (Cys397) in its RLD. We constructed a plasmid harboring a <italic>UBA4</italic> mutant in which Cys397 was replaced with Ser (pUBA4 C397S). Approximately half the fraction of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> in the &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> strain could be 2-thiolated by the introduction of a plasmid encoding the wild-type <italic>UBA4</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B). When pUBA4 C397S was introduced, no 2-thiouridine formation of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> occurred. This result demonstrated that Cys397 in the RLD of <italic>UBA4</italic> is critical for 2-thiouridine formation.</p><p>We then examined whether Uba4p directly accepts a sulfur atom from Nfs1p by means of an <italic>in vitro</italic> sulfur transfer experiment. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B, both recombinant Nfs1p and Uba4p were slightly labeled by [<sup>35</sup>S] sulfur due to their intrinsic sulfur transfer activities (lanes 1 and 2). When they were mixed together, Uba4p was apparently, but inefficiently, labeled by [<sup>35</sup>S] sulfur. The labeling efficiency of Uba4p was enhanced in proportion to increasing amounts of Uba4p, indicating that the activated sulfur of Nfs1p was transferred to Uba4p. As the [<sup>35</sup>S] labeled sulfur was removed from Uba4p by DTT treatment (data not shown), Uba4p accepted the sulfur atom as a persulfide form. However, we did not observe any apparent activation of Nfs1p with the addition of increasing amounts of Uba4p. These results suggested that Uba4p has the potential to act as an acceptor of the persulfide sulfur from Nfs1p, but does not function as an activator for Nfs1p. It is likely that the catalytic Cys397 in the RLD of Uba4p is involved in the sulfur transfer reaction.</p><p>In addition to <italic>TUM1</italic>, we also found that the RLD of <italic>UBA4</italic> acts as a sulfur carrier. In the &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> strain, we found that the small fraction of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> still remained to be 2-thiolated, indicating a minor pathway for sulfur flow. On the other hand, no thiolation of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> could be observed in the &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> strain introduced with pUBA4 C397S. These observations prompted us to speculate that Tum1p first activates Nfs1p and accepts the sulfur, then probably transfers the sulfur to the RLD of Uba4p. Meanwhile, Uba4p also acts as a minor sulfur mediator to accept the sulfur atom directly from Nfs1p, by bypassing Tum1p-mediated sulfur transfer.</p></sec><sec><title>Urm1p is thiocarboxylated by Uba4p through an acyl-adenylated intermediate</title><p><italic>URM1</italic> has been known as an ubiquitin-related modifier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). Conjugation of Urm1p (urmylation) to its target proteins depends on the E1-like activating enzyme Uba4p. Similar to ubiquitination, at the first step of urmylation, Urm1p is known to form a thioester link with Uba4p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). <italic>URM1</italic> has conserved Gly-Gly residues at its C-terminus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C) and it was shown that the conjugation reaction requires the C-terminal glycine of Urm1p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). The conserved C-terminal Gly&#x02013;Gly sequence of ubiquitin, or ubiquitin-like proteins, is also generally required for protein conjugation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42 B43 B44">42&#x02013;44</xref>). It is thought that Urm1p attaches to a target protein through an isopeptide bond between the C-terminal Gly of <italic>URM1</italic> and a lysine residue of the target protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). To test the functional importance of the C-terminal Gly-Gly of <italic>URM1</italic>, we constructed a plasmid harboring a <italic>URM1</italic> mutant (&#x00394;GG) in which the C-terminal Gly&#x02013;Gly was removed. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, 2-thiouridine formation of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> in the &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> strain could be restored by the introduction of a plasmid harboring wild-type <italic>URM1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B). When the <italic>URM1</italic> with the &#x00394;GG mutation was introduced, no thiouridine formation of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> took place, showing that the C-terminal Gly&#x02013;Gly of <italic>URM1</italic> is a critical motif not only for protein conjugation, but also for 2-thiouridine formation.</p><p><italic>UBA4</italic> is an E1-like enzyme which was assumed to activate <italic>URM1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). In this study, we found that <italic>UBA4</italic> has an RLD in the C-terminal region, which acts as a carrier of persulfide sulfur. In the N-terminal region, <italic>UBA4</italic> contains some conserved motifs shared with E1-like enzymes, such as an ATP-binding motif and a metal-binding motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). Considering the analogy to ubiquitination, the active-site cysteine residue of the E1 enzyme resides about 10-to-20-amino-acid residues downstream of the metal-binding motif (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45 B46 B47">45&#x02013;47</xref>). Therefore, the conserved Cys225 was predicted as the active-site cysteine residue for the E1-like function. When a plasmid harboring <italic>UBA4</italic> with a C225S mutation was introduced into the &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> strain, no thiouridine formation of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> could be observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A and B), demonstrating that Cys225 is the active-site cysteine residue of <italic>UBA4</italic> required for 2-thiouridine formation.</p><p>To test whether Urm1p receives a sulfur atom from Nfs1p as a thiocarboxylated form, we carried out an <italic>in vitro</italic> sulfur transfer assay with recombinant Nfs1p, Tum1p, Urm1p and Uba4p. Recombinant proteins were incubated with [<sup>35</sup>S] cysteine in the presence, or absence, of ATP. In the presence of ATP, Urm1p was specifically labeled with [<sup>35</sup>S] sulfur (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A). In the absence of ATP, no incorporation of [<sup>35</sup>S] sulfur into Urm1p was observed. Thus, Urm1p accepts a sulfur atom from cysteine in an ATP-dependent manner. Nfs1p receives a sulfur atom from cysteine as a persulfide form by employing PLP as a cofactor. This reaction is stimulated by the RLDs of Tum1p and Uba4p as observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>. Both proteins accept the persulfide sulfur from Nfs1p. In fact, recombinant Nfs1p, Tum1p and Uba4p were labeled with [<sup>35</sup>S] sulfur during the reaction. The labeling efficiency of Urm1p was not altered when the reaction mixture was treated with DTT, whereas [<sup>35</sup>S]-labeled persulfide sulfurs were readily dissociated from Nfs1p, Tum1p and Uba4p by this treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A). The data suggested that Urm1p was not labeled by nonspecific sulfur transfer as a persulfide, but that the C-terminal Gly of Urm1p was thiocarboxylated by the E1-like activity of Uba4p. <fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Thiocarboxylation of Urm1p through an acyl-adenylated intermediate. (<bold>A</bold>) <italic>In vitro</italic> sulfur transfer from Nfs1p to Urm1p. Recombinant Nfs1p, Tum1p, Urm1p and Uba4p were mixed and incubated with [<sup>35</sup>S] cysteine in the presence (lane 1) or absence (lane 2) of ATP. The reaction mixture was further incubated with 50 mM DTT (lane 3). The gel was stained with CBB (upper panels) and [<sup>35</sup>S] radioactivity was visualized on a phosphor-imaging plate (lower panels). The band for each protein is indicated. (<bold>B</bold>) Whole-mass analysis of the thiocarboxylation of Urm1p. Left panels are mass chromatograms for detecting +9-charged ions of Urm1p with unmodified C-terminus (-COOH, black line), Urm1- with thiocarboxylated C-terminus (-COSH, red line) and Urm1p with acyl-adenylated C-terminus (-COAMP, green line). Right panels are deconvoluted mass spectra for Urm1p detecting unmodified Urm1p (-COOH, 12 083 Da), thiocarboxylated Urm1p (-COSH, 12099 Da) and acyl-adenylated Urm1p (-COAMP, 12 413 Da). Top panels show whole-mass analysis of purified Urm1p used in this study. <italic>In vitro</italic> thiocarboxylation of Urm1p by Uba4p was carried out in the absence (middle panels) or presence (bottom panels) of ATP. (<bold>C</bold>) Mass spectrum of Urm1p with an acyl-adenylated C-terminus (-COAMP). A series of multiply charged ions are detected. The parent ion (m/z 1380.022, +9) for collision-induced dissociation (CID) analysis is indicated. (<bold>D</bold>) CID spectrum of Urm1p-COAMP. The product ion (m/z 348.095) for AMP originated from Urm1p-COAMP is shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn1023f6"/></fig></p><p>We further characterized the thiocarboxylation of Urm1p by mass spectrometry. The recombinant Urm1p was directly analyzed by LC/MS using tandem quadrupole mass spectrometry. Proton adducts of Urm1p were detected as a series of multiply charged ions (i.e. +7 to +15). The exact molecular mass of Urm1p was calculated as 12 083 &#x000b1; 1 Da by deconvoluting these ions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B), which was consistent with the theoretical mass of 12 082.37 Da. We also found a small fraction of the Urm1p derivative with a molecular mass of 12 099 &#x000b1; 1 Da (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B), which was assumed to be the thiocarboxylated form of Urm1p (Urm1p-COSH) whose theoretical value is 12 098.37 Da. As Urm1p was recombinantly expressed in yeast cells, it is likely that the C-terminal Gly of Urm1p was partially thiocarboxylated in the cell. Urm1p was then incubated with Nfs1p, Tum1p and Uba4p in the presence or absence of ATP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). In the absence of ATP, no change in the molecular mass of Urm1p was observed, while in the presence of ATP, we could clearly observe the acyl-adenylated form of Urm1p (Urm1p-COAMP; 12 413 Da) which is consistent with its theoretical value (12 411.59 Da). To confirm the acyl-adenylated intermediate, the proton adduct ion with +9 charge state of Urm1p-COAMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C) was subjected to collision-induced dissociation to be decomposed in the instrument using an MS/MS experiment. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>D, AMP from the acyl-adenylate intermediate of Urm1p was clearly observed as a product ion. These results revealed that the C-terminal Gly of Urm1p was first activated by Uba4p to synthesize the acyl-adenylated intermediate, then thiocarboxylated by releasing AMP.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> reconstitution of 2-thiouridine formation</title><p>To investigate whether 2-thiouridine formation occurs through a ubiquitin-like pathway, we attempted an <italic>in vitro</italic> reconstitution of 2-thiouridine of tRNAs with recombinant proteins. With respect to Ncs2p and Ncs6p, we failed to obtain recombinant proteins in soluble form (data not shown). The TAP-tagged Ncs6p was pulled down by IgG beads. Since it was reported that Ctu1/Ncs6p in fission yeast is physically associated with Ctu2/Ncs2p (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), it should be possible to isolate a small fraction of endogenous Ncs2p as an Ncs6p/Ncs2p hetero-complex in this preparation. We employed nonthiolated tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup> which was obtained from a &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> strain as a substrate for the <italic>in vitro</italic> 2-thiouridine formation. Recombinant Nfs1p, Tum1p, Urm1p and Uba4p were mixed with the IgG beads retaining the Ncs6p and 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P-labeled tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup> in a reaction mixture containing ATP, PLP and cysteine. After the reaction, the substrate tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup> was subjected to APM-containing PAGE to detect 2-thiouridine formation. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>, we partially succeeded in reconstituting the ATP-dependent 2-thiouridine formation of tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup>, but only in the presence of the recombinant proteins (Nfs1p, Tum1p, Urm1p and Uba4p), and with Ncs6p trapped on the IgG beads. As a negative control for TAP-tagged Ncs6p, we employed the IgG beads treated with wild-type cell lysate for the <italic>in vitro</italic> 2-thiouridine formation, and observed no 2-thiouridine formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). It is possible that there are still unidentified proteins, and as the exact conditions and requirements for this reaction, further studies will be necessary for the complete reconstitution of 2-thiouridine in eukaryote. <fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Reconstitution of 2-thiouridine formation <italic>in vitro</italic> using recombinant proteins. Thiouridine formation was detected by retardation of the tRNA band on the gel in the presence (lanes 1&#x02013;4) or absence (lanes 5&#x02013;8) of APM. 2-thiouridine formation of [<sup>32</sup>P]-labeled tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup> was carried out with recombinant proteins (Nfs1p, Tum1p, Uba4p and Urm1p) in the presence (lanes 1and 5) or absence (lanes 2 and 6) of IgG beads retaining the Ncs6p, or in the presence of IgG beads treated with wild-type cell lysate (lanes 4 and 8) as a negative control. The reaction was also performed only in the presence of IgG beads retaining the Ncs6p without recombinant proteins (lanes 3 and 7).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn1023f7"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Biogenesis of 5-methoxycarbonylmethyl-group is required for efficient 2-thiouridine formation</title><p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> MnmA and MnmE/GidA are RNA-modifying enzymes responsible for synthesizing 2-thio and 5-methylaminomethyl groups of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>). It is known that mnm<sup>5</sup>U and s<sup>2</sup>U are observed respectively observed in tRNAs from &#x00394;<italic>mnmA</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>mnmE</italic> (or &#x00394;<italic>gidA</italic>) strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>), indicating that 2-thiolation and C5-modification occurred independently. In the case of mitochondrial cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, we previously showed that 2-thio and cmnm<sup>5</sup> groups are modified independently (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). In this study, we have investigated whether, or not, 2-thio and 5-methoxycarbonylmethyl groups of cytoplasmic mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U are synthesized independently. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>A and B, mass spectrometry analyses revealed that mcm<sup>5</sup>U was clearly detected instead of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in a series of knockout strains, suggesting that lack of 2-thiouridine formation does never inhibit mcm<sup>5</sup>-modification. We employed APM/northern blotting to analyze the thiolation status of tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup> and tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> from a series of strains in which genes (<italic>ELP4</italic> and <italic>TRM9</italic>) responsible for mcm<sup>5</sup>-formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>) were knocked out. In tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> from &#x00394;<italic>ELP4</italic>, we observed a complete loss of mcm<sup>5</sup>-modification by LC/MS analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). Thus, <italic>ELP4</italic> is one of the genes responsible for the initial step of mcm<sup>5</sup>-formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>). In the APM/northern analysis, we could detect the small fraction of thiolated tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup> in the &#x00394;<italic>ELP4</italic> strain, but the large fraction remained nonthiolated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). In tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> from &#x00394;<italic>TRM9</italic>, we have identified 5-aminocarbonylmethyluridine (ncm<sup>5</sup>U) as a modification intermediate of mcm<sup>5</sup>U by mass spectrometry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>B). The thiolation status of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> was clearly increased as compared to that observed in &#x00394;<italic>ELP4</italic>, indicating that biosynthesis of the C5-substituent of the uracil ring promotes 2-thiouridine formation. However, the small fraction of non-thiolated tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> still existed in &#x00394;<italic>TRM9</italic> as compared to the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). These results demonstrated that mcm<sup>5</sup>-formation is required for efficient 2-thiouridine formation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>We here described identification of five genes responsible for 2-thiouridine formation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, through exploratory search of uncharacterized genes in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> by using &#x02018;ribonucleome analysis&#x02019;. Although there may still be, as yet uncharacterized, enzymes or proteins responsible for this modification, we have revealed a large portion of the mechanism involved in cytoplasmic 2-thiouridine formation in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. During the time we were revising this paper, Bystrom and co-workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>) published identification of the same subset of genes responsible for 2-thio modification by the genetic screen. Ploegh and co-workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>) published human Urm1 to be required for 2-thio modification. Our present study is completely independent from their studies.</p><p>Similar to bacterial 2-thiouridine formation, it was known that the cysteine desulfurase <italic>NFS1</italic> is involved in 2-thiolation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). However, since 2-thiolation in cytoplasmic tRNAs essentially requires a protein component with an Fe/S cluster, it was uncertain whether <italic>NFS1</italic> functions as a direct supplier of active sulfur to 2-thiouridine. We identified <italic>TUM1</italic> which contains tandem rhodanese-like domains (RLDs). Rhodanese is a widespread and versatile sulfur-carrier enzyme catalyzing the sulfur-transfer reaction in distinct metabolic and regulatory pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). An <italic>in vitro</italic> sulfur transfer reaction revealed that Tum1p stimulated Nfs1p and accepted a persulfide sulfur atom from Nfs1p (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>A). In addition, we have shown that Cys259 in RLD2 is responsible for efficient 2-thiouridine formation. RLD1 of Tum1p seems to be a catalytically inactive RLD, often found in various rhodanese-containing proteins, because it has no conserved cysteine residue. The result demonstrated that <italic>NFS1</italic> not only provides a sulfur atom to Fe/S cluster formation, but also directly supplies a sulfur atom to the formation of 2-thiouridine. Tum1p acts as an activator for the desulfurase of Nfs1p as well as a mediator of the persulfide from Nfs1p.</p><p>Although the large fraction of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> lacked 2-thio modification in &#x00394;<italic>TUM1</italic> strain, we found that the small fraction of tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> still contained mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>B, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>A and B). <italic>TUM1</italic> is not an essential protein for the biogenesis of 2-thiouridine, but it is required for efficient 2-thiouridine formation in the cell. This finding implies the presence of a minor sulfur flow pathway, capable of bypassing the Tum1p-mediated major pathway to 2-thiouridine formation. Since <italic>UBA4</italic> also has an RLD in the C-terminal region, we speculated that Uba4p functions as a minor sulfur mediator and accepts the persulfide sulfur directly from Nfs1p. In an <italic>in vitro</italic> sulfur transfer experiment, Uba4p accepted the sulfur from Nfs1p in the absence of Tum1p but did so inefficiently (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>B). In addition, it seemed that Uba4p did not activate the Nfs1p desulfurase. Thus, the direct transfer of sulfur from Nfs1p to Uba4p is a minor pathway in the biogenesis of 2-thiouridine. Very recently, it has been reported that the C-terminal RLD of Uba4p has an <italic>in vitro</italic> sulfur transfer activity from thiosulfate to cyanide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). This result is completely consistent with our observations. Although sulfur transfer from Nfs1p to Uba4p is a minor pathway, Cys397 in the RLD of Uba4p was found to be essential for 2-thiouridine formation. Taken together with the role of Tum1p, we speculate that the persulfide sulfur of Nfs1p is mainly transferred to the RLD2 (Cys259) of Tum1p, and the sulfur is then relayed to the RLD (Cys397) of Uba4p. In addition, direct sulfur transfer from Nfs1p to the RLD (Cys397) of Uba4p also takes place as a minor pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). <fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Comparison of cellular sulfur trafficking related to thiouridine formation of tRNA anticodon in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic>. (A) Proposed sulfur flow system for 2-thiouridine formation of mcm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. Nfs1p accepts sulfur from Cys to form a persulfide using PLP as a cofactor. The persulfide sulfur is mainly transferred to the RLD2 (Cys259) of Tum1p, and partially to the RLD (Cys397) of Uba4p. Uba4p, as an E1-like enzyme in the ubiquitin-related pathway, activates the C-terminus of Urm1p to form the acyl-adenylated intermediate, then transfers the persulfide sulfur from the RLD to form thiocarboxylated Urm1p (Urm1p-COSH) by releasing AMP. Urm1p-COSH is a substrate of 2-thiouridine formation catalyzed by Ncs2p and Ncs6p. For protein urmylation, Urm1p-COSH is conjugated with Uba4p, then the putative E3 enzyme transfers Urm1p to target proteins such as Ahp1p. (B) Sulfur-relay system by Tus-proteins in <italic>E. coli</italic>. IscS accepts sulfur from Cys to form a persulfide using PLP as a cofactor. TusA interacts with IscS to stimulate its desulfurase activity, and accepts the persulfide sulfur. The sulfur is transferred to TusD in the TusBCD complex. It is then transferred to TusE. TusE interacts with MnmA to transfer the sulfur. MnmA recognizes the tRNA and activates the wobble uridine by forming an adenylated intermediate, then the persulfide sulfur attacks this position to release the AMP resulting in the synthesis of the 2-thiouridine of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkn1023f8"/></fig></p><p>Ubiquitin and ubiquitin-related modifiers (Ubls) are involved in various biological processes through conjugation of target proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>). As the first step of ubiquitination, the C-terminal glycine of Ubl is activated by the activating enzyme (E1) to form an acyl-adenylate intermediate, which is then transferred to an active-site cysteine residue of the E1 enzyme via a thioester-linkage. <italic>URM1</italic> is a ubiquitin-related modifier, and <italic>UBA4</italic> is an E1-like enzyme of <italic>URM1</italic> involved in protein urmylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). In this study we have demonstrated that Uba4p first activates the C-terminus of Urm1p as an acyl-adenylated form by employing ATP, then converts the C-terminal acyl-adenylate (Urm1p-COAMP) to the thiocarboxylate (Urm1p-COSH) by replacing AMP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). Moreover, the <italic>in vitro</italic> sulfur transfer experiment revealed that the labeled sulfur of [<sup>35</sup>S] cysteine was actually transferred to the thiocarboxylated C-terminus of Urm1p via the catalytic functions of Nfs1p, Tum1p and Uba4p (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A and B).</p><p>Although there may still be missing proteins needed for the formation of 2-thiouridine, we were able to partially reconstitute 2-thiouridine formation of tRNA<sup>Lys2</sup>, <italic>in vitro</italic>, with recombinant Nfs1p, Tum1p, Urm1p, Uba4p and TAP-tagged Ncs6p, which was pulled down with IgG beads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). It is possible that Ncs2p may be co-precipitated with Ncs6p, as Ctu1/Ncs6p is complexed with Ctu2/Ncs2p in fission yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>). The thiocarboxylate at the C-terminus of Urm1p might be utilized in the subsequent reactions mediated by Ncs2p/Ncs6p. <italic>NCS6</italic>/<italic>CTU-1</italic>/<italic>TUC1</italic> is a homolog of bacterial <italic>ttcA</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>), which is required for the biogenesis of 2-thiocytidine (s<sup>2</sup>C) at position 32 of bacterial tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>). <italic>NCS6</italic> and <italic>ttcA</italic> share a PP-loop motif (SGGxDS) in the N-terminal region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). The PP-loop is a catalytic motif of N-type ATP pyrophosphatases including TilS involved in lysidine formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>), MnmA for bacterial s<sup>2</sup>U formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>) and ThiI for s<sup>4</sup>U formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>). These RNA-modifying enzymes commonly activate the target positions of pyrimidine bases by forming acyl-adenylate intermediates, which are then converted to their respective modifications. Although there is no evidence that TtcA catalyzes s<sup>2</sup>C formation, it is likely that s<sup>2</sup>C can be synthesized through similar chemical reactions with other RNA modifications generated by PP-loop containing enzymes. To characterize the final step of 2-thiouridine formation, it will be necessary to generate a recombinant Ncs6p/Ncs2p complex. We still neither know which protein receives the thiocarboxylate from Urm1p nor how the Ncs6p/Ncs2p complex recognizes the tRNA and catalyzes 2-thiouridine formation. Since we have shown that biogenesis of the mcm<sup>5</sup>-group of the wobble base is required for efficient formation of 2-thiouridine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C), it is possible that the Ncs6p/Ncs2p complex might recognize the C5 substituent of uracil base.</p><p>Where does 2-thiouridine formation take place in the cell? Nfs1p is mainly localized in mitochondria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60 B61 B62">60&#x02013;62</xref>). According to a high-throughput search on the subcellular localization of yeast proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63 B64 B65">63&#x02013;65</xref>), Tum1p is localized in mitochondria and cytoplasm. Thus, Tum1p might interact with Nfs1p and accept a persulfide sulfur in mitochondria. It is assumed that Tum1p is then exported to the cytoplasm where Uba4p relays the activated sulfur from Tum1p. Given this perspective, Tum1p could be a shuttling protein between the cytoplasm and mitochondria. Urm1p is thiocarboxylated by Uba4p in the cytoplasm. The subsequent 2-thiouridine formation of tRNAs, mediated by Ncs2p/Ncs6p, also takes place in the cytoplasm.</p><p><italic>URM1</italic> and <italic>UBA4</italic> show strong similarities to bacterial proteins responsible for the biogenesis of sulfur-containing cofactors. In <italic>E. coli</italic>, MoaD and MoeB, which are homologous to <italic>URM1</italic> and <italic>UBA4</italic> respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B and C), are involved in molybdopterin biogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>). The C-terminus of MoaD is first activated as an acyl-adenylated form (MoaD-COAMP) by its E1-like enzyme MoeB. The acyl-adenylated C-terminus of MoaD is then converted to thiocarboxylated MoaD (MoaD-COSH) through the action of MoeB and cysteine desulfurases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>). In the case of thiamine biogenesis in <italic>E. coli</italic>, ThiS and ThiF, which are homologous to <italic>URM1</italic> and <italic>UBA4</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B and C), undergo the same chemical reactions to generate a thiocarboxylated form of ThiS (ThiS-COSH), which is then used as a substrate for thiamine biogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>). In this reaction, it is known that the RLD-containing protein ThiI accepts a persulfide sulfur from IscS, then transfers the sulfur for thiocarboxylate formation to the C-terminus of ThiS which is catalyzed by ThiF. ThiI has another function as an RNA-modifying enzyme as it is involved in the synthesis of 4-thiouridine at position 8 of tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>). Human <italic>MOCS2A</italic> is a paralog of human <italic>URM1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C). Human ortholog of <italic>UBA4</italic> is <italic>MOCS3</italic> which is an E1-like enzyme for <italic>MOCS2A</italic> as well as <italic>URM1</italic>. <italic>MOCS2A</italic> and <italic>MOCS3</italic> encode proteins required for molybdopterin biogenesis in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>). Although a system of molybdopterin biogenesis is well conserved in eukaryotes, <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> is one of the rare organisms that has lost molybdopterin biogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). Thus, <italic>URM1</italic> and <italic>UBA4</italic> are only involved in protein urmylation and 2-thiouridine formation in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. With respect to thiamine biogenesis, the yeast functional homolog of ThiF is <italic>THI4</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>) which is a different gene from <italic>UBA4</italic>. To confirm whether <italic>URM1</italic> and <italic>UBA4</italic> are involved in thiamine biogenesis in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, we tested the requirement of thiamine for normal growth of &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> strains. When we inoculated &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> strains, together with a &#x00394;<italic>THI4</italic> strain as a control on thiamine-deficient plates, normal growth of &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> strains was observed, while no growth of &#x00394;<italic>THI4</italic> strain was observed as expected (data not shown). This result is consistent with the previous observation that temperature sensitivity of &#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic> was not suppressed by thiamine addition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>). These data revealed that thiamine biogenesis in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> is a distinct pathway from the <italic>URM1</italic>/<italic>UBA4</italic>-mediated pathway.</p><p>According to sequence alignment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B), <italic>UBA4</italic> along with other eukaryotic homologs contain a C-terminal RLD with a conserved cysteine residue, whereas <italic>E. coli</italic> MoeB and ThiF lack a C-terminal RLD. We have shown in this study that Cys397 in the RLD of Uba4p plays an essential role in s<sup>2</sup>U formation. Moreover, a recent study on molybdopterin biogenesis clearly reported that Nfs1p specifically interacts with the RLD of human <italic>MOCS3</italic> and transfers the persulfide sulfur to this domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>). These facts reveal a mechanistic difference between cytoplasmic s<sup>2</sup>U formation and bacterial cofactor biogenesis; namely, Uba4p utilizes its own RLD as a sulfur carrier for generating Urm1p-COSH, while ThiF uses the rhodanese-containing protein ThiI as a sulfur carrier for generating ThiS-COSH. Even if Tum1p is assumed to be a functional homolog of ThiI, the RLD of Uba4p is essential for cytoplasmic s<sup>2</sup>U formation.</p><p>It was reported that the loss of <italic>URM1</italic> together with the loss of <italic>CLA4</italic>, a p21-activated kinase required for the budding process resulted in a synthetic lethal phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>). The loss of <italic>URM1</italic> resulted in deficient invasive growth and rapamycin sensitivity, indicating that the urmylation pathway has a genetic interaction with the TOR pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). In addition, it has been reported that the urmylation pathway regulates the expression of genes involved in sensing and controlling amino acids levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). Thus, the urmylation pathway has been implicated in budding and nutrient sensing. It is known that Urm1p conjugates with a number of proteins in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. Ahp1p was identified as the first <italic>in vivo</italic> target of urmylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Ahp1p is a peroxiredoxin, an antioxidant protein, that eliminates alkyl peroxide or thiol oxidant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>). Loss of the urmylation pathway (&#x00394;<italic>URM1</italic> and &#x00394;<italic>UBA4</italic>) results in sensitivity to a thiol-specific oxidant, as does the loss of <italic>AHP1</italic>, indicating that the urmylation pathway has a possible link with an oxidative stress response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). In this study, we have shown that the urmylation pathway is shared with the biogenesis of s<sup>2</sup>U. Lack of 2-thiouridine in the tRNA anticodon modulates the decoding activity of NNR codons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). tRNAs bearing hypomodified wobble bases may affect the global translation profile (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>). Therefore, various cellular responses related to loss of the urmylation pathway can be explained, not only by protein modification, but also by the lack of 2-thiouridine formation of tRNA anticodon. Futher studies will be required to reveal both sides of the urmylation pathway in various cellular functions.</p><p>In <italic>E. coli</italic>, we have previously shown that the sulfur-relay system mediated by Tus-proteins is required for 2-thiouridine formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>B). IscS initially accepts a persulfide sulfur from cysteine. TusA then interacts with IscS to stimulate its desulfurase activity, and accepts the persulfide sulfur. The sulfur is transferred to TusD in the TusBCD complex, then to TusE. TusE interacts with MnmA to transfer the sulfur. MnmA recognizes the tRNA and facilitates the 2-thiouridine synthesis of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U using the persulfide sulfur. Thus, the sulfur flow system in <italic>E. coli</italic> is based on persulfide chemistry. In <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, Tum1p is a functional homolog of TusA in <italic>E. coli</italic>. However, the subsequent sulfur-relay system in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> is completely distinct from the bacterial sulfur-relay system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>A). The most striking aspect in eukaryotic 2-thiouridine formation is that the activated sulfur is further relayed by the protein conjugation system of a ubiquitin-related modifier. A similar system of sulfur-flow can be found in some thermophilic bacteria. In <italic>Thermus thermophilus</italic>, 2-thiolated ribothymidine (s<sup>2</sup>T) can be found at position 54 in the T-loop of tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>). It is known that s<sup>2</sup>T54 confers tRNA stability at higher temperatures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>). Shigi <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>) identified three genes from <italic>T. thermophilus</italic>, named <italic>ttuA</italic>, <italic>ttuB</italic> and <italic>ttuC</italic>, which are responsible for 2-thiouridine formation of s<sup>2</sup>T54 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>). <italic>ttuA</italic> is a homologous protein of <italic>E. coli ttcA</italic> and <italic>NCS6</italic>, indicating that s<sup>2</sup>T formation in these organisms occurs through a similar mechanism to that found in eubacterial s<sup>2</sup>C formation and eukaryotic 2-thiouridine formation. In addition, <italic>ttuB</italic> and <italic>ttuC</italic> are homologous to <italic>URM1</italic> and <italic>UBA4</italic>, respectively. In fact, the C-terminal glycine of TtuB was shown to be acyl-adenylated, then thiocarboxylated by TtuC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>). The activated sulfur atom of the thiocarboxylate is further transferred to tRNA by the action of TtuA. Therefore, sulfur flow systems for 2-thiouridine formation are diversified in various living organisms.</p></sec><sec><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkn1023/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p></sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p>The Ministry of Education, Science, Sports, and Culture of Japan (MEXT) (to T.S.); a JSPS Fellowship for Japanese Junior Scientists (to A.N.); and a grant from the New Energy and Industrial Technology Development Organization (NEDO) (to T.S.). Funding for open access charge: MEXT.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>[Supplementary Data]</title></caption><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="gkn1023_index.html"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="gkn1023_nar-02364-w-2008-File010.jpg"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We are grateful to the Suzuki lab members, especially to Takeo Suzuki, K. Miyauchi, Y. Ikeuchi and Y. Kirino for technical assistance and fruitful discussions. We also thank to N. Shigi (AIST) for critical comments and suggestions. Special thanks are due to Dr. R. Lill (Univ of Marburg) for providing us with a plasmid for Nfs1p expression.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rozenski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RNA modification database: 1999 update</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847178</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bjork</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>S&#x000f6;ll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>RajBhandary</surname><given-names>UL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis and function of modified nucleosides</article-title><source>tRNA: Structure, Biosynthesis and Function.</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>205</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Benne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modified nucleosides in translation</article-title><source>Modification and Editing of RNA: The Alteration of RNA Structure and Function.</source><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>516</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis and function of tRNA wobble modifications</article-title><source>Fine-Tuning of RNA Functions by Modification and Editing</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>69</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaizumi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanism of codon recognition by tRNA species with modified uridine in the first position of the anticodon</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1985</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>4905</fpage><lpage>4909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3860833</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agris</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Soll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Seno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological function of 2-thiouridine in Escherichia coli glutamic acid transfer ribonucleic acid</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1973</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>4331</fpage><lpage>4337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4584321</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sochacka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Guenther</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Malkiewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Agris</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single atom modification (O&#x02013;&#x0003e;S) of tRNA confers ribosome binding</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>1999</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10024171</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sylvers</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtsuka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Soll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 2-thiouridine derivative in tRNAGlu is a positive determinant for aminoacylation by Escherichia coli glutamyl-tRNA synthetase</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1993</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>3836</fpage><lpage>3841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8385989</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yasukawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defect in modification at the anticodon wobble nucleotide of mitochondrial tRNA(Lys) with the MERRF encephalomyopathy pathogenic mutation</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>2000</year><volume>467</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10675533</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yasukawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wobble modification defect in tRNA disturbs codon-anticodon interaction in a mitochondrial disease</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>4794</fpage><lpage>4802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11532943</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trafficking in persulfides: delivering sulfur in biosynthetic pathways</article-title><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16547481</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marquet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzymology of carbon-sulfur bond formation</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11578927</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lauhon</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orchestrating sulfur incorporation into RNA</article-title><source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16547479</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhlenhoff</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maturation of iron-sulfur proteins in eukaryotes: mechanisms, connected processes, and diseases</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18366324</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frazzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation of iron-sulfur clusters in bacteria: an emerging field in bioinorganic chemistry</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12714048</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lauhon</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Requirement for IscS in biosynthesis of all thionucleosides in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>6820</fpage><lpage>6829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12446632</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagervall</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjork</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cysteine desulfurase IscS is required for synthesis of all five thiolated nucleosides present in tRNA from Salmonella enterica serovar typhimurium</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>6830</fpage><lpage>6835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12446633</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanistic insights into sulfur relay by multiple sulfur mediators involved in thiouridine biosynthesis at tRNA wobble positions</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387657</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Numata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nureki</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Snapshots of tRNA sulphuration via an adenylated intermediate</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>442</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16871210</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Umeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagamiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast Nfs1p is involved in thio-modification of both mitochondrial and cytoplasmic tRNAs</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>12363</fpage><lpage>12368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14722066</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thio modification of yeast cytosolic tRNA is an iron-sulfur protein-dependent pathway</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2841</fpage><lpage>2847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17283054</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yukawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shindo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondria-specific RNA-modifying enzymes responsible for the biosynthesis of the wobble base in mitochondrial tRNAs. Implications for the molecular pathogenesis of human mitochondrial diseases</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>1613</fpage><lpage>1624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15509579</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bjork</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bystrom</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A conserved modified wobble nucleoside (mcm5s2U) in lysyl-tRNA is required for viability in yeast</article-title><source>RNA.</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17592039</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dewez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dieu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenhaute</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The conserved Wobble uridine tRNA thiolase Ctu1-Ctu2 is required to maintain genome integrity</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>5459</fpage><lpage>5464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18391219</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of wybutosine, a hyper-modified nucleoside in eukaryotic phenylalanine tRNA</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2142</fpage><lpage>2154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16642040</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Noma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mass spectrometric identification and characterization of RNA-modifying enzymes</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>425</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17673085</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanemasa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ote</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekine</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An RNA-modifying enzyme that governs both the codon and amino acid specificities of isoleucine tRNA</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527414</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitahara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RNA acetyltransferase driven by ATP hydrolysis synthesizes N4-acetylcytidine of tRNA anticodon</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2194</fpage><lpage>2203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18668122</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muhlenhoff</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Richhardt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of iron-sulfur protein assembly in isolated mitochondria. A requirement for ATP, NADH, and reduced iron</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>29810</fpage><lpage>29816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12065597</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapushoc</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghazvini</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wobble modification differences and subcellular localization of tRNAs in Leishmania tarentolae: implication for tRNA sorting mechanism</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12554666</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chaplet column chromatography: isolation of a large set of individual RNAs in a single step</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>425</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17673086</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyauchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated parallel isolation of multiple species of non-coding RNAs by the reciprocal circulating chromatography method</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>e24</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17251194</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Igloi</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of tRNAs and of phosphorothioate-substituted nucleic acids with an organomercurial. Probing the chemical environment of thiolated residues by affinity electrophoresis</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1988</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>3842</fpage><lpage>3849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3044450</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guldener</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Munsterkotter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kastenmuller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>van Helden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Richelles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wodak</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Martinez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Ortin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CYGD: the Comprehensive Yeast Genome Database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>D364</fpage><lpage>D368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608217</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goehring</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivers</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Urmylation: a ubiquitin-like pathway that functions during invasive growth and budding in yeast</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>4329</fpage><lpage>4341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14551258</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goehring</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivers</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Attachment of the ubiquitin-related protein Urm1p to the antioxidant protein Ahp1p</article-title><source>Eukaryot. Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>930</fpage><lpage>936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14555475</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubio-Texeira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urmylation controls Nil1p and Gln3p-dependent expression of nitrogen-catabolite repressed genes in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>2007</year><volume>581</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17254574</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohsumi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A protein conjugation system in yeast with homology to biosynthetic enzyme reaction of prokaryotes</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>7462</fpage><lpage>7465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10713047</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thio modification of yeast cytosolic tRNA requires a ubiquitin-related system that resembles bacterial sulfur transfer systems</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>27469</fpage><lpage>27476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18664566</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bordo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rhodanese/Cdc25 phosphatase superfamily. Sequence-structure-function relations</article-title><source>EMBO Rep.</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12151332</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanzelmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimtz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Schindelin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leimkuhler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The sulfurtransferase activity of Uba4 presents a link between ubiquitin-like protein conjugation and activation of sulfur carrier proteins</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>6479</fpage><lpage>6489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18491921</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerscher</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Felberbaum</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochstrasser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modification of proteins by ubiquitin and ubiquitin-like proteins</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16753028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinsland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Backstrom</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>McLafferty</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thiamin biosynthesis in Escherichia coli. Identification of this thiocarboxylate as the immediate sulfur donor in the thiazole formation</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>16555</fpage><lpage>16560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632726</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutzke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendel</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thiocarboxylation of molybdopterin synthase provides evidence for the mechanism of dithiolene formation in metal-binding pterins</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>36268</fpage><lpage>36274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459846</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwienhorst</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohmen</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blobel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ubiquitin-like protein Smt3p is activated for conjugation to other proteins by an Aos1p/Uba2p heterodimer</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>5509</fpage><lpage>5519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9312010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liakopoulos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Doenges</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Matuschewski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jentsch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel protein modification pathway related to the ubiquitin system</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2208</fpage><lpage>2214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9545234</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanida</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyooka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohsumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohsumi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kominami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apg7p/Cvt2p: A novel protein-activating enzyme essential for autophagy</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10233150</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kambampati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauhon</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MnmA and IscS are required for in vitro 2-thiouridine biosynthesis in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1109</fpage><lpage>1117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12549933</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elseviers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrullo</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel <italic>E. coli</italic> mutants deficient in biosynthesis of 5-methylaminomethyl-2-thiouridine</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1984</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3521</fpage><lpage>3534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6427754</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagervall</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced misreading of asparagine codons by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> tRNALys with hypomodified derivatives of 5-methylaminomethyl-2-thiouridine in the wobble position</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9811540</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bystrom</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An early step in wobble uridine tRNA modification requires the Elongator complex</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15769872</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalhor</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel methyltransferase for modified uridine residues at the wobble position of tRNA</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>9283</fpage><lpage>9292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14645538</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bystrom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide screen identifies genes required for formation of the wobble nucleoside 5-methoxycarbonylmethyl-2-thiouridine in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2183</fpage><lpage>2194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18755837</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlieker</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Veen</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Damon</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Spooner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ploegh</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A functional proteomics approach links the ubiquitin-related modifier Urm1 to a tRNA modification pathway</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>18255</fpage><lpage>18260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017811</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochstrasser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution and function of ubiquitin-like protein-conjugation systems</article-title><source>Nat. Cell Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>E153</fpage><lpage>E157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10934491</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pickart</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms underlying ubiquitination</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><year>2001</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11395416</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Leipuviene</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjork</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The conserved Cys-X1-X2-Cys motif present in the TtcA protein is required for the thiolation of cytidine in position 32 of tRNA from Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium</article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14729701</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Soma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ote</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekine</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechamism of lysidine synthesis that determines tRNA identity and codon recognition</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16039592</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kambampati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauhon</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for the transfer of sulfane sulfur from IscS to ThiI during the in vitro biosynthesis of 4-thiouridine in Escherichia coli tRNA</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>10727</fpage><lpage>10730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10753862</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kispal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Csere</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Prohl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mitochondrial proteins Atm1p and Nfs1p are essential for biogenesis of cytosolic Fe/S proteins</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3981</fpage><lpage>3989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10406803</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kogan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pain</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dancis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Yeast mitochondrial protein, Nfs1p, coordinately regulates iron-sulfur cluster proteins, cellular iron uptake, and iron distribution</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>33025</fpage><lpage>33034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10551871</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagamiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cDNA cloning and characterization of mouse nifS-like protein, m-Nfs1: mitochondrial localization of eukaryotic NifS-like proteins</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1998</year><volume>433</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9738949</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heidtman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Piccirillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Umansky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Drawid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subcellular localization of the yeast proteome</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11914276</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Falvo</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerke</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Shea</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of protein localization in budding yeast</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>425</volume><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14562095</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sickmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinders</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Joppich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahedi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schonfisch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Perschil</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chacinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The proteome of Saccharomyces cerevisiae mitochondria</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>13207</fpage><lpage>13212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576278</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajagopalan</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis and processing of the molybdenum cofactors</article-title><source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9388540</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leimkuhler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuebbens</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajagopalan</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of Escherichia coli MoeB and its involvement in the activation of molybdopterin synthase for the biosynthesis of the molybdenum cofactor</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>34695</fpage><lpage>34701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11463785</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leimkuhler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajagopalan</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sulfurtransferase is required in the transfer of cysteine sulfur in the in vitro synthesis of molybdopterin from precursor Z in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>22024</fpage><lpage>22031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11290749</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyavaiah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rooney</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>DiRenzo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Conklin</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zitomer</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Begley</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trm9-catalyzed tRNA modifications link translation to the DNA damage response</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18082610</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palenchar</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence that ThiI, an enzyme shared between thiamin and 4-thiouridine biosynthesis, may be a sulfurtransferase that proceeds through a persulfide intermediate</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>8283</fpage><lpage>8286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10722656</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krepinsky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Leimkuhler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Site-directed mutagenesis of the active site loop of the rhodanese-like domain of the human molybdopterin synthase sulfurase MOCS3. Major differences in substrate specificity between eukaryotic and bacterial homologs</article-title><source>FEBS J.</source><year>2007</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>2778</fpage><lpage>2787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17459099</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leimkuhler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Freuer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajagopalan</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendel</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanistic studies of human molybdopterin synthase reaction and characterization of mutants identified in group B patients of molybdenum cofactor deficiency</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>26127</fpage><lpage>26134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12732628</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Praekelt</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Meacock</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of THI4 (MOL1), a thiamine-biosynthetic gene of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1994</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7941734</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marelja</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Stocklein</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimtz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leimkuhler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel role for human Nfs1 in the cytoplasm: Nfs1 acts as a sulfur donor for MOCS3, a protein involved in molybdenum cofactor biosynthesis</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>25178</fpage><lpage>25185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18650437</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goehring</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Keniry</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Synthetic lethal analysis implicates Ste20p, a p21-activated potein kinase, in polarisome activation</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1501</fpage><lpage>1516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12686605</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of a second type thioredoxin peroxidase (type II TPx) from Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>776</fpage><lpage>783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9888818</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct physiological functions of thiol peroxidase isoenzymes in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>5723</fpage><lpage>5732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10681558</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saneyoshi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replacement of ribothymidine by 5-methyl-2-thiouridine in sequence GT psi C in tRNA of an extreme thermophile</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1974</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4369142</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic structures and functions of transfer ribonucleic acids from extreme thermophiles</article-title><source>Adv. Biophys.</source><year>1987</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2449804</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shigi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of two tRNA thiolation genes required for cell growth at extremely high temperatures</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>14296</fpage><lpage>14306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16547008</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shigi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Common thiolation mechanism in the biosynthesis of tRNA thiouridine and sulphur-containing cofactors</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>3267</fpage><lpage>3278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19037260</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Plewniak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeanmougin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The CLUSTAL_X windows interface: flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>4876</fpage><lpage>4882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9396791</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 