<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><?properties open_access?><?properties no_embargo?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ern332</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Allantoate amidohydrolase transcript expression is independent of drought tolerance in soybean</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>Dirk V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Korth</surname><given-names>Kenneth L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>Larry C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Crop, Soil, and Environmental Sciences, University of Arkansas, 1366 West Altheimer Drive, Fayetteville, Arkansas 72704-6898, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Plant Pathology, University of Arkansas, 217 Plant Sciences, Fayetteville, Arkansas 72701,USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed: E-mail: <email>lpurcell@uark.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>847</fpage><lpage>851</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2009 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><p>This paper is available online free of all access charges (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html">http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html</ext-link> for further details)</p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Drought is a limiting factor for N<sub>2</sub> fixation in soybean [<italic>Glycine max</italic> (L.) Merr.] thereby resulting in reduced biomass accumulation and yield. Drought-sensitive genotypes accumulate ureides, a product of N<sub>2</sub> fixation, during drought stress; however, drought-tolerant genotypes have lower shoot ureide concentrations, which appear to alleviate drought stress on N<sub>2</sub> fixation. A key enzyme involved in ureide breakdown in shoots is allantoate amidohydrolase (AAH). It is hypothesized that <italic>AAH</italic> gene expression in soybean determines shoot ureide concentrations during water-deficit stress and is responsible for the differential sensitivities of the N<sub>2</sub>-fixation response to drought among soybean genotypes. The objectives were to examine the relationship between <italic>AAH</italic> transcript levels and shoot ureide concentration and drought tolerance. Drought-tolerant (Jackson) and drought-sensitive (Williams) genotypes were subjected to three water-availability treatments: well-watered control, moderate water-deficit stress, and severe water-deficit stress. Shoot ureide concentrations were examined, in addition to gene expression of <italic>AAH</italic> and <italic>DREB2</italic>, a gene expressed during water-deficit stress. As expected, <italic>DREB2</italic> expression was detected only during severe water-deficit stress, and shoot ureide concentrations were greatest in the drought-sensitive genotype relative to the drought-tolerant genotype during water-deficit stress. However, expression of <italic>AAH</italic> transcripts was similar among water treatments and genotypes, indicating that <italic>AAH</italic> mRNA was not closely associated with drought tolerance. Ureide concentrations in shoots were weakly associated with <italic>AAH</italic> mRNA levels. These results indicate that <italic>AAH</italic> expression is probably not associated with the increased ureide catabolism observed in drought-tolerant genotypes, such as Jackson. Further study of <italic>AAH</italic> at the post-translational and enzymatic levels is warranted in order to dissect the potential role of this gene in drought tolerance.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Allantoate amidohydrolase</kwd><kwd>drought</kwd><kwd><italic>Glycine max</italic></kwd><kwd>manganese</kwd><kwd>nitrogen fixation</kwd><kwd>soybean</kwd><kwd>ureides</kwd><kwd>water-deficit stress</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Drought is often a yield constraint for crops worldwide. A major benefit of producing soybean [<italic>Glycine max</italic> (L.) Merr.] is that it grows symbiotically with <italic>Bradyrhizobium japonicum</italic> and reduces (fixes) atmospheric nitrogen to nitrogen-compounds that the plant can utilize without the need for expensive nitrogen fertilizer. However, N<sub>2</sub> fixation is sensitive to water-deficit stress thereby reducing the plant's ability to fix and utilize nitrogen for biomass accumulation and seed production (see reviews by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Serraj <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Purcell and Specht, 2004</xref>).</p><p>Although N<sub>2</sub> fixation decreases during drought, the products of N<sub>2</sub> fixation, ureides (allantoin and allantoate), increase in leaves of drought-sensitive soybean genotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">King and Purcell, 2001</xref>). Experiments have shown that increases in shoot ureide concentration are associated with the inhibition of N<sub>2</sub> fixation in the nodules and, subsequently, drought sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Purcell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Drought-sensitive N<sub>2</sub>-fixation genotypes subjected to water-deficit stress (i.e. Williams, Biloxi, and KS4895) exhibit a reduction in nitrogenase activity, a decrease in ureide degradation, and an increase in shoot ureide concentrations relative to Jackson, a genotype with drought-tolerant N<sub>2</sub>-fixation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Purcell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Vadez and Sinclair, 2001</xref>). Therefore, lower ureide concentrations in leaves during water-deficit stress appears to prolong N<sub>2</sub> fixation and thereby to confer drought tolerance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Purcell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">King and Purcell, 2005</xref>). In addition, physiological studies have shown that increases in Mn<sup>2+</sup> availability to the plant during water-deficit stress increases ureide degradation in leaves and prolongs N<sub>2</sub> fixation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Purcell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Vadez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). An enzyme responsible for allantoate breakdown, allantoate amidohydrolase (<italic>AAH</italic>; EC 3.5.3.9), requires Mn<sup>2+</sup> as a co-factor for activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Lukaszewski <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Werner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>) and this enzyme has greater activity in Jackson than in the drought-sensitive genotype KS4895 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Purcell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Therefore, <italic>AAH</italic> is a likely candidate for an important role conferring drought tolerance in soybean.</p><p>Allantoate amidohydrolase is important in purine salvage, and is found in many plant species that do not fix nitrogen. This gene was first cloned from plants using the model organism <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Todd and Polacco (2006)</xref> demonstrated the functional complementation of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene in a yeast strain unable to utilize ureides. The yeast strain transformed with <italic>AtAAH</italic> was able to utilize allantoin as the sole nitrogen source, whereas the untransformed mutant yeast strain grew poorly in the presence of allantoin. Furthermore, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Todd and Polacco (2006)</xref> showed that an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutant lacking the functional <italic>AAH</italic> was not able to breakdown ureides. Recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Werner <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> cloned the soybean homologue of <italic>AAH</italic>. They demonstrated that the AAH protein is involved in allantoate catabolism <italic>in vivo</italic> and that Mn<sup>2+</sup> is required for optimal activity.</p><p>It is hypothesized that <italic>AAH</italic> gene expression in soybean determines the shoot ureide concentrations during water-deficit stress and is responsible for the differential sensitivities of the N<sub>2</sub>-fixation response to drought among soybean genotypes. From this hypothesis, it is predicted that <italic>AAH</italic> mRNA levels in shoots are (i) higher in drought-tolerant versus drought-sensitive soybean genotypes, (ii) differentially expressed in response to water-deficit stress, and (iii) inversely correlated with shoot ureide concentrations. Therefore, the objectives were to examine <italic>AAH</italic> mRNA levels and ureide concentrations in shoots during well-watered and water-deficit stress for two soybean genotypes differing in drought tolerance.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Drought-tolerant (Jackson; PI 548657) and drought-sensitive (Williams; PI 548631) soybean genotypes were planted in 1.0 l volume pots containing 2 parts N-free peat-perlite-vermiculite mixture (LB2, Sungro Horticulture Inc., Bellevue, WA) to 1 part Captina silt loam (fine-silty, siliceous, mesic Typic Fragiudult) soil collected from the University of Arkansas Experiment Station near Fayetteville, AR. The soil was saturated with 1.0 l of a N-free nutrient solution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">deSilva <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>), drained overnight, and the soil water capacity determined as soil weight. One seed was planted per pot and soil inoculated with <italic>Bradyrhyizobium japonicum</italic> (strain USDA 110).</p><p>Growth chamber conditions included day/night temperature of 25/23 &#x000b0;C and a 16 h photoperiod beginning at 06.00 h with metal halide lamps providing approximately 300 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> photosynthetically active radiation at plant height. Plants were watered as needed for 30 d after emergence to maintain 70% soil water capacity (SWC). The experiment consisted of a 2&#x000d7;3 factorial with randomized complete block design with five blocks for Experiment One and 2 blocks for Experiment Two. Two genotypes (Jackson and Williams) were examined over three water treatments on the basis of SWC: well-watered at 70%; moderate water deficit at 50%, and severe water deficit at 30%. To reach each percentage SWC for simultaneous sampling, the soil was dried in several intervals. The first interval was to allow all pots, except for the 70% SWC treatment, to reach 50% SWC. During the second interval, water was added to maintain corresponding pots at 70% and 50% SWC, while the remaining pots were allowed to dry to 30% SWC. The entire drying period was 4 d.</p><p>At the V7 stage of development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Fehr and Caviness, 1977</xref>), fully expanded trifoliolate leaves at the fifth node were collected from each genotype, water treatment, and replication combination. Three 1 cm diameter leaf punches were collected and combined into one sample per leaf. The tissue was dried at 55 &#x000b0;C, and a 30 mg subsample was ground to pass a 1 mm sieve. Ureide concentration was determined using the colorimetric procedure of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Young and Conway (1942)</xref> as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">deSilva <italic>et al.</italic> (1996)</xref>.</p><p>RNA was collected from the remaining leaf tissue, frozen in liquid N<sub>2</sub>, and stored at &#x02013;80 &#x000b0;C before extraction. Total RNA was isolated from leaves using TriReagent (Molecular Research). Total RNA (15 &#x003bc;g) from each sample was separated on 1% agarose formaldehyde gels. The accumulation of transcripts by RNA-blot hybridization was measured using standard techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Sambrook <italic>et al.</italic>, 1989</xref>) and <sup>32</sup>P-labelled probes as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Gomez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p><p>Three probes were used for RNA-blot analysis. Probes for <italic>AAH</italic> and <italic>DREB2</italic> were obtained through a standard PCR procedure using gene-specific primers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Charlson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006). The <italic>AAH</italic> probe was amplified from Williams EST clone Gm-c1019-6420 (GenBank no. AW704657) using primer sequences 5&#x02032;-CACCACCACAACCACCATGTATTCTGCCAC-3&#x02032; (forward) and 5&#x02032;-ACAGTTACCATATCACTTATGATAGGTTTTCCAG-3&#x02032; (reverse) (See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/ern332/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). The soybean <italic>DREB2</italic> gene was used as a positive control to validate that plants were responding differentially to water availability at the transcript level of gene expression; <italic>DREB2</italic> was amplified from genomic DNA of Jackson. <italic>DREB2</italic> (GenBank No. DQ208968), primers were 5&#x02032;-ATGGAAGAAGCGGGTTTAGG-3&#x02032; (forward) and 5&#x02032;-ATCTTCAGGTTTGGGATACT-3&#x02032; (reverse) and amplified a 480 bp amplicon probe starting at the start codon (ATG) and ending near the stop codon (TAG). Probes were sequenced to confirm identity. Levels of gene expression were calculated as a ratio of <italic>AAH</italic> or <italic>DREB2</italic> to the 18S ribosomal RNA from rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.).</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The response of Jackson (drought-tolerant) and Williams (drought-sensitive) to water availability was as expected regarding ureide concentration between both experiments across water treatments. For well-watered and moderate-water stress, Jackson and Williams had similar ureide concentrations within an experiment: &#x0223c;10 &#x003bc;M and &#x0223c;50 &#x003bc;M mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dw for Experiments One and Two, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). As expected, Williams had a 2&#x02013;3-fold greater ureide concentration during severe-water stress relative to well-watered conditions, whereas Jackson showed very little increase in ureide concentrations during severe-water stress.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Shoot ureide concentrations versus water availability and cultivar. The experiment was conducted twice in a growth chamber. Drought-tolerant (Jackson) and drought-sensitive (Williams) soybean genotypes were subjected to three water-availability treatments: well-watered control (70% soil water capacity, SWC), moderate water-deficit stress (50% SWC), and severe (30% SWC) water-deficit stress. Data were averaged within treatment and cultivar for five replications in Experiment One (A) and two replications in Experiment Two (B). Bars indicate the standard error of the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern332f01_ht"/></fig><p>In addition to the observation of expected levels of ureides in water-stressed samples, expression patterns of a known drought-induced gene were also as anticipated. The <italic>DREB2</italic> gene encodes a transcription factor that binds to a drought-responsive element found in the promoters of many plant genes thought to be active in water-stress responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Sakuma <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Transcripts encoding <italic>DREB2</italic> are strongly induced in response to water stress in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Liu <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>) and soybean (Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006). Therefore, <italic>DREB2</italic> was a useful, positive control to validate that changes in gene expression resulting from water-deficit stress could be detected using our experimental approach. The transcript level of soybean <italic>DREB2</italic> was similar between genotypes and &#x0223c;2-fold greater at severe water-deficit stress compared with the control plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref>). The data support that ureide concentration for Jackson and Williams and <italic>DREB2</italic> responded to water availability as expected from previous research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Purcell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Vadez and Sinclair, 2001</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Northern blot analysis of allantoate amidohydrolase (<italic>AAH</italic>), <italic>DREB2</italic>, and 18S ribosomal RNAs. Gene expression between experiments was similar, therefore, only data from Experiment One are shown. RNA from five replications was combined at equal concentrations of 15 &#x003bc;g. The same membrane was exposed with all three probes independently. Gene expression was examined for drought-tolerant (Jackson) and drought-sensitive (Williams) soybean genotypes over three water availability treatments; well-watered control (70% soil water capacity, SWC), moderate water-deficit stress (50% SWC), and severe (30% SWC) water-deficit stress.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern332f02_ht"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Response of <italic>DREB2</italic> expression to severe water-deficit stress. Gene expression between experiments was similar, therefore, only data from Experiment One are shown. Gene expression was examined for drought-tolerant (Jackson) and drought-sensitive (Williams) soybean genotypes over three water-availability treatments; well-watered control (70% soil water capacity, SWC), moderate water-deficit stress (50% SWC), and severe (30% SWC) water-deficit stress. Data were standardized over treatments for comparison by comparing all treatments to <italic>DREB2</italic> expression for Williams at well-watered conditions. Relative expression for Jackson at 70% SWC was 1.1, therefore values are only shown for the moderate and severe water-deficit stress treatments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern332f03_ht"/></fig><p>Although ureide concentrations were lower for Jackson relative to Williams (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>), <italic>AAH</italic> transcript levels were similar between the drought-tolerant and drought-sensitive soybean genotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). In addition, and contrary to the observation of shoot ureide concentrations differing among water-deficit treatments, <italic>AAH</italic> transcript levels remained stable regardless of water-deficit stress (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). Furthermore, the <italic>GmAAH</italic> probe was gene specific, as indicated by the detection of only one band from Southern blot analysis (data not shown). Therefore, the disparity between transcript expression and ureide concentration may not be accounted for by a cross-hybridization of the probe with the expression of one or more homologous genes during Northern blot analysis.</p><p>Since AAH breaks down allantoate, a ureide, to a non-ureide (ureidoglycolate), we expected to observe <italic>AAH</italic> transcript levels increasing with a concurrent decrease in shoot ureide concentrations. Linear regression analysis indicated that the response of ureide concentration to <italic>AAH</italic> expression was significant (<italic>P</italic>=0.02), however, the relationship was weak (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>=0.15) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Regression of <italic>AAH</italic> expression to shoot ureide concentrations. Each point represents an experimental unit from two independent experiments. Data collected from Jackson and Williams subjected to three water-availability treatments from well-watered control to severe water-deficit stress.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexbotern332f04_lw"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Soybean genotypes with drought tolerance have lesser shoot ureide concentrations relative to drought-sensitive genotypes during water-deficit stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">King and Purcell, 2001</xref>), and AAH is involved in ureide breakdown in shoots. Therefore, the role of <italic>AAH</italic> transcript expression relative to the drought-tolerance trait and ureide concentration in shoots was examined. The results of this study indicated that mRNA levels of <italic>AAH</italic> were weakly associated with shoot ureide concentration and independent of soybean response to water-deficit stress or the drought-tolerance trait in soybean. These data indicate that either <italic>AAH</italic> does not play a role in drought tolerance or post-translational regulation is involved in AAH activity. There are several lines of physiological and biochemical evidence supporting post-translational regulation of AAH enzymatic activity.</p><p>Two enzymes are involved in ureide catabolism: allantoinase (EC 3.5.2.5) and AAH. During ureide catabolism, allantoinase breaks down allantoin to allantoate. Subsequently, allantoate is catabolized by AAH to ureideglycolate. Ureide catabolism is proposed to occur in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Werner <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref> demonstrated that both allantoinase and AAH proteins are localized to the ER in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, supporting that ureide catabolism occurs in the ER. Allantoin is stored in peroxisomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Corpas <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>) before transport to the ER for ureide catabolism as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Werner <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>. Increases in ureide shoot concentrations during water-deficit stress may reflect increases in stored allantoin rather than of allantoate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Rice <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>). In addition, <italic>AAH</italic> mRNA expression is not affected by allantoin concentrations in shoots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Todd and Polacco, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Werner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Furthermore, AAH enzymatic activity is not affected by shoot allantoate levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Rice <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>). The weak relationship between <italic>AAH</italic> transcripts and shoot ureide concentrations may have resulted from the sequestration of allantoin in peroxisomes. However, if the process of ureide catabolism is maintained at a constant state in the ER regardless of overall shoot ureide concentrations, then <italic>AAH</italic> mRNA levels would remain stable. The actual ratio of allantoin to allantoate during water-deficit stress deserves further consideration in the regulation of ureide catabolism.</p><p>Several reports show that increases in Mn<sup>2+</sup> concentration <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in planta</italic> result in increases in AAH enzymatic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Lukaszewski <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Purcell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Vadez <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Vadez and Sinclair, 2001</xref>), and Mn<sup>2+</sup> is an important co-factor for optimal AAH enzymatic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Lukaszewski <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Werner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). The drought-tolerant genotype Jackson acquires Mn<sup>2+</sup> to a greater extent than KS4895, a drought-sensitive genotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Purcell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">King and Purcell, 2005</xref>). On the basis of the association of Mn<sup>2+</sup> with shoot ureide concentrations, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Purcell <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref> proposed that differences in shoot ureide concentrations between drought-tolerant and drought-sensitive soybean genotypes may result from regulation of AAH enzymatic activity during water-deficit stress. However in this study, differences in drought tolerance were not associated with differential transcript expression of <italic>AAH</italic>. This may indicate that differences in AAH enzymatic activity due to Mn<sup>2+</sup> availability are responsible for the differences in shoot ureide concentration during water-deficit stress. The AAH enzyme is proposed to have a multimeric structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Agarwall <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Werner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). The role of Mn<sup>2+</sup> in enzyme assembly is unknown. It is possible that the regulation of enzyme assembly may be regulated by Mn<sup>2+</sup> availability, which might account for differences in the response of AAH activity between drought-tolerant and drought-sensitive genotypes. For example, Jackson may be more efficient at supplying Mn<sup>2+</sup> to AAH, which results in a greater metabolism of allantoate. Greater demand for allantoate may drive the movement of stored allantoin from the peroxisomes to the ER. Therefore, ureide concentrations in the shoots would decrease as a result of increased ureide catabolism. Our results, combined with other reports, support focusing attention on the importance of the AAH enzyme in the regulation of shoot ureide concentrations and conferring of drought tolerance in soybean.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary data</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/ern332/DC1">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p><p><bold><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/ern111/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link>.</bold> Sequence of GenBank Acc. AW704657 (EST name sk54406.y1).</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>[Supplementary Material]</title></caption><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="ern332_index.html"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="ern332_null029611-file001.doc"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research was supported by a grant from the Arkansas Agricultural Experiment Station, University of Arkansas and the United Soybean Board (Project 8213). Randy Shoemaker of the USDA-ARS-CICGR kindly provided the <italic>GmAAH</italic> cDNA clone from the Public Soybean EST Project.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Burley</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaminathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural analysis of a ternary complex of allantoate amidohyrdolase from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> reveals its mechanics</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17362992</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charlson</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cianzio</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular marker Satt481 is associated with iron-deficiency chlorosis resistance in a soybean breeding population</article-title><source>Crop Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>2394</fpage><lpage>2399</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>X-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y-Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>GmDREB2</italic>, a soybean DRE-binding transcription factor, conferred drought and high-salt tolerance in transgenic plants</article-title><source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications</source><year>2007</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17178106</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corpas</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Colina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Rasero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Rio</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for leaf peroxisomes in the catobolism of purines</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Physiology</source><year>1987</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>250</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>deSilva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soybean petiole ureide response to water deficits and decreased transpiration</article-title><source>Crop Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>616</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Caviness</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><source>Stages of soybean development</source><year>1977</year><comment>Iowa Cooperative Extension Service, Iowa Agricultural and Home Economics Experiment Station: Special Report 80</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bede</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Alborn</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumlinson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Korth</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lepidopteran herbivory and oral factors induce transcripts encoding novel terpene synthases in <italic>Medicago truncatula</italic></article-title><source>Archives of Insect Biochemistry and Physiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15660362</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soybean nodule size and relationship to nitrogen fixation response to water deficit</article-title><source>Crop Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1376</fpage><lpage>1378</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of N<sub>2</sub> fixation in soybean is associated with elevated ureides and amino acids</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>1389</fpage><lpage>1396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15778462</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasuga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinazaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two transcription factors, DREB1 and DREB2, with an AP2/EREBP DNA-binding domain separate two cellular signal transduction pathways in drought- and low-temperature-responsive gene expression in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1391</fpage><lpage>1406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9707537</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lukaszewski</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Randell</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asparagine and boric acid cause allantoate accumulation in soybean leaves by inhibiting manganese-dependent allantoate amidohydrolase</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>1992</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>1670</fpage><lpage>1676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16669089</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soybean genotype differences in ureides and the relationship to drought-tolerant nitrogen fixation and manganese nutrition</article-title><source>Crop Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1062</fpage><lpage>1070</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Specht</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Boerma</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Specht</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological traits for ameliorating drought stress</article-title><source>Soybeans: Improvements, production and uses. <italic>Agronomy monograph no. 16</italic></source><year>2004</year><edition>3rd edn</edition><publisher-loc>Madison, WI</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Society of Agronomists, Crop Science Society of America, Soil Science Society of America</publisher-name><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>520</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukaszewski</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in ureide synthesis, transport and assimilation following ammonium nitrate fertilization of nodulated soybean</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Nutrition</source><year>1990</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1539</fpage><lpage>1553</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubouzet</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA-binding specificity of the ERF/AP2 domain of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> DREBs, transcription factors involved in dehydration- and cold-inducible gene expression</article-title><source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications</source><year>2002</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>998</fpage><lpage>1009</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11798174</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritsch</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular cloning: a laboratory manual</source><year>1989</year><edition>2nd edn</edition><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serraj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclai</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Symbiotic N<sub>2</sub> fixation response to drought</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>1999</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>155</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Polacco</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>At</italic>AAH encodes a protein with allantoate amidohydrolase activity from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2006</year><volume>223</volume><fpage>1108</fpage><lpage>1113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16496096</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vadez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leaf ureide degradation and N<sub>2</sub> fixation tolerance to water deficit in soybean</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2001</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11181724</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vadez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Serraj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manganese application alleviates the water deficit-induced decline of N<sub>2</sub> fixation</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>2000</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>505</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparkes</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Romeis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>C-P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification, biochemical characterization, and subcellular localization of allantoate amidohydrolases from Arabidopsis and soybean</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2008</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18065556</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the estimation of allantoin by the Rimini&#x02013;Schryver reaction</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1942</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>853</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 