<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PONE-RA-05755R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004937</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Physiology/Muscle and Connective Tissue</subject><subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology/Obesity</subject><subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology/Type 2 Diabetes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Myostatin Inhibition in Muscle, but Not Adipose Tissue, Decreases Fat Mass and Improves Insulin Sensitivity</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Mstn Inhibition and Metabolism</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Tingqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jou</surname><given-names>William</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chanturiya</surname><given-names>Tatyana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Portas</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gavrilova</surname><given-names>Oksana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McPherron</surname><given-names>Alexandra C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Genetics of Development and Disease Branch, National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Mouse Metabolic Core Laboratory, National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Calbet</surname><given-names>Jose A. L.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria, Spain</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>mcpherrona@niddk.nih.gov</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: TG OG ACM. Performed the experiments: TG WJ TC JP ACM. Analyzed the data: TG OG ACM. Wrote the paper: TG ACM.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e4937</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><copyright-statement>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Public Domain declaration which stipulates that, once placed in the public domain, this work may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><abstract><p>Myostatin (Mstn) is a secreted growth factor expressed in skeletal muscle and adipose tissue that negatively regulates skeletal muscle mass. <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have a dramatic increase in muscle mass, reduction in fat mass, and resistance to diet-induced and genetic obesity. To determine how <italic>Mstn</italic> deletion causes reduced adiposity and resistance to obesity, we analyzed substrate utilization and insulin sensitivity in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice fed a standard chow. Despite reduced lipid oxidation in skeletal muscle, <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice had no change in the rate of whole body lipid oxidation. In contrast, <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice had increased glucose utilization and insulin sensitivity as measured by indirect calorimetry, glucose and insulin tolerance tests, and hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp. To determine whether these metabolic effects were due primarily to the loss of myostatin signaling in muscle or adipose tissue, we compared two transgenic mouse lines carrying a dominant negative activin IIB receptor expressed specifically in adipocytes or skeletal muscle. We found that inhibition of myostatin signaling in adipose tissue had no effect on body composition, weight gain, or glucose and insulin tolerance in mice fed a standard diet or a high-fat diet. In contrast, inhibition of myostatin signaling in skeletal muscle, like <italic>Mstn</italic> deletion, resulted in increased lean mass, decreased fat mass, improved glucose metabolism on standard and high-fat diets, and resistance to diet-induced obesity. Our results demonstrate that <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have an increase in insulin sensitivity and glucose uptake, and that the reduction in adipose tissue mass in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice is an indirect result of metabolic changes in skeletal muscle. These data suggest that increasing muscle mass by administration of myostatin antagonists may be a promising therapeutic target for treating patients with obesity or diabetes.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Myostatin (Mstn), a member of the transforming growth factor &#x003b2; (TGF&#x003b2;) superfamily of secreted growth factors, is an important regulator of skeletal muscle development and adult homeostasis. <italic>Mstn</italic> is strongly expressed in skeletal muscle and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have a great increase in muscle mass demonstrating that myostatin is a muscle-specific negative regulator of skeletal muscle size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lee1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Patel1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>. Mutations in the <italic>Mstn</italic> gene in cattle, sheep, dogs, and one child cause an increase in skeletal muscle mass indicating conservation of function in mammals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lee2">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. Myostatin also regulates muscle mass in adult mice: Inhibition of myostatin by injection of neutralizing antibodies or antagonists causes an increase in skeletal muscle mass in both healthy adult mice and in mouse models of muscular dystrophy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Bogdanovich1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Bogdanovich2">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Bogdanovich3">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lee3">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Girgenrath1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Whittemore1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Gamer1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Wolfman1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. Myostatin inhibitors have therefore generated great interest as candidates for treatment of muscle wasting diseases.</p><p>The myostatin protein is synthesized as a full-length precursor that is cleaved into an amino-terminal pro-peptide and a carboxy-terminal mature region which is the active form of the molecule. In skeletal muscle and in circulation, myostatin is found in inactive complexes of differing composition with other proteins such as its own pro-peptide, follistatin-like 3 (Fstl3, also known as follistatin-related gene), and latent TGF&#x003b2; binding protein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lee1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Anderson1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Hill1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>. The mechanism of activation of these inactive complexes or whether all of these complexes are capable of being activated is unknown. For complexes containing the pro-peptide, activation likely requires proteolysis of the pro-peptide, perhaps by specific target cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Wolfman1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lee4">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>. Once activated, myostatin has high affinity for the activin IIB receptor (Acvr2b, also known as ActRIIB) and weak affinity for Acvr2a (also known as ActRII and ActRIIA), both of which, like other receptors for TGF&#x003b2; family members, bind multiple ligands <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-deCaestecker1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>The effects of <italic>Mstn</italic> deletion are not restricted to skeletal muscle. Many skeletal muscles of <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice are twice the mass of those of <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> while, in contrast, adipose tissue is greatly reduced in size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lin1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron2">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. Deletion of <italic>Mstn</italic> in genetic mouse models of obesity and diabetes improves obesity and glucose metabolism <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron2">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice in a CD-1 genetic background are resistant to weight gain due to diet-induced obesity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Hamrick1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>. Furthermore, transgenic mice overexpressing the secreted myostatin pro-peptide antagonist in muscle have increased muscle mass and are resistant to both weight gain and the development of insulin resistance when fed a high-fat diet (HFD) although these mice do not have reduced adiposity or improved insulin sensitivity when fed a standard diet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Zhao1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>The <italic>Mstn</italic> gene is expressed at low levels in adipose tissue and myostatin protein is found in circulation suggesting that myostatin could have a direct role in regulating adipocyte differentiation or function <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lee1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>. In vitro, myostatin promotes adipogenesis in the multipotential C3H 10T1/2 mesenchymal cell line <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Artaza1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Feldman1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref> and inhibits adipogenesis in 3T3L1 preadipocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Kim1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Zimmers1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref> indicating that myostatin actions are different during determination and differentiation steps. In vivo, <italic>Mstn</italic> overexpression in adipose tissue results in small immature adipocytes, increased energy expenditure, and resistance to diet-induced obesity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Feldman1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>. Furthermore, the expression of <italic>Mstn</italic>, <italic>Fstl3</italic>, and <italic>Acvr2b</italic> is upregulated in adipocytes from obese mice suggesting myostatin signaling may play a role in the response of adipocytes to obesity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Allen1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Whether myostatin directly regulates the overall mass of adipose tissue as it does skeletal muscle, however, is unclear. Experiments using direct injection of myostatin protein have produced conflicting results in regard to the effect on fat mass <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Zimmers1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Stolz1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>. Transgenic mice overexpressing <italic>Mstn</italic> specifically in adipose tissue have normal body composition despite a reduction in adipocyte size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Feldman1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>. In contrast, high systemic levels of myostatin or deletion of the antagonist <italic>Fstl3</italic> cause a loss of adipose tissue mass <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Zimmers1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Mukherjee1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Several other transgenic mouse models that have increased muscle mass, including some using muscle-specific promoters to drive expression of genes that cause muscle hypertrophy, also have decreased adiposity demonstrating that changes in adipose tissue size can be indirectly caused by changes in skeletal muscle size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lai1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Musaro1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Sutrave1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>. For example, HFD-fed mice expressing a muscle-specific inducible constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> transgene lose body and adipose tissue weight after muscle hypertrophy is induced <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. Thus, a role for myostatin in regulating adipose tissue mass directly cannot be determined by analysis of the extremely muscular <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mouse.</p><p>Here, we asked what metabolic changes cause the reduced adiposity and resistance to obesity in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. We then determined whether these changes were mediated by the loss of direct myostatin signaling in adipose tissue, or whether the altered metabolism is due to the loss of myostatin signaling in skeletal muscle.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Altered substrate utilization in Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice</title><p>One possible explanation for a decrease in adiposity is an increase in metabolic rate. It has been previously shown that <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have a slightly higher metabolic rate per animal and slightly lower metabolic rate normalized to total body weight <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron2">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. We reexamined oxygen consumption in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice fed a standard diet and normalized the data to lean mass. Our results confirmed that <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have a lower metabolic rate when normalized to lean mass or to total body weight (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s004">Table S1</xref>). Additionally, <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice had no change in total or ambulatory activity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s004">Table S1</xref>). Thus, the improved glucose metabolism in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice does not appear to be caused by an increase in metabolic rate or activity.</p><p>We also determined the respiratory exchange ratio (RER) in fed mice by indirect calorimetry. The RER is a measure of the ratio of the volume of CO<sub>2</sub> produced to the volume of O<sub>2</sub> consumed by an animal which reflects the relative oxidation of carbohydrates to lipids. The RER in fed <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice was significantly higher than in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice suggesting the mutant mice have increased carbohydrate utilization, reduced lipid utilization, or both (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0004937-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004937.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Substrate utilization in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow.</title><p>(A) Total respiratory exchange ratio determined by indirect calorimetry. (B) Amount of palmitate oxidized per soleus muscle. (C) Amount of palmitate oxidized by soleus muscle normalized to soleus mass. (D) Rate of oleic acid oxidation per mouse. (E) Rate of oleic acid oxidation normalized to lean mass. <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;6&#x02013;10. &#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004937.g001"/></fig><p>To determine whether <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice fed standard chow had a change in the utilization of lipid, we measured fatty acid oxidation rates in whole animals and in soleus muscle. The rate of fatty acid oxidation per animal was not significantly different between genotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g001">Fig. 1D</xref>). <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice had significantly lower rates of fatty acid oxidation compared to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice, however, after normalization to lean mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g001">Fig. 1E</xref>). This difference was also seen in isolated soleus muscle. The rate of fatty acid oxidation was not different per muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>), but was significantly lower in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> soleus muscle normalized to muscle mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>). These results suggest that the increase in RER in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice is due to increased carbohydrate utilization for energy while overall lipid utilization per animal is unchanged.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Glucose metabolism in Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice</title><p>The decreased adiposity and increased carbohydrate utilization in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice suggest they may have altered glucose metabolism. As previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron2">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, fed and fasting glucose and fed insulin levels in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice were not significantly different from controls although insulin tended to be lower (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.067) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004937-t001">Table 1</xref>). To examine the response to exogenous glucose, we performed glucose tolerance tests (GTT) on mice fed standard chow. <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice had significantly improved glucose tolerance compared to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). To determine whether the reduced glucose levels in response to exogenous glucose load were due to higher insulin secretion, we measured serum insulin at 0 and 30 minutes after glucose injection in fasted mice. Fasting blood glucose and serum insulin levels were lower in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice compared to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice 30 minutes after glucose injection suggesting that the improvement in the GTT was due to increased response to insulin rather than to increased insulin secretion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g002">Fig. 2C</xref>). We therefore performed insulin tolerance tests (ITT) to measure blood glucose changes after insulin administration. <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice had lower blood glucose levels than <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> littermates after insulin injection demonstrating improved insulin tolerance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0004937-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004937.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have increased insulin sensitivity and reduced weight gain on standard chow and HFD.</title><p>(A) Blood glucose levels during GTT of <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow or HFD. <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;8&#x02013;16. (B) Percent of starting glucose during ITT of <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow or HFD. <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;6&#x02013;10. (C) Blood glucose (left panel) and insulin (right panel) 0 and 30 minutes after glucose injection in fasted mice maintained on standard chow. <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;6. (D) Body weight gained by <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice after 10 weeks on diets. <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;7&#x02013;16. &#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001. A and B, <italic>P</italic> value symbols are for comparisons between genotypes on the same diet; below curves, mice on standard chow; above curves, mice on HFD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004937.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0004937-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004937.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Serum chemistry from mice on standard chow and HFD.</title></caption><graphic id="pone-0004937-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0004937.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" alternate-form-of="pone-0004937-t001-1"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fed glucose (mg/dl)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fasting glucose (mg/dl)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insulin (pmol/L)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resistin (ng/ml)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leptin (ng/mL)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free fatty acids (mM)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglyceride (mg/dl)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Standard Chow</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142&#x000b1;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102&#x000b1;7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">544&#x000b1;98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78&#x000b1;0.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.60&#x000b1;1.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323&#x000b1;0.040</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3&#x000b1;5.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140&#x000b1;9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87&#x000b1;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103&#x000b1;34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48&#x000b1;0.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96&#x000b1;0.57<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">&#x02021;&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219&#x000b1;0.022</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1&#x000b1;3.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">&#x0002a;&#x0002a;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>HFD</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143&#x000b1;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126&#x000b1;6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">884&#x000b1;96<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79&#x000b1;0.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">&#x0002a;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.34&#x000b1;1.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300&#x000b1;0.020</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8&#x000b1;5.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140&#x000b1;7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109&#x000b1;8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">&#x0002a;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177&#x000b1;50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">&#x02021;&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72&#x000b1;0.26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.28&#x000b1;3.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.252&#x000b1;0.034</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3&#x000b1;3.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Standard Chow</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Non-tg</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140&#x000b1;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95&#x000b1;3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">332&#x000b1;110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36&#x000b1;0.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.47&#x000b1;2.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.479&#x000b1;0.069</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.7&#x000b1;5.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Muscle-DN</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124&#x000b1;4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81&#x000b1;4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60&#x000b1;9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10&#x000b1;0.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34&#x000b1;0.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.222&#x000b1;0.026<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">&#x02020;&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.7&#x000b1;2.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">&#x0002a;&#x0002a;</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>HFD</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Non-tg</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136&#x000b1;4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113&#x000b1;10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">&#x0002a;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">676&#x000b1;107<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">&#x0002a;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.84&#x000b1;0.50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.12&#x000b1;3.56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.431&#x000b1;0.052</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.5&#x000b1;4.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">&#x0002a;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Muscle-DN</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124&#x000b1;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89&#x000b1;6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182&#x000b1;50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">&#x02020;&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59&#x000b1;0.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35&#x000b1;0.99<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">&#x0002a;&#x0002a;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271&#x000b1;0.037</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6&#x000b1;3.9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>Standard Chow</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Non-tg.</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142&#x000b1;5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83&#x000b1;3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346&#x000b1;91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.79&#x000b1;0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.06&#x000b1;5.81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.378&#x000b1;0.059</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5&#x000b1;8.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fat-DN</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146&#x000b1;7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104&#x000b1;10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136&#x000b1;21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82&#x000b1;0.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.37&#x000b1;3.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181&#x000b1;0.017<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">&#x02020;&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.4&#x000b1;5.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8" align="left" rowspan="1"><bold>HFD</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Non-tg</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180&#x000b1;12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144&#x000b1;6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">652&#x000b1;120<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">&#x0002a;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.94&#x000b1;0.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.42&#x000b1;4.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.286&#x000b1;0.034</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6&#x000b1;9.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fat-DN</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167&#x000b1;5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">&#x0002a;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115&#x000b1;7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">513&#x000b1;139<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">&#x02020;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.10&#x000b1;0.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">&#x02021;,&#x02021;&#x02021;</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.39&#x000b1;4.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199&#x000b1;0.019</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5&#x000b1;3.3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Data are expressed as mean&#x000b1;SEM of 5&#x02013;17 per group.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>&#x02020;</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>&#x02021;</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 vs. same genotype on standard chow.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>&#x0002a;&#x0002a;</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>&#x02020;&#x02020;</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01.</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>&#x02021;&#x02021;</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 vs. control on the same diet.</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><p>Non-tg, non-transgenic controls.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Response to high-fat diet</title><p>We determined whether this improvement in glucose metabolism was maintained in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice fed a HFD. Mice were fed a HFD for 10 weeks and compared to age-matched littermates fed standard chow. Food intake as a function of body weight was not different between genotypes on HFD (data not shown). As expected, <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice gained significantly less weight than <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> controls on a HFD over the 10 week interval (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>). Unlike <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice, <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice gained the same amount of body weight on HFD as they did on standard chow over the same time period. <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, however, were not completely resistant to the effects of diet-induced obesity. <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice fed a HFD had increased fat pad mass (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s001">Fig. S1</xref>) and larger adipocytes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s002">Fig. S2</xref>) compared to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice fed a standard diet. The weights of individual muscles, in contrast, were unaffected by diet (data not shown).</p><p>A HFD caused glucose intolerance in both genotypes relative to their response on standard chow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). Similar to the results from mice fed a standard chow, however, <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on HFD had better glucose tolerance compared to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice on HFD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>). <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice also had better insulin tolerance on HFD compared to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). Fed and fasting glucose in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice were not significantly different from controls fed a HFD (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004937-t001">Table 1</xref>). Serum insulin was significantly lower in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice fed a HFD demonstrating that less insulin was required to maintain normal glycemia compared to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004937-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>To determine whether other circulating molecules relevant to metabolism were affected by <italic>Mstn</italic> deletion in mice on either diet, we measured levels of free fatty acids (FFA), triglycerides, and the adipokines leptin and resistin. Serum triglycerides were significantly lower in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice than in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow while FFA levels were normal (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004937-t001">Table 1</xref>). As previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron2">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, serum leptin was significantly lower in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow than in controls. Serum resistin levels were normal. On HFD, the levels of FFA, triglycerides, leptin, and resistin were not significantly different between <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice. Liver triglyceride concentrations were also significantly lower in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on both diets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s005">Table S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Insulin sensitivity in Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice</title><p>The improvement in glucose and insulin tolerance, reduction in serum insulin levels, and decrease in adipose mass in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice suggest that these mice have increased insulin sensitivity relative to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice even on standard chow. To determine whether <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have higher glucose uptake than <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice, we carried out a hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp experiment. In the basal state, <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice had significantly reduced plasma glucose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>) and insulin levels (189&#x000b1;52 pmol/L in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice vs. 361&#x000b1;69 pmol/L in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.018). Basal glucose turnover, however, was not significantly different between genotypes (89&#x000b1;21 &#x000b5;mol/kg/minute in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice vs. 103&#x000b1;15 &#x000b5;mol/kg/minute in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice). During the clamp, although insulin levels were raised to &#x0223c;688 pmol/L in both strains, the glucose infusion rate (GIR) required to maintain normal glycemia was 181&#x00025; higher in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice than in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice indicating that overall insulin sensitivity was improved in the mutant mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). Under the clamp conditions used, endogenous glucose production was completely suppressed in both genotypes (data not shown). Whole body glucose uptake in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice was significantly higher (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g003">Fig. 3C</xref>), and the increase in skeletal muscle glucose uptake was nearly significant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g003">Fig. 3D</xref>, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.053). Glucose uptake was also increased in adipose tissue of <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, particularly white adipose tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g003">Fig. 3E and F</xref>). This result may be at least partially due to an increase in cell number per gram of fat pad because of smaller adipocyte size (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s002">Fig. S2</xref>). These results demonstrate that <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have greatly improved whole body glucose uptake in response to insulin even on standard chow.</p><fig id="pone-0004937-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004937.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have increased glucose uptake by hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp.</title><p>(A) Plasma glucose concentration before and during clamp. Insulin was infused at time 0. (B) Glucose infusion rate during clamp. Glucose uptake in (C) whole body, (D) skeletal muscle, (E) WAT, and (F) BAT. <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;7&#x02013;8. &#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004937.g003"/></fig><p>The increase in glucose uptake in muscle and adipose tissues during the clamp suggests these tissues in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice may have enhanced insulin signaling. We injected insulin into fasted mice and assessed activation of the insulin signaling pathway by Western blot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). Insulin signaling normally increases the phosphorylation of Akt as seen in muscle from <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice. In muscle from <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, the level of phosphorylated Akt was higher than in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice in response to insulin. Similarly, Akt was also activated to a greater extent in response to insulin in WAT and BAT from <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice compared to control mice demonstrating enhanced in vivo insulin signaling in mutant skeletal muscle and adipose tissues.</p><fig id="pone-0004937-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004937.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Insulin-stimulated activation of Akt by Western blot.</title><p>In vivo total Akt and phospho-Akt in gastrocnemius muscle, WAT, and BAT from <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice with or without insulin stimulation. Each lane contains protein from a different animal.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004937.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Tissue-specific inhibition of myostatin signaling</title><p>The metabolic changes we found in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice could be due to the loss of myostatin signaling in adipose tissue as well as skeletal muscle. To determine whether inhibition of myostatin signaling in adipose tissue alters adipose tissue mass and glucose metabolism independent of increased skeletal muscle mass, we generated a transgenic mouse line expressing a dominant negative (DN) <italic>Acvr2b</italic> gene specifically in adipocytes. An <italic>aP2</italic> (fatty acid binding protein 4) promoter fragment, previously used to control expression of transgenes in differentiated adipocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Moitra1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>, was inserted upstream of the <italic>Acvr2b</italic> coding sequence consisting of the extracellular ligand-binding and transmembrane domains without the intracellular kinase domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). This construct was used for pronuclear injections. Northern blot analysis of RNA from tissues obtained from mice expressing the adipose-specific dominant negative transgene (<italic>fat-DN</italic>) showed high transgene expression in white and brown adipose tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>). A low level of transgene expression was detectable in skeletal muscle either from leaky transgene expression in muscle cells or possibly from intermuscular adipocytes. Heart tissue similarly had low transgene expression. No signal was detectable in brain, liver, kidney, and testes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g005">Fig. 5B</xref> and data not shown).</p><fig id="pone-0004937-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004937.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Tissue-specific inhibition of myostatin signaling.</title><p>(A) Diagram of the construct used to make <italic>fat-DN</italic> transgenic mice with the <italic>aP2</italic> promoter controlling expression of a truncated <italic>Acvr2b</italic> containing the extracellular ligand binding and transmembrane domains. (B) Northern blot analysis of expression of <italic>fat-DN</italic> transgene and <italic>Gapdh</italic> loading control from different tissues from non-transgenic (&#x02212;) and transgenic (&#x0002b;) mice. Body composition of (C) <italic>fat-DN</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;10&#x02013;11) and (D) <italic>muscle-DN</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;5) male mice compared to non-transgenic littermates. Lean and fat mass are shown as absolute values. Body weight gained by (E) <italic>fat-DN</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;9&#x02013;17) and (F) <italic>muscle-DN</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;9&#x02013;14) male mice and littermate controls after 10 weeks on diets. Blood glucose levels during GTT of (G) <italic>fat-DN</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;7&#x02013;8) and (H) <italic>muscle-DN</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;9&#x02013;14) male mice and littermate controls on standard chow and HFD. Percent of starting glucose during ITT of (I) <italic>fat-DN</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;7&#x02013;8) and (J) <italic>muscle-DN</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;9&#x02013;12) male mice and littermate controls on standard chow and HFD. &#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001. G&#x02013;J, <italic>P</italic> value symbols are for comparisons between genotypes on the same diet; below curves, mice on standard chow; above curves, mice on HFD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004937.g005"/></fig><p>We compared <italic>fat-DN</italic> mice to mice expressing the same dominant negative receptor specifically in skeletal muscle (<italic>muscle-DN</italic>) which have an increase in muscle mass comparable to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lee5">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>. We detected some expression of the transgene in BAT in <italic>muscle-DN</italic> mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s003">Fig. S3</xref>). This expression, however, was considerably lower than the expression of the transgene in <italic>muscle-DN</italic> skeletal muscle or in <italic>fat-DN</italic> BAT (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s003">Fig. S3</xref> and 5B). Both the <italic>fat-DN</italic> and <italic>muscle-DN</italic> mice, unlike <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, still secrete myostatin into circulation (data not shown). We first measured body composition in each line to determine whether fat mass was affected by these transgenes. We did not detect any differences in body composition in <italic>fat-DN</italic> mice compared to controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g005">Fig. 5C</xref>) although transgenic mice tended to have higher body weight at older ages (data not shown). By histology, the adipocyte cell sizes were similar between <italic>fat-DN</italic> and non-transgenic littermates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s002">Fig. S2</xref>). In contrast, <italic>muscle-DN</italic> mice, like <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, had an increase in lean mass and a decrease in fat mass compared to non-transgenic littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g005">Fig. 5D</xref>). Despite having intact myostatin signaling in adipose tissue, <italic>muscle-DN</italic> mice had smaller adipocytes than control littermates, as did <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s002">Fig. S2</xref>).</p><p>These results suggest that the decrease in fat mass in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice is an indirect effect of increased muscle mass or loss of myostatin signaling in muscle rather than a direct effect of the loss of myostatin signaling in adipose tissue. It is possible, however, that a role for myostatin and/or Acvr2b in regulating adipose tissue size might only be seen under conditions that lead to increased adiposity. To test this hypothesis, mice from both transgenic lines were placed on HFD. After 10 weeks, there was no difference in body weight gained between <italic>fat-DN</italic> mice and non-transgenic littermates on standard chow or HFD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g005">Fig. 5E</xref>). Liver triglyceride concentrations were also similar between <italic>fat-DN</italic> and control mice on both diets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s005">Table S2</xref>). Furthermore, there was little or no difference in glucose or insulin tolerance between <italic>fat-DN</italic> and control mice on either diet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g005">Fig. 5G and I</xref>) demonstrating that myostatin inhibition in adipocytes does not affect whole body glucose metabolism under these conditions.</p><p>We also measured adipokines and other serum parameters. <italic>Fat-DN</italic> mice had lower circulating free fatty acid levels than control mice on standard chow (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004937-t001">Table 1</xref>). Serum resistin was higher in <italic>fat-DN</italic> mice which was significant in mice on HFD. These results suggest that myostatin and/or other Acvr2b-binding ligands may have a role in adipocyte function. All other values were not significantly different from control mice.</p><p>In contrast to <italic>fat-DN mice</italic>, <italic>muscle-DN</italic> mice were resistant to weight gain due to diet-induced obesity and did not gain more weight on HFD than on standard chow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g005">Fig. 5F</xref>) similar to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>). <italic>Muscle-DN</italic> mice also had improved glucose and insulin tolerance compared to controls on both diets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g005">Fig. 5H and J</xref>). <italic>Muscle-DN</italic> mice had lower insulin and leptin levels compared to littermate control mice, which were significant on HFD (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0004937-t001">Table 1</xref>). <italic>Muscle-DN</italic> mice also had lower serum triglyceride and FFA levels on standard chow and tended to have lower liver triglyceride concentrations compared to control mice on both diets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s005">Table S2</xref>). Overall, these results demonstrate that <italic>muscle-DN</italic> mice have a similar metabolic profile to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, and that inhibition of myostatin signaling specifically in skeletal muscle, but not adipose tissue, results in reduced adipose tissue mass and ameliorates the consequences of diet-induced obesity.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Adaptation to increased muscle mass in Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice</title><p>We next asked whether <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have similar metabolic responses to increased muscle mass as HFD-fed mice expressing a muscle-specific inducible constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> transgene. First, we examined <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice for evidence of an increase in gluconeogenesis and glycolysis relative to control mice. Constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> mice have an increase in expression in liver of genes encoding enzymes involved in gluconeogenesis, phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (<italic>Pepck</italic>) and glucose 6-phosphatase (<italic>G6Pase</italic>), and an increase in serum levels of glucagon, which stimulates gluconeogenesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. We found an increase in expression of <italic>Pepck</italic> in the liver of <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice relative to control littermates on standard chow but not HFD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>). The expression of <italic>Pepck</italic> in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice on HFD was significantly higher than in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>). <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice, however, did not have increased expression of <italic>Pepck</italic> when fed a HFD relative to standard chow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>). There was no statistically significant difference in the expression of <italic>G6Pase</italic> in liver between genotypes on either diet although the level of <italic>G6Pase</italic> expression appeared to be higher in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice than in controls on standard chow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>). Furthermore, there was no difference in serum glucagon levels between <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow or HFD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>) or in basal endogenous glucose production on standard chow as measured prior to insulin infusion during the hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp experiment (89&#x000b1;21 &#x000b5;mol/kg/minute in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice vs. 103&#x000b1;15 &#x000b5;mol/kg/minute in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice). Constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> transgenic mice fed a HFD also have an increase in serum lactate levels, the end product of anaerobic glycolysis, but <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice did not have increased serum lactate levels compared to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice on either diet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6C</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0004937-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004937.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Adaptation to increased muscle mass.</title><p>(A) Relative mRNA expression levels in liver of <italic>Pepck</italic>, <italic>G6Pase</italic>, <italic>Cpt1</italic>, <italic>Acadm</italic>, and <italic>Scd1</italic> measured by quantitative RT-PCR in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow or HFD. (B) Serum glucagon, (C) lactate, and (D) &#x003b2;-hydroxybutyrate levels in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow and HFD. <italic>n</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;6&#x02013;12. &#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004937.g006"/></fig><p>We next looked for evidence of altered metabolism of fatty acids in the liver. <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have a lower concentration of liver triglycerides than <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice on both diets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0004937.s005">Table S2</xref>). The expression of liver carnitine palmitoyl transferase-1 (<italic>Cpt1</italic>), an enzyme required for fatty acid import into mitochondria, and medium chain acyl-Coenzyme A dehydrogenase (<italic>Acadm</italic>, also known as <italic>Mcad</italic> and <italic>Acad1</italic>), an enzyme that metabolizes medium chain fatty acids, are increased in liver from HFD-fed constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. We found a non-significant increase in expression of <italic>Cpt1</italic> in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice compared to <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.085), but there were no differences in expression of <italic>Acadm</italic> between genotypes on either diet (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.321 on standard chow and <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.161 on HFD) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>). Constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> transgenic mice on HFD also have higher serum ketone levels indicating increased fatty acid oxidation by the liver <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. We therefore measured the concentration of the ketone &#x003b2;-hydroxybutyrate in serum from <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on standard chow and HFD. There was no increase in &#x003b2;-hydroxybutyrate levels in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on either diet compared to control mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6D</xref>). Finally, the expression of stearoyl-Coenzyme A desaturase 1 (<italic>Scd1</italic>), which catalyzes the conversion of saturated fatty acids to monounsaturated fatty acids, is decreased in the liver of constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> transgenic mice on HFD reflecting a reduction in lipid synthesis. We did not find any difference in expression of <italic>Scd1</italic> between <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice on either diet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>). These results demonstrate that the response to diet-induced obesity is different between <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice and constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> mice.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our results show that <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice have improved glucose metabolism and increased insulin sensitivity on both standard chow and high fat diet. We also show that the changes in glucose metabolism and adiposity are a consequence of alteration of skeletal muscle rather than a direct effect of the inhibition of myostatin signaling in adipose tissue. Although the adipocyte- and muscle-expressed transgenes showed faint expression in muscle and adipose tissue, respectively, the phenotypes of the mice were very different. Thus, it is unlikely that the leaky expression accounts for the phenotypes presented here.</p><p>Like transgenic mice overexpressing myostatin in adipose tissue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Feldman1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>, inhibition of Acvr2b function in adipocytes did not alter body composition. Taken together, the data suggest that the loss of adipose tissue in mice with high serum myostatin caused by a myostatin-secreting tumor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Zimmers1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref> required supraphysiologic levels of myostatin. Because the <italic>aP2</italic> promoter we used to express the dominant negative receptor is expressed relatively late in adipogenesis, it remains possible that inhibition of myostatin signaling in very early stage progenitors would have an effect on overall adipose mass. This may be unlikely because, in adipose-specific <italic>Mstn</italic> transgenic mice, no change in body composition was detected even though myostatin secreted by mature adipocytes would in theory be capable of signaling on uncommitted and undifferentiated progenitors within the fat pad <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Feldman1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>. It is also possible that, although Acvr2b inhibition in skeletal muscle phenocopies <italic>Mstn</italic> deletion, multiple ligands with opposite rather than redundant functions bind Acvr2b in mature adipocytes blunting an effect of inhibition of myostatin alone.</p><p>The decrease in serum free fatty acid levels in <italic>fat-DN</italic> mice suggests some function for myostatin and/or other Acvr2b-binding ligands in mature adipocytes. However, we and others were not able to see any change in the rate of lipolysis in adipocytes in vitro in response to myostatin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Stolz1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, and data not shown&#x0005d;. Other metabolic challenges to <italic>fat-DN</italic> mice may reveal specific functions for Acvr2b ligands in adipocytes.</p><p>Given our results presented here and the reduction in adiposity in transgenic mice with increased muscularity caused by changes in other signaling pathways such as IGFI <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lai1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Musaro1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Sutrave1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>, we hypothesize that the decrease in adipose tissue size in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> and <italic>muscle-DN</italic> mice is most likely an indirect result of the increased muscle mass. It is also possible the myostatin signaling pathway might have a direct role in regulating muscle metabolism that consequently affects adipose tissue mass separate from its role in regulating muscle mass. In this regard, some in vitro studies have suggested a role for myostatin in regulation of Akt activation. For example, myostatin has been shown to inhibit activation of Akt in phenylephrine-treated cardiomyocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Morissette1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref> and reduce the basal level of phosphorylated Akt in C2C12 myotubes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McFarlane1">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>. Myostatin also reduces the level of Akt activation in C2C12 undifferentiated myoblasts engineered to overexpress <italic>Akt</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Yang1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>. In contrast, myostatin increases basal glucose uptake in human placental extracts <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Mitchell1">&#x0005b;37&#x0005d;</xref>. It will be important to examine other signaling pathways in myostatin-deficient skeletal muscle that might regulate metabolism to determine whether the improved metabolism is due to increased muscle mass, the loss of myostatin signaling, or both.</p><p>Another plausible explanation for reduced adipose tissue mass in muscular mice is &#x0201c;substrate steal&#x0201d; by skeletal muscle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Reitman1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>. If skeletal muscle has increased glucose uptake, fewer carbohydrates would be available as substrates for liver triglyceride synthesis and subsequent storage in adipocytes. In this regard, induction of constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> caused fast glycolytic fiber hypertrophy in mice on HFD, an increase in glucose uptake into muscle, and an increase in lipid oxidation in liver <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice also have fiber hypertrophy in muscles comprised of predominantly fast glycolytic fibers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Mendias1">&#x0005b;39&#x0005d;</xref>. In addition, <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice are considerably more muscular than constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> mice, have a higher number of fast glycolytic fibers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Girgenrath1">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron1">16</xref>, and have less adipose mass even on standard chow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lin1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron2">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. It might therefore be expected that deletion of the <italic>Mstn</italic> gene would result in even more dramatic effects on liver metabolism. We did not find this to be the case although the gene expression data from liver from <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice fed a standard chow suggest a slight trend toward reduced lipogenesis, increased gluconeogenesis, and increased lipid oxidation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g006">Fig. 6</xref>). This trend was not, however, seen in liver from mice fed a HFD unlike in constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic>-expressing mice fed a HFD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. Furthermore, consistent with our data, Stolz et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Stolz1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref> found no difference in the rate of fatty acid oxidation in the liver of <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice fed standard chow.</p><p>There are several differences between the constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mouse models which might explain why these two muscular mutants did not have the same changes in liver gene expression and in serum values when fed a HFD. By approximately weaning age, <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice are more muscular than <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> mice due to both hypertrophy and hyperplasia of muscle fibers. In contrast, constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> transgenic mice gain muscle due to hypertrophy of existing fibers only after transgene induction in adulthood. More subtle compensatory metabolic changes could already have occurred in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice in prenatal or early postnatal life. Furthermore, the altered signaling pathways that result in muscle hypertrophy are different in each model. Basal levels of activated Akt are high in constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> transgenic muscle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>, but not in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> muscle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004937-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). Consequently, signaling to other tissues by myokines or muscle metabolites may be different. Like induction of constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic>, postnatal inhibition of myostatin signaling in mice causes fiber hypertrophy without hyperplasia or change in fiber composition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Girgenrath1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Whittemore1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. Postnatal inhibition of myostatin signaling in mice with diet-induced obesity will be necessary to directly compare these two muscle hypertrophy models to determine whether the reduction in adipose tissue mass in HFD-fed constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> mice is caused by hypertrophy of fast glycolytic fibers, by increasing the activation of the Akt signaling pathways, or both.</p><p>Injection of a myostatin neutralizing monoclonal antibody in mice on standard chow, however, does not cause a reduction in adipose tissue mass even though the weight of individual muscles is increased 20&#x02013;30&#x00025; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Whittemore1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. Similarly, a milder increase in muscle mass caused by injection of the same monoclonal antibody in the extremely obese leptin receptor-deficient mice does not reduce adipose tissue mass <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Stolz1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>. Mice null for both <italic>Mstn</italic> and <italic>leptin</italic> have a mild decrease in adipose tissue compared to <italic>leptin</italic> null mice, but this improvement is found only in young animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron2">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. These results suggest that mice deficient in leptin signaling might be too obese to be rescued by muscle hypertrophy after the onset of obesity. Treatment of mice that are obese due to different genetic or dietary causes with myostatin antagonists will clarify which, if any, specific types of obesity are rescued by postnatal inhibition of myostatin. Additionally, varying the degree of muscle hypertrophy by treatment with different doses of myostatin antagonists will help determine whether there is a threshold level of hypertrophy required for a reduction in obesity.</p><p>In addition to the potential for reducing adiposity, we believe that the improved insulin sensitivity in <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic>, <italic>muscle-DN</italic>, and constitutively active <italic>Akt1</italic> mice suggests that altering metabolism by increasing muscle mass might be a promising strategy for treating diabetes and the metabolic syndrome. Skeletal muscle of diabetics has reduced insulin sensitivity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Rabol1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref>, and recent clinical trials suggest that resistance training improves insulin sensitivity in diabetic patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Sigal1">&#x0005b;41&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Sigal2">&#x0005b;42&#x0005d;</xref>. Similar to the muscle phenotype caused by postnatal myostatin inhibition or inducible constitutively active <italic>Akt</italic> expression <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lee1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Patel1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Izumiya1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>, resistance exercise causes an increase in fiber size <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Folland1">&#x0005b;43&#x0005d;</xref>. Some studies have shown, however, that resistance training in humans can also cause shifts in fiber type not seen in these mouse models of postnatal muscle hypertrophy, and mouse muscle contains relatively more fast fibers than human muscle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Folland1">&#x0005b;43&#x0005d;</xref>. Nevertheless, it is possible that increasing muscle mass by pharmacologic interventions such as inhibiting myostatin signaling may improve glucose metabolism in diabetics, particularly those in poor physical condition who are unable to perform resistance exercise.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>All animals were handled in strict accordance with good animal practice as defined by the relevant national and/or local animal welfare bodies, and all animal work was approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of the NIDDK, NIH.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Generation and maintenance of animals</title><p>Generation N6 <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-McPherron1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref> in the C57BL/6Ncr genetic background were obtained from homozygous matings for all experiments except diet experiments in which N6 <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x0002b;/&#x0002b;</sup></italic> and <italic>Mstn<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice were obtained from heterozygous matings. <italic>Mstn</italic> genotypes were determined by PCR as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Manceau1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>. The muscle-specific dominant negative <italic>Acvr2b</italic> transgenic line, C11, in the C57BL6/Ncr genetic background (&#x0003e;N10) has been previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Lee5">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>. <italic>Muscle-DN</italic> mice were genotyped by PCR (forward, <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-CCATTTATAGTCTGAGCCCGAATGCC-3&#x02032;</named-content>; reverse, <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-AATTGAAGTCATCTAGCCAGCAGCCC-3&#x02032;</named-content>; 500 bp). For generation of adipose-specific dominant negative <italic>Acvr2b</italic> transgenic mice, the same truncated mouse <italic>Acvr2b</italic> coding sequence which was used for generation of line C11 (amino acids 1&#x02013;174) was inserted into the <italic>Pst</italic>I site of KS/422-Flag &#x000d8;10 3heptad-F/splice <italic>aP2</italic> promoter vector <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Moitra1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref> after removal of the &#x000d8;10 3heptad-F insert. Founders in the FVB genetic background were backcrossed to C57BL/6Ncr at least 5 times to generate animals for experiments and were genotyped by PCR (forward, <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-GCTGCTGCGAAGGCAACTTCTGCAACGAG -3&#x02032;</named-content>; reverse, <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-CTCTGTAGGTAGTTTGTCCAATTATGTC-3&#x02032;</named-content>; 341 bp). Non-transgenic littermates were used as controls for both transgenic lines. Mice were fed ad lib and kept under a 12-hour light/dark cycle.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Metabolic analyses</title><p>Hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps were performed in awake mice fasted for 5 hour as previously described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Toyoshima1">&#x0005b;45&#x0005d;</xref> with modifications. Experiments used primed-continuous infusion of &#x0005b;3-<sup>3</sup>H&#x0005d; glucose (2.5 &#x000b5;Ci bolus, 0.05 &#x000b5;Ci/minute during the basal state, and 0.1 &#x000b5;Ci/minute during the clamp period). Insulin was infused at the rate of 2.5 mU/kg/minute (without bolus). Indirect calorimetry and activity measurements were performed as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Yu1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref>. Lipid oxidation was carried out on conscious animals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Gautam1">&#x0005b;47&#x0005d;</xref> and on isolated soleus muscle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Toyoshima1">&#x0005b;45&#x0005d;</xref> as described. Body composition of 5&#x02013;7 month old animals was measured using the EchoMRI 3-in-1&#x02122; (Echo Medical Systems).</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>High-fat diet treatment and analysis</title><p>Nine week old males were fed either standard chow (NIH-31 Open Formula, Zeigler) or a 4.73 kcal/g HFD with 45&#x00025; kcal from fat and 35&#x00025; kcal from carbohydrates (D12451, Research Diets) for 10 weeks. GTT and ITT were performed after 8 and 9 weeks, respectively (see below). After 10 weeks, fed animals were anesthetized by i.p. injection of 80 mg/kg BW pentobarbital, and serum samples were collected by cardiac puncture. Liver and adipose samples were quickly frozen on dry ice or put in RNA Later (Ambion) for protein and RNA analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Glucose tolerance and insulin tolerance tests</title><p>GTT and ITT were performed as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Zhao1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>. Blood glucose was measured by tail bleeding at indicated time points using an Elite Glucometer (Bayer). Blood from tail tips of fasted mice was taken before and 30 minutes after injection of 2 mg/kg BW glucose for measurements of serum insulin during glucose challenge.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>RNA isolation, Northern blotting, and quantitative RT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from tissues using Trizol Reagent (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. For Northern analysis, 20 &#x000b5;g total RNA was used for electrophoresis and blotting to GeneScreen Plus membrane (Perkin Elmer) and hybridized according to the manufacturer's instructions with a probe corresponding to the extracellular region of mouse <italic>Acvr2b</italic>. For real-time quantitative PCR, samples were digested with DNase followed by reverse transcription of 500 ng total RNA using Superscript II (Invitrogen). The resulting cDNA was quantified by real-time quantitative PCR on an ABI Prism&#x000ae; 7000 Sequence Detection System using indicated Taqman primers (Applied Biosystems) and normalized to <italic>18S</italic> expression.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Serum measurements</title><p>Serum insulin, leptin, resistin, and glucagon were determined by radioimmunoassay (Millipore). Serum triglycerides (Infinity triglycerides kit, Thermo), free fatty acids (half micro test kit, Roche), &#x003b2;-hydroxybutyrate (Stanbio Laboratory), and lactate (BioVision) were determined by colorimetric methods according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Phospho-Akt detection</title><p>For in vivo Akt detection, mice were fasted overnight, anesthetized with pentobarbital (80 mg/kg body weight), and injected i.p. with 10 U/kg BW insulin (Lilly). Gastrocnemius muscle, gonadal WAT and intrascapular BAT were removed after 10 minutes and frozen in a dry ice ethanol bath, homogenized in RIPA buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 1&#x00025; NP-40, 0.25&#x00025; sodium deoxycholate, 150 mM sodium chloride, 1 mM EDTA) containing 1 mM sodium orthovanadate, 1 mM sodium fluoride, and proteinase inhibitor cocktail (Roche), and centrifuged at 13,000 g for 10 minutes to collect supernatants. Supernatants (20 &#x000b5;g protein) were used for reducing SDS PAGE and Western blotting. For immunoblotting analysis of phospho-Akt, Western blots were incubated with a 1&#x02236;2000 dilution of rabbit anti-phospho-Akt-Ser473 (Cell Signaling), followed by a 1&#x02236;5000 dilution of HRP-conjugated goat anti-rabbit secondary antibody (Invitrogen), and detected by ECL (Pierce). Blots were then stripped (H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.2N sodium hydroxide, H<sub>2</sub>O, for 5 minutes each) and incubated with a 1&#x02236;2000 dilution of rabbit anti-Akt primary antibody (Cell Signaling) followed by detection as above to detect total Akt.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>Liver triglyceride measurements</title><p>Extraction of tissue triglycerides with chloroform/methanol was modified from Burant et al <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Burant1">&#x0005b;48&#x0005d;</xref>. After hydrolysis with 200 &#x000b5;L of 3 M potassium hydroxide in 65&#x00025; ethanol, triglycerides were measured radiometrically using a glycerol kinase assay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004937-Gavrilova1">&#x0005b;49&#x0005d;</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Histology</title><p>Tissues were dissected, fixed in 10&#x00025; formalin, dehydrated, embedded in paraffin, sectioned, and stained with H&#x00026;E.</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Results are expressed as mean&#x000b1;SEM. Statistical analysis of the hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp data for increases in glucose infusion rate and glucose uptake in <italic>Mstn <sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup></italic> mice was performed using one-tailed student's <italic>t</italic> test. Statistical analysis of data from HFD experiments, except GTT and ITT, was performed using SPSS software by two-factor ANOVA with genotype and diet as the factors. When between-subjects effects were significant, data were further analyzed by pairwise comparisons using Bonferroni confidence interval adjustment for multiple comparisons. Indirect calorimetry, GTT, and ITT data were analyzed by 2-tailed student's <italic>t</italic> test. <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004937.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>Fat pad mass of Mstn&#x0002b;/&#x0002b; and Mstn&#x02212;/&#x02212; mice on standard chow or HFD.</p><p>(0.10 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004937.s001.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004937.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>Representative images of H&#x00026;E stained gonadal fat pads from mutant mice and control littermates on standard chow or high fat diet (HFD).</p><p>(0.99 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004937.s002.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004937.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>Northern blot analysis of expression of muscle-DN transgene and Gapdh loading control from non-transgenic (&#x02212;) and transgenic (&#x0002b;) mice.</p><p>(0.12 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004937.s003.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004937.s004"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>Indirect calorimetry</p><p>(0.05 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004937.s004.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0004937.s005"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>Liver triglyceride concentration on standard or HFD</p><p>(0.11 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0004937.s005.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Kong Chen for helpful discussions on the data and manuscript, Sam Cushman for helpful discussions, Marc Laplante for assistance with statistical analysis, Michelle Olive, Charles Vinson, and Dan Lane for the <italic>aP2</italic> vector, Se-Jin Lee for making the <italic>fat-DN</italic> construct, and the Johns Hopkins Transgenic Core Facility for pronuclear injections and embryo transfer.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0004937-Lee1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Regulation of muscle mass by myostatin.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15473835</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Patel1"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Amthor</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>The function of Myostatin and strategies of Myostatin blockade-new hope for therapies aimed at promoting growth of skeletal muscle.</article-title><source>Neuromuscul Disord</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15694133</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Lee2"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Sprinting without myostatin: a genetic determinant of athletic prowess.</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17884234</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Bogdanovich1"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bogdanovich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krag</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Functional improvement of dystrophic muscle by myostatin blockade.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>420</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12459784</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Bogdanovich2"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bogdanovich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Myostatin blockade improves function but not histopathology in a murine model of limb-girdle muscular dystrophy 2C.</article-title><source>Muscle Nerve</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18041051</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Bogdanovich3"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bogdanovich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Krag</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Myostatin propeptide-mediated amelioration of dystrophic pathophysiology.</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15791004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Lee3"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Girgenrath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goad</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Regulation of muscle growth by multiple ligands signaling through activin type II receptors.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>102</volume><fpage>18117</fpage><lpage>18122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16330774</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Girgenrath1"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Girgenrath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Loss of myostatin expression alters fiber-type distribution and expression of myosin heavy chain isoforms in slow- and fast-type skeletal muscle.</article-title><source>Muscle Nerve</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15468312</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Whittemore1"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittemore</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Aghajanian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Inhibition of myostatin in adult mice increases skeletal muscle mass and strength.</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>300</volume><fpage>965</fpage><lpage>971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12559968</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Gamer1"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gamer</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfman</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Celeste</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattersley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hewick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>A novel BMP expressed in developing mouse limb, spinal cord, and tail bud is a potent mesoderm inducer in Xenopus embryos.</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>208</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10075854</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Wolfman1"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfman</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>McPherron</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappano</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Activation of latent myostatin by the BMP-1/tolloid family of metalloproteinases.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>15842</fpage><lpage>15846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14671324</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Anderson1"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Identification of a novel pool of extracellular pro-myostatin in skeletal muscle.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>283</volume><fpage>7027</fpage><lpage>7035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18175804</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Hill1"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hewick</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The myostatin propeptide and the follistatin-related gene are inhibitory binding proteins of myostatin in normal serum.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>277</volume><fpage>40735</fpage><lpage>40741</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12194980</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Lee4"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Genetic analysis of the role of proteolysis in the activation of latent myostatin.</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>e1628</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18286185</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-deCaestecker1"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Caestecker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The transforming growth factor-&#x003b2; superfamily of receptors.</article-title><source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14746809</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-McPherron1"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McPherron</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawler</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Regulation of skeletal muscle mass in mice by a new TGF-&#x003b2; superfamily member.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>387</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9139826</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Lin1"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Della-Fera</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Azain</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartzell</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Myostatin knockout in mice increases myogenesis and decreases adipogenesis.</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>291</volume><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11855847</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-McPherron2"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McPherron</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Suppression of body fat accumulation in myostatin-deficient mice.</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11877467</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Hamrick1"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamrick</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Isales</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Resistance to body fat gain in &#x02018;double-muscled&#x02019; mice fed a high-fat diet.</article-title><source>Int J Obes (Lond)</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>868</fpage><lpage>870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16404405</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Zhao1"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Transgenic expression of myostatin propeptide prevents diet-induced obesity and insulin resistance.</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>337</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16182246</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Artaza1"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Artaza</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhasin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Magee</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reisz-Porszasz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Myostatin inhibits myogenesis and promotes adipogenesis in C3H 10T(1/2) mesenchymal multipotent cells.</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>146</volume><fpage>3547</fpage><lpage>3557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15878958</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Feldman1"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Streeper</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Farese</surname><given-names>RV</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Myostatin modulates adipogenesis to generate adipocytes with favorable metabolic effects.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>15675</fpage><lpage>15680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17030820</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Kim1"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausman</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartzell</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Inhibition of preadipocyte differentiation by myostatin treatment in 3T3-L1 cultures.</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>281</volume><fpage>902</fpage><lpage>906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11237745</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Zimmers1"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmers</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Koniaris</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Esquela</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Induction of cachexia in mice by systemically administered myostatin.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>296</volume><fpage>1486</fpage><lpage>1488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029139</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Allen1"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Speaker</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Uyenishi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Myostatin, activin receptor IIb, and follistatin-like-3 gene expression are altered in adipose tissue and skeletal muscle of obese mice.</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><volume>294</volume><fpage>E918</fpage><lpage>927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18334608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Stolz1"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Qadri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jalenak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaman</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Administration of myostatin does not alter fat mass in adult mice.</article-title><source>Diabetes Obes Metab</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18190427</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Mukherjee1"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raher</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>FSTL3 deletion reveals roles for TGF-&#x003b2; family ligands in glucose and fat homeostasis in adults.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>104</volume><fpage>1348</fpage><lpage>1353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17229845</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Lai1"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Poueymirou</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Conditional activation of Akt in adult skeletal muscle induces rapid hypertrophy.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>9295</fpage><lpage>9304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15485899</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Izumiya1"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izumiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Fast/Glycolytic muscle fiber growth reduces fat mass and improves metabolic parameters in obese mice.</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18249175</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Musaro1"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Musaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McCullagh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobrowolny</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Localized Igf-1 transgene expression sustains hypertrophy and regeneration in senescent skeletal muscle.</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175789</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Sutrave1"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutrave</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>ski can cause selective growth of skeletal muscle in transgenic mice.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>1462</fpage><lpage>1472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2253874</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Moitra1"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moitra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Olive</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krylov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavrilova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Life without white fat: a transgenic mouse.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>3168</fpage><lpage>3181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9784492</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Lee5"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McPherron</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Regulation of myostatin activity and muscle growth.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>9306</fpage><lpage>9311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459935</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Morissette1"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morissette</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McKoy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Myostatin regulates cardiomyocyte growth through modulation of Akt signaling.</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16763166</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-McFarlane1"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McFarlane</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennebry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Myostatin induces cachexia by activating the ubiquitin proteolytic system through an NF-kappaB-independent, FoxO1-dependent mechanism.</article-title><source>J Cell Physiol</source><volume>209</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16883577</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Yang1"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Myostatin induces cyclin D1 degradation to cause cell cycle arrest through a phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/AKT/GSK-3&#x003b2; pathway and is antagonized by insulin-like growth factor 1.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>282</volume><fpage>3799</fpage><lpage>3808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17130121</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Mitchell1"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Osepchook</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Myostatin is a human placental product that regulates glucose uptake.</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>1434</fpage><lpage>1437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16464946</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Reitman1"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reitman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Metabolic lessons from genetically lean mice.</article-title><source>Annu Rev Nutr</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12055354</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Mendias1"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendias</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcin</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Calerdon</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Contractile properties of EDL and soleus muscles of myostatin-deficient mice.</article-title><source>J Appl Physiol</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>898</fpage><lpage>905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16709649</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Rabol1"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabol</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Boushel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dela</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Mitochondrial oxidative function and type 2 diabetes.</article-title><source>Appl Physiol Nutr Metab</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17213881</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Sigal1"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sigal</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Boule</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Prud'homme</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Effects of aerobic training, resistance training, or both on glycemic control in type 2 diabetes: a randomized trial.</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><volume>147</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17876019</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Sigal2"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sigal</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Castaneda-Sceppa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Physical activity/exercise and type 2 diabetes: a consensus statement from the American Diabetes Association.</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>1433</fpage><lpage>1438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16732040</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Folland1"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Folland</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The adaptations to strength training : morphological and neurological contributions to increased strength.</article-title><source>Sports Med</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17241104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Manceau1"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manceau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thome</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>McPherron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Myostatin promotes the terminal differentiation of embryonic muscle progenitors.</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>668</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18316481</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Toyoshima1"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toyoshima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavrilova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Pack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Leptin improves insulin resistance and hyperglycemia in a mouse model of type 2 diabetes.</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>146</volume><fpage>4024</fpage><lpage>4035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15947005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Yu1"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavrilova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Paternal versus maternal transmission of a stimulatory G-protein &#x003b1; subunit knockout produces opposite effects on energy metabolism.</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10712433</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Gautam1"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavrilova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Beneficial metabolic effects of M3 muscarinic acetylcholine receptor deficiency.</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17084710</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Burant1"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burant</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sreenan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmiller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Troglitazone action is independent of adipose tissue.</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>2900</fpage><lpage>2908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9389757</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004937-Gavrilova1"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gavrilova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcus-Samuels</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Torpor in mice is induced by both leptin-dependent and -independent mechanisms.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>14623</fpage><lpage>14628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10588755</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>Under a licensing agreement between MetaMorphix, Inc. (MMI) and the Johns Hopkins University, A.C.M. is entitled to a share of royalty received by the University on sales of myostatin. A.C.M. and the University own MMI stock, which is subject to certain restrictions under University policy. The terms of these arrangements are being managed by the University in accordance with its conflict of interest policies.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This research is supported by the Intramural Research Program of the NIH, NIDDK. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article> 