<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">08-PONE-RA-07512R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Biochemistry/Chemical Biology of the Cell</subject><subject>Biochemistry/Macromolecular Chemistry</subject><subject>Cell Biology/Chemical Biology of the Cell</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>PP1&#x003b3;2 and PPP1R11 Are Parts of a Multimeric Complex in Developing Testicular Germ Cells in which their Steady State Levels Are Reciprocally Related</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">A Role of PPP1R11 in Testis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Lina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pilder</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nairn</surname><given-names>Angus C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramdas</surname><given-names>Shandilya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>Srinivasan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, Kent State University, Kent, Ohio, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology, Temple University School of Medicine, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Psychiatry, Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Wenqing</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Washington, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>svijayar@kent.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LC SV. Performed the experiments: LC SR. Analyzed the data: LC SP AN SV. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AN SV. Wrote the paper: LC SP SV. Contributed to the revision of the paper: AN.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e4861</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Cheng et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><abstract><p>Mice lacking the protein phosphatase 1 gamma isoforms, PP1&#x003b3;1 and PP1&#x003b3;2, are male-sterile due to defective germ cell morphogenesis and apoptosis. However, this deficiency causes no obvious abnormality in other tissues. A biochemical approach was employed to learn how expression versus deficiency of PP1&#x003b3;2, the predominant PP1 isoform in male germ cells, affects spermatogenesis. Methods used in this study include column chromatography, western blot and northern blot analyses, GST pull-down assays, immunoprecipitation, non-denaturing gel electrophoresis, phosphatase enzyme assays, protein sequencing, and immunohistochemistry. We report for the first time that in wild-type testis, PP1&#x003b3;2 forms an inactive complex with actin, protein phosphatase 1 regulatory subunit 7 (PPP1R7), and protein phosphatase 1 regulatory subunit 11 (PPP1R11), the latter, a potent PP1 inhibitor. Interestingly, PPP1R11 protein, but not its mRNA level, falls significantly in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis where mature sperm are virtually absent. Conversely, both mature sperm numbers and the PPP1R11 level increase substantially in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis expressing transgenic PP1&#x003b3;2. PPP1R11 also appears to be ubiquitinated in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis. The levels of PP1&#x003b3;2 and PPP1R11 were increased in phenotypically normal PP1&#x003b1;-null testis. However, in PP1&#x003b1;-null spleen, where PP1&#x003b3;2 normally is not expressed, PPP1R11 levels remained unchanged. Our data clearly show a direct reciprocal relationship between the levels of the protein phosphatase isoform PP1&#x003b3;2 and its regulator PPP1R11, and suggest that complex formation between these polypeptides in testis may prevent proteolysis of PPP1R11 and thus, germ cell apoptosis.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>All four isoforms of protein phosphatase 1 (PP1), PP1&#x003b1;, PP1&#x003b2;, PP1&#x003b3;1 and PP1&#x003b3;2, are expressed in mammalian testis. Targeted disruption of the <italic>Ppp1cc</italic> gene, resulting in ablation of both PP1&#x003b3;1 and PP1&#x003b3;2, leads to aberrant sperm morphogenesis, testicular apoptosis, and subsequent male sterility, despite increased &#x0201c;compensatory&#x0201d; expression of PP1&#x003b1; and PP1&#x003b2; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Chakrabarti1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>. Because PP1&#x003b3;2 is the only PP1 isoform to exhibit significant expression in differentiating male germ cells, particularly in spermatids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Vijayaraghavan1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Smith1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, its absence could be at the heart of the PP1&#x003b3;-null phenotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Chakrabarti1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>. Thus, PP1&#x003b3;2 might have a fundamental, isoform-specific role in mammalian spermiogenesis.</p><p>PP1&#x003b3;2 is also the only PP1 isoform detected in mammalian spermatozoa <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Vijayaraghavan1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Smith1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, where inhibition of its activity in caudal epididymal sperm has been linked to the onset of progressive motility, and to a significant increase in vigor in already progressively motile sperm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Vijayaraghavan1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Smith1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>. These findings suggest that PP1&#x003b3;2 is a vital mediator of sperm function in mammals. However, the reason for this is not yet clear since the genomes of eukaryotic species other than mammals do not contain a PP1 orthologue resembling PP1&#x003b3;2.</p><p>What differentiates PP1&#x003b3;2 from other PP1 isoforms is its distinctive, almost completely conserved 21-amino acid C-terminal extension. Even so, the function of this unique C-terminus remains unknown, as it does not appear to be essential for the catalytic activity of PP1&#x003b3;2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Sasaki1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Puntoni1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>A number of PP1 interacting proteins in somatic cells have been detected by a variety of approaches, and considerable progress has been made in defining the functions of these proteins and how they regulate PP1 in those cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Bennett1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. In comparison, our understanding of the regulation of PP1&#x003b3;2 in male germ cells is limited primarily to what we have learned about generic PP1 function in somatic cells. Yeast two-hybrid approaches have identified several PP1 interacting proteins in testis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Helps1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Hrabchak2">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>. However, the dimunition/termination of transcriptional and translational activities in haploid spermatids and terminally differentiated testicular spermatozoa make the application of this technique ineffectual in determining the role of PP1&#x003b3;2 and its binding partners in these cell types. Thus, to elucidate the functional interactions of PP1&#x003b3;2 with its regulators and other substrates in developing and mature male gametes, biochemical approaches are generally employed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Chakrabarti1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Smith1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Mishra1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>To date, such studies have shown that sperm do not appear to contain any detectable PPP1R1 (phosphoprotein phosphatase 1 regulatory subunit 1, inhibitor 1, I1), a PP1 regulatory subunit whose activity is controlled by protein kinase A phosphorylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Cohen1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Nimmo1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>. Sperm do contain inhibitor activity similar to that of PPP1R2 (phosphoprotein phosphatase 1 regulatory subunit 2, inhibitor 2, I2), mediated by GSK3 (glycogen synthase kinase 3) phosphorylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Chakrabarti1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Vijayaraghavan1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>. Experiments, using column/affinity purification techniques with anti-PP1&#x003b3;2 antibodies have demonstrated that sperm contain the homologue of the yeast PP1 binding protein, PPP1R7 (phosphoprotein phosphatase 1 regulatory subunit 7, Sds22) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>. The protein Sds22 was originally identified in yeast as a positive regulator of protein phosphatase-1, required for the mitotic metaphase/anaphase transition <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Ohkura1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Ceulemans1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>. Nonetheless, in cultured mammalian cells, a partial inhibitory effect on a recombinant catalytic subunit of PP1 by a synthetic polypeptide corresponding to the Sds22 sixth leucine-rich repeat (LRR) has been demonstrated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Dinischiotu1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>. Additionally, characterization of the Sds22-PP1&#x003b3;2 complex in spermatozoa revealed that the complex was catalytically inactive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>. Thus, Sds22 is currently believed to be an inhibitor of PP1 in mammals. However, other components in the male germ cell complex containing Sds22 and PP1&#x003b3;2 have not yet been identified.</p><p>Finally, a potent heat-stable PP1 inhibitor, PPP1R11 (phosphoprotein phosphatase 1 regulatory subunit 11, inhibitor 3, I3), first discovered in yeast, and later in human brain through yeast two-hybrid studies <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Zhang1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>, was identified subsequently as the orthologue of the mouse <italic>t</italic> complex testis-expressed gene, <italic>Tctex5</italic> (<italic>t</italic> complex testis expressed gene 5). Its PP1 inhibitory power has since been demonstrated against both recombinant Mn<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup>-dependent and metal-independent isoforms of PP1&#x003b1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang5">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>. A recent study suggests that cleavage of this PP1 inhibitor by Caspase-3 in actinomyosin D-treated HL60 cells promotes apoptosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Other recent studies in yeast and mammalian cell culture have suggested that Sds22, PPP1R11, and PP1&#x003b1; form a trimeric complex in which PP1&#x003b1; is catalytically inactive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Lesage1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Pedelini1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>. The physiological role of the complex between PP1, Sds22, and PPP1R11, and whether such a complex exists in developing male germ cells are not known. However, the conserved presence of PPP1R11 and Sds22 in a broad range of eukaryotic organisms and tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Hugo1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>, including the mammalian testis, suggests that both may be vital regulators of PP1 activity in the male gonad.</p><p>In this study, we demonstrate the formation of a complex between PP1&#x003b3;2, PPP1R11, Sds22, and actin in both wild-type differentiating and terminally differentiated male germ cells, in which PP1&#x003b3;2 appears to be held in a catalytically inactive state. We also show evidence that PP1&#x003b3;2 has an anti-apoptotic effect in the testis, and explore the possibility that this result could be mediated by its ability to enhance the stability of PPP1R11.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>PPP1R11 mRNA and protein were abundantly expressed in testis compared to other tissues</title><p>A previous study documented the presence of <italic>ppp1r11</italic> mRNA in testis, and showed that the steady state level of this message is clearly higher in testis than in other tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Han1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>. We confirmed, by northern blot analysis of mRNAs isolated from testis and numerous other tissues, that <italic>ppp1r11</italic> testicular mRNA is significantly more abundant than it is in other tissues (data not shown). To determine if the steady state levels of PPP1R11 protein in various tissues reflect these mRNA results, we prepared an affinity-purified polyclonal antibody (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>), and demonstrated that it specifically recognized both recombinant PPP1R11 and endogenous testicular PPP1R11 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). Subsequent western blots of protein extracts from testis and various somatic tissues probed with our PPP1R11 antibody, established the existence of a single immunoreactive protein at 27-kDa at significantly higher levels in testis than in other tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0004861-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>PPP1R11 is present in various tissues including testis.</title><p><italic>A</italic>. Validation of PPP1R11 antibody was performed as follows: recombinant PPP1R11 and testis protein extracts were separated by SDS-PAGE followed by western blot analysis with affinity purified rabbit polyclonal anti-PPP1R11. Size markers (left) were derived from &#x003b2;-Galactosidase (116-kDa), Phosphorylase b (97.4-kDa), Albumin (66-kDa), Glutamic dehydrogenase (55-kDa), Ovalbumin (45-kDa), Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (36-kDa), Carbonic anhydrase (29-kDa), and Soybean trypsin inhibitor (20-kDa). <italic>B</italic>. Soluble protein extracts from testis and somatic tissues were separated by SDS-PAGE followed by western blot analysis with the validated affinity purified PPP1R11 antibody, and the same blot was stripped and reprobed with anti-actin used as a loading control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>PPP1R11 binds to testis-expressed PP1&#x003b3;2 and Sds22 both in vitro and in vivo</title><p>The protein PPP1R11 has been reported to co-localize with PP1&#x003b3;1 in nucleoli and with PP1&#x003b1; in centrosomes in somatic cells, and has been co-precipitated with PP1&#x003b3;1 and PP1&#x003b1; but not PP1&#x003b2; in HEK cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang5">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>. However, it was not known whether PPP1R11 binds PP1&#x003b3;2 in testicular germ cells. To determine if PPP1R11 is capable of binding to PP1&#x003b3;2 <italic>in vitro</italic>, we made GST-tagged recombinant PPP1R11 protein in bacteria, immobilized it on glutathione Sepharose 4B beads, and incubated it with mouse testis extracts. After extensive washing, bound proteins released by reduced glutathione were analyzed on western blots probed with anti-PP1&#x003b3;2 and anti-Sds22 antibodies. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g002">Figure 2A</xref> demonstrates that PP1&#x003b3;2 from testis extracts was bound to GST-PPP1R11 but not to GST alone. Not surprisingly, Sds22 was also identified as a potential PPP1R11 and/or PP1&#x003b3;2 binding protein in testis extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g002">Fig. 2A</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0004861-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Sds22, PPP1R11, and PP1&#x003b3;2 are bound to each other in crude testis protein extracts.</title><p><italic>A</italic>. The recombinant proteins GST-PPP1R11 and control GST were incubated with testis cell lysates in the presence of Glutathione-Sepharose beads. The eluted proteins and testis extracts alone were resolved by SDS-PAGE and subjected to western blot analysis with anti-Sds22 and anti-PP1&#x003b3;2 antibodies. <italic>B</italic>. Testis protein extracts and buffer controls were incubated with anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, anti-PPP1R11, or preimmune serum immobilized on Protein G-Sepharose-4 beads, as indicated at the top of the figure. The immunoprecipitates were separated by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted for the proteins indicated at the bottom of the figure. (ND: not done).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g002"/></fig><p>Immunoprecipitation was used to further explore whether endogenous PPP1R11 is bound to PP1&#x003b3;2 and/or Sds22. Proteins immunoprecipitated by antibodies to PPP1R11 or PP1&#x003b3;2 were separated by SDS-PAGE, and gels were analyzed by western blotting with anti-PP1&#x003b3;2 and anti-Sds22 antibodies as probes for proteins precipitated by anti-PPP1R11, and anti-PPP1R11 and anti-Sds22 antibodies as probes for proteins precipitated by anti-PP1&#x003b3;2. The results established that anti-PPP1R11 co-precipitated both PP1&#x003b3;2 and Sds22, whereas anti-PP1&#x003b3;2 co-precipitated both PPP1R11 and Sds22 from mouse testis extracts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>). Taken together with our GST-pull down results, these data strongly suggest that PPP1R11, Sds22, and PP1&#x003b3;2 are part of a single complex or exist as multiple pairs of heterodimers in testis.</p><p>To further clarify these binding relationships <italic>in vivo</italic>, chromatographic fractionation of mouse testis protein extracts was performed to purify the putative complex(es) containing PPP1R11, PP1&#x003b3;2 and Sds22. Column fractions were analyzed for PPP1R11, PP1&#x003b3;2, and Sds22 immunoreactivities. The presence and abundance of all three proteins in DEAE, MonoQ, and Superose 6 column fractions is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g003">Figure 3A, B, and C</xref>, respectively, providing further evidence that the three proteins may be part or all of a single soluble complex <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><fig id="pone-0004861-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>PPP1R11, Sds22 and PP1&#x003b3;2 co-elute during chromatographic purification of testis extracts.</title><p>Western blot analysis of purified column fractions shows a consistent co-elution pattern of testicular PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11 through a series of chromatographic media. <italic>A</italic>. DEAE chromatography showing PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11 co-eluting primarily in fractions A3 and A4. <italic>B</italic>. A3 and A4 fractions from the DEAE column were pooled and purified by MonoQ column fractionation. PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11 co-eluted in fractions B8&#x02013;11. <italic>C</italic>. B8&#x02013;B11 fractions from the MonoQ column were pooled and purified by Superose 6 column chromatography, from which PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11 co-eluted from 14.05&#x02013;15.05 ml. In each instance 0.5 ml of co-eluting fractions were collected and concentrated, then assayed by SDS-PAGE/western blot analysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g003"/></fig><p>To expand this assessment, we immunoprecipitated these fractions with anti-PPP1R11, anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, and anti-Sds22 antibodies, and evaluated the immunoprecipitates by SDS-PAGE/western blotting as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g002">Figure 2B</xref>. In all cases, antibodies raised against each of the three proteins were able to reciprocally precipitate the other two proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). The fractions containing the co-eluted proteins from the final sizing column were further analyzed by native PAGE/western blotting. Replicate blot strips were separately probed with anti-PPP1R11, anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, or anti-Sds22 antibodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). The results showed that all three proteins co-migrated, thus, offering further evidence that PPP1R11, Sds22, and PP1&#x003b3;2 are bound to one another in a single complex in testis.</p><fig id="pone-0004861-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>PPP1R11, Sds22, and PP1&#x003b3;2 from co-eluting fractions are reciprocally co-immunoprecipitated, and co-migrate by native PAGE.</title><p><italic>A</italic>. Superose 6 fractions (C4 and C5 from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g003">Figure 3C</xref>) of testis extracts containing co-eluted PPP1R11, PP1&#x003b3;2, and Sds22 were incubated with anti-PPP1R11, anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, anti-Sds22, or preimmune serum immobilized on Protein G-Sepharose 4 beads, as indicated at the top of the figure. The immunoprecipitates were separated by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted for co-precipitating proteins as indicated below each blot strip (The reason why Sds22 migrates as a doublet is not known). <italic>B</italic>. C4 and C5 fractions of testis proteins purified by Superose 6 column chromatography were also separated by native PAGE followed by western blot analysis. Triplicated blot strips probed with either anti-PPP1R11, anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, or anti-Sds22 antibodies, as indicated, demonstrate that PPP1R11, PP1&#x003b3;2, and Sds22 co-migrate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Estimation of the molecular weight of the complex suggests that it consists of more than three subunits</title><p>In a recent study with somatic cells in culture, PP1, PPP1R11, and Sds22 were shown to exist as a trimeric complex in which PP1 was catalytically inactive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Lesage1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. To test whether the putative testis complex containing PP1&#x003b3;2, PPP1R11, and Sds22 was a simple trimer or existed as a larger multimer, we estimated the molecular weight of the chromatographically purified testicular fractions of interest by further size exclusion chromatography through Superdex 200. A calibration curve (data not shown) suggested that the apparent total molecular weight of proteins eluting in these fractions was &#x0223c;175 kDa. Based on their primary sequences, the calculated molecular weight of a trimeric complex of just one copy each of PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11 is &#x0223c;96 kDa. This suggests that a complex containing one copy each of the three proteins either migrates anomalously through the sizing column or exists as part of a larger multimeric complex.</p><p>To determine if there were components other than PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11 in the (presumed) larger complex, non-denaturing gel electrophoresis of the Superdex 200 column fraction containing PPP1R11, PP1&#x003b3;2, and Sds22 was performed as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g004">Figure 4B</xref>, but this time in quadruplicate, rather than in triplicate on the same gel (data not shown). Three lanes of the gel were transferred to a PVDF membrane and each was evaluated on a western blot probed with anti-PPP1R11, anti-Sds22, or anti-PP1&#x003b3;2 antibodies, while the fourth lane of the gel was stained with Coomassie blue. The band in the Coomassie blue-stained portion of the gel corresponding to the common immunoreactive band in the western blots was excised from the gel and microsequenced following in-gel proteolysis. Interestingly, around 15 proteins were identified. Of these, actin was well represented, along with all PP1 isoforms, Sds22, and PPP1R11. Together, the elution profile of the complex on the size-exclusion column and the sequencing results following native gel electrophoresis revealed that the complex containing PPP1R11, Sds22, and PP1&#x003b3;2 is probably larger than a trimer.</p><p>Subsequent to microsequencing, chromatographically-purified protein fractions from wild-type mouse testis were immunoprecipitated with anti-actin, anti-PPP1R11, anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, and anti-Sds22 antibodies. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g005">Figure 5</xref> shows that each antibody not only precipitated its cognate antigen, but co-precipitated the other three proteins as well, suggesting that PP1&#x003b3;2, PPP1R11, Sds22, and actin constitute either the entirety or components of several related multimeric protein complexes in testis.</p><fig id="pone-0004861-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Actin co-precipitates with PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11 in testis.</title><p>Fractions from mouse testis protein extracts first purified by DEAE-, MonoQ-, and Superdex 200-column chromatography were immunoprecipitated with anti-actin, anti-PPP1R11, anti-Sds22 and anti-PP1&#x003b3;2 antibodies. Following SDS-PAGE of the immunoprecipitates, the gels were analyzed by western blotting with antibodies against the proteins indicated to the right of the blots.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>PP1&#x003b3;2 is catalytically inactive in a purified fraction of sperm proteins also containing PPP1R11, Sds22, and actin</title><p>The testis contains all four PP1 isoforms, PPP1R11, and Sds22, as well as abundant PP2A co-eluting with them. Because PP1&#x003b3;2 is the only PP1 isoform present in cauda epididymal sperm, and PP2A is nearly undetectable in fractions containing PP1&#x003b3;2, PPP1R11, Sds22, and actin, serine/threonine phosphatase activity was measured in the appropriate chromatographically-purified protein fractions from sperm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g006">Fig. 6A &#x00026; 6B</xref>). These assays revealed that there was little if any serine-threonine phosphatase activity in fractions containing a low level of PP2A and abundant PP1&#x003b3;2, PPP1R11, Sds22, and actin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0004861-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>PP1&#x003b3;2 is inactive in chromatographically-purified fractions containing PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, PPP1R11, and actin.</title><p><italic>A</italic>. Protein phosphatase activity in 5-&#x000b5;l aliquots of DEAE-, MonoQ-, and Superose 6-purified fractions from cauda sperm protein extracts. <italic>B</italic>. SDS-PAGE/immunoblot analysis of the corresponding fractions probed with anti-Sds22, anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, anti-PPP1R11, anti-PP2A, and anti-actin antibodies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>The mutual increase of PPP1R11, PP1&#x003b3;2, and Sds22 levels in the testis from adolescence to adulthood parallels the progression of haploid male germ cell morphogenesis</title><p>To gain further insight into possible functional relationships between PPP1R11, Sds22, and PP1&#x003b3;2 in developing male germ cells, the expression and localization patterns of the three proteins in testis were compared. Western blot analysis showed that significant amounts of Sds22 were present in the testis at days 8 and 18 post partum when little PP1&#x003b3;2 or PPP1R11 was detectable. However, the steady state levels of PP1&#x003b3;2, PPP1R11, and Sds22, all rose to their highest levels between days 30 and 45 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g007">Fig. 7</xref>). This pattern of high level co-expression correlates closely with a time course over which spermatids differentiate into mature testicular spermatozoa. Consistent with this data, immunohistochemical analysis of testis sections confirmed that Sds22 was relatively more abundant in the cytoplasm of spermatocytes than either PP1&#x003b3;2 or PPP1R11, with PP1&#x003b3;2 more pronounced than PPP1R11 in these cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g008">Figs. 8A, 8B, &#x00026; 8C</xref>). PPP1R11 fluorescence intensity in the cytoplasms of round and elongating spermatids and in spermatozoa confirmed that it is primarily a haploid germ cell-restricted protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g008">Fig. 8C</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0004861-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Increasing steady state levels of PPP1R11, PP1&#x003b3;2 and Sds22 in testis parallel the temporal progression of spermiogenesis.</title><p>In each experiment, postnatal testis levels of PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11 were monitored by assessing equal concentrations of protein (25 &#x000b5;g) from extracts prepared from each age group. Proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE, and gels were assayed by western blotting with antibodies against PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11. Results indicating that postnatal expression of PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22, and PPP1R11 increased over the age range in which the initial round of spermiogenesis takes place were visualized by chemiluminescence. A duplicate blot was probed with an anti-actin antibody to demonstrate equal protein loading.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g007"/></fig><fig id="pone-0004861-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Cellular localization of PP1&#x003b3;2, PPP1R11 and Sds22 in wild-type mouse testis sections.</title><p><italic>A</italic>. Sds22 expression is prominent in the cytoplasm of most germ cells in the testis (from spermatogonia, primary spermatocytes, secondary spermatocytes, and round spermatids to spermatozoa). <italic>B</italic>. PP1&#x003b3;2 is prominently expressed in the cytoplasms of secondary spermatocytes, spermatids, and mature testicular spermatozoa. <italic>C</italic>. PPP1R11 is prominently expressed in the cytoplasm of haploid germ cells (from round spermatids through spermatozoa). <italic>D</italic>. Immunohistochemistry performed without primary antibody (negative control). Blue fluorescence indicates TO-PRO3 staining of nuclei.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g008"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Localization of PPP1R11 in the PP1&#x003b3;-null testis is essentially wild-type although fluorescence intensity is significantly reduced</title><p>Because PPP1R11 shows haploid germ cell-restricted expression, we performed an immunohistochemical evaluation of its expression pattern in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis where apoptosis is most pronounced in haploid germ cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Varmuza1">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Figure 9A</xref>, the localization of PPP1R11 appeared roughly similar in both PP1&#x003b3;-null and wild-type testis, though fluorescence intensity was significantly reduced in the former, and the depleted spermatids appeared to be disorganized in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis, possibly reflecting the apoptotic state of these cells. However, to determine the effect of the absence of PP1&#x003b3;2 vs. PP1&#x003b3;1 on the PP1&#x003b3;-null testicular phenotype, including effects on expression/stability of proteins with which PP1&#x003b3;2 interacts, we produced PP1&#x003b3;-null mice expressing transgenic PP1&#x003b3;2 specifically in the testis (PP1&#x003b3;2-rescue mice; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). Immunohistochemical staining of sections from PP1&#x003b3;2-rescue testis suggested a significant recovery of PPP1R11 expression levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Fig. 9A</xref>). Interestingly, a comparison of histological sections from the testis of PP1&#x003b3;-null and PP1&#x003b3;2-rescue mice revealed that PP1&#x003b3;2 expression in the mutant testis had an obvious anti-apoptotic effect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Fig. 9B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0004861-g009" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Testicular phenotypes related to the expression of PP1&#x003b3;2.</title><p><italic>A</italic>. Immunofluorescence of PP1&#x003b3;-null (KO), wild-type (WT), and PP1&#x003b3;2-rescue testis sections probed with anti-PPP1R11 antibody. Negative (&#x02212;) control&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;no primary antibody. <italic>B</italic>. Histological analysis of hematoxalin-stained testis sections from PP1&#x003b3;-null (Null) and PP1&#x003b3;2-rescue (Rescue) mice demonstrating an antiapoptotic effect of PP1&#x003b3;2. <italic>C</italic>. Western blot of testis protein extracts from PP1&#x003b3;-null (left lane), PP1&#x003b3;2-rescue (center lane), and wild-type (right lane) animals probed with anti-Sds22, anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, anti-PPP1R11, and anti-actin antibodies. <italic>D</italic>. Upper panel: PPP1R11 level in PP1&#x003b3;-null spleen is not significantly diminished compared to its level in wild-type spleen, but is significantly diminished in tissues normally expressing PP1&#x003b3;2 (testis and brain); Lower panel: histogram of immunosignal ratios of PPP1R11 in PP1&#x003b3;-null vs wild-type tissues. <italic>E</italic>. Northern blot analysis showing that <italic>Ppp1r11</italic> mRNA levels are comparable in PP1&#x003b3;-null and wild-type brain and testis, respectively. Actin mRNA levels are used as gel loading control. <italic>F</italic>. Left panel: PP1&#x003b3; isoform levels are increased and PPP1R11 levels rise dramatically in PP1&#x003b1;-null vs wild-type testis and brain, but PP1&#x003b3;1 and PPP1R11 levels in PP1&#x003b1;-null spleen are unchanged; Right panel: histogram of immunosignal ratios of PPP1R11 in PP1&#x003b1;-null vs wild-type tissues.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g009"/></fig><p>Western blotting also showed that the steady state level of PPP1R11 was significantly reduced in the PP1&#x003b3;-null testis, while the levels of Sds22 and actin were essentially unaltered relative to their wild-type levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Fig. 9C</xref>). In contrast, western blot analysis of testis extracts from the PP1&#x003b3;2-rescue mice showed that the PP1&#x003b3;2 steady state level was &#x0223c;35&#x00025; of wild-type, and, as expected, the level of PPP1R11 increased, though not quite to wild-type levels, while the levels of Sds22 and actin again appeared unaltered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Fig. 9C</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>The steady state level of PPP1R11 varies directly with the level of PP1&#x003b3;2 in apoptotic and non-apoptotic tissues</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Figure 9C</xref> could be interpreted in one of three ways: either (1) the actin/Sds22 levels appear unaltered in the PP1&#x003b3;-null testis protein extract because increased diploid germ cell/somatic cell proteins relative to haploid germ cell proteins are loaded on the gel due to predominant spermatid apoptosis; (2) the absence of the PP1&#x003b3; isoforms results in increased translation/stability of Sds22 and/or reduced translation/instability of PPP1R11; or (3) a combination of (1) and (2).</p><p>To further explore these options, we focused our attention on the fate of PPP1R11 steady state levels in wild-type and PP1&#x003b3;-null testis, brain, and spleen (where these tissues in wild-type animals show major, minor, and no PP1&#x003b3;2 expression, respectively). As demonstrated by western blot analysis, the PPP1R11 level in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis was reduced to about 14&#x00025; of wild-type testis PPP1R11 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Fig. 9D</xref>). Interestingly, the level of PPP1R11 was also diminished in PP1&#x003b3;-null brain to &#x0223c;59&#x00025; of wild-type brain PPP1R11, while in PP1&#x003b3;-null and wild-type spleen, the levels of PPP1R11 were similar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Fig. 9D</xref>). It is noteworthy that other than testis, the only tissue expressing the PP1&#x003b3;2 isoform, albeit at low levels, is brain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Strack1">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>, where no structural, apoptotic, or other neurological phenotype has been reported in PP1&#x003b3;-null mice. In addition, northern blot analysis showed that <italic>ppp1r11</italic> mRNA is present at comparable levels in wild-type and PP1&#x003b3;-null testis and brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Fig. 9E</xref>). Together, these results suggest that in haploid male germ cells undergoing morphogenesis, the presence of PP1&#x003b3;2 could be instrumental in maintaining adequate levels of PPP1R11.</p><p>Because the increase in PP1&#x003b1; and PP1&#x003b2; levels in germ cells from PP1&#x003b3;&#x02212;null testis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Chakrabarti2">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref> did not appear to compensate for the loss of PP1&#x003b3; isoforms with regard to steady state levels of PPP1R11 in those cells, we studied whether either PP1&#x003b3;1 or PP1&#x003b3;2 were up-regulated in PP1&#x003b1;-null testis, brain, or spleen, and if so, would the up-regulation of either or both correlate with any change in PPP1R11 levels. Of note, PP1&#x003b1;-null animals display no overt defect and, thus, appear phenotypically normal (Dr. Angus Nairn, unpublished results). Interestingly, in tissues where both PP1&#x003b3; isoforms are normally expressed (testis and brain), not only were the levels of both PP1&#x003b3; isoforms enhanced in PP1&#x003b1;-null mice compared to their wild-type levels, but the steady state level of PPP1R11 was significantly increased over the wild-type level (&#x0223c;160&#x00025; and &#x0223c;316&#x00025; respectively in PP1&#x003b1;-null testis and brain; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Fig. 9F</xref>). However, in PP1&#x003b1;-null spleen, a tissue where PP1&#x003b3;1 is normally abundant but PP1&#x003b3;2 is not expressed, PP1&#x003b3;1 and PPP1R11 levels did not appear to be affected by the loss of PP1&#x003b1; or the absence of PP1&#x003b3;2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g009">Fig. 9F</xref>). These results further support the idea that the presence or absence of PP1&#x003b3;2 has a positive effect on the translation efficiency or stability of PPP1R11 in both testis and brain.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>PPP1R11 may be ubiquitinated in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis</title><p>PPP1R11 was recently shown to enhance apoptosis via its Caspase3-mediated cleavage and subsequent degradation in actinomyosin D-treated HL60 cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. We have shown that the expression of PP1&#x003b3;2 in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis has an anti-apoptotic effect, and appears to enhance the steady state level of PPP1R11 in both apoptotic and non-apoptotic tissues. Because Caspase-mediated apoptosis is known to play an important role in eliminating defective germ cells in the post-natal developing wild-type testis, and proteins cleaved by this process are polyubiquitinated and degraded via the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Kwon1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>, we determined the ubiquitinated state of PPP1R11 in wild-type vs. PP1&#x003b3;-null testis. Western blot analysis with an anti-ubiquitin monoclonal antibody suggested that a protein, with an apparent molecular weight identical to that of PPP1R11 is considerably more ubiquitinated in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis extracts than in extracts from wild-type testis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g010">Fig. 10A</xref>). Additional western blot studies of anti-PPP1R11-immunoprecipitated testis extracts with the same anti-ubiquitin monoclonal antibody demonstrated that either this ubiquitinated protein is a PPP1R11-associated protein in testis or is PPP1R11 (or an N-terminal fragment thereof) itself (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0004861-g010">Fig. 10B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0004861-g010" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0004861.g010</object-id><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title>In PP1&#x003b3;-null testis, PPP1R11 is ubiquitinated or associated with an ubiquitinated protein whose apparent size is equivalent to that of PPP1R11.</title><p><italic>A</italic>. Western blot analysis of wild-type and PP1&#x003b3;-null testis protein extracts probed with either anti-mono- and poly-ubiquitinylated conjugates or anti-PPP1R11 antibodies, as indicated below the blots. <italic>B</italic>. Western blot of anti-PPP1R11 or preimmune serum immunoprecipitates from testis extracts probed with a monoclonal antibody that recognizes mono- and poly-ubiquitinylated conjugates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0004861.g010"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Previous studies established that aberrant male germ cell development and testicular apoptosis, particularly during spermiogenesis, were two dominant features of the male sterility phenotype in PP1&#x003b3;-null mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Varmuza1">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Chakrabarti2">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>. Because the latter study showed that PP1&#x003b3;1 localizes primarily in Leydig (somatic) cells in the testis, we have speculated that the absence of PP1&#x003b3;2 from developing spermatocytes and spermatids of PP1&#x003b3;-null mice is the predominant feature underlying the development of structurally abnormal male germ cell characters leading to their apoptotic demise in these mice. Therefore, the present study was initially undertaken to test the assumption that PP1&#x003b3;2 plays a singular, but as yet unknown role among PP1 isoforms in the development of mammalian male germ cells (particularly spermatids), and to begin to elucidate the biochemical basis of its uniqueness.</p><p>Our first goal was to identify potential wild-type testicular interaction(s) of PP1&#x003b3;2 with its regulators, PPP1R11 (inhibitor 3; I3; previously known as TCTEX5), a highly conserved and potent PP1 inhibitor genetically linked to the male sterility phenotypes of impaired sperm tail development and poor sperm motility in <italic>t</italic> complex mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-CebraThomas1">&#x0005b;37&#x0005d;</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Pilder3">&#x0005b;41&#x0005d;</xref>; and with PPP1R7 (Sds22), an evolutionarily ancient PP1 regulator bound to PP1&#x003b3;2 in mammalian caudal epididymal sperm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>. These prospective relationships were of particular interest because in yeast and in cultured mammalian somatic cells, PP1 isoforms were known to form trimeric complexes with PPP1R11 and Sds22 in which the PP1 isoforms were held in a catalytically inactive state <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Lesage1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Pedelini1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Our results thus far have indicated that in wild-type testis, PP1&#x003b3;2, PPP1R11, and Sds22 are present at their highest steady state levels in developing spermatids, and that these three proteins plus actin comprise a tetrameric (or parts of a larger) protein complex. While we could not determine the state of PP1&#x003b3;2 activity in this testicular complex, we have demonstrated that PP1&#x003b3;2 is rendered catalytically inactive in its cauda epididymal spermatozoon equivalent. We assume that PP1&#x003b3;2 inactivity is not an artifact of the protein purification process for the following reasons: (1) our results are in agreement with those of the aforementioned studies showing that PP1-PPP1R11-Sds22 trimers in yeast or somatic cell culture are catalytically inactive <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Lesage1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>; and (2) we used identical techniques here to those employed previously to purify a catalytically active complex of PP1&#x003b3;2 bound to 14-3-3&#x003b6; in sperm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang6">&#x0005b;42&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Because the role of a catalytically inactive PP1 complex could be relevant to the preservation of one or more of its component parts for future function in sperm during fertilization, our second goal was to determine the fate of PPP1R11 and Sds22 in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis and brain. Repeated analyses have established that the steady state protein (but not mRNA) level of PPP1R11 is dramatically diminished in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis, whereas the levels of Sds22 and actin remain relatively equivalent to their levels in wild-type testis. A simple explanation for this result is that lower PPP1R11 levels reflect the apoptotic loss of spermatids in the PP1&#x003b3;-null testis, while Sds22 and actin, which are also expressed in earlier germ cells, are upregulated in those cells (or in somatic cells in the case of actin) in the PP1&#x003b3;-null testis. A test of this explanation, an examination of PPP1R11 and Sds22 levels in PP1&#x003b3;-null non-apoptotic brain, demonstrated that cell loss in the apoptotic PP1&#x003b3;-null testis might not completely account for the diminished level of PPP1R11, as significantly diminished PPP1R11 levels and unperturbed Sds22 levels were noted in the non-apoptotic PP1&#x003b3;-null brain. These results demonstrated a correlation between diminished PPP1R11 levels and the absence of the PP1&#x003b3; isoforms irrespective of the apoptotic state of cells, a relationship whose probability has been raised by the finding that a significant increase in PPP1R11 levels in the PP1&#x003b1;&#x02013;null testis and brain correlates with the increased expression of &#x0201c;compensatory&#x0201d; PP1&#x003b3; isoforms. In addition, in the PP1&#x003b3;-null and the PP1&#x003b1;&#x02013;null spleen, a tissue in which PP1&#x003b3;1 is normally highly expressed, but PP1&#x003b3;2 is not expressed, PPP1R11 and Sds22 levels are neither diminished nor enhanced, but instead remain essentially wild-type. These results indicate that a primary role for PP1&#x003b3;2 in cells in which it is expressed could be to enhance the translation efficiency and/or stability of its own inhibitor, PPP1R11. Whether catalysis by an active pool of PP1&#x003b3;2 or the structure of the inactive PP1&#x003b3;2-PPP1R11-Sds22-actin complex described here contributes either directly or indirectly to maintenance of a stable steady state level of PPP1R11 in the testis is not known at this time.</p><p>We have also demonstrated that the expression of transgenic PP1&#x003b3;2 can significantly reduce or overcome programmed cell death in the PP1&#x003b3;-null testis. While admittedly not yet directly tested, it is tempting to speculate that this finding regarding PP1&#x003b3;2 is either directly or indirectly related to the correlation between its expression and enhanced steady state levels of PPP1R11 in all tissues so far tested. A recent study by Huang and Lee (2008) demonstrated that Caspase-mediated apoptosis in actinomyosin D-treated HL60 cells is controlled at the level of the ability of activated Caspase 3 to recognize PPP1R11 and cleave it at a site located between an upstream PP1 binding site and a downstream PP1 inhibitory site. When this cleavage site on PPP1R11 is altered so that Caspase 3 can no longer sever it, apoptosis in these cells is significantly reduced. Earlier studies have also shown that the cleaved products of Caspase 3-mediated male germ cell apoptosis in immature testis undergoing the primary wave of spermatogenesis are degraded by the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Kwon1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>. With this in mind, we have demonstrated that either PPP1R11 is ubiquitinated and migrates anomalously on SDS gels (the addition of one or more 8.5-kDa ubiquitin polypeptides to PPP1R11 might be masked, since non-ubiquitinated PPP1R11 normally migrates at nearly twice its calculated molecular weight on SDS gels <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Huang1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>), a ubiquitinated N-terminal fragment of PPP1R11 is present in the PP1&#x003b3;-null testis (anti-PPP1R11 antibodies used here were raised against PPP1R11 N-terminal peptides), or another ubiquitinated protein of apparent identical size associates with PPP1R11 in PP1&#x003b3;-null testis.</p><p>It remains puzzling why the other PP1 isoforms, PP1&#x003b1; and PP1&#x003b2;, are unable to enhance PPP1R11 levels, even though they are fully capable of interacting with it (and with Sds22 and actin) (data not shown), and appear to increase in amount in PP1&#x003b3;-null germ cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Chakrabarti2">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>. One possibility is that the unique and highly conserved C-terminus of the mammalian-specific, testis/sperm-restricted PP1&#x003b3;2 isoform has evolved to provide this function, whereas the C-termini of the other more evolutionarily ancient isoforms are not designed to do so. This idea is in keeping with the fact that mammalian sperm, in which PP1&#x003b3;2 exists as the only PP1 isoform, have evolved many novel structural and functional attributes that seemingly would require the evolution of original regulatory mechanisms. We are currently investigating this possibility.</p><p>In summary, our studies document, for the first time, the ability of PP1&#x003b3;2 to form a catalytically-inactive complex with PPP1R11, Sds22, and actin in testicular germ cells and sperm. Furthermore we also show that there exists a reciprocal relationship between the level of PP1&#x003b3;2, a testis- and sperm-restricted PP1 isoform present only in mammals, and the steady state level of PPPR11.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>All procedures involving animals used in this study were approved by the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences Animal Care and Use Committee and the Kent State University Animal Care and Use Committee.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Mice Used In This Study</title><p>Founder PP1&#x003b3;-null mice were a kind gift of Dr. Susan Varmuza (University of Toronto, Canada). To produce PP1&#x003b3;-null mice expressing transgenic PP1&#x003b3;2 in testis, a human <italic>Pgk2</italic> (phosphoglycerate kinase 2) promoter fragment was used &#x0005b;provided by Dr. John McCarrey (University of Texas, San Antonio, USA)&#x0005d;. This promoter fragment was subcloned into pBluescript SK&#x0002b; between the restriction sites Sac I and Xba I. Rat testis PP1&#x003b3;2 cDNA was subcloned downstream of the <italic>Pgk2</italic> promoter fragment between the BamHI and XhoI sites. An SV40 poly A signal was produced by PCR amplification of a pcDNA4.0 plasmid (forward and reverse oligonucleotide PCR primers were: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-CTCCTCGAGTCTCATGCTGGAGTTCT-3&#x02032;</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-CTCGGTACCACCATGATTACGCCAAG-3&#x02032;</named-content>, respectively), and the resultant fragment was subcloned downstream of the PP1&#x003b3;2 cDNA between the XhoI and KpnI sites. The entire fragment containing the <italic>Pgk2</italic> promoter, PP1&#x003b3;2 cDNA, and SV40 poly A signal was then excised from the pBluescript SK&#x0002b; vector with BamH1 and KpnI and used for pronuclear injection to produce transgenic mice at the Case Western Reserve University Transgenic Animal Facility (Cleveland, Ohio, USA). PP1&#x003b3;2 transgenic positive mice in a PP1&#x003b3; &#x02212;/&#x02212; background were obtained by first crossing transgenic founder mice with PP1&#x003b3; &#x02212;/&#x02212; CD1 female mice or PP1&#x003b3; &#x0002b;/&#x02212; male mice, then intercrossing PP1&#x003b3;2 transgenic/PP1&#x003b3;&#x0002b;/&#x02212; progeny. The presence of PP1&#x003b3;2 transgene in a PP1&#x003b3;-null background and subsequent expression of PP1&#x003b3;2 were verified by a combination of PCR, RT-PCR, and western blotting. A manuscript describing the complete phenotype of these mice is currently in preparation. Testis, brain, and spleen were also obtained from PP1&#x003b1;-null mice. A manuscript describing the generation of these mice is also in preparation.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Protein Extract Preparation</title><p>Testis, brain, spleen, lung, liver, and heart tissues were homogenized in Buffer B (10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.0, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, 10 mM benzamidine-HCl, 1 mM PMSF, 0.1 mM N-tosyl-L-phenylalanine chloromethyl ketone &#x0005b;TPCK&#x0005d;, 0.1&#x00025; &#x0005b;V/V&#x0005d; &#x003b2;-mecaptoethanol). The homogenates were centrifuged at 16,000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> to remove insoluble material.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Western Blot Analysis</title><p>Protein extracts boiled in Laemmli sample buffer and separated by 12&#x00025; SDS-PAGE were electrophoretically transferred to Immobilon-P PVDF membranes (Millipore Corp., Billerica, MA, USA). After blocking non-specific binding sites with 5&#x00025; nonfat dry milk in Tris-buffered saline (TBS: 25 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl), blots were incubated with primary antibody overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. All primary antibodies were commercially prepared. Anti-PP1&#x003b3;2 (Zymed Laboratories, San Francisco, CA, USA) was raised against a peptide corresponding to the unique, highly conserved carboxyl terminus of PP1&#x003b3;2 (amino acid residues 315 to 337, VGSGLNPSIQKASNYRNNTVLYE), 1&#x02236;5,000 dilution. The rabbit polyclonal anti-PPP1R11 (Affinity BioReagents, Golden, CO, USA) was raised against two synthetic peptides, the first containing the 1<sup>st</sup> to 16<sup>th</sup> amino acid residues (MAETGAGISETVTETT), and the second containing the 27<sup>th</sup> to 41<sup>st</sup> amino acid residues (EPENQSLTMKLRKRK), 1&#x02236;2,000 dilution. Anti-Sds22 (Affinity Bio Reagents, Golden, CO, USA) was raised against two synthetic peptides, the first containing the 70<sup>th</sup> to 84<sup>th</sup> amino acid residues (ETINLDRDAEDVDLC) and the second containing the 347<sup>th</sup> to 360<sup>th</sup> amino acid residues (LPSVRQIDATYVRF), 1&#x02236;2,000 dilution. Antibodies were affinity purified with the synthetic peptides conjugated to a sulfo-link column (Pierce, Rockford, IL, USA). Anti-mono- and polyubiquitinylated conjugates, monoclonal (clone FK2), was purchased from BIOMOL International, L.P. (Plymouth Meeting, PA, USA), 1&#x02236;1,000 dilution. After washing, blots were incubated with anti-rabbit/mouse secondary antibody (1&#x02236;2000 dilution) conjugated to horseradish peroxidase (GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ, USA) for 1 h at room temperature. Blots were washed with TTBS twice for 15 min each and four times for 5 min each, and then developed with a homemade ECL chemiluminescence kit.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Expression of Recombinant PPP1R11 in the pGEX vector</title><p>We inserted the full-length mouse <italic>PPP1R11</italic> cDNA into the pGEX vector, 4T-2 (GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ, USA) and expressed it as a glutathione S-transferase (GST) fusion protein in Escherichia coli. The recombinant protein was subsequently purified on a Glutathione Sepharose 4B affinity column.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>GST Pull-Down Assay</title><p>Glutathione Sepharose 4B beads (GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ, USA) bound to GST-PPP1R11 or GST alone (as a negative control) were incubated with mouse testis extracts with rocking for 2 h at 4&#x000b0;C. After washing, the proteins were eluted with 20 mM reduced glutathione, 50 mM Tris, pH 8.0. Western blot analysis was performed on the extracts used for pull-down assay and the eluted fractions to identify bound proteins.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Immunoprecipitation</title><p>Crude lysates or purified FPLC fractions of mouse testis were incubated for 1 h at 4&#x000b0;C with &#x0223c;5 &#x000b5;g of anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, anti-PPP1R11, or anti-Sds22 antibody or diluted rabbit pre-immune serum as a negative control. Protein G-Sepharose 4 Fast Flow beads (GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ, USA) were washed once with distilled water and twice with TTBS. Each extract/antibody solution was incubated with the beads by rocking for 1 h at 4&#x000b0;C. After incubation, the beads were washed once with TTBS and five times with Buffer B. After washing, the beads were resuspended in 2&#x000d7;SDS reducing sample buffer (6&#x00025;SDS, 25 mM Tris-HCl pH 6.5, 50 mM DTT, 10&#x00025; glycerol and Bromphenol blue), boiled for 10 min and centrifuged at 10,000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> for 10 min. Supernatants were separated by SDS-PAGE, followed by western blot analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Column Chromatography</title><p>All column procedures were conducted at room temperature following protocols from the manufacturer (GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ, USA) on an AKTA FPLC chromatographic system (GE Healthcare, Piscataway, NJ, USA). Mouse testis extracts were first passed through two anion-exchange columns pre-equilibrated with 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0: a HiTrap DEAE FF (1 ml) column and a Mono Q 5/50 GL (1 ml) column, with proteins eluting in a linear gradient of 0&#x02013;1 M NaCl in 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0. Pooled gradient fractions containing the co-eluted proteins, PP1&#x003b3;2, Sds22 and PPP1R11, from the MonoQ column were passed through the MonoQ column again and proteins were eluted in a linear gradient of 250&#x02013;550 mM NaCl in 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0. Subsequentially, the fractions containing the co-eluted proteins were combined and passed through a HiTrap Blue HP column pre-equilibrated with 50 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.0. Proteins were eluted in a linear gradient of 0&#x02013;1.5 M NaCl in 50 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.0. The final step of purification involved passing the co-eluting fractions through a size-exclusion column, a Superose 6 10/300 GL column pre-equilibrated with 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 1 mM EDTA and/or a Superdex 200 10/300 GL column pre-equilibrated with 20 mM sodium phosphate, 150 mM NaCl, pH 7.0. The same approach was employed to isolate PPP1R11/PP1/Sds22-containing fractions from mouse brain and PP1&#x003b3;-null mouse testis. Purified fractions were analyzed either by western blotting with anti-PPP1R11, anti-PP1&#x003b3;2 and anti-Sds22, by immunoprecipitation, or concentrated with Centricon-10 filters (Millipore Corp., Bedford, MA, USA) for native PAGE analysis. A molecular weight calibration curve for Superdex 200 was generated with the following standards: Catalase (240-kDa), Phosphorylase b (194-kDa), Aldolase (158-kDa), Albumin (68-kDa) and Ovalbumin (43-kDa).</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>Native PAGE</title><p>Column fractions were mixed with 5&#x000d7; sample buffer (31&#x00025; &#x0005b;V/V&#x0005d; 1 M Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 5&#x00025; &#x0005b;V/V&#x0005d; 1&#x00025; &#x0005b;W/V&#x0005d; bromophenol blue solution, 50&#x00025; &#x0005b;V/V&#x0005d; glycerol) and separated by electrophoresis through a 10&#x00025; Tris-HCl Ready Gel (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA) at &#x0223c;20&#x02013;25 mA for about three hours followed by western blot analysis with anti-PPP1R11, anti-Sds22, anti-PP1&#x003b3;2, or anti-E9 antibodies &#x0005b;E9 antibody: mouse monoclonal anti-PP1c (PP1 catalytic subunit) antibody recognizing all PP1c isoforms from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc. (Santa Cruz, CA)&#x0005d;.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Phosphatase Assay</title><p>Phosphatase activity was assayed using a <sup>32</sup>P-labeled <italic>glycogen phosphorylase a</italic> substrate, as previously reported <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0004861-Vijayaraghavan1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>. Briefly, purified fractions of caudal sperm extracts produced by anion exchange and size-exclusion chromatography were preincubated in a buffer containing 1 mM Mn<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> in a total volume of 30 &#x000b5;l at 30&#x000b0;C for 5 min, followed by addition of labeled <italic>phosphorylase a</italic>. At the end of a 10-minute incubation, the reaction was terminated with 95 &#x000b5;l of cold 20&#x00025; trichloroacetic acid (TCA), after which the reaction tubes were centrifuged for 5 min at 12,000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> at 4&#x000b0;C. <sup>32</sup>PO<sub>4</sub> counts released from <italic>phosphorylase a</italic> into the supernatants were quantitated. One unit of enzyme activity is defined as the amount of enzyme that catalyzes the release of 1 nmol of <sup>32</sup>PO<sub>4</sub> /min.</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Immnohistochemistry of Mouse Testis</title><p>Testes were fixed by immersion in 4&#x00025; paraformaldehyde in PBS at 4&#x000b0;C for 40 h. The fixed testes were transferred to 75&#x00025; Ethanol and dehydrated, permeabilized, and embedded in paraffin using a Shandon Tissue Processor (Thermo Electron Corp., Waltham, MA, USA). Multiple 8 &#x000b5;m-thick sections of the whole testis were attached to poly-L-lysine-coated slides, deparaffinized, and rehydrated using a standard procedure. Antigen retrieval was performed using 1&#x000d7;Antigen Retrieval Citra Solution (BioGenex, San Ramon, CA, USA). Sections immersed in Citra solution were microwaved for three separate 3-min periods on high setting, with a cooling period of 1 min between each heating cycle. Slides were incubated for 1 h at room temperature in a blocking solution containing 10&#x00025; normal goat serum in PBS, and then incubated with primary antibodies for 2 h at room temperature or overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. After this, slides were washed three times with PBS, and incubated with corresponding secondary antibody (1&#x02236;250) conjugated to indocarbocyanine (Cy3; Jackson Laboratories, West, Grove, PA) for 1 h at room temperature. The slides were washed five times with PBS, mounted with Vectashield (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA) mounting media, and examined using a Fluo View 500 Confocal Fluorescence Microscope (Olympus, Melville, NY, USA). Control slides were processed in the same manner except that the primary antibody incubation was omitted. Cell nuclei were stained with TO-PRO&#x000ae;-3 iodide (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, California) (1&#x02236;500) for 20 mins.</p></sec><sec id="s4l"><title>Northern Blot</title><p>A 20 &#x000b5;l mixture containing 20 &#x000b5;g of total RNA, 2 &#x000b5;l 10&#x000d7;MOPS buffer, 4 &#x000b5;l HCHO (37&#x00025; solution, Amresco, OH, USA), 10 &#x000b5;l deionized formamide (Amresco, OH, USA) and 1 &#x000b5;l Ethidium Bromide (200 &#x000b5;g/ml), was heated at 85&#x000b0;C for 10 min, and chilled on ice for another 10 min. A 2 &#x000b5;l aliquot of 10&#x000d7; gel loading buffer (50&#x00025; Glycerol, 10 mM EDTA pH 8.0, 0.25&#x00025; w/v bromophenol blue, 0.25&#x00025; w/v xylene cyanol FF) was added to each sample, and samples were vortexed and briefly centrifuged. Samples were loaded onto 1&#x00025; agarose/MOPS gel (SeaKem GTG Agarose, Cambrex, NJ, USA), and electrophoresed at 70 V. The gel was denatured in a solution of 0.05 M NaOH and 1.5 M NaCl for 30 min, neutralized in a solution of 0.5 M Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 1.5 M NaCl, and then equilibrated in 20&#x000d7;SSC. The gel was transferred to Hybond-XL nylon membrane (GE Healthcare, NJ, USA) in 10&#x000d7;SSC for 16 hours. The membrane containing RNA was then baked at 85&#x000b0;C for 2 hours, after which it was prehybridized in 8 ml modified Church buffer (1 mM EDTA, pH 8.0, 0.5 M NaHPO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.2, and 5&#x00025;SDS) for one hour at 65&#x000b0;C in a water bath. Fresh Church buffer containing radiolabeled probe (actin cDNA or PPP1R11 cDNA labeled with P<sup>32-</sup>dCTP &#x0005b;MP Biomedicals, OH, USA&#x0005d;) was used for hybridization overnight at 65&#x000b0;C in a water bath. The membrane was then washed in 1&#x000d7;SSC/0.1&#x00025;SDS three times for 2 min each at room temperature, followed by washing in 0.1&#x000d7;SSC/0.1&#x00025;SDS twice for 5 min in a 65&#x000b0;C water bath. After washing, the membrane was dried at room temperature, covered with plastic wrap, exposed to film in a cassette with an intensifying screen overnight, and was then developed in a Typhoon&#x02122; automated film developer (GE Healthcare, NJ, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s4m"><title>Hematoxylin Staining of Testis</title><p>Testes were fixed overnight by immersion in 4&#x00025; formaldehyde in PBS and then transferred to 70&#x00025; ethanol and stored at 4&#x000b0;C until processed further. The fixed testis was embedded in paraffin using a Shandon Tissue Processor (Thermo Electron Corp., Waltham, MA, USA). Multiple 8 &#x000b5;m sections were attached to poly L-lysine coated slides and dried overnight at room temperature. The tissue sections were deparaffinized in Citrisolv (Fisher Scientific, Pittsburgh, PA, USA), rehydrated through a graded series of decreasing ethanol percentages in distilled water for 5 minutes. 500 &#x000b5;L of hematoxylin stain (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) was added to each section for 2 minutes, and slides were rinsed in tap water for 2 minutes. The water was replaced once during the rinse. Slides were then dipped 10 times in fresh acid rinse solution (1 ml glacial acetic acid in 49 ml distilled water) and placed in 0.1&#x00025; NaHCO<sub>3</sub> for one minute, followed by dipping 10 times in fresh distilled water. Sections were dehydrated through a graded series of increasing ethanol percentages then dipped in Citrisolv for one minute. Excess Citrisolv was wicked, and sections were mounted for histology in a drop of DPX, followed by observation by light microscopy.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We greatly appreciate the gifts of a human <italic>Pgk2</italic> promoter fragment from Dr. John McCarrey (University of Texas, San Antonio, TX, USA) and PP1&#x003b3;-null mice from Dr. Susan Varmuza (University of Toronto, Toronto, Canada). We also thank Elizabeth Cedars (Rockefeller University, New York, NY, USA) for preparing PP1&#x003b1;-null tissues, Kimberley Myers, and David Soler for their expert help in the laboratory. We thank Dr. Mike Model for his assistance on confocal laser scanning microscopy, and Dr. Michael Kinter (Cleveland Clinic Lerner Research Institute, Cleveland, OH, USA) for his critical input on the microsequencing results.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0004861-Chakrabarti1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakrabarti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Soler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Protein phosphatase PP1 gamma 2 in sperm morphogenesis and epididymal initiation of sperm motility.</article-title><source>Asian J Androl</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17589781</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Vijayaraghavan1"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Sperm Motility Development in the Epididymis Is Associated with Decreased Glycogen Synthase Kinase-3 and Protein Phosphatase 1 Activity.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>718</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8835395</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Smith1"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautman</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>EFdaCe</given-names></name><name><surname>Greengard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Primate Sperm Contain Protein Phosphatase 1, a Biochemical Mediator of Motility.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8835396</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Sasaki1"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Irino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Identification of members of the protein phosphatase 1 gene family in the rat and enhanced expression of protein phosphatase 1 alpha gene in rat hepatocellular carcinomas.</article-title><source>Jpn J Cancer Res</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>1272</fpage><lpage>1280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2177460</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Puntoni1"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puntoni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa-Moruzzi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Phosphorylation of protein phosphatase-1 isoforms by cdc2-cyclin B in vitro.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biochem</source><volume>171</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9201703</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Bennett1"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyulcheva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Alphey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Towards a comprehensive analysis of the protein phosphatase 1 interactome in Drosophila.</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>364</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17007873</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Meiselbach1"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meiselbach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sticht</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Enz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Structural analysis of the protein phosphatase 1 docking motif: molecular description of binding specificities identifies interacting proteins.</article-title><source>Chem Biol</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16426971</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Walsh1"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamont</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Proteins interacting with Saccharomyces cerevisiae type 1 protein phosphatase catalytic subunit identified by single-step affinity purification and mass spectrometry.</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><volume>365</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17200566</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Huang1"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Protein phosphatase-1 inhibitor-3 is an in vivo target of caspase-3 and participates in the apoptotic response.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>283(26)</volume><fpage>18135</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18450750</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Helps1"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helps</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergidou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaskell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Characterisation of a novel Drosophila melanogaster testis specific PP1 inhibitor related to mammalian inhibitor-2: identification of the site of interaction with PP1.</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>438</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9821974</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Fardilha1"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fardilha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fidalgo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Alternatively spliced protein variants as potential therapeutic targets for male infertility and contraception.</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><volume>1030</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659832</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Hrabchak1"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hrabchak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Varmuza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Identification of the spermatogenic zip protein Spz1 as a putative protein phosphatase-1 (PP1) regulatory protein that specifically binds the PP1cgamma2 splice variant in mouse testis.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>37079</fpage><lpage>37086</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15226296</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Hrabchak2"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hrabchak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Varmuza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A testis specific isoform of endophilin B1, endophilin B1t, interacts specifically with protein phosphatase-1c gamma2 in mouse testis and is abnormally expressed in PP1c gamma null mice.</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>4635</fpage><lpage>4644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17381077</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Huang2"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Sperm PP1&#x003b3;2 Is Regulated by a Homologue of the Yeast Protein Phosphatase Binding Protein Sds22.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>1936</fpage><lpage>1942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12444072</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Vijayaraghavan2"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautman</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Goueli</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>A tyrosine-phosphorylated 55-kilodalton motility-associated bovine sperm protein is regulated by cyclic adenosine 3&#x02032;,5&#x02032;-monophosphates and calcium.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>1450</fpage><lpage>1457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9166697</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Huang3"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozarowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Darzynkiewicz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Protein phosphatase-1 inhibitor-3 is co-localized to the nucleoli and centrosomes with PP11 and PP1, respectively.</article-title><source>Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics</source><volume>443</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16256067</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Bajpai1"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bajpai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>AKAP3 Selectively Binds PDE4A Isoforms in Bovine Spermatozoa.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16177223</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Huang4"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Increased Phosphorylation of a Distinct Subcellular Pool of Protein Phosphatase, PP1&#x003b3;2, During Epididymal Sperm Maturation.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>70</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14568912</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Vijayaraghavan3"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>NagDas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Winfrey</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Subcellular localization of the regulatory subunits of cyclic adenosine 3&#x02032;,5&#x02032;-monophosphate-dependent protein kinase in bovine spermatozoa.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod Dec</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>1517</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Mishra1"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Somanath</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Binding and Inactivation of the Germ Cell-Specific Protein Phosphatase PP1&#x003b3;2 by Sds22 During Epididymal Sperm Maturation.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>69</volume><fpage>1572</fpage><lpage>1579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12826576</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Cohen1"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimmo</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year><article-title>The purification and characterization of protein phosphatase inhibitor-1 from rabbit skeletal muscle.</article-title><source>Biochem Soc Trans</source><volume>69</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">205460</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Nimmo1"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nimmo</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year><article-title>The regulation of glycogen metabolism. Purification and characterisation of protein phosphatase inhibitor-1 from rabbit skeletal muscle.</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">208844</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Ohkura1"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohkura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagida</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Pombe gene Sds22&#x0002b; essential for a midmitotic transition encodes a leucine-rich repeat protein that positively modulates protein phosphatase-1.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1846086</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Renouf1"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renouf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beullens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikela</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Molecular cloning of a human polypeptide related to yeast Sds22, a regulator of protein phosphatase-1.</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>375</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7498485</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Ceulemans1"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ceulemans</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Van</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Callejon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Beullens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stalmans</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Structure and splice products of the human gene encoding sds22, a putative mitotic regulator of protein phosphatase-1.</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><volume>262</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10231361</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Dinischiotu1"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dinischiotu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beullens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stalmans</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Identification of Sds22 as an inhibitory subunit of protein phosphatase-1 in rat liver nuclei.</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>402</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9037183</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Zhang1"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Identification and characterisation of the human HCG V gene product as a novel inhibitor of protein phosphatase-1.</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>16728</fpage><lpage>16734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843442</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Huang5"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Somanath</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakrabarti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Changes in Intracellular Distribution and Activity of Protein Phosphatase PP1&#x003b3;2 and Its Regulating Proteins in Spermatozoa Lacking AKAP4.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod Feb</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>392</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Lesage1"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lesage</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Beullens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedelini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Gimeno</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Waelkens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>A complex of catalytically inactive protein phosphatase-1 sandwiched between Sds22 and inhibitor-3.</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>8909</fpage><lpage>8919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630778</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Pedelini1"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedelini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ari&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Casamayor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>YPI1 and SDS22 proteins regulate the nuclear localization and function of yeast type 1 phosphatase Glc7.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>3282</fpage><lpage>3292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17142459</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Hugo1"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hugo</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeyer</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatchell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stalmans</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Binding of the Concave Surface of the Sds22 Superhelix to the 4/ 5/ 6-Triangle of Protein Phosphatase-1.</article-title><source>JBC</source><volume>2002; 277</volume><fpage>47331</fpage><lpage>47337</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Han1"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Expression of a novel T-complex testis expressed 5 (Tctex5) in mouse testis, epididymis, and spermatozoa.</article-title><source>Mol Reprod Dev</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>1132</fpage><lpage>1140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17342733</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Varmuza1"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varmuza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurisicova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Okano</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boekelheide</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Spermiogenesis is impaired in mice bearing a targeted mutation in the protein phosphatase 1cgamma gene.</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>205</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9882500</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Strack1"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebner</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadzinski</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Colbran</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Differential cellular and subcellular localization of protein phosphatase 1 isoforms in brain.</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><volume>413</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10502246</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Chakrabarti2"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chakrabarti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Orth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Analysis of Ppp1cc-null Mice Suggests a Role for PP1gamma2 in Sperm Morphogenesis.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>992</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17301292</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Kwon1"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Ubiquitin C-terminal hydrolase L-1 is essential for the early apoptotic wave of germinal cells and for sperm quality control during spermatogenesis.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15744022</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-CebraThomas1"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cebra-Thomas</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>Allele- and haploid-specific product generated by alternative splicing from a mouse t complex responder locus candidate.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>349</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1987476</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Pilder1"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>A novel mouse chromosome 17 hybrid sterility locus: implications for the origin of t haplotypes.</article-title><source>Genetics</source><volume>129</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1936961</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Pilder2"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Olds-Clarke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Hybrid sterility-6: a mouse t complex locus controlling sperm flagellar assembly and movement.</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><volume>159</volume><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8405685</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Hui1"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The mouse T complex gene Tsga2, encoding polypeptides located in the sperm tail and anterior acrosome, maps to a locus associated with sperm motility and sperm-egg interaction abnormalities.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16354795</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Pilder3"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilder</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Samant</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The molecular basis of &#x0201c;curlicue&#x0201d;: a sperm motility abnormality linked to the sterility of t haplotype homozygous male mice.</article-title><source>Soc Reprod Fertil</source><issue>Suppl 63</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>133</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="pone.0004861-Huang6"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Protein 14-3-3 Binds to Protein Phosphatase PP1&#x003b3;2 in Bovine Epididymal Spermatozoa.</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><volume>71</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15028637</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work was supported by NIH grants R01 HD38520 (SV), HD31164 (SP), and DA10044 (ACN). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article> 