<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Biol Chem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jbc</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Biological Chemistry</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9258</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1083-351X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">7733</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M806192200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19129197</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>DNA: Replication, Repair, Recombination, and Chromosome Dynamics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cooperativity of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 with Rad54 in the Resolution of Recombination and Replication Intermediates<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">&#x00053;&#x020de;</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2"/></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matulova</surname><given-names>Petra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1f73f80N0x1db06f0">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marini</surname><given-names>Victoria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1f73f80N0x1db06f0">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>Rebecca C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1f73f80N0x1db06f0">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sisakova</surname><given-names>Alexandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1f73f80N0x1db06f0">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>Youngho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1f73f80N0x1db06f0">&#x000b6;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rothstein</surname><given-names>Rodney</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1f73f80N0x1db06f0">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>Patrick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1f73f80N0x1db06f0">&#x000b6;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krejci</surname><given-names>Lumir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x1f73f80N0x1db06f0">&#x02021;</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x1f73f80N0x1db06f0"><label>&#x02021;</label>National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Masaryk University, Brno 62500, Czech Republic, <label>&#x000b6;</label>Department of Molecular Biophysics and Biochemistry, Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, Connecticut 06520, and <label>&#x000a7;</label>Department of Genetics and Development, Columbia University Medical Center, New York, New York 10032-2704</aff><author-notes><fn id="cor1"><label>1</label><p> To whom correspondence should be addressed: National Centre for Biomolecular Research, Masaryk University, Kamenice 5/A4, Brno 62500, Czech Republic. Tel.: 420-549493767; Fax: 420-549492556; E-mail: <email>lkrejci@chemi.muni.cz</email>. </p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the copyright element. --><volume>284</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>7733</fpage><lpage>7745</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009, The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Inc.</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><p><italic>Author's Choice</italic></p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License</ext-link> applies to Author Choice Articles</p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="zbc01209007733.pdf"/><abstract><p>The <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 protein complex, a DNA structure-specific endonuclease, helps preserve genomic integrity by resolving pathological DNA structures that arise from damaged or aborted replication forks and may also play a role in the resolution of DNA intermediates arising through homologous recombination. Previous yeast two-hybrid studies have found an interaction of the Mus81 protein with Rad54, a Swi2/Snf2-like factor that serves multiple roles in homologous recombination processes. However, the functional significance of this novel interaction remains unknown. Here, using highly purified <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> proteins, we show that Rad54 strongly stimulates the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 nuclease activity on a broad range of DNA substrates. This nuclease enhancement does not require ATP binding nor its hydrolysis by Rad54. We present evidence that Rad54 acts by targeting the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 complex to its DNA substrates. In addition, we demonstrate that the Rad54-mediated enhancement of the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1) nuclease function is evolutionarily conserved. We propose that Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 together with Rad54 efficiently process perturbed replication forks to promote recovery and may constitute an alternative mechanism to the resolution/dissolution of the recombination intermediates by Sgs1&#x000b7;Top3. These findings provide functional insights into the biological importance of the higher order complex of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 or its orthologue with Rad54.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes><fn-group><fn id="fn1"><label>*</label><p>This work was supported, in whole or in part, by <grant-sponsor>National Institutes of Health</grant-sponsor> Grants <grant-num>ES07061</grant-num> (to P. S.), <grant-num>GM57814</grant-num> (to P. S.), <grant-num>GM50237</grant-num> (to R. R.), <grant-num>GM67055</grant-num> (to R. R.), and <grant-num>GM73567</grant-num> (to R. C. B.). This study was also supported by <grant-sponsor>Wellcome International Senior Research Fellowship</grant-sponsor><grant-num>WT076476</grant-num>, <grant-sponsor>EMBO/HHMI</grant-sponsor> start up program, <grant-sponsor>Ministry of Education Youth and Sport of the Czech Republic</grant-sponsor> Grants <grant-num>ME 888</grant-num>, <grant-num>MSM 0021622413</grant-num>, and <grant-num>LC06030</grant-num>, and by the <grant-sponsor>Grant Agency of Czech Republic</grant-sponsor> Grants <grant-num>GACR 301/09/1917</grant-num> and <grant-num>GACR 203/09/HO46</grant-num>. The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked &#x0201c;<italic>advertisement</italic>&#x0201d; in accordance with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>&#x00053;&#x020de;</label><p>The on-line version of this article (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jbc.org">http://www.jbc.org</ext-link>) contains supplemental Figs. 1&#x02013;4.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label><inline-graphic xlink:href="flower.gif"/></label><p><italic>Author's Choice</italic>&#x02014;Final version full access.</p></fn></fn-group></notes></front><body><p>Barriers arising from DNA structures or lesions caused by endogenous and exogenous genotoxic agents are frequently encountered during DNA replication. Because of this, the successful completion of DNA replication relies on its coordination with a variety of replication fork repair and restart mechanisms. Several such mechanisms have been described. Depending on the circumstance, a mechanism that employs end tail repriming, template switch, fork regression and recovery, or translesion DNA synthesis may be used (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>). Alternatively, the perturbed fork can be cleaved, creating a DNA double-strand break that is repaired by the homologous recombination machinery in a manner that leads to fork restart (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>).</p><p>Mounting evidence has implicated the Mus81 protein in the processing of stalled DNA replication forks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>). The <italic>mus81</italic> mutant exhibits hypersensitivity to methyl methanesulfonate, camptothecin (CPT),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">2</xref> UV, and hydroxyurea (HU), reagents that in general cause replication fork stalling or collapse, and it also shows synthetic interactions with mutations in DNA replication proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>). Mus81 inactivation results in elevated levels of genomic instability, elicits checkpoint activation, and also leads to checkpoint-dependent cell cycle arrest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>). Mus81 is a member of the XPF family of endonucleases that play crucial roles in various DNA repair processes, including nucleotide excision repair, DNA interstrand cross-link repair, and homology-directed repair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>). XPF and its homologs function in the context of a heterodimeric complex with a partner protein. Mms4 (Eme1 in fission yeast and human) is the partner protein for Mus81, and the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 complex shows a preference for branched DNA structures that are believed to arise during the processing of stalled or collapsed replication forks as well as during recombination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>).</p><p>In general, Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 prefers to cleave substrates with three- and four-way junctions containing a 5&#x02032; end at the junction, which serves to direct the cleavage reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>). Mus81 in complex with Mms4 or Eme1 also cleaves nicked Holliday junctions (HJ), and to a much lesser degree, intact HJs as well (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>). Whether the HJ represents a physiological substrate for the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1) complex remains unclear. It has been also suggested that the activity of the Mus81 complex on intact HJ may be enhanced by a cellular factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>). Nevertheless, <italic>mus81</italic>/<italic>mms4</italic>/<italic>eme1</italic> mutants show severe meiotic phenotypes, indicating an essential role of this complex in processing recombination intermediates during meiotic recombination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>).</p><p>Several models have been postulated in regard to the role of homologous recombination in processing stalled, blocked, and collapsed replication forks as well as their restart (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>). Furthermore, Mus81 was suggested to be required for processing recombination intermediates that form downstream of collapsed replication forks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>). In these models recombinational processing or repair of the damaged or collapsed forks is initiated via the assembly of the Rad51 nucleoprotein filament on single-stranded DNA to mediate the invasion of the sister chromatid. The product of this DNA strand invasion reaction is a structure called a D-loop, and this step appears to be enhanced by the Swi2/Snf2-like factor Rad54 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>). Interestingly, Mus81 was initially identified in a two-hybrid screen for Rad54 interaction partners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>). Here, using purified proteins, we show a direct association between Rad54 and Mus81 and present data to reveal a dramatic stimulation of the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 nuclease activity by Rad54. In addition, we demonstrate that the ATP binding and hydrolysis by Rad54 is not required for Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 enhancement and that Rad54 acts by targeting the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 complex to its substrates. We discuss the biological significance of the physical and functional interactions between Rad54 and Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1).</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</title><p><italic>Purification of Rad54 Protein and Mutants</italic>&#x02014;The expression and purification of Rad54 was carried out as described by Raschle <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>) with slight modifications. The cells (30 g) were resuspended in 200 ml of lysis buffer C (50 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 10% sucrose, 10 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 1 m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, 0.01% Nonidet P-40, protease inhibitors) containing 0.6 <sc>m</sc> KCl and lysed by sonication. All subsequent steps were performed at 4 &#x000b0;C. The lysate was clarified by centrifugation for 50 min at 100,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> and applied sequentially onto a 20-ml Q-Sepharose (Amersham Biosciences) column and a 20-ml SP-Sepharose (Amersham Biosciences) column. The SP-Sepharose column was developed with a 210-ml gradient of 150&#x02013;1000 m<sc>m</sc> KCl in buffer K (20 m<sc>m</sc> K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.5, 20% glycerol and 0.5 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 0.01% Nonidet P-40, and 1 m<sc>m</sc> &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol). <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> Rad54 protein was eluted at 400 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, and the peak fractions were mixed with 1 ml of His-Select nickel affinity gel (Sigma) for 30 min. The beads were washed with buffer K containing 10 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole and 600 m<sc>m</sc> KCl and eluted with a step-gradient using 50, 150, and 270 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole in buffer K. The 50 and 150 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole fractions were concentrated in a Vivaspin concentrator (Sigma) and stored in small portions at -80 &#x000b0;C. The human Rad54 protein and <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> rad54-K341A and rad54-K341R mutant proteins were expressed and purified according to published procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>). The concentration of all these proteins was determined by densitometric scanning of SDS-polyacrylamide gels containing multiple loadings of purified proteins against known quantities of bovine serum albumin.</p><p><italic>Purification of Mus81 and Mus81</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>Mms4</italic>&#x02014;The <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> protein expression constructs were generous gifts from Steven Brill (Rutgers University). Protein expression and purification was based on a previously described procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>). <italic>E. coli</italic> cells (21 g of cell paste) were resuspended in 80 ml of cell lysis buffer C containing 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl. After sonication, the crude lysate was clarified by centrifugation (100,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>, 90 min). The clarified lysate was applied sequentially onto Q-Sepharose (20 ml) and then SP-Sepharose (20 ml). Proteins were eluted from SP-Sepharose with a 200-ml gradient of 150&#x02013;1000 m<sc>m</sc> KCl in buffer K. Mus81 or Mms4-Mus81 fractions were pooled and mixed with 1 ml of His-Select nickel affinity gel for 1 h at 4 &#x000b0;C. After extensive washing with buffer K containing 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl and 10 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole, the bound proteins were eluted using 50, 150, and 300 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole in buffer K containing 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl. The 150 and 300 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole fractions were pooled and loaded on a 1 ml hydroxyapatite column (Bio-Rad), and proteins were eluted with a 10-ml gradient from 0 to 500 m<sc>m</sc> KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> in buffer K. Peak fractions were pooled, loaded onto a 1-ml Mono S column (GE Healthcare), and eluted with a 10-ml gradient from 150 to 1000 m<sc>m</sc> KCl in buffer K. Pooled fractions were and stored in small portions at -80 &#x000b0;C.</p><p><italic>Purification of Mus81</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>Eme1</italic>&#x02014;The Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 expression construct was a kind gift from Stephen West (Cancer Research UK), and protein complex was expressed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>). Lysate was prepared from 10 g of <italic>E. coli</italic> cell paste using sonication in 50 ml of buffer C containing 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl. The cleared lysate was applied sequentially onto a 7-ml Q-Sepharose column and a 7-ml SP-Sepharose column. Proteins were eluted from the SP-Sepharose column with a 70-ml gradient from 150 to 800 m<sc>m</sc> KCl in buffer K. The peak fractions were pooled and mixed with 1 ml of His-Select nickel affinity gel for 2 h at 4 &#x000b0;C. The column was washed with 10 ml of buffer K containing 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl and 10 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole, and the bound proteins were eluted using 50, 150, 300, and 500 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole in buffer K containing 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl. The 150, 300, and 500 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole fractions were loaded onto a 1-ml hydroxyapatite column which was eluted with a 10-ml gradient from 0 to 500 m<sc>m</sc> KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> in buffer K. The peak fractions were concentrated and stored in 5-&#x003bc;l aliquots at -80 &#x000b0;C.</p><p><italic>Expression and Purification of Fen1</italic>&#x02014;The plasmid for expression of Fen1 in <italic>E. coli</italic> was a generous gift from Binghui Shen (City of Hope National Medical Center). Fen1 protein was expressed and purified by a method modified from that described for the human FEN-1 protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>). Lysate was prepared from 6 g of <italic>E. coli</italic> cell paste using sonication in 30 ml of buffer C containing 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl. The crude lysate was clarified by centrifugation (100,000 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>, 90 min). The clarified lysate was applied sequentially onto a 7-ml Q-Sepharose column and a 7-ml SP-Sepharose column. The SP-Sepharose column was developed with a 70-ml gradient from 0 to 800 m<sc>m</sc> KCl in buffer K. The peak fractions were pooled and mixed with 0.5 ml of His-Select nickel affinity gel. The beads were washed with 10 column volumes of buffer K containing 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl and 5 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole. The bound proteins were eluted from the affinity beads using 50, 150, 300, and 500 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole in buffer K containing 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl. The 150, 300, and 500 m<sc>m</sc> imidazole fractions were pooled and further fractionated in a 0.5-ml Mono S column with a 5-ml gradient of 220 to 700 m<sc>m</sc> KCl in buffer K. Fractions with purified Fen1 were pooled, concentrated in a Vivaspin concentrator, and then stored in 5-&#x003bc;l aliquots at -80 &#x000b0;C.</p><p><italic>DNA Substrates</italic>&#x02014;Oligonucleotides were purchased from VBC Biotech. The sequences of the oligonucleotides and the structures of DNA substrates made from these oligonucleotides are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>. The asterisk in the substrates denotes end modification by a fluorescent dye (fluorescein or Cy3). The substrates were prepared by mixing an equimolar amount of the constituent oligonucleotides in the hybridization buffer (50 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 100 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 10 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>) heated at 90 &#x000b0;C for 3 min and cooled slowly to room temperature to allow DNA annealing. The substrates were purified by fractionation in a 1-ml Mono Q column (GE Healthcare) with a 20-ml gradient of 50&#x02013;1000 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl in 10 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.5. Peak fractions were filtered dialyzed into 50 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, containing 5 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub> and concentrated in a Vivaspin concentrator with a 5-kDa cutoff. The concentration of the DNA substrates was determined by absorbance measurement at 260 nm.</p><p><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p><bold>DNA substrates used in this study</bold> The list includes oligonucleotides used in substrate construction. In each substrate schematic, the numbers denote the constituent oligonucleotides and are positioned at the 5&#x02032; end of these oligonucleotides. The asterisk denotes the position of the fluorescent dye (FITC or Cy3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc014096927t001"></graphic></table-wrap></p><p><italic>Affinity Pulldown Studies</italic>&#x02014;<italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Rad54-containing protein complexes were captured using S-protein-agarose (Novagen), specific for the S-tag on Rad54. Purified Rad54 (4 &#x003bc;g in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref> and 3 &#x003bc;g in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>C</italic></xref>) was incubated with Mus81 (4 &#x003bc;g), Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (3 &#x003bc;g), Rad51 (4 &#x003bc;g), or Fen1 (3 &#x003bc;g) in 30 &#x003bc;l of buffer T (20 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 150 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 1 m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, 0.5 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, and 0.01% Nonidet P-40) for 30 min at 4 &#x000b0;C. The reactions were mixed with 15 &#x003bc;l of S-Protein-agarose at 4 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and then treated with DNase I (2 units, New England Biolabs) for 10 min at 37 &#x000b0;C. After washing the beads twice with 150 &#x003bc;l of buffer T, the bound proteins were eluted with 30 &#x003bc;l of 5% SDS. The supernatant, wash, and SDS eluate, 10 &#x003bc;l each, were subject to SDS-PAGE analysis.</p><p><italic>Nuclease Assay</italic>&#x02014;The nuclease assay with Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 was performed essentially as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>). Reaction mixtures containing the indicated amount of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 and 6 n<sc>m</sc> DNA substrate in 20 &#x003bc;l of buffer N (20 m<sc>m</sc> Tris, pH 8.0, 100 m<sc>m</sc> NaCl, 100 &#x003bc;g/ml bovine serum albumin, 0.2 m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, 5% glycerol, and 10 m<sc>m</sc> MgCl<sub>2</sub>) were incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for the indicated times. After deproteinization by incubation with 0.1% SDS and 500 &#x003bc;g/ml of proteinase K at 37 &#x000b0;C for 10 min, the reactions were mixed with &#x02155; volume of loading buffer (60% glycerol, 10 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 60 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, 0.10% Orange G) and resolved in a 10% polyacrylamide gel in TAE buffer (40 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, 20 m<sc>m</sc> sodium acetate, 2 m<sc>m</sc> EDTA, pH 7.5). The fluorescent DNA species were visualized and quantified in the PharosFX Plus imager with the QuantityOne software (Bio-Rad). The experiment addressing the effect of rad54-K341A and rad54-K341R mutants was done in the presence of 2 m<sc>m</sc> ATP and ATP-regenerating system (10 &#x003bc;g/ml creatine phosphokinase and 20 m<sc>m</sc> creatine phosphate). In the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 targeting assay (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>), preincubation of the indicated DNA substrate with Rad54 was for 5 min at 25 &#x000b0;C. The nuclease assay with Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 or Fen1 was carried out as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>).</p><p><italic>DNA Mobility Shift Assay</italic>&#x02014;Purified <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> Rad54 (50 or 100 n<sc>m</sc>) was incubated with the indicated fluorescently labeled substrate (12 n<sc>m</sc>) at 37 &#x000b0;C in 10 &#x003bc;l of buffer D (40 m<sc>m</sc> Tris-HCl, pH 7.8, 50 m<sc>m</sc> KCl, 1 m<sc>m</sc> dithiothreitol, and 100 &#x003bc;g/ml bovine serum albumin) for 10 min. After the addition of gel loading buffer, the reaction mixtures were resolved in 10% native polyacrylamide gels in TAE buffer at 4 &#x000b0;C and analyzed as above.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>FIGURE 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Physical interaction of Rad54 with Mus81 and Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4.</bold><italic>A</italic>, purified Rad54 (<italic>lane 1</italic>), Mus81 (<italic>lane 2</italic>), Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (<italic>lane 3</italic>), Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 (<italic>lane 4</italic>), and Fen1 (<italic>lane 5</italic>) were resolved by SDS-PAGE and stained with Coomassie Blue. <italic>B</italic>, Mus81 (4 &#x003bc;g) was mixed with S-protein-agarose in the presence of dsDNA (<italic>lane 1&#x02013;3</italic>) or with S-protein-agarose beads coated with Rad54 (4 &#x003bc;g) in the presence of ssDNA (<italic>lanes 4&#x02013;6</italic>) or dsDNA (<italic>lanes 7&#x02013;9</italic>). The beads were incubated with DNase I (2 units), washed, and treated with SDS to elute bound proteins. The supernatant that contained unbound proteins (<italic>S</italic>), the wash (<italic>W</italic>), and the SDS eluate (<italic>E</italic>) were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. As a positive control, Rad51 (4 &#x003bc;g) was mixed with S-protein-agarose beads coated with Rad54 (4 &#x003bc;g) in the absence of DNA (<italic>lanes 10&#x02013;12</italic>) and then analyzed. <italic>C</italic>, Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (3 &#x003bc;g) was mixed with S-protein-agarose beads (<italic>lanes 1&#x02013;3</italic>) or S-protein-agarose beads coated with Rad54 (3 &#x003bc;g; <italic>lanes 4&#x02013;6</italic>) in the presence of dsDNA. As a negative control, Fen1 (3 &#x003bc;g) was mixed with S-protein-agarose beads coated with Rad54 (3 &#x003bc;g) in the presence of dsDNA (<italic>lanes 7&#x02013;9</italic>) and then analyzed. <italic>BSA</italic>, bovine serum albumin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0140969270001"></graphic></fig></p><p><italic>Camptothecin Sensitivity Spot Assays</italic>&#x02014;Cells were grown to mid- to late-log phase and diluted in water to <italic>A</italic><sub>600</sub> of &#x0223c;0.2. 10-Fold serial dilutions were made in water such that the most concentrated spot contained &#x0223c;10<sup>5</sup> cells, and the dilutions were spotted on synthetic complete plates (SC), SC + DMSO, or SC + 1 &#x003bc;g/ml CPT (from a stock of 2 mg/ml in DMSO). In all experiments, the SC + DMSO plate mirrored the SC alone plate and, therefore, are not shown. For HU, dilutions were spotted on yeast extract/peptone/dextrose (YPD) or YPD + 200 m<sc>m</sc> HU. Drugs were added to the agar medium just before pouring the plates.</p><p><italic>Live Cell Fluorescent Microscopy</italic>&#x02014;Cells for microscopic analysis were grown and processed as detailed previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>) with the following changes; cells were harvested by brief centrifugation (3800 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>) and resuspended in approximately 10 times the cell pellet volume of growth media. Immobilization of cells was carried out by mixing equal volumes of cell suspension and 1.4% low-melt-agarose (Nu-Sieve 3:1, FMC) plus growth medium solution (held at 42 &#x000b0;C before mixing) on a glass slide. When applicable, cells were treated with &#x003b3;-irradiation (40 Gy from a Gammacell-220 <sup>60</sup>Co source, Atomic Energy, Ottawa, Canada) or CPT (5 &#x003bc;g/ml) during mid-log phase growth and harvested for microscopy as above at the indicated times.</p><p>Images were acquired identically as in Lisby <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>) on the microscope apparatus described therein. For Mus81-yellow fluorescent protein detection, an exposure time of 3000 ms was used. Images were false-colored and overlaid in Openlab (Improvision, Lexington, MA), then transferred to Adobe Photoshop for scaling.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p><italic>Association of Rad54 with Mus81 and Mus81</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>Mms4 Complex Occurs on dsDNA</italic>&#x02014;Results from a yeast two-hybrid screen for Rad54 partner proteins have identified a fragment of Mus81 protein as capable of Rad54 interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>). We used purified proteins (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>A</italic></xref>) to ascertain Rad54&#x000b7;Mus81 interaction. For this purpose we mixed S- and His<sub>6</sub>-tagged Rad54 with His<sub>6</sub>-tagged Mus81 or His<sub>6</sub>-Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 and then incubated the reaction mixtures with S-protein conjugated agarose to capture any Rad54 protein complex that might have formed. We eluted the bound proteins from the S-protein-agarose beads with SDS and then analyzed them by SDS-PAGE. However, we were not able to detect any significant association of Rad54 with either Mus81 or Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (data not shown). We note that, as determined by co-immunoprecipitation, Interthal and Heyer found only weak or transient interaction between Rad54 and overexpressed Mus81 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>). One strong possibility is that complex formation between Mus81 and Rad54 occurs on DNA. Therefore, we examined this possibility by incubating Rad54 with Mus81 or Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 in the presence of 49-mer ss- or dsDNA. We used an amount of Rad54 in excess over DNA as determined by binding experiments (supplemental Fig. 1). Furthermore, the mixture was treated with DNase I to ensure that the association was not due to direct bridging of the interaction via free DNA. As shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic></xref>, only reactions containing dsDNA retained a stoichiometric amount of Mus81 or Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 on the Rad54-S-protein beads. As expected, Mus81 or Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 was not retained on the S-protein beads in the absence of Rad54 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1, <italic>B</italic> and <italic>C</italic></xref>). The interaction of Mus81 with Rad54 is specific, as Fen1, also a DNA structure-specific endonuclease, did not show any association with Rad54 in the presence of dsDNA (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>C</italic></xref>). As reported before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>), Rad54 forms a complex with Rad51 in the absence of DNA (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1<italic>B</italic></xref>). Taken together, the results show an ability of Mus81 and Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 to associate with Rad54 protein in a dsDNA-dependent manner.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>FIGURE 2.</label><caption><p><bold>Rad54 concentration-dependent enhancement of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4-mediated 3&#x02032; DNA flap cleavage.</bold> Reaction mixtures containing 3&#x02032; DNA flap (6 n<sc>m</sc>), Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.25 n<sc>m</sc>), and the indicated amount of Rad54 (0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, or 16 n<sc>m</sc>) were incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for 10 min (<italic>A</italic>) and 30 min (<italic>B</italic>) and then analyzed. <italic>C</italic>, quantification of the data in <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> with S.D. based on three independent experiments. <italic>D</italic>, plot of percent of product formation as a logarithm of Rad54 concentration with indicated median effective concentration (EC<sub>50</sub>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0140969270002"></graphic></fig></p><p><italic>Rad54 Binds Branched DNA Substrates Preferentially</italic>&#x02014;The requirement for dsDNA in the Rad54&#x000b7;Mus81 interaction prompted us to test the affinity of yeast Rad54 for DNA structures that Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 complex is able to cleave. Specifically, we examined the affinity of yeast Rad54 protein toward ssDNA, dsDNA, 3&#x02032; flap (3Fl), fork, Y form DNA (Y), intact HJ, and also a nicked HJ (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). To do this increasing amounts of Rad54 protein was incubated with the fluorescently labeled substrates followed by resolution of the reaction mixtures on native polyacrylamide gels. Fluorescence imaging analysis of the gels allowed us to detect and quantify the extent of DNA mobility shift. As shown in supplemental Fig. 1, Rad54 protein bound all these DNA substrates with higher affinity for the branched structures. We note that human Rad54 also prefers to bind similar types of DNA molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>).</p><p><italic>Rad54 Stimulates Cleavage of 3</italic>&#x02032; <italic>DNA Flap</italic>&#x02014;The physical interaction between Rad54 and Mus81 together with the demonstrated binding preference of Rad54 for substrates that Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 acts on prompted us to test whether Rad54 might modulate the nuclease activity of the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 complex. We first used the 3&#x02032; DNA flap substrate, as it is bound by Rad54 with higher affinity and represents a relevant DNA intermediate that arises during DNA repair or replication. We performed a Rad54 protein titration with 0.25 n<sc>m</sc> Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4, an amount that could cleave only a small fraction of the substrate (supplemental Fig. 2, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>C</italic>). Importantly, strong enhancement of the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 DNA cleavage activity occurred in a Rad54 protein concentration-dependent manner. Flap cleavage was stimulated 3-fold by 1 n<sc>m</sc> Rad54 and 5-fold by 2 n<sc>m</sc> Rad54, and complete incision of the substrate was seen when 8 n<sc>m</sc> Rad54 was added (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, <italic>A&#x02013;C</italic></xref>). The plot of the percent product formed as a logarithmic function of Rad54 concentration yields a sigmoid curve for stimulation, with the median effective concentration EC<sub>50</sub> = 1.56 n<sc>m</sc> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2<italic>D</italic></xref>). This Rad54 amount corresponds to 6 times that of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 heterodimer. Because Rad54 forms oligomeric complexes on DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>), our results are consistent with the premise that optimal stimulation of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 occurs upon assembly of a Rad54 oligomer. As expected, Rad54 alone was devoid of nucleolytic activity (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref><italic>, lane 9</italic>). Time course experiments provided further details on the effect of Rad54 on the rate of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4-mediated DNA cleavage (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). We note that the presence of Rad54 does not affect the position of the cleavage site within the flap structure (data not shown). In addition, the presence of His<sub>6</sub> affinity tag on Mms4 does not have any significant effect on the nuclease activity of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 or on the enhancement of substrate cleavage by Rad54 (supplemental Fig. 3). Taken together, the results demonstrate that Rad54 can strongly stimulate the ability of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 to cleave the 3&#x02032; DNA flap structure and also suggest that optimal enhancement is contingent upon oligomerization of Rad54.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>FIGURE 3.</label><caption><p><bold>Time course of the enhancement of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4-mediated 3&#x02032; DNA flap cleavage by Rad54.</bold><italic>A</italic>, Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.25 n<sc>m</sc>) was incubated with the 3&#x02032; DNA flap (6 n<sc>m</sc>) at 37 &#x000b0;C in the absence (<italic>panel I</italic>) or presence of 0.5, 1.5, or 3 n<sc>m</sc> Rad54 (<italic>panels II, III</italic>, and <italic>IV</italic>). Aliquots of the reactions were taken at the indicated times and analyzed. <italic>B</italic>, quantification of the data with S.D. based on three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0140969270003"></graphic></fig></p><p><italic>Enhancement of Gapped 3</italic>&#x02032; <italic>DNA Flap Cleavage by Rad54</italic>&#x02014;It has been suggested that a crucial determinant for Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 endonuclease activity is recognition of the 5&#x02032; end at the flap junction as the DNA cleavage efficiency declines with increasing DNA gap size in the flap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>). Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4-mediated cleavage of the 3&#x02032; DNA flap substrate that harbors a 1-nt gap occurred with a similar efficiency as that of the 3&#x02032; DNA flap without any gap (data not shown). However, the cleavage efficiency decreased as the gap size increased to 5 nt and was much lower with a 10-nt gap (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>A</italic></xref>). Under the conditions used, the Y substrate was resistant to Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 cleavage (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>A</italic></xref>). Then we tested the ability of Rad54 to stimulate Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 activity on the gapped 3&#x02032; DNA flap structures. The addition of Rad54 (from 0.5 to 16 n<sc>m</sc>) resulted in the up-regulation of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.25 n<sc>m</sc>) activity on flaps containing a 1- or 5-nt gap (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>B</italic></xref>) without effecting significant cleavage of the flap with the 10-nt gap. Interestingly, at 2 n<sc>m</sc> Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 that could afford an &#x0223c;10% incision of the flap with the 10-nt gap, the addition of Rad54 (from 0.5 to 16 n<sc>m</sc>) also enhanced DNA cleavage (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>C</italic></xref>). In the case of the Y substrate, cleavage was not seen with as high as 10 n<sc>m</sc> Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 regardless of whether Rad54 (up to 40 n<sc>m</sc>) was added or not (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>C</italic></xref>).</p><p><italic>Cleavage of Nicked HJ and D-loop Structures Is Also Stimulated by Rad54</italic>&#x02014;Next we wanted to test substrates that are known to arise during homologous recombination, including the D-loop, nicked HJ, and intact HJ. As stated elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref>) and confirmed here, Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 has only a limited ability to cleave an intact HJ. Specifically, as much as 65 n<sc>m</sc> Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 cleaved only 6% of the HJ after 30 min of incubation (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>D</italic></xref>). The addition of up to 400 n<sc>m</sc> Rad54 had only a slight stimulatory effect (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4<italic>D</italic></xref>). As reported before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref>) and in our hands also, the cleavage of nicked HJs by Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 was very efficient and was greatly stimulated by Rad54 to the same extent as when the 3&#x02032; DNA flap substrate was used (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4, <italic>E</italic> and <italic>F</italic></xref>). In addition, we also tested the ability of Rad54 to activate the cleavage of a D-loop substrate by Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4, and a similar level of stimulation was observed (supplemental Fig. 4). In summary, Rad54 is able to dramatically increase the DNA cleavage activity of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 on the D-loop and nicked HJ but has little or no effect on the cleavage of the intact HJ.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>FIGURE 4.</label><caption><p><bold>Effect of Rad54 on Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 cleavage of 3&#x02032; DNA flap substrates with varying gap sizes.</bold><italic>A</italic>, cleavage of 3&#x02032; DNA flap (<italic>Fl</italic>) substrates with increasing gap size (1, 5, or 10 nt) and of Y form DNA. Each of these substrates (6 n<sc>m</sc>) was incubated with Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.13, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, or 8 n<sc>m</sc>) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and then analyzed. <italic>B</italic>, reaction mixtures containing gapped 3&#x02032; DNA flaps or Y form DNA (6 n<sc>m</sc> each), Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.25 n<sc>m</sc>), and the indicated amounts of Rad54 (0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, or 16 n<sc>m</sc>) were incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and then analyzed. <italic>C</italic>, Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (2 n<sc>m</sc>) was incubated with the 3&#x02032; DNA flap containing a 10-nt gap and Rad54 (0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 20, or 40 n<sc>m</sc>) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and then analyzed. For the Y form DNA substrate, 10% of cleavage could not be achieved; therefore, 10 n<sc>m</sc> Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 was incubated with the indicated amounts of Rad54 (0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 20, or 40 n<sc>m</sc>) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and then analyzed. <italic>D</italic>, Rad54 has little effect on the cleavage of an intact HJ. The HJ substrate (2 n<sc>m</sc>) was incubated with Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (65 n<sc>m</sc>) and with or without Rad54 (15 or 400 n<sc>m</sc>) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and then analyzed. Quantification of the data with S.D. was based on three independent experiments. <italic>E</italic>, cleavage of a nicked HJ (2 n<sc>m</sc>) by Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.05 n<sc>m</sc>) is greatly stimulated by Rad54 (0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, or 16 n<sc>m</sc>) in a dose-dependent manner. <italic>F</italic>, graphical representation of the data shown in <italic>panel E</italic> with S.D. based on three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0140969270004"></graphic></fig></p><p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>FIGURE 5.</label><caption><p><bold>Enhancement of the human Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 nuclease function by human Rad54.</bold><italic>A</italic>, the 3&#x02032; DNA flap substrate (6 n<sc>m</sc>) was incubated with human Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 (0.13 n<sc>m</sc>) and without or with human Rad54 (<italic>hRad54</italic>) (0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, or 16 n<sc>m</sc>) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and then analyzed. <italic>B</italic>, quantification of the data shown in <italic>panel A. C</italic>, human Rad54 enhances the nuclease activity of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4. The 3&#x02032; DNA flap (6 n<sc>m</sc>) was incubated with Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.25 n<sc>m</sc>) and the indicated amounts of human Rad54 (4, 8, or 16 n<sc>m</sc>) or yeast Rad54 (<italic>yRad54</italic>, 2 or 4 n<sc>m</sc>) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and then analyzed. <italic>D</italic>, quantification of the data shown in <italic>C</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0140969270005"></graphic></fig></p><p><fig position="float" id="fig6"><label>FIGURE 6.</label><caption><p><bold>ATP binding and hydrolysis by Rad54 is dispensable for Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 enhancement.</bold><italic>A</italic>, the nuclease activity of Fen1 is unresponsive to Rad54. The 5&#x02032; DNA flap (6 n<sc>m</sc>) was incubated with Fen1 (2 n<sc>m</sc>) without or with Rad54 (0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8, or 16 n<sc>m</sc>) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 30 min and then analyzed. <italic>B</italic>, quantification of the data shown in <italic>panel A</italic> with S.D. based on three independent experiments. <italic>C</italic>, the 3&#x02032; DNA flap (6 n<sc>m</sc>) was incubated in buffer containing ATP with Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.25 n<sc>m</sc>) and Rad54, rad54-K341A, or rad54-K341R (1, 2, or 4 n<sc>m</sc> concentrations of each protein) at 37 &#x000b0;C for 10 min and then analyzed. <italic>wt</italic>, wild type. <italic>D</italic>, the data from the 10- and 30-min time points of the experiment in <italic>C</italic> were plotted.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0140969270006"></graphic></fig></p><p><italic>Stimulation of Mus81 Activity by Rad54 Is Evolutionarily Conserved</italic>&#x02014;To determine whether the functional interaction of Rad54 with Mus81 is evolutionarily conserved, we examined the effect of human Rad54 on the nuclease activity of the human Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 complex. We used the 3&#x02032; DNA flap substrate and demonstrated that the addition of human Rad54 (0.5&#x02013;16 n<sc>m</sc>) to the reaction containing 0.13 n<sc>m</sc> Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 resulted in a robust enhancement of nuclease activity (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>). The extent of stimulation was similar to that obtained with the equivalent yeast proteins.</p><p>We next asked whether human and yeast Rad54 proteins are interchangeable with regard to the enhancement of the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1) nuclease function. As shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic></xref>, hRad54, at the relatively higher concentration of 4&#x02013;16 n<sc>m</sc>, exerted a 2.5&#x02013;5-fold stimulatory effect on the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.25 n<sc>m</sc>) activity. Similarly, yeast Rad54, at the relatively high concentration of 4&#x02013;16 n<sc>m</sc>, was also able to stimulate Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 (0.13 n<sc>m</sc>) by about 3-fold (data not shown). On the other hand, yeast Rad54 does not have any effect on the activity of another DNA structure-specific nuclease, Fen1 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>). Overall, the results in this section provide evidence that the Rad54-mediated enhancement of the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1) nuclease function is specific and evolutionarily conserved.</p><p><italic>ATP Binding and Hydrolysis by Rad54 Is Dispensable for Mus81</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>Mms4 Nuclease Enhancement</italic>&#x02014; Rad54 possesses a dsDNA-dependent ATPase activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref>). We sought to establish the role of ATP binding and hydrolysis in the Rad54-mediated stimulation of the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 nuclease activity. For this purpose we used two mutants, rad54-K341A and rad54-K341R, that are expected to be defective in interaction with ATP and to retain the ability to bind but not hydrolyze ATP, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>). As shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic></xref>, rad54-K341A and rad54-K341R were just as proficient as the wild type protein in enhancing the cleavage of the 3&#x02032; flap DNA by Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 in the presence of ATP, thus formally establishing that the up-regulation of the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 nuclease function does not require binding or hydrolysis of ATP by Rad54.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig7"><label>FIGURE 7.</label><caption><p><bold>Substrate targeting of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 by Rad54.</bold> The DNA substrate pairs (the HJ and the DNA fork (<italic>Fk</italic>) in <italic>A</italic>; the nicked Holliday junction (<italic>nHJ</italic>) and 3&#x02032; DNA flap (<italic>Fl</italic>) in <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>), 3 n<sc>m</sc> each, were incubated with Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (<italic>M/M</italic>; 0.25 n<sc>m</sc>) and Rad54 (<italic>R54</italic>; 2 n<sc>m</sc>) in the indicated orders at 37 &#x000b0;C for 20 min and then analyzed. The reaction mixtures that contained FITC-labeled HJ and Fk are shown in <italic>A</italic>, and the results with S.D. based on three independent experiments are presented in the histogram in <italic>B</italic>. The reactions that contained FITC-labeled nicked HJ and Cy3-labeled Fl are shown in <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic>, and the results with S.D. based on three independent experiments are presented in the histogram in <italic>E</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0140969270007"></graphic></fig></p><p><italic>Rad54 Targets Mus81</italic>&#x000b7;<italic>Mms4 Complex to the DNA Substrate</italic>&#x02014; Because our results have suggested that physical interaction between Rad54 and Mus81 or Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 occurs when these protein species are DNA-bound (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), we asked whether Rad54 serves to target Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 to various DNA substrates. We set up two experiments using mixtures of different substrates to address this possibility. In one reaction Rad54 (2 n<sc>m</sc>) was preincubated with a non-cleavable intact HJ before the cleavable DNA fork substrate was added together with Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (0.25 n<sc>m</sc>). This resulted in a modest stimulation of DNA fork cleavage compared with the control reaction without Rad54 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>, compare <italic>lanes 2</italic> and <italic>3</italic>). On the other hand, preincubation of Rad54 with the fork substrate resulted in strong stimulation of its cleavage (&#x0223c;9-fold) (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref><italic>, lane 4</italic>). In the other assay we used two cleavable substrates, a nicked HJ and a 3&#x02032; DNA flap, labeled with FITC and Cy3 fluorescent dyes, respectively, to allow us to distinguish the products resulting from the cleavage of these substrates. Preincubation with Rad54 again led to a greater enhancement of substrate cleavage (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7, <italic>C&#x02013;E</italic></xref>, compare <italic>lanes 3</italic> and <italic>4</italic>). Altogether these results suggest that Rad54 acts by targeting the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 complex to its cleavage substrate, and it does not seem to function in <italic>trans</italic>.</p><p><italic>Epistatic Relationship of Rad54 and Mus81</italic>&#x02014;Previous genetic analysis showed that Rad54 and Mus81 act together in the recombination pathway for the repair of &#x003b3;-ray induced DNA damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>). We wanted to investigate their relationship in regard to the removal of replication-blocking damage. Therefore, we tested sensitivities of <italic>rad54, mus81</italic>, or the double mutant to CPT and HU, which impede DNA replication by poisoning topoisomerase I and ribonucleotide reductase, respectively. As shown in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic></xref>, the <italic>mus81 rad54</italic> double mutant was no more sensitive to CPT or HU than the <italic>rad54</italic> single mutant. Thus, <italic>RAD54</italic> and <italic>MUS81</italic> likely act in the same pathway for the repair of injured DNA replication forks.</p><p>This observation together with our biochemical data prompted us to test whether Rad54 and Mus81 co-localize <italic>in vivo</italic> with or without DNA damaging treatment. Only about 5% of the budded cells contained spontaneous Mus81 foci, and this formation was induced to 9% by DNA damage treatment. In contrast to frequent and bright Rad54 foci (&#x0223c;70% of budded cells after DNA damage treatment, data not shown), Mus81 foci were quite dim (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8<italic>C</italic></xref>), suggesting that these foci contain only very few Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 molecules. Interestingly, we noticed only transient co-localization of both proteins (data not shown), which is in agreement with the nature of this protein-protein interaction seen in a biochemical pulldown. Importantly, deletion of the <italic>RAD54</italic> gene causes a significant reduction of Mus81 focus formation especially in the presence of DNA damage (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8<italic>D</italic></xref>). However, Mus81 focus formation is decreased only by the absence of Rad54 but not by the lack of Rad54 ATPase activity, as both the <italic>rad54-K341R</italic> and <italic>rad54-K341A</italic> mutants are still able to assemble DNA damage-induced Mus81 foci (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8<italic>D</italic></xref>). Taken together, our results suggest that Rad54 and Mus81 function together in the repair of chromosome damage caused by &#x003b3;-rays as well as replication blocking agents and that the ATPase activity of Rad54 is dispensable in this regard.</p><p><fig position="float" id="fig8"><label>FIGURE 8.</label><caption><p><bold>Epistatic relationship of Rad54 and Mus81.</bold> Sensitivity of wild type (<italic>WT</italic>), <italic>mus81</italic>&#x00394;, <italic>rad54</italic>&#x00394;, and double mutant cells to DNA-damaging agents was assayed by growth on plates containing the indicated concentrations of CPT (<italic>A</italic>) or HU (<italic>B</italic>). <italic>YPD</italic>, yeast extract/peptone/dextrose. <italic>C</italic>, representative maximum intensity projection image of CPT-induced Mus81-yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) foci (indicated by <italic>arrows</italic>). Images were captured 5 h after treatment. <italic>Scale bar</italic>, 3 &#x003bc;m. <italic>DIC</italic>, differential interference contrast. <italic>D</italic>, quantification of Mus81 foci in <italic>RAD54, rad54</italic>&#x00394;, <italic>rad54-K341A</italic> (<italic>rad54-K/A</italic>), and <italic>rad54-K341R (rad54-K/R</italic>) genetic backgrounds. IR-treated cells were examined for foci 3 h after treatment. CPT-treated cells were examined 5 h post-treatment. <italic>Bars</italic> indicate the frequency of Mus81 foci observed in S phase or G<sub>2</sub>/M cells (<italic>Budded cells</italic>). <italic>Error bars</italic> depict the binomial S.E. Significance from the wild type was determined by a &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zbc0140969270008"></graphic></fig></p></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1) complex is believed to be responsible for processing intermediates of homologous recombination as well as those derived from stalled, blocked, and broken replication forks. However, the manner in which the activities of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 are connected to these cellular processes is still not clear. Interestingly, Mus81 was first identified in a two-hybrid screen for Rad54 interacting partners, and this interaction seems to be evolutionary conserved from yeast to humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref>). Rad54 is one of the key proteins involved in homologous recombination. It interacts with the Rad51 recombinase, promotes the assembly and stability of Rad51 filament, stimulates D-loop formation, and could allow Rad51 filament to engage in homology search. In addition, Rad54 removes Rad51 from dsDNA, remodels chromatin structure, and also promotes the migration of branched DNA structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>).</p><p>We have presented data showing a direct physical interaction of Rad54 with Mus81 and the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 complex when dsDNA is present. It is possible that the two-hybrid signal of Mus81&#x000b7;Rad54 interaction reflects a transient association of these proteins or that it stems from an interaction of these proteins on DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>). We note that even though yeast Rad52 binds RPA in the yeast two-hybrid assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref>), significant complex formation between the two purified proteins requires ssDNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>). We also show that the association of Rad54 with Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 leads to a strong stimulation of the nuclease activity of the latter on a variety of substrates and that cleavage by human Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 is similarly enhanced by human Rad54, indicating evolutionary conservation of the functional interaction between these two protein species. We note that while our work was undergoing peer review, a paper by Mazina and Mazin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>) showing enhancement of the Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 nuclease activity by human Rad54 had appeared. Rad54 possesses ATP-dependent branch migration activity on Holliday junctions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>). Our results and those of Mazina and Mazin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>) provide biochemical and biological insights linking the ability of Rad54 to promote D-loop formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>) and branch migration of late recombination intermediates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>) with the nucleolytic processing of replication and/or recombination intermediates by Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1).</p><p>Interestingly, neither ATP binding nor its hydrolysis by Rad54 is needed for the stimulation of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 nuclease activity <italic>in vitro</italic>. Genetic results presented here and elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>) establish that Rad54 and Mus81 function together in the same pathways of DNA damage and replication fork repair and that the assembly of DNA damage-induced Mus81 foci is dependent on Rad54. Both the <italic>rad54-K341R</italic> and <italic>rad54-K341A</italic> mutants are still able to assemble DNA damage-induced Mus81 foci. This observation is in congruence with a less severe defect in recombination rates for both mutants compared with the <italic>rad54</italic>&#x00394; mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>). However, we expect the dsDNA translocase and DNA branch migration activities of Rad54 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref>) to facilitate the formation of substrates that are resolved by the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 complex <italic>in vivo</italic>. The yeast <italic>mus81</italic> and <italic>rad54</italic> mutants fall into the same epistasis group regarding &#x003b3;-ray sensitivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>), and we have presented data showing epistasis of these mutants in the repair of damaged replication forks as well. We note that homologous recombination mediated by Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 and Rad54 is needed for the DNA replication-dependent interstrand DNA cross-link repair pathway in human cells, with Mus81 contributing to replication restart by generating double-strand breaks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref>). In addition, the yeast <italic>mus81</italic> and <italic>mms4</italic> mutants are inviable in the absence of the Sgs1 helicase, which is thought to act in conjunction with Top3 and Rmi1 to resolve late recombination intermediates, such as the double Holliday junction, to generate non-crossover recombinants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref>). Thus, Rad54 together with Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1) comprises an alternative mechanism for the resolution of DNA intermediates parallel to the Sgs1&#x000b7;Top3 (BLM&#x000b7;Top3) pathway. Both <italic>mus81</italic> and <italic>mms4</italic> mutants show severe meiotic phenotypes as a result of unprocessed recombination intermediates that activate a meiotic checkpoint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>). Importantly, defects in the initiation of recombination are able to overcome the <italic>sgs1</italic> synthetic lethality in both budding and fission yeasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>). Overall, the available evidence is consistent with the premise that Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1) helps to resolve otherwise toxic recombination intermediates in mitotic and meiotic cells, and our biochemical data reveal an involvement of Rad54 in the enhancement of these Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 (Eme1) activities.</p><p>There has been much discussion regarding the possible role of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 in the nucleolytic resolution of intact HJs. We have confirmed that a nicked HJ is more efficiently cleaved by Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 than an intact HJ. Although Rad54 renders the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4-mediated cleavage of flap substrates efficiently, it has only minimal stimulatory effect on the cleavage of an intact HJ. This result argues against Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 acting to resolve HJ structures in cells and is consistent with the suggestion that the cleavage of intact HJs reflects a secondary effect of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 flap cleavage activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>). Furthermore, the efficient cleavage of nicked HJ structure supports a mechanism by which Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 could act on the nascent D-loop before it is converted into an intact HJ. As discussed by others previously, Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4-mediated D-loop cleavage may favor crossover production during meiosis and could account for the decrease in crossovers observed for <italic>mus81</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>). However, one cannot exclude the possibility that there is another partner of Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 that allows the latter to act on intact HJs in cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref>).</p><p>The successful assembly of a Rad51 nucleoprotein filament is a prerequisite for Rad54 recruitment to recombination substrates in cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>) placing Rad54 in temporal and spatial arrangement to mediate later steps in recombination. During these steps, via its ability to stimulate the recombinase activity of Rad51 and to migrate branched DNA structures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>), Rad54 is expected to mediate the formation of certain DNA structures, such as the D-loop or nicked Holliday junction, that are subject to nucleolytic processing by the Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 complex. In this regard, Rad54 likely targets Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 to these structures to affect their processing. However, from genetic experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>), it seems clear that Mus81&#x000b7;Mms4 and Rad54 also possess additional functions during meiotic or damage-induced double-strand break repair.</p><p>Recently, the human BLM helicase was also shown to stimulate the nuclease activity of the Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 complex, albeit to a lesser degree than what we have documented for Rad54 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref>). Interestingly, both BLM and Rad54 are capable of mediating the migration of branched DNA structures. The lesser ability of BLM to activate Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 could reflect a role of BLM as a backup to the Rad54-mediated up-regulation of the Mus81&#x000b7;Eme1 nuclease function.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>[Supplemental Data]</title></caption><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="M806192200_index.html"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="M806192200_1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Steven Brill, Binghui Shen, and Stephen West for providing protein expression plasmids.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal">Heller, R. C., and Marians, K. J. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Nature</source><volume>439</volume><fpage>557</fpage>-562<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452972</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="N0x1f73f80N0x1dccc98"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lehmann, A. R. (<year>2003</year>) <source>Cell Cycle</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>300</fpage>-302<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12851478</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal">McGlynn, P., and Lloyd, R. G. (<year>2002</year>) <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>859</fpage>-870<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12415303</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal">Michel, B., Flores, M. J., Viguera, E., Grompone, G., Seigneur, M., and Bidnenko, V. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>8181</fpage>-8188<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459951</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal">Higgins, N. P., Kato, K., and Strauss, B. (<year>1976</year>) <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>417</fpage>-425<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1255724</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal">Osman, F., and Whitby, M. C. (<year>2007</year>) <source>DNA Repair</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>1004</fpage>-1017<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17409028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal">Haber, J. E., and Heyer, W. D. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Cell</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>551</fpage>-554<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11733053</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kaliraman, V., Mullen, J. R., Fricke, W. M., Bastin-Shanower, S. A., and Brill, S. J. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Genes Dev.</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>2730</fpage>-2740<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641278</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal">Mullen, J. R., Kaliraman, V., Ibrahim, S. S., and Brill, S. J. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Genetics</source><volume>157</volume><fpage>103</fpage>-118<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11139495</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal">Hollingsworth, N. M., and Brill, S. J. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Genes Dev.</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>117</fpage>-125<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14752007</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal">Boddy, M. N., Lopez-Girona, A., Shanahan, P., Interthal, H., Heyer, W. D., and Russell, P. (<year>2000</year>) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>8758</fpage>-8766<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11073977</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="N0x1f73f80N0x430d6e0"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal">Chen, C., and Kolodner, R. D. (<year>1999</year>) <source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>81</fpage>-85<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10471504</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal">Hiyama, T., Katsura, M., Yoshihara, T., Ishida, M., Kinomura, A., Tonda, T., Asahara, T., and Miyagawa, K. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>880</fpage>-892<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16456034</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal">Interthal, H., and Heyer, W. D. (<year>2000</year>) <source>Mol. Gen. Genet.</source><volume>263</volume><fpage>812</fpage>-827<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10905349</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal">Boddy, M. N., Gaillard, P. H., McDonald, W. H., Shanahan, P., Yates, J. R., III, and Russell, P. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Cell</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>537</fpage>-548<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719193</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal">Chen, X. B., Melchionna, R., Denis, C. M., Gaillard, P. H., Blasina, A., Van de Weyer, I., Boddy, M. N., Russell, P., Vialard, J., and McGowan, C. H. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Mol. Cell</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>1117</fpage>-1127<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11741546</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal">Gaillard, P. H., Noguchi, E., Shanahan, P., and Russell, P. (<year>2003</year>) <source>Mol. Cell</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>747</fpage>-759<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527419</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal">Bastin-Shanower, S. A., Fricke, W. M., Mullen, J. R., and Brill, S. J. (<year>2003</year>) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>3487</fpage>-3496<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724407</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal">Petukhova, G., Stratton, S., and Sung, P. (<year>1998</year>) <source>Nature</source><volume>393</volume><fpage>91</fpage>-94<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9590697</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal">Sung, P., Krejci, L., Van Komen, S., and Sehorn, M. G. (<year>2003</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>42729</fpage>-42732<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12912992</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal">Raschle, M., Van Komen, S., Chi, P., Ellenberger, T., and Sung, P. (<year>2004</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>51973</fpage>-51980<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15465810</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal">Petukhova, G., Van Komen, S., Vergano, S., Klein, H., and Sung, P. (<year>1999</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>274</volume><fpage>29453</fpage>-29462<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10506208</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal">Sigurdsson, S., Van Komen, S., Petukhova, G., and Sung, P. (<year>2002</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>277</volume><fpage>42790</fpage>-42794<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12205100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ciccia, A., Constantinou, A., and West, S. C. (<year>2003</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>25172</fpage>-25178<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12721304</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal">Qiu, J., Qian, Y., Frank, P., Wintersberger, U., and Shen, B. (<year>1999</year>) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>8361</fpage>-8371<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10567561</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal">Lisby, M., Barlow, J. H., Burgess, R. C., and Rothstein, R. (<year>2004</year>) <source>Cell</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>699</fpage>-713<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15369670</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal">Clever, B., Interthal, H., Schmuckli-Maurer, J., King, J., Sigrist, M., and Heyer, W. D. (<year>1997</year>) <source>EMBO J.</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>2535</fpage>-2544<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9171366</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal">Mazina, O. M., Rossi, M. J., Thomaa, N. H., and Mazin, A. V. (<year>2007</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>282</volume><fpage>21068</fpage>-21080<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17545145</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal">Kiianitsa, K., Solinger, J. A., and Heyer, W. D. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>103</volume><fpage>9767</fpage>-9772<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16785421</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ristic, D., Wyman, C., Paulusma, C., and Kanaar, R. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>8454</fpage>-8460<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459989</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal">Constantinou, A., Chen, X. B., McGowan, C. H., and West, S. C. (<year>2002</year>) <source>EMBO J.</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>5577</fpage>-5585<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12374758</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="N0x1f73f80N0x209f258"><label>32</label><citation citation-type="journal">Fricke, W. M., Bastin-Shanower, S. A., and Brill, S. J. (<year>2005</year>) <source>DNA Repair</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>243</fpage>-251<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15590332</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><citation citation-type="journal">Whitby, M. C., Osman, F., and Dixon, J. (<year>2003</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>6928</fpage>-6935<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12473680</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><citation citation-type="journal">Osman, F., Dixon, J., Doe, C. L., and Whitby, M. C. (<year>2003</year>) <source>Mol. Cell</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>761</fpage>-774<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14527420</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><citation citation-type="journal">Swagemakers, S. M., Essers, J., de Wit, J., Hoeijmakers, J. H., and Kanaar, R. (<year>1998</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>273</volume><fpage>28292</fpage>-28297<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9774452</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><citation citation-type="journal">Hanada, K., Budzowska, M., Modesti, M., Maas, A., Wyman, C., Essers, J., and Kanaar, R. (<year>2006</year>) <source>EMBO J.</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>4921</fpage>-4932<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17036055</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><citation citation-type="journal">Mimida, N., Kitamoto, H., Osakabe, K., Nakashima, M., Ito, Y., Heyer, W. D., Toki, S., and Ichikawa, H. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>648</fpage>-654<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17327258</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><citation citation-type="journal">San Filippo, J., Sung, P., and Klein, H. (<year>2008</year>) <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>229</fpage>-257<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18275380</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><citation citation-type="journal">Tan, T. L., Kanaar, R., and Wyman, C. (<year>2003</year>) <source>DNA Repair</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>787</fpage>-794<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12826279</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40</label><citation citation-type="journal">Hays, S. L., Firmenich, A. A., Massey, P., Banerjee, R., and Berg, P. (<year>1998</year>) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>4400</fpage>-4406<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632824</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41</label><citation citation-type="journal">Seong, C., Sehorn, M. G., Plate, I., Shi, I., Song, B., Chi, P., Mortensen, U., Sung, P., and Krejci, L. (<year>2008</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>283</volume><fpage>12166</fpage>-12174<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18310075</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42</label><citation citation-type="journal">Mazina, O. M., and Mazin, A. V. (<year>2008</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>18249</fpage>-18254<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017809</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43</label><citation citation-type="journal">Bugreev, D. V., Hanaoka, F., and Mazin, A. V. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>746</fpage>-753<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17660833</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44</label><citation citation-type="journal">Bugreev, D. V., Mazina, O. M., and Mazin, A. V. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Nature</source><volume>442</volume><fpage>590</fpage>-593<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16862129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="N0x1f73f80N0x43034a0"><label>45</label><citation citation-type="journal">Amitani, I., Baskin, R. J., and Kowalczykowski, S. C. (<year>2006</year>) <source>Mol. Cell</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>143</fpage>-148<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818238</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46</label><citation citation-type="journal">Van Komen, S., Petukhova, G., Sigurdsson, S., Stratton, S., and Sung, P. (<year>2000</year>) <source>Mol. Cell</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>563</fpage>-572<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11030336</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47</label><citation citation-type="journal">Abraham, J., Lemmers, B., Hande, M. P., Moynahan, M. E., Chahwan, C., Ciccia, A., Essers, J., Hanada, K., Chahwan, R., Khaw, A. K., McPherson, P., Shehabeldin, A., Laister, R., Arrowsmith, C., Kanaar, R., West, S. C., Jasin, M., and Hakem, R. (<year>2003</year>) <source>EMBO J.</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>6137</fpage>-6147<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14609959</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48</label><citation citation-type="journal">Hanada, K., Budzowska, M., Davies, S. L., van Drunen, E., Onizawa, H., Beverloo, H. B., Maas, A., Essers, J., Hickson, I. D., and Kanaar, R. (<year>2007</year>) <source>Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>1096</fpage>-1104<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17934473</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49</label><citation citation-type="journal">Fabre, F., Chan, A., Heyer, W. D., and Gangloff, S. (<year>2002</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>16887</fpage>-16892<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12475932</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50</label><citation citation-type="journal">de los Santos, T., Hunter, N., Lee, C., Larkin, B., Loidl, J., and Hollingsworth, N. M. (<year>2003</year>) <source>Genetics</source><volume>164</volume><fpage>81</fpage>-94<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12750322</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51</label><citation citation-type="journal">de los Santos, T., Loidl, J., Larkin, B., and Hollingsworth, N. M. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Genetics</source><volume>159</volume><fpage>1511</fpage>-1525<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11779793</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52</label><citation citation-type="journal">Gaskell, L. J., Osman, F., Gilbert, R. J., and Whitby, M. C. (<year>2007</year>) <source>EMBO J.</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>1891</fpage>-1901<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17363897</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="N0x1f73f80N0x1f64578"><label>53</label><citation citation-type="journal">Ehmsen, K. T., and Heyer, W. D. (<year>2008</year>) <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>2182</fpage>-2195<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18281703</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54</label><citation citation-type="journal">Taylor, E. R., and McGowan, C. H. (<year>2008</year>) <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>3757</fpage>-3762<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18310322</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55</label><citation citation-type="journal">Jiang, H., Xie, Y., Houston, P., Stemke-Hale, K., Mortensen, U. H., Rothstein, R., and Kodadek, T. (<year>1996</year>) <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>271</volume><fpage>33181</fpage>-33186<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8969173</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56</label><citation citation-type="journal">Krejci, L., Damborsky, J., Thomsen, B., Duno, M., and Bendixen, C. (<year>2001</year>) <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>966</fpage>-976<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11154282</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57</label><citation citation-type="journal">Zhang, R., Sengupta, S., Yang, Q., Linke, S. P., Yanaihara, N., Bradsher, J., Blais, V., McGowan, C. H., and Harris, C. C. (<year>2005</year>) <source>Cancer Res.</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>2526</fpage>-2531<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805243</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="fn4"><label>2</label><p>The abbreviations used are: CPT, camptothecin; HU, hydroxyurea; HJ, Holliday junction; SC, synthetic complete; nt, nucleotide(s); dsDNA and ssDNA, double-stranded and single-stranded DNA, respectively; FITC, fluorescein isothiocyanate.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article> 