<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol</journal-id><journal-title>Genome Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1465-6906</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-6914</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gb-2009-10-1-r8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19161630</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2009-10-1-r8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization of taxonomically restricted genes in a phylum-restricted cell type</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Milde</surname><given-names>Sabine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>smilde@zoologie.uni-kiel.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hemmrich</surname><given-names>Georg</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ghemmrich@zoologie.uni-kiel.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anton-Erxleben</surname><given-names>Friederike</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>fanton-erxleben@zoologie.uni-kiel.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khalturin</surname><given-names>Konstantin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kkhalturin@zoologie.uni-kiel.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wittlieb</surname><given-names>J&#x000f6;rg</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jwittlieb@zoologie.uni-kiel.de</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>Thomas CG</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tbosch@zoologie.uni-kiel.de</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Zoological Institute, Christian-Albrechts-University Kiel, Olshausenstr. 40, 24098 Kiel, Germany</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>R8</fpage><lpage>R8</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genomebiology.com/2009/10/1/R8"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Milde et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Milde et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author> Milde Sabine smilde@zoologie.uni-kiel.de </dc:author><dc:title> Characterization of taxonomically restricted genes in a phylum-restricted cell type </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Genome Biology 10(1): R8-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1465-6906(2009)10:1&#x0003c;R8&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1465-6906</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="short"><p>Computational and functional genomic analyses in Hydra magnipapillata suggest that taxonomically-restricted genes are involved in the evolution of morphological novelties such as the cnidarian nematocyte</p></abstract><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Despite decades of research, the molecular mechanisms responsible for the evolution of morphological diversity remain poorly understood. While current models assume that species-specific morphologies are governed by differential use of conserved genetic regulatory circuits, it is debated whether non-conserved taxonomically restricted genes are also involved in making taxonomically relevant structures. The genomic resources available in <italic>Hydra</italic>, a member of the early branching animal phylum Cnidaria, provide a unique opportunity to study the molecular evolution of morphological novelties such as the nematocyte, a cell type characteristic of, and unique to, Cnidaria.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We have identified nematocyte-specific genes by suppression subtractive hybridization and find that a considerable portion has no homologues to any sequences in animals outside <italic>Hydra</italic>. By analyzing the transcripts of these taxonomically restricted genes and mining of the <italic>Hydra magnipapillata </italic>genome, we find unexpected complexity in gene structure and transcript processing. Transgenic <italic>Hydra </italic>expressing the green fluorescent protein reporter under control of one of the taxonomically restricted gene promoters recapitulate faithfully the described expression pattern, indicating that promoters of taxonomically restricted genes contain all elements essential for spatial and temporal control mechanisms. Surprisingly, phylogenetic footprinting of this promoter did not reveal any conserved <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our findings suggest that taxonomically restricted genes are involved in the evolution of morphological novelties such as the cnidarian nematocyte. The transcriptional regulatory network controlling taxonomically restricted gene expression may contain not yet characterized transcription factors or <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Cnidaria represent the simplest animals at the tissue grade of organization. In order to catch prey, cnidarians have evolved a unique "high-tech cellular weaponry" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] - the stinging cells (cnidocytes, nematocytes) - single cells able to shoot structures at their target and inject toxic substances into it. Nematocytes are unique to and present in all species of the phylum Cnidaria. Different phylogenetic lines have different nematocyte types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Evolution of cnidarian families appears to be accompanied by expansion of the nematocyte repertoire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. In <italic>Hydra</italic>, four types of nematocytes can be distinguished based on the distinct morphology of the nematocyte capsule: stenotele, desmoneme, holotrichous isorhiza and atrichous isorhiza. Previous work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] has identified unusually short proteins with a collagen-related domain (minicollagens) as major constituents of the nematocyst capsule wall. Intermolecular disulfide bonds between the cysteine-rich domains of these minicollagens and an additional capsule protein, NOWA, are thought to stabilize the capsule wall [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. The spines inside the capsules contain spinalin, another protein unrelated to any protein in other animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>How novel morphological structures evolve is an open and important question. One currently popular view is that since many genes are shared throughout the animal kingdom, animal diversity is largely based on differential use of conserved genes and regulatory circuits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. However, all genome and expressed sequence tag (EST) projects to date in every taxonomic group studied so far have uncovered a substantial amount of genes that are without known homologues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. A previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] has discovered that a family of such taxonomically restricted 'orphan' genes plays a significant role in controlling phenotypic features referred to as species-specific traits in the genus <italic>Hydra</italic>. Thus, morphological diversity in closely related species may be generated through changes in the spatial and temporal deployment of genes that are not highly conserved across long evolutionary distances [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p><p>We here have chosen an unbiased comparative approach based on suppression subtractive hybridization (SSH) to identify additional nematocyte-specific genes in <italic>Hydra</italic>. Among those detected, a considerable portion has no homologues in animals outside <italic>Hydra</italic>. Since they are exclusively restricted to the phylum Cnidaria, they are considered as 'orphans' or 'taxonomically restricted genes' (TRGs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p><p>Analysis of these TRGs indicates striking complexity in their genomic organization and transcript processing. In order to understand how such TRGs are regulated, we generated transgenic polyps that express green fluorescent protein (GFP) under control of one of the TRG promoters. Transgenic <italic>Hydra </italic>recapitulate faithfully the previously described expression pattern, indicating that the promoter contains all elements essential for spatial and temporal control mechanisms. Surprisingly, phylogenetic footprinting of this promoter did not reveal any conserved <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements. This may indicate that the transcriptional regulatory network controlling TRG expression may contain not yet characterized transcription factors or <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements.</p><p>Our data provide a detailed genomic description of several taxonomically restricted genes in a basal metazoan, and functional evidence that TRGs are integrated in transcriptional regulatory networks to form functional signaling cascades.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Identification of taxonomically restricted genes expressed in nematocytes</title><p>In order to isolate not yet identified genes potentially involved in nematocyte differentiation, we made use of the sf-1 mutant strain of <italic>H. magnipapillata</italic>, which has temperature-sensitive interstitial stem cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Interstitial cells are located between the ectodermal epithelial cells and contain both germline and somatic components, giving rise to all nerve cells, gland cells and nematocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Treatment for a few hours at the restrictive temperature (28&#x000b0;C) induces quantitative loss of the entire interstitial cell lineage, including nematocytes from the ectodermal epithelium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p><p>To identify genes that are transcriptionally active in differentiating nematocytes, we compared transcriptomes of control and nematocyte-free <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>by SSH of cDNAs. As shown schematically in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, subtractive hybridization resulted in a cDNA library enriched for interstitial stem cell lineage-specific transcripts. Sequencing of 2,500 clones revealed 105 consensus contig sequences that could be grouped by BLASTx analysis into three different categories of homology (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). One set (45 sequences; 43%) had strong similarities (e-value &#x0003c; 1e-20) to known metazoan proteins. The second set (44 sequences; 42%) had low e-values (&#x0003e;1e -7) and represents genes related but not identical to previously identified metazoan genes. The third set (16 sequences; 15%) had no homologues in the National Centre for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) protein database (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), representing, therefore, genes putatively restricted to <italic>Hydra </italic>or Hydrozoa. Further sequence analysis of these 16 contigs revealed that some of them (contigs 049 and 129 as well as 035 and 109) represent fragments of the same primary transcript. Thus, the approach resulted in identification of a total of 14 genes without significant homology.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Identification of interstitial cell lineage-specific genes in <italic>Hydra </italic>by suppression subtractive hybridization (SSH)</bold>. <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>(strain sf-1) cDNA was used as tester and cDNA of interstitial cell free <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>(sf1) as driver to generate a library enriched for transcripts of the interstitial cell lineage. BLASTx analysis could group 105 EST-contig sequences into three categories of homology: 45 sequences (43%) had strong similarities (e-value &#x0003c; 1e-20) to known metazoan proteins; 44 sequences (42%) had low e-values (&#x0003e;1e -7); 16 sequences (15%) had no homologues in the NCBI protein database, representing genes putatively restricted to the genus <italic>Hydra</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-1"/></fig><p>Next, we analyzed the expression of these putative TRGs by whole mount <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization. Out of the 14 genes, 9 represent transcripts expressed exclusively in differentiating nematocytes. While five of them (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a-h</xref>; <italic>nb001</italic>, <italic>nb035</italic>, <italic>nb039</italic>, <italic>nb042</italic>, <italic>nb082</italic>) show expression in all types of differentiating nematocytes, three genes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2i-k</xref>; <italic>nb012</italic>, <italic>nb054</italic>, <italic>nb092</italic>) are expressed only in isorhiza and desmonemes. One gene (<italic>nb031</italic>; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2l</xref>) is exclusively expressed in stenoteles, predominantly at the base of tentacles.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Expression of taxonomically restricted genes identified in the suppression subtractive hybridization screening in <italic>Hydra </italic>nematocytes</bold>. Whole mount <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization of nine TRG sequences represent transcripts expressed exclusively in differentiating nematocytes. <bold>(a-h) </bold>Five transcripts show expression in all types of differentiating nematocytes: <italic>nb001 </italic>(a), <italic>nb035 </italic>(e), <italic>nb039 </italic>(f), <italic>nb042 </italic>(g), <italic>nb082 </italic>(h). <bold>(b-d)</bold> Magnifications of nematoblast nests: stenotheles (b); izorhiza (c); desmonemes (d). <bold>(i-k) </bold>Three TRGs are expressed only in isorhiza and desmonemes: <italic>nb012 </italic>(i); <italic>nb054 </italic>(j); <italic>nb092 </italic>(k). <bold>(l) </bold>One TRG, <italic>nb031</italic>, is exclusively expressed in stenoteles predominantly at the base of tentacles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-2"/></fig><p>To investigate whether the identified genes were restricted to the species <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>or are also present in other <italic>Hydra </italic>species (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3a</xref>), we analyzed their expression in the related <italic>Hydra oligactis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref> indicates that genes <italic>nb012</italic>, <italic>nb035</italic>, <italic>nb039</italic>, <italic>nb042 </italic>and <italic>nb054 </italic>give a strong <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization signal in differentiating nematocytes in both <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>and <italic>H. oligactis</italic>, representing, therefore, genes putatively restricted to the genus <italic>Hydra</italic>. TRGs found to be expressed in nematocytes in both species share high sequence similarity at the nucleotide and amino acid levels. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref> also indicates that transcripts for <italic>nb031</italic>, <italic>nb082</italic>, and <italic>nb092 </italic>cannot be detected in <italic>H. oligactis</italic>, representing, therefore, genes putatively restricted to the species <italic>H. magnipapillata</italic>. Interestingly, screening the genome of the anthozoan sea anemone <italic>Nematostella vectensis </italic>provided evidence for the presence of at least two of the above-described nematocyte-specific TRGs in this distantly related cnidarian (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>). Thus, these genes seem to be present in many classes of the phylum Cnidaria but absent in other metazoan taxa. Therefore, such genes might be considered 'cnidaria-specific'.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Comparative expression analysis of taxonomically restricted genes in different types of developing nematocytes</bold>. <bold>(a) </bold>Phylogenetic relationships in the genus <italic>Hydra</italic>; colors indicate the examined species referred to in the table in (b); phylogenetic tree modified from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. <bold>(b) </bold>TRG expression in developing nematocytes in two different <italic>Hydra </italic>species (<italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>and <italic>H. oligactis</italic>) as well as conservation of corresponding TRGs between the two species and possible othologuous sequences in the distantly related anthozoan sea anemone <italic>Nematostella vectensis</italic>. aa, amino acid; nt, nucleotide.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Characterization of taxonomically restricted genes expressed in nematocytes</title><sec><title>A novel family of minicollagen proteins originates from one genomic locus</title><p>Detailed analysis of the gene <italic>nb001 </italic>revealed that it encodes a novel member of the minicollagen family of proteins containing the previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] structural features such as a signal peptide, propetide, cystein rich domain, and a proline-repeat flanked collagen-like domain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>). In a recent review [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] the protein encoded by <italic>nb001 </italic>was referred to as 'minicollagen 6'. At the nucleotide level, <italic>nb001 </italic>shares no similarity to previously published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] minicollagens.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Genomic organization and alternative transcripts of <italic>nb001</italic>/<italic>minicollagen</italic></bold>. <bold>(a) </bold>Mapping of <italic>nb001 </italic>EST-contigs (<italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv1 </italic>to <italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv5</italic>; black) and amplified PCR products (<italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv6 </italic>to <italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv9</italic>; blue) to the corresponding genomic locus (<italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>genomic scaffold NW_002161526). <italic>nb001 </italic>transcripts encode a protein with a signal peptide (sp; green), pro-peptide (pro; black) and a collagen-like domain (yellow) flanked by two praline repeats (P<sub>n</sub>; magenta) and two cystein-rich-domains (CRD; red). <bold>(b) </bold>Alignment of the amino acid sequences of predicted splice variants. <bold>(c) </bold>Northern blot indicates the presence of <italic>nb001 </italic>transcripts corresponding to most of the predicted splice variants. Probe for hybridization corresponds to exon 2 and the first half of exon 3 (yellow line in (a)). Asterisks indicate stop codons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-4"/></fig><p>Analysis of <italic>nb001 </italic>transcripts in the EST data bank and the corresponding genomic locus uncovered five different splice variants (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>, <italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv1 </italic>to <italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv5</italic>: CL1Contig4, CL1Contig3, CL1Contig2, CL1Contig1 and CL1Contig5, respectively). In addition, by PCR amplification we could identify four more splice variants (<italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv6 </italic>to <italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv9</italic>; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>). Interestingly, while the first two introns are spliced by conventional splicing sites (GT/AG), additional variants of the transcripts are generated by processing of exon 3. As a result of this process, which may use unconventional 'splicing' sites, various regions of exon 3 are removed.</p><p>The resulting nb001 predicted proteins (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4b</xref>) indicate domain length variations of the collagen-like domain as well as the proline and cysteine repeats. In contrast to previously reported minicollagens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], all nb001 variants described here have 19-27 Gly-X-Y repeats instead of 12-16, resulting in an expanded collagen-like domain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4b</xref>). Other nb001 variants are characterized by a shortened praline repeat following the collagen-like domain. Three variants (<italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv7 </italic>to <italic>nb001</italic>-<italic>sv9</italic>) lack both the collagen-like domain and the proline repeats. These variants contain only a single cystein rich domain with an altered cysteine pattern - (CXXX)<sub>7</sub>-CC, (CXXX)<sub>5</sub>-CC or (CXXX)<sub>2</sub>-CC - instead of the conserved (CXXX)<sub>4</sub>-CC. Northern blot analysis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4c</xref>) shows a strong signal at around 700 bp, indicating the presence of <italic>nb001 </italic>transcripts corresponding to most of the predicted variants.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Spinalin</italic>, a previously identified nematocyte-specific gene is a splice variant derived from a complex genetic locus</title><p>Genomic analysis of TRG <italic>nb054 </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref>) revealed that the corresponding 50 kb spanning genomic locus contains the gene <italic>spinalin</italic>, which was previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] to be involved in spine development of nematocysts. Sequence analysis confirmed by PCR amplification studies revealed that <italic>spinalin </italic>and <italic>nb054 </italic>are, in fact, encoded by a single gene and, therefore, must be considered as splice variants. While the first six exons encode the previously identified <italic>spinalin</italic>, splicing within the 6th exon leads to much longer transcript variants containing the first 6 exons plus an additional 2-16 exons, resulting in a large number of differentially spliced transcripts of about 3,000 bp (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref>). The short 983 bp transcript encoding spinalin is produced by alternative splicing and usage of the resulting stop codon within exon 6. Since this genomic region is rich in AT repeats (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref>), some sequence areas encoding the TRG <italic>nb054 </italic>remain unresolved and, therefore, the final number of <italic>nb054</italic>-specific exons remains to be determined. Northern blot analysis with <italic>spinalin</italic>- and <italic>nb054</italic>-specific probes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5b</xref>) revealed three distinct signals of about 1, 1.7 and 3 kb corresponding to the predicted <italic>spinalin </italic>and <italic>nb054 </italic>transcripts.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Genomic organization and alternative transcripts of <italic>nb054</italic>/<italic>spinalin</italic></bold>. <bold>(a) </bold>Mapping of <italic>spinalin </italic>and <italic>nb054 </italic>alternative transcripts to the corresponding genomic locus (<italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>genomic scaffold NW_002161446). The resulting gene-model shows two alternatively used stop codons indicated by asterisks. Since this genomic region is rich in AT repeats (n), some sequence areas remain unresolved and, therefore, the final number of <italic>nb054</italic>-specific exons remains to be determined. <bold>(b) </bold>Northern blot analysis with <italic>spinalin </italic>and <italic>nb054 </italic>specific probes (yellow lines in (a)).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Gene duplication contributes to the complexity of nematocyte-specific gene families</title><p>The TRG <italic>nb039 </italic>has blast hits to two distinct but similar genomic contigs (NW_002158707, NW_002162805), which we named nb039-A and nb039-B (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a,b</xref>). Corresponding ESTs could be grouped into two independent sets of EST contigs, which are identical to the respective genomic locus and represent several different splice variants. Additionally, we were able to amplify 11 more partial splice variants for nb039-A and three more partial splice variants for nb039-B. From the locus nb039-A, two splice variants use alternative 3' untranslated regions (UTRs; <italic>nb039a</italic>-<italic>sv4</italic>/CL1Contig423, <italic>nb039a</italic>-<italic>sv10</italic>) due to early stop codons, which most likely were inserted by alternative splicing. Comparison of the exon/intron distribution pattern in the 5' adjacent region of nb039-A and nb039-B (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6a,b</xref>) indicates striking structural similarity. A comparative sequence analysis of both loci (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6c</xref>) provided evidence that they are the result of a gene duplication event since the gene-encoding part of nb039-A and nb039-B is highly conserved but flanked by stretches of non-conserved genomic sequences.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Genomic organization and alternative transcripts of <italic>nb039 </italic>loci A and B</bold>. <bold>(a) </bold>Genomic organization and alternative transcripts of <italic>nb039 </italic>locus A. <bold>(b) </bold>Genomic organization and alternative transcripts of <italic>nb039 </italic>locus B. <bold>(c) </bold>Comparative sequence analysis of both loci. Note that the gene-encoding part of nb039-A and nb039-B is highly conserved but flanked by stretches of non-conserved genomic sequences. Asterisks indicate stop codons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-6"/></fig><p>A second example of a putative gene duplication event in a TRG gene expressed in nematocytes was discovered when analyzing the genomic locus of <italic>nb012</italic>. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7a</xref>, this gene consists of seven exons corresponding to one EST contig (<italic>nb012a</italic>/CL243Contig1). The full-length transcript of this EST-contig contains a laminin-G-like domain located on exons 4 and 5. Screening the available <italic>Hydra </italic>EST collections revealed a second partial transcript with a laminin G-like domain with a sequence related but not identical to <italic>nb012a</italic>. We termed this transcript <italic>nb012b </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7b</xref>). The available genome assembly suggests that this second partial transcript is encoded within the gene encoding <italic>nb012a</italic>. PCR based analysis, however, did not provide evidence for a transcript containing sequences of both <italic>nb012a </italic>and <italic>nb012b</italic>. Since a more informative re-assembly of the <italic>nb012 </italic>locus is currently not possible because of limited sequence data, we assume but cannot prove that <italic>nb012a </italic>and <italic>nb012b </italic>represent gene duplication events. <italic>In situ </italic>hybridization using <italic>nb012a</italic>- and <italic>nb012b</italic>-specific probes indicated (Figure 7c-e) that <italic>nb012b </italic>indeed represents a gene co-expressed with <italic>nb012a</italic>. The low level of sequence similarity in the probes used for the <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization analysis excluded the possibility of cross-hybridization. Double <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization confirmed that both genes are spatially and temporarily co-expressed in the same set of nematocytes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7e</xref>). Furthermore, Northern blot analysis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7f</xref>) using the <italic>nb012a</italic>- and <italic>nb012b</italic>-specific probes indicated the presence of two independent transcripts of about 1,700 and 2,200 bp, respectively. This supports the view that both genes are located on different genomic loci.</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Genomic organization of <italic>nb012 </italic>loci A and B</bold>. <bold>(a) </bold>Genomic organization of <italic>nb012 </italic>locus A. <bold>(b) </bold>Genomic organization of <italic>nb012 </italic>locus B. <bold>(c, d) </bold>Expression of <italic>nb012a </italic>and <italic>nb012b </italic>in nematoblasts. <bold>(e) </bold>Double <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization using digoxigenin- and biotin-labeled probes for <italic>n012a </italic>and <italic>nb012b</italic>, respectively. As indicated in the higher magnification inset, both transcripts are co-localized in the same set of nematoblasts. <bold>(f) </bold>Northern blot analysis using <italic>nb012a</italic>- and <italic>nb012b</italic>-specific probes (yellow lines in (a, b)). Asterisks indicate stop codons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-7"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sharing 3' UTRs in some nematocyte specific genes indicates common regulation of different splice variants</title><p>Analyzing the genomic locus encoding TRG <italic>nb035 </italic>revealed a gene consisting of two exons (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8a</xref>). While the first exon encodes a large open reading frame of 2,347 bp, the second exon is short and represents mainly 3' UTR. Three partial contigs (CL1Contig431, CL1Contig609, CL1Contig10) could be identified in the EST project and map to this locus. Rapid amplification of cDNA ends (3' and 5' RACE; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8a</xref>) revealed that <italic>nb035 </italic>encodes three distinct splice variants (<italic>nb035</italic>-<italic>sv1 </italic>to <italic>nb035</italic>-<italic>sv3</italic>) that share a common 3' UTR. While the stop codon of <italic>nb035</italic>-<italic>sv1 </italic>is located at the end of the first exon, the stop codons for <italic>nb035</italic>-<italic>sv2 </italic>and <italic>nb035</italic>-<italic>sv3 </italic>are located in exon 2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8a,b</xref>). As a result, corresponding proteins differ in their carboxy-terminal parts. Exon 1 encodes an extensin-related domain, which is altered in <italic>nb035</italic>-<italic>sv3</italic>. Northern blot analysis using probes specific for the three splice variants (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8c</xref>) shows three distinct signals of 1,400, 2,400 and 3,100 bp, respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Genomic organization and alternative transcripts of <italic>nb035</italic></bold>. <bold>(a) </bold>Genomic organization and splice variants of <italic>nb035 </italic>(<italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>genomic scaffold NW_002151021). <bold>(b) </bold>As a result of alternative splicing three proteins with different carboxy-terminal sequences are encoded. <bold>(c) </bold>Northern blot analysis using probes specific for the three splice variants (yellow lines in (a)). Asterisks indicate stop codons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-8"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>How are taxonomically restricted genes regulated?</title><sec><title>The 1 kb upstream region of <italic>nb001 </italic>lacks any conserved transcription factor binding sites</title><p>How are genes that lack sequence similarity to known genes regulated? In an attempt to unravel the transcriptional regulatory network controlling expression of a TRG, we analyzed the <italic>nb001 </italic>5' flanking sequence. To identify the 5' regulatory sequence, we used the <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>genome data deposited at NCBI. Since <italic>nb001 </italic>is expressed in a seemingly identical manner across species borders (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>), we reasoned that sequences important for control of <italic>nb001 </italic>expression were strongly conserved at the nucleotide level, since their potential for mutation is constrained by their function. As described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], such evolutionarily conserved <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements can be identified by phylogenetic footprinting.</p><p>Approximately 1 kb of 5' flanking sequence of the <italic>nb001 </italic>gene was analyzed from <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>(strain 105) and closely related <italic>H. vulgaris </italic>(strain AEP) using the previously described ConSite platform [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9a</xref>, the 5' flanking regions are of unexpected high overall identity, with three regions, named regions I, II and III (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9a</xref>), nearly identical between the two different species. These regions were subjected to conserved transcription factor binding site prediction (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9b</xref>). As <italic>Hydra </italic>has an AT-rich genome composition, several cycles of analysis were performed with increasing transcription factor score thresholds, thus modulating the stringency of the sequence analysis. However, apart from AT-rich stretches, no conserved and informative binding motif remained detectable (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9b</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F9"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><bold>Analysis of the <italic>nb001 </italic>promoter by phylogenetic footprinting</bold>. <bold>(a) </bold>Conservation profile of <italic>H. vulgaris </italic>strain AEP and <italic>H. magnipapillata nb001 </italic>5' flanking regions. Three regions (1-3) exceed the conservation cut-off (98%) used for transcription factor (TF) binding site prediction. <bold>(b) </bold>Top-scoring motifs resulting from computational transcription factor binding site prediction (Consite).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-9"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The 1 kb upstream region of <italic>nb001 </italic>is essential and sufficient for correct expression <italic>in vivo</italic></title><p>To functionally characterize the putative regulatory sequence of <italic>nb001 in vivo</italic>, we have generated transgenic polyps that express enhanced GFP (eGFP) under the control of the isolated <italic>nb001 </italic>5' flanking sequence. The transgenic construct was made by placing the 1,035 bp <italic>nb001 </italic>promoter (-305 to -1274 relative to the transcription initiation site and including the signal peptide of <italic>nb001</italic>) in front of the GFP reporter gene (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10a</xref>). The plasmid was injected into <italic>Hydra </italic>embryos as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Embryos hatched within 2-3 weeks after injection. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref> shows examples of such transgenic polyps and demonstrates that the 1035 bp 5' flanking region of the <italic>nb001 </italic>gene is able to direct the expression of eGFP in differentiating nematocytes in a pattern that recapitulates precisely the endogenous expression pattern of the <italic>nb001 </italic>gene (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> for comparison). Stereo- and confocal microscopy (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10b-f</xref>) shows nests of nematocytes with eGFP in groups of 4, 8 and 16 along the body column. This provides <italic>in vivo </italic>proof for the view [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] that differentiating nematocytes undergo several rounds of synchronous cell division and remain connected to each other by cytoplasmic bridges prior to terminal differentiation. The <italic>nb001 </italic>gene has a signal peptide, which was included in the construct (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10a</xref>). Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10c-f</xref> shows that the signal peptide drives the eGFP reporter protein into the lumen of the secretory vesicle within differentiating nematocytes. In control transgenic <italic>Hydra </italic>expressing eGFP in nematocytes driven by the <italic>Hydra </italic>actin promoter without a signal peptide, the reporter protein is localized in the cytoplasm (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10g</xref>). These results identify the 1035 bp as essential and sufficient for <italic>nb001 </italic>expression <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><fig position="float" id="F10"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p><bold>Functional analysis of the <italic>nb001 </italic>promoter using transgenic polyps</bold>. <bold>(a) </bold>Expression constructs for generation of transgenic <italic>Hydra </italic>(SP, signal peptide). <bold>(b) </bold>Polyp with eGFP-expressing differentiating nematocytes. Note that the <italic>nb001 </italic>driven eGFP expression recapitulates the nb001 expression shown in Figure 2a. As indicated by the dashed lines, expression is located only in the bodycolumn and not in the head or foot. <bold>(c) </bold>Confocal analysis of polyp containing eGFP-expressing nematocytes reveals that the promoter drives expression of eGFP in all four types of nematocytes; scale bar, 50 &#x003bc;m. The inset indicates control transgenic nematocytes with eGFP expression under control of actin promoter. <bold>(d) </bold>Transgenic nematocytes provide <italic>in vivo </italic>evidence for the view [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] that differentiating nematocytes undergo several rounds of synchronous cell division and remain connected to each other by cytoplasmic bridges to form nests of 4, 8 or more cells; scale bar, 25 &#x003bc;m. <bold>(e) </bold>Tentacle of transgenic polyp in which many but not all nematocytes are expressing eGFP. Confocal analysis. Green, eGFP protein; red, actin filaments; scale bar, 10 &#x003bc;m. <bold>(f) </bold>Confocal analysis of transgenic stenotele (arrow) in the gastric region showing eGFP protein localized within the capsule wall and tubule of the nematocyst. Red, actin filaments; scale bar, 15 &#x003bc;m. <bold>(g) </bold>Control transgenic polyp with eGFP expression under control of actin promoter. Note that eGFP is localized within the cytoplasm and the nematocyst is eGFP negative (arrows). Green, eGFP protein; red, actin filaments; scale bar, 15 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-10"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>One of the main challenges in evolutionary biology is to identify the molecular changes that underlie phenotypic differences that are of evolutionary significance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Our results suggest that taxonomically restricted genes are involved in the evolution of morphological novelties such as the cnidarian nematocyst.</p><sec><title>The nematocyte, a cnidarian invention, expresses cnidarian-specific genes</title><p>The nematocyte is a cell type exclusively restricted to cnidarians and - from an evolutionary perspective - is considered a neuronal sensory cell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. During evolution, these neuron-like cells obviously became highly diverged and acquired new cytological features such as the nematocysts (capsules). Each nematocyst consists of an inner and outer capsule wall, an inverted tubule armed with long arrays of spines, and an operculum (for a recent review, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]). Development of this cnidarian-specific structure requires complex genetic machinery, consisting of at least two sets of proteins, regulatory transcription factors and structural proteins. One of the few transcription factors identified up to now as being involved in nematocyte differentiation, <italic>Hyzic</italic>, is a homolog of the Zn-finger transcription factor gene <italic>zic</italic>/<italic>odd</italic>-<italic>paired</italic>. <italic>Hyzic </italic>is expressed in the early nematocyte differentiation pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] and may act before, and possibly directly upstream of, <italic>Cnash</italic>, a homolog of the proneural basic helix-loop helix transcription factor gene <italic>achaete</italic>-<italic>scute</italic>.</p><p>In contrast to these conserved transcription factors, the downstream structural proteins responsible for putting the nematocysts into shape appear to belong to the group of taxonomically restricted genes. Some of them, such as some minicollagens, spinalin and NOWA, have been reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. Interestingly, in addition to nematocysts, novel proteins appear also to be essential components of other structures of the nematocyte, such as the cnidocil, a cnidarian-specific mechanosensory ciliary structure acting as a 'trigger' for discharge of the nematocyst capsule. The central core of the cnidocil contains a protein, nematocilin, that lacks homologues outside <italic>Hydra </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Two paralogous sequences of nematocilin are present in the <italic>Hydra </italic>genome and appear to be the result of recent gene duplication. Nematocilin is absent in the anthozoan <italic>Nematostella vectensis</italic>; it seems, therefore, to be a gene restricted to the class Hydrozoa.</p><p>Nematocysts arguably are one of the most complex secretory products produced by an animal cell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. How the different nematocyst morphologies evolved is unknown. David and co-workers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] have proposed that a diverse set of minicollagen proteins together with a disulfide-linked network of not yet identified fiber-like structures could have been instrumental in the evolution of the different nematocyst morphologies. Our discovery of striking complexity of nematocyte-specific genes at both the genomic and transcriptomic levels may indicate that bundles of protein variants produced by alternative splicing (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) and transcription at multiple loci (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>) contribute to the conformational and structural flexibility of the nematocyst.</p><p>Alternative splicing has been proposed as the primary driver of the evolution of phenotypic complexity in mammals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. While alternative splicing is known to affect more than half of all human genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>], it has been unclear whether and to what extent a similar mechanism operates in early branching metazoans. Our finding of numerous splice variants in <italic>Hydra</italic>, therefore, was surprising and points to a strong conservation of splicing regulation throughout animal evolution.</p><p>Taken together, as described here and consistent with previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], the majority of genes encoding nematocyst components have no homologues in higher metazoans and are unique to the cnidarian lineage.</p></sec><sec><title>Transgenic <italic>Hydra </italic>contribute to understanding regulatory evolution and transcriptional control of TRGs</title><p>The finding that the differentiation of a taxon-specific cell type, the nematocyte, involves the expression of taxon-specific genes promises to unveil novel aspects of the evolution of this complex cell type in particular and of species-specific traits in general. The work also raises an important question: how do these novel genes interact with upstream transcriptional regulators? Do they contain binding sites for conserved transcription factors? Or do they require novel transcription factors? We have previously hypothesized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] that taxon-specific genes in combination with the rewiring of the genetic networks of conserved regulatory genes accomplish specification of cnidarian morphologies. Here, in order to address this question experimentally, we took advantage of the recent development of transgenic techniques by embryo-microinjection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], which offers a rich opportunity to expand research activities in <italic>Hydra </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. As expected, transgenic <italic>Hydra </italic>appear to yield usable insight into the regulatory network controlling expression of genes that lack sequence similarity to known genes. According to the functional analysis of the <italic>nb001 </italic>promoter (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>), the transcriptional machinery regulating TRG expression may involve not yet identified transcription factors. Alternatively, regulatory elements for conserved transcription factors may be highly diverged in promoters of TRGs and, therefore, not detectable in the present approach. Current efforts are directed towards identification of transcription factors causally involved in control of TRG expression.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Taken together, although certainly much remains to be discovered about the role of TRGs in <italic>Hydra</italic>, the observations presented here reaffirm the view [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] that taxon-specific genes account for a substantial part of the <italic>Hydra </italic>genome and may be of profound evolutionary significance both in animals that reach back to the beginnings of metazoan life as well as in more complex organisms.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Animals and culture conditions</title><p>Experiments were carried out with <italic>H. vulgaris </italic>strain AEP, <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>strain 105, and <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>strain sf1. Transgenic animals were generated using <italic>H. vulgaris </italic>strain AEP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Animals were cultured according to standard procedures at 18&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Supression subtractive hybridization and cDNA library construction</title><p>For SSH, double-stranded cDNA was synthesized using 2 &#x003bc;g of mRNA from the temperature sensitive mutant <italic>H. magnipapillata </italic>sf1. SSH was performed using PCR-Select&#x02122; cDNA Subtraction kit (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol. Two RNA pools were used for subtractive hybridization (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Tester double-stranded cDNA was synthesized from mRNA isolated from heat shocked animals free of i-cells and their derivatives. Driver double-stranded cDNA was synthesized from mRNA from untreated polyps containing all cell types. cDNAs were cloned into pGEM-T vector (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) and transformed into DH5 &#x003b1; <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>cells. Bacterial clones were picked into 384 well plates using Q-Pix roboter and plasmid inserts were sequenced at the Washington University Genome Sequencing Centre (St Louis, MO, USA). Raw sequences were submitted to NCBI dbEST database ([GenBank:<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="CO371734">CO371734</ext-link>-<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="CO372031">CO372031</ext-link>], [GenBank:<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="CO373914">CO373914</ext-link>-<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="CO377781">CO377781</ext-link>], [GenBank:<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="CO508771">CO508771</ext-link>-<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="CO510748">CO510748</ext-link>]).</p></sec><sec><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p>To analyze gene expression, whole mount <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization was carried out as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Whole mount double <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization was performed using DIG- and Biotin-labeled RNA probes simultaneously. Antibody incubation and substrate reactions were carried out consecutively as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. NBT/BCIP- and Fast Red substrates were used for probe detection according to the manufacturer's instructions (Roche, Nutley, NJ, USA). Riboprobes were prepared with the Dig- and Biotin- RNA labeling kit according to the manufacturer's instructions (Roche).</p></sec><sec><title>Northern blotting</title><p>RNA-electrophoresis, transfer, probe-labeling, hybridization and detection procedures were carried out according to standard protocols. For primer sequences used for probe amplification, see Additional data file 1.</p></sec><sec><title>Access to primer and sequence data</title><p>For primer sequences used to amplify full-length sequences and splice variants, see Additional data file 1. For retrieval of sequence data and EST contigs, see Additional data file 2.</p></sec><sec><title>Generation of transgenic <italic>H. vulgaris </italic>AEP expressing <italic>nb001</italic>:eGFP</title><p>Transgenic founder polyps expressing eGFP under control of the <italic>nb001 </italic>promoter were produced at the University of Kiel Transgenic <italic>Hydra </italic>Facility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. The transgenic construct was made by placing the 1,035 bp <italic>nb001 </italic>promoter (-1,075 to +65 relative to the transcription initiation site and including the signal peptide of <italic>nb001</italic>) in front of the reporter gene for eGFP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10a</xref>). The resulting plasmid ligAB was injected into <italic>Hydra </italic>embryos as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Out of 64 injected embryos, 21 (32%) hatched, from which two lines contained eGFP-positive nematocytes and no eGFP expression in any other cell type. Initial founder transgenic animals were expanded into a mass culture by clonal propagation by budding.</p></sec><sec><title>Microscopy analysis</title><p>Fluorescent images were taken on a Zeiss Axioscope fluorescence microscope with an Axiocam (Zeiss) digital camera. Confocal laser microscopy was done using a LEICA TCS SP1 CLS microscope. A Zeiss S420 microscope was used for scanning electron microscopy.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>EGFP: enhanced GFP; EST: expressed sequence tag; GFP: green fluorescent protein; NCBI: National Centre for Biotechnology Information; SSH: suppression subtractive hybridization; TRG: taxonomically restricted gene; UTR: untranslated region.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>SM, GH, and KK designed and carried out the experiments; FAE carried out the confocal microscopy analysis; JW carried out embryo microinjection; TB conceived of the study and participated in its design and coordination; SM, GH, KK, and TB drafted, read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Additional data files</title><p>The following additional data are available with the online version of this paper. Additional data file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref> is a table listing all primer sequences used to amplify full length sequences and splice variants of the described <italic>Hydra </italic>TRGs. Additional data file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref> is a table showing all GenBank accession numbers of full-length sequences and splice variants and sequence IDs for retrieval of EST contig sequences at [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional data file 1</title><p>Primer sequences used to amplify full length sequences and splice variants of the described <italic>Hydra </italic>TRGs.</p></caption><media xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-S1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional data file 2</title><p>GenBank accession numbers of full-length sequences and splice variants and sequence IDs for retrieval of EST contig sequences at [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>].</p></caption><media xlink:href="gb-2009-10-1-r8-S2.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank three anonymous referees for their helpful and constructive comments on the manuscript. We thank the members of the Bosch laboratory for discussion and Antje Thomas and Meike Friedrichsen for excellent technical help, and Jan Lohman, Ingrid Lohman and Sebastian Fraune for valuable comments on a previous version of the manuscript. We are grateful to Holger Zill and Ren&#x000e9; Augustin for assistance with the SSH libraries. Supported in part by grants from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft, and grants from the DFG Cluster of Excellence programs "The Future Ocean" and "Inflammation at Interfaces" (to TCGB).</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tardent</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zierold</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Klug</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>X-ray microanalysis of elements present in the matrix of cnidarian nematocysts.</article-title><source>Tissue Cell</source><year>1990</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18620323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0040-8166(90)90060-M</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tardent</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leutert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Frei</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Untersuchungen zur Taxonomie von <italic>Hydra circumcincta </italic>Schulze <italic>Hydra stellata </italic>Schulze 1914, und <italic>Hydra ovata </italic>Boecker 1920.</article-title><source>Rev Suisse Zool</source><year>1968</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4389019</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Emschermann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cnidaria: Hydrozoa</source><year>1995</year><publisher-name>Stuttgard, Jena, New York: Gustav Fischer Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;zbek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Adamczyk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gojobori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of complex structures: minicollagens shape the cnidarian nematocyst.</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18676050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2008.07.001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mini-collagens in <italic>Hydra </italic>nematocytes.</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>1159</fpage><lpage>1169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1955459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.115.4.1159</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A switch in disulfide linkage during minicollagen assembly in <italic>Hydra </italic>nematocysts.</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>3063</fpage><lpage>3073</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11406583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/20.12.3063</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;zbek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Streitwolf-Engel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lottspeich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nowa, a novel protein with minicollagen Cys-rich domains, is involved in nematocyst formation in <italic>Hydra</italic>.</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>3923</fpage><lpage>3934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12244130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.00084</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mala</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spinalin, a new glycine- and histidine-rich protein in spines of <italic>Hydra </italic>nematocysts.</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>1545</fpage><lpage>1554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9580562</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duboule</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolution of 'bricolage'.</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9520598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-9525(97)01358-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution at two levels: on genes and form.</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e245</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16000021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030245</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evo-devo and an expanding evolutionary synthesis: a genetic theory of morphological evolution.</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18614008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.06.030</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalturin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterning and cell differentiation in <italic>Hydra</italic>: novel genes and the limits to conservation.</article-title><source>Can J Zool</source><year>2002</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1670</fpage><lpage>1677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/z02-129</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalturin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Anton-Erxleben</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittlieb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmrich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel gene family controls species-specific morphological traits in <italic>Hydra</italic>.</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e278</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19018660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0060278</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Finding families for genomic ORFans.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>1999</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10498776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/15.9.759</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of the eukaryotes.</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>2204</fpage><lpage>2215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.287.5461.2204</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-scale comparative genomic ranking of taxonomically restricted genes (TRGs) in bacterial and archaeal genomes.</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e324</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17389915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0000324</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of developmental mechanisms in <italic>Hydra</italic>. II. Isolation and characterization of an interstitial cell-deficient strain.</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1978</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">627611</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bosch TCG</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Stem cells in immortal <italic>Hydra</italic>.</article-title><source>Stem Cells: From Hydra to Man</source><year>2008</year><publisher-name>Berlin Heidelberg: Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigenaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of developmental mechanisms in hydra. XVIII. Mechanism for elimination of the interstitial cell lineage in the mutant strain Sf-1.</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>1988</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3350211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0012-1606(88)90137-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemmrich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Anokhin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacharias</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular phylogenetics in <italic>Hydra</italic>, a classical model in evolutionary developmental biology.</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2007</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17174108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2006.10.031</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;zbek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwager</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lustig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure/function relationship in the minicollagen of <italic>Hydra </italic>nematocysts.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>49200</fpage><lpage>49204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M209401200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adamczyk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobmayer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grzesiek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;chinger</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;zbek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minicollagen-15, a novel minicollagen isolated from <italic>Hydra</italic>, forms tubule structures in nematocysts.</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>376</volume><fpage>1008</fpage><lpage>1020</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18206162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2007.10.090</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siebert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of foot differentiation in <italic>Hydra</italic>: phylogenetic footprinting indicates interaction of head, bud and foot patterning systems.</article-title><source>Mech Dev</source><year>2005</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>998</fpage><lpage>1007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15922570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mod.2005.04.010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wittlieb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalturin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>Anton-Erxleben</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transgenic <italic>Hydra </italic>allow <italic>in vivo </italic>tracking of individual stem cells during morphogenesis.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>6208</fpage><lpage>6211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16556723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0510163103</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teilungsfolgen und Determination von I-Zellen f&#x000fc;r die Cnidenbildung bei <italic>Hydra</italic>.</article-title><source>Z Naturforsch</source><year>1951</year><volume>6b</volume><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>391</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slautterback</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The development of the cnidoblasts of <italic>Hydra</italic>; an electron microscope study of cell differentiation.</article-title><source>J Biophys Biochem Cytol</source><year>1959</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13664685</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tardent</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Untersuchung zur Nematocyten-Differenzierung bei <italic>Hydra attenuata</italic>.</article-title><source>Rev Suisse Zool</source><year>1966</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4394046</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Commitment during nematocyte differentiation in <italic>Hydra</italic>.</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1981</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7276089</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of development in closely related species of flies and worms.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>907</fpage><lpage>917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12459721</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg947</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bode</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary conservation of a cell fate specification gene: the <italic>Hydra </italic>achaete-scute homolog has proneural activity in <italic>Drosophila</italic>.</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1995</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>4027</fpage><lpage>4035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8575303</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedders</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Augustin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Dickkopf-3 related gene is expressed in differentiating nematocytes in the basal metazoan <italic>Hydra</italic>.</article-title><source>Dev Genes Evol</source><year>2004</year><volume>214</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14727109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00427-003-0378-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindgens</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Technau</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hyzic, the <italic>Hydra </italic>homolog of the zic/odd-paired gene, is involved in the early specification of the sensory nematocytes.</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2004</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.00903</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohyanagi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Osato</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimiya-Fujisawa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gojobori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolutionary emergence of cell type-specific genes inferred from the gene expression analysis of <italic>Hydra</italic>.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>14735</fpage><lpage>14740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17766437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0703331104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Takaku</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gojobori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cilium evolution: identification of a novel protein, nematocilin, in the mechanosensory cilium of <italic>Hydra </italic>nematocytes.</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2009</fpage><lpage>2017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msn154</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The morphogenesis of nematocytes in <italic>Hydra </italic>and Forsk&#x000e5;lia: an ultrastructural study.</article-title><source>J Ultrastruct Res</source><year>1981</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7277568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5320(81)80085-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Linton</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Birren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusbaum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zody</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Devon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>FitzHugh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Funke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heaford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Howland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehoczky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>LeVine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McEwan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McKernan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldrim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheridan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sougnez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Initial sequencing and analysis of the human genome.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>409</volume><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11237011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35057062</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrett-Engele</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Loerch</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Armour</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schadt</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoughton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide survey of human alternative pre-mRNA splicing with exon junction microarrays.</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>302</volume><fpage>2141</fpage><lpage>2144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14684825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1090100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khrebtukova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsmore</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroth</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative isoform regulation in human tissue transcriptomes.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>456</volume><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18978772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07509</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalturin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Anton-Erxleben</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Milde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pl&#x000f6;tz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittlieb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmrich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transgenic stem cells in <italic>Hydra </italic>reveal an early evolutionary origin for key elements controlling self-renewal and differentiation.</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17659272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2007.06.013</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siebert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anton-Erxleben</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell type complexity in the basal metazoan <italic>Hydra </italic>is maintained by both stem cell based mechanisms and transdifferentiation.</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>313</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18029279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2007.09.007</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anton-Erxleben</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittlieb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraune</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>TCG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasticity of epithelial cell shape in response to upstream signals: a whole-organism study using transgenic <italic>Hydra</italic>.</article-title><source>Zoology</source><year>2009</year><comment>doi10.1016/j.zool.2008.09.002.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19201587</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bode</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CnNK-2, an NK-2 homeobox gene, has a role in patterning the basal end of the axis in hydra.</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8954720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/dbio.1996.0321</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimmelikhuijzen</surname><given-names>CJP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two-color double-labeling <italic>in situ </italic>hybridization of whole-mount <italic>Hydra </italic>using RNA probes for five different <italic>Hydra </italic>neuropeptide preprohormones: evidence for colocalization.</article-title><source>Cell Tissue Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>301</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10955720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004410000240</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Transgenic <italic>Hydra </italic>Facility</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.transgenic-hydra.org"/></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Compagen, a comparative genomics platform for early branching Metazoa</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.compagen.org"/></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 