<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2164-10-261</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505301</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-10-261</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular signature of cell cycle exit induced in human T lymphoblasts by IL-2 withdrawal</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chechlinska</surname><given-names>Magdalena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>chech@coi.waw.pl</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Siwicki</surname><given-names>Jan Konrad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jksiwicki@coi.waw.pl</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gos</surname><given-names>Monika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>monikagos@coi.waw.pl</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oczko-Wojciechowska</surname><given-names>Malgorzata</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>gosiaoczko@io.gliwice.pl</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jarzab</surname><given-names>Michal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>mjarzab@io.gliwice.pl</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>Aleksandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>apfeifer@io.gliwice.pl</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jarzab</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>bjarzab@io.gliwice.pl</email></contrib><contrib id="A8" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jsteffen@coi.waw.pl</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Immunology, Maria Sklodowska-Curie Memorial Cancer Centre and Institute of Oncology, Warsaw, Poland</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Cell Biology, Maria Sklodowska-Curie Memorial Cancer Centre and Institute of Oncology, Warsaw, Poland</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Nuclear Medicine and Endocrine Oncology, Maria Sklodowska-Curie Memorial Cancer Centre and Institute of Oncology, Gliwice, Poland</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Tumor Biology and Clinical Oncology, Maria Sklodowska-Curie Memorial Cancer Centre and Institute of Oncology, Gliwice, Poland</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2164/10/261"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2009 Chechlinska et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chechlinska et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author> Chechlinska Magdalena chech@coi.waw.pl </dc:author><dc:title> Molecular signature of cell cycle exit induced in human T lymphoblasts by IL-2 withdrawal </dc:title><dc:date>2009</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Genomics 10(1): 261-. (2009)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2164(2009)10:1&#x0003c;261&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2164</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The molecular mechanisms of cell cycle exit are poorly understood. Studies on lymphocytes at cell cycle exit after growth factor deprivation have predominantly focused on the initiation of apoptosis. We aimed to study gene expression profile of primary and immortalised IL-2-dependent human T cells forced to exit the cell cycle by growth factor withdrawal, before apoptosis could be evidenced.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>By the Affymetrix microarrays HG-U133 2.0 Plus, 53 genes were distinguished as differentially expressed before and soon after IL-2 deprivation. Among those, <italic>PIM1, BCL2, IL-8, HBEGF, DUSP6, OSM, CISH, SOCS2, SOCS3, LIF </italic>and <italic>IL13 </italic>were down-regulated and <italic>RPS24, SQSTM1, TMEM1, LRRC8D, ECOP, YY1AP1, C1orf63, ASAH1, SLC25A46 </italic>and <italic>MIA3 </italic>were up-regulated. Genes linked to transcription, cell cycle, cell growth, proliferation and differentiation, cell adhesion, and immune functions were found to be overrepresented within the set of the differentially expressed genes.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Cell cycle exit of the growth factor-deprived T lymphocytes is characterised by a signature of differentially expressed genes. A coordinate repression of a set of genes known to be induced during T cell activation is observed. However, growth arrest following exit from the cell cycle is actively controlled by several up-regulated genes that enforce the non-dividing state. The identification of genes involved in cell cycle exit and quiescence provides new hints for further studies on the molecular mechanisms regulating the non-dividing state of a cell, the mechanisms closely related to cancer development and to many biological processes.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Cell growth, proliferation and arrest mechanisms are crucial for development and homeostasis. Extensive studies have examined the mechanisms of cell activation and cell cycle progression, which involve sequential effects of growth factors and their receptors and activation of intracellular signal transduction pathways, transcription factors, cyclins and cyclin-dependent kinases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Studies on lymphocytes withdrawn from the cell cycle have focused on the initiation of apoptosis following growth factor deprivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] or on the cell-to-cell contact mechanisms that prevent cells from apopotosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Still, the molecular mechanisms of cell cycle exit remain poorly understood. With the lack of mitogenic signals, and in response to antiproliferative signals such as mitogen withdrawal, growth factor starvation, contact inhibition or DNA damage, a proliferating cell arrests to become quiescent (a reversible, nondividing state) or senescent, or to undergo apoptotic death. Most somatic cells in an adult body remain in a postmitotic G<sub>0 </sub>phase. However, during tissue regeneration and repair, wound healing and immune response, cells re-enter the cell cycle and subsequently withdraw from proliferation.</p><p>Studies in lymphocytes and fibroblasts have shown that resting cells are not in a passive state resulting simply from the lack of stimulation. Pajalunga et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] summarized cell cycle exit as "a shift in the balance between positive and negative regulators of proliferation in favour of the latter". Indeed, resting cells were found to express sets of up-regulated and down-regulated genes that maintained an active state of non-division [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. A group of genes required for cell cycle exit and the maintenance of cell quiescence in human fibroblasts following serum deprivation has been recently identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Comparative studies of transcriptional profiles of resting and stimulated lymphocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] have shown that T lymphocyte quiescence is actively maintained by products of a set of genes, including <italic>TOB </italic>and <italic>KLF </italic>(<italic>LKLF, GKLF </italic>and <italic>BKLF) </italic>and <italic>FOXO </italic>families of transcription factors. Other candidate genes involved in lymphocyte quiescence, including <italic>TSC-22 </italic>and <italic>Dyrk1</italic>, have been identified in a mouse model among genes highly expressed in resting lymphocytes and down-regulated after T or B cell activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>The present study on a human T cell model may provide new insights into the molecular changes involved in cell proliferation control, cell cycle exit and cellular quiescence. Cellular quiescence represents an important safeguard against tumorigenesis; therefore the identification of quiescence-controlling genes and a better understanding of the relevant molecular pathways may open new possibilities in cancer diagnosis and treatment. Thus, in our study, proliferating interleukin (IL)-2-dependent human T cells were forced to exit cell cycle by growth factor withdrawal, and their gene expression profiles were examined.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>To gain new insights into cell cycle exit of T lymphocytes, we performed gene expression profiling in human IL-2-dependent T lymphoblasts deprived of the growth factor. Following IL-2 withdrawal, IL-2-dependent, proliferating T lymphoblasts cease to divide and undergo apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Therefore, transcription profiles of T cells were analysed soon after IL-2 withdrawal (8 hours), before apoptotic changes could be observed. In addition, to minimize effects associated with the heterogeneity of primary T cell populations, we also studied clonal populations of immortalised IL-2-dependent T lymphoblasts and looked for the common changes in the two cellular models. We believe that this approach also limited the "non-specific" gene expression changes in the primary IL-2-deprived T lymphoblasts, i.e. not related to IL-2 withdrawal, but rather to the possible paracrine signalling in polyclonal populations by other cytokines characterised by a redundant activity.</p><p>Five cell lines were subjected to IL-2 deprivation and microarray analysis, three primary, IL-2-dependent T lymphoblast lines derived from three different donors (denoted "6", "43" and "j") and two immortalised T cell lines (denoted line 5 and S9), examined in three biological replicates each. Altogether, 18 microarray hybridisations were performed.</p><p>In the first step, unsupervised Principal Component Analysis was performed to assess the reliability of the experiments. Biological replicates were shown to cluster together. The gene expression profile of all the analysed cell lines was shown to be affected by IL-2 withdrawal, but the major variability of the gene expression profile in the analysed dataset was found between primary and immortalised cell lines (unpublished data). Differences between primary and immortalised cells were much greater than those resulting from IL-2 withdrawal. Therefore, our analysis was carried out in a block design, and changes in gene expression following IL-2 withdrawal were assessed separately in primary and immortalised cell lines. By means of the parametric non-corrected t-test we selected 158 differentially expressed genes at p &#x0003c; 0.001 (see Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table A1 for genes differentiating between samples before and after IL-2 withdrawal, selected by a non-paired analysis). The probability of a random selection of such a number of genes was low (0.03 in a global test) which confirmed the reliability of the observed differences. A false discovery rate for the selected genes ranged from 0.003 to 0.12. The hierarchical clustering of the 158 differentially expressed probe-sets obtained in this analysis resulted in an ideal discrimination between the samples before and after IL-2 withdrawal, with a rather uniform pattern of expression (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Hierarchical clustering analysis based on the expression values of 158 probesets differentiating samples before and after IL-2 withdrawal in the non-paired analysis</bold>. Samples before IL-2 withdrawal are in the light-blue columns, samples after IL-2 withdrawal in the navy-blue columns. Primary samples are in the yellow column, immortalised samples are in the green one. The names of the genes of the "T lymphocyte cell cycle exit signature" (Table 2) are marked.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-10-261-1"/></fig><p>Having confirmed the statistical significance of differences related to IL-2 withdrawal, we have selected the most consistently changed genes in all five different cell lines analysed, by employing a paired analysis (of the corresponding cells before and after IL-2 withdrawal). The univariate non-corrected permutation test revealed 166 probe-sets changed significantly at P &#x0003c; 0.001 (while in a global test, a borderline significance of P = 0.0625 was obtained). A hundred and eight of these genes were repressed after growth factor withdrawal, and the remaining 58 were up-regulated (see Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Table A2 for genes differentiating between samples before and after IL-2 withdrawal, selected by a paired sample analysis). Out of those, <italic>DUSP6, OSM, CISH, SOCS2, LIF </italic>and <italic>IL13 </italic>were found to be the most prominently down-regulated (more than 20-fold), and the expression of <italic>EMB, SOX4, RPS24, WNT5B, SLC1A4, SQSTM1, SUMF1, TMEM1, STK38, LAMP2 </italic>and <italic>C17orf42 </italic>was found to be the most increased (2-fold to 3.5-fold change).</p><p>We carried out an external validation of the results obtained in the microarray analysis by a qRT-PCR. For validation we used the same cell lines and we chose 8 genes from the list of 158 most significantly changed transcripts, and a further 4 genes, known for their interesting function, with lower significance of differences. Most of the qRT-PCR results confirmed the microarray findings (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>): 7 of 8 top genes and 3 of 4 less significant transcripts were confirmed in a qRT-PCR experiment, usually with a similar fold-change.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Validation of the selected microarray data by the qRT-PCR.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Rank</td><td align="left">Gene symbol</td><td align="left">Description</td><td align="right">Probe set</td><td align="center" colspan="10">Signal Log Ratio (microarray analysis)</td><td align="center">Micorarray<break/>Fold-change<break/>(after/before<break/>IL2 withdrawal)</td><td align="center">Parametric<break/>p-value<break/>(non-paired<break/>comparison)</td><td align="center">qRT-PCR Fold change</td><td align="center">qRT-PCR p-value (non-paired)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td colspan="10"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left" colspan="2">j</td><td align="left" colspan="2">43</td><td align="left" colspan="2">6</td><td align="left" colspan="2">line 5</td><td align="left" colspan="2">S9</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="18"><bold>genes with P &#x0003c; 0.0001 in the microarray gene expression analysis</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="18"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center">2</td><td align="left">CISH</td><td align="left">cytokine inducible SH2-containing protein</td><td align="left">223377_x_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-5.01</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.936</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-5.435</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.649</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.519</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.08</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="center">7</td><td align="left">DUSP6</td><td align="left">dual specificity phosphatase 6</td><td align="left">208893_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-6.236</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-5.771</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-5.75</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.873</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-5.028</td><td align="center">0.02</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.04</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="center">11</td><td align="left">C3orf59</td><td align="left">chromosome 3 open reading frame 59</td><td align="left">227599_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-3.035</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-2.559</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-2.647</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-2.401</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-2.29</td><td align="center">0.17</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.32</td><td align="center">0.0082</td></tr><tr><td align="center">18</td><td align="left">ASAH1</td><td align="left">N-acylsphingosine amidohydrolase (acid ceramidase) 1</td><td align="left">213702_x_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.726</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.671</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.612</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.569</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.787</td><td align="center">1.59</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">2.08</td><td align="center">0.0069</td></tr><tr><td colspan="18"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="18"><bold>genes with P &#x0003c; 0.001 in the microarray gene expression analysis</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="18"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center">33</td><td align="left">SOCS2</td><td align="left">suppressor of cytokine signaling 2</td><td align="left">203373_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.178</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.954</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-5.332</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-3.528</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.438</td><td align="center">0.04</td><td align="center">0.0001</td><td align="center">0.12</td><td align="center">0.0058</td></tr><tr><td align="center">45</td><td align="left">OSM</td><td align="left">oncostatin M</td><td align="left">214637_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.201</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.671</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-3.352</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.564</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-5.351</td><td align="center">0.04</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.04</td><td align="center">0.0011</td></tr><tr><td align="center">66</td><td align="left">IL8</td><td align="left">interleukin 8</td><td align="left">211506_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-3.537</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-2.395</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-3.14</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.011</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-3.575</td><td align="center">0.10</td><td align="center">0.0003</td><td align="center">0.19</td><td align="center">0.2333</td></tr><tr><td align="center">92</td><td align="left">HBEGF</td><td align="left">heparin-binding EGF-like growth factor</td><td align="left">203821_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-5.121</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-3.605</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-4.72</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-3.679</td><td align="left" colspan="2">-3.178</td><td align="center">0.06</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.08</td><td align="center">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="18"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="18"><bold>genes with P &#x0003c; 0.01 in the microarray gene expression analysis</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="18"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center">221</td><td align="left">MT1F</td><td align="left">metallothionein 1F</td><td align="left">217165_x_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">2.408</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.794</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.091</td><td align="left" colspan="2">2.344</td><td align="left" colspan="2">2.002</td><td align="center">3.80</td><td align="center">0.0013</td><td align="center">7.05</td><td align="center">0.0004</td></tr><tr><td align="center">348</td><td align="left">MT1X</td><td align="left">metallothionein X</td><td align="left">208581_x_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">2.066</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.764</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.997</td><td align="left" colspan="2">2.656</td><td align="left" colspan="2">2.005</td><td align="center">3.73</td><td align="center">0.0021</td><td align="center">4.76</td><td align="center">0.0004</td></tr><tr><td align="center">514</td><td align="left">CLK4</td><td align="left">CDC-like kinase 4</td><td align="left">210346_s_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.399</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.014</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.729</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.188</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.576</td><td align="center">2.27</td><td align="center">0.0036</td><td align="center">2.41</td><td align="center">0.0046</td></tr><tr><td align="center">600</td><td align="left">IL7R</td><td align="left">interleukin 7 receptor</td><td align="left">205798_at</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.923</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.919</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.965</td><td align="left" colspan="2">2.962</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.721</td><td align="center">3.73</td><td align="center">0.0043</td><td align="center">3.19</td><td align="center">0.2734</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To select transcripts consistently changed upon IL-2 withdrawal, we combined the two lists of 166 and 158 significant genes, obtained in the paired and non-paired analyses, respectively. We identified a set of 53 genes comprised of 13 up-regulated and 40 down-regulated genes, which we designated a "T lymphocyte cell cycle exit signature" (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Gene expression signature of T lymphocyte cell cycle exit.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Probe set</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Gene symbol</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Description</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Fold-change (after IL-2 withdrawal vs. before)</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><bold>Paired design</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><bold>Non-paired design</bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td colspan="4"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Parametric p-value</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>FDR<sup>1</sup></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Parametric p-value</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>FDR</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="9"><bold>Up-regulated</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center">1</td><td align="left">1555878_at</td><td align="left">RPS24</td><td align="left">ribosomal protein S24</td><td align="center">3.21</td><td align="center">0.0003</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2</td><td align="left">201471_s_at</td><td align="left">SQSTM1</td><td align="left">sequestosome 1</td><td align="center">2.48</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3</td><td align="left">226831_at</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="left">NA</td><td align="center">2.04</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4</td><td align="left">1555446_s_at</td><td align="left">TMEM1</td><td align="left">transmembrane protein 1</td><td align="center">2.04</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">5</td><td align="left">218684_at</td><td align="left">LRRC8D</td><td align="left">leucine rich repeat containing 8 family, member D</td><td align="center">1.72</td><td align="center">0.0007</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">0.0003</td><td align="center">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="center">6</td><td align="left">208091_s_at</td><td align="left">ECOP</td><td align="left">EGFR-coamplified and overexpressed protein</td><td align="center">1.69</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="center">7</td><td align="left">244803_at</td><td align="left">YY1AP1</td><td align="left">YY1 associated protein 1</td><td align="center">1.66</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="center">8</td><td align="left">209006_s_at</td><td align="left">C1orf63</td><td align="left">chromosome 1 open reading frame 63</td><td align="center">1.65</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">0.0007</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">9</td><td align="left">213702_x_at</td><td align="left">ASAH1</td><td align="left">N-acylsphingosine amidohydrolase (acid ceramidase) 1</td><td align="center">1.59</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="center">10</td><td align="left">212833_at</td><td align="left">SLC25A46</td><td align="left">solute carrier family 25, member 46</td><td align="center">1.58</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">11</td><td align="left">212310_at</td><td align="left">MIA3</td><td align="left">melanoma inhibitory activity family, member 3</td><td align="center">1.50</td><td align="center">0.0007</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="center">12</td><td align="left">1562612_at</td><td align="left">ME2</td><td align="left">malic enzyme 2, NAD(+)-dependent, mitochondrial</td><td align="center">1.47</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.309</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">13</td><td align="left">230161_at</td><td align="left">CD99</td><td align="left">CD99 molecule</td><td align="center">1.45</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="9"><bold>Down-regulated</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center">1</td><td align="left">1553101_a_at</td><td align="left">ALKBH5</td><td align="left">alkB, alkylation repair homolog 5 (E. coli)</td><td align="center">0.72</td><td align="center">0.0003</td><td align="center">0.23</td><td align="center">0.0009</td><td align="center">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2</td><td align="left">201968_s_at</td><td align="left">PGM1</td><td align="left">phosphoglucomutase 1</td><td align="center">0.64</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.22</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">3</td><td align="left">206055_s_at</td><td align="left">SNRPA1</td><td align="left">small nuclear ribonucleoprotein polypeptide</td><td align="center">0.62</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.22</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4</td><td align="left">228146_at</td><td align="left">C17orf51</td><td align="left">chromosome 17 open reading frame 51</td><td align="center">0.55</td><td align="center">0.0007</td><td align="center">0.22</td><td align="center">0.0007</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">5</td><td align="left">207339_s_at</td><td align="left">LTB</td><td align="left">lymphotoxin beta (TNF superfamily, member 3)</td><td align="center">0.54</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.22</td><td align="center">0.0008</td><td align="center">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="center">6</td><td align="left">201170_s_at</td><td align="left">BHLHB2</td><td align="left">basic helix-loop-helix domain containing, class B, 2</td><td align="center">0.53</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.22</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="center">7</td><td align="left">202932_at</td><td align="left">YES1</td><td align="left">v-yes-1 Yamaguchi sarcoma viral oncogene homolog 1</td><td align="center">0.50</td><td align="center">0.0008</td><td align="center">0.224</td><td align="center">0.0009</td><td align="center">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="center">8</td><td align="left">206999_at</td><td align="left">IL12RB2</td><td align="left">interleukin 12 receptor, beta 2</td><td align="center">0.49</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.22</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">9</td><td align="left">201041_s_at</td><td align="left">DUSP1</td><td align="left">dual specificity phosphatase 1</td><td align="center">0.44</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.21</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="center">10</td><td align="left">202081_at</td><td align="left">IER2</td><td align="left">immediate early response 2</td><td align="center">0.43</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.21</td><td align="center">0.0009</td><td align="center">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="center">11</td><td align="left">227262_at</td><td align="left">HAPLN3</td><td align="left">hyaluronan and proteoglycan link protein 3</td><td align="center">0.41</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">12</td><td align="left">218551_at</td><td align="left">RP5-1077B9.4</td><td align="left">invasion inhibitory protein 45</td><td align="center">0.41</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">13</td><td align="left">212590_at</td><td align="left">RRAS2</td><td align="left">related RAS viral (r-ras) oncogene homolog 2</td><td align="center">0.40</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="center">14</td><td align="left">226283_at</td><td align="left">WDR51B</td><td align="left">WD repeat domain 51B</td><td align="center">0.39</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">15</td><td align="left">219681_s_at</td><td align="left">RAB11FIP1</td><td align="left">RAB11 family interacting protein 1 (class I)</td><td align="center">0.38</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="center">16</td><td align="left">219255_x_at</td><td align="left">IL17RB</td><td align="left">interleukin 17 receptor B</td><td align="center">0.38</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">17</td><td align="left">224156_x_at</td><td align="left">IL17RB</td><td align="left">interleukin 17 receptor B</td><td align="center">0.37</td><td align="center">0.0007</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">18</td><td align="left">210845_s_at</td><td align="left">PLAUR</td><td align="left">plasminogen activator, urokinase receptor</td><td align="center">0.36</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">0.0003</td><td align="center">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="center">19</td><td align="left">214508_x_at</td><td align="left">CREM</td><td align="left">cAMP responsive element modulator</td><td align="center">0.30</td><td align="center">0.0007</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="center">20</td><td align="left">209488_s_at</td><td align="left">RBPMS</td><td align="left">RNA binding protein with multiple splicing</td><td align="center">0.28</td><td align="center">0.0007</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="center">21</td><td align="left">223217_s_at</td><td align="left">NFKBIZ</td><td align="left">nuclear factor of kappa light polypeptide gene enhancer in B-cells inhibitor, zeta</td><td align="center">0.25</td><td align="center">0.0008</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">22</td><td align="left">209193_at</td><td align="left">PIM1</td><td align="left">pim-1 oncogene</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">23</td><td align="left">225262_at</td><td align="left">FOSL2</td><td align="left">FOS-like antigen 2</td><td align="center">0.17</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.20</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">24</td><td align="left">227599_at</td><td align="left">C3orf59</td><td align="left">chromosome 3 open reading frame 59</td><td align="center">0.17</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.19</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">25</td><td align="left">244035_at</td><td align="left">BCL2</td><td align="left">B-cell CLL/lymphoma 2</td><td align="center">0.16</td><td align="center">0.0008</td><td align="center">0.19</td><td align="center">0.0009</td><td align="center">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="center">26</td><td align="left">202859_x_at</td><td align="left">IL8</td><td align="left">interleukin 8</td><td align="center">0.15</td><td align="center">0.0009</td><td align="center">0.19</td><td align="center">0.0006</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">27</td><td align="left">211506_s_at</td><td align="left">IL8</td><td align="left">interleukin 8</td><td align="center">0.10</td><td align="center">0.0003</td><td align="center">0.19</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="center">28</td><td align="left">203821_at</td><td align="left">HBEGF</td><td align="left">heparin-binding EGF-like growth factor</td><td align="center">0.06</td><td align="center">0.0004</td><td align="center">0.19</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="center">29</td><td align="left">207844_at</td><td align="left">IL13</td><td align="left">interleukin 13</td><td align="center">0.05</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.19</td><td align="center">0.0007</td><td align="center">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="center">30</td><td align="left">214637_at</td><td align="left">OSM</td><td align="left">oncostatin M</td><td align="center">0.05</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.18</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">31</td><td align="left">203373_at</td><td align="left">SOCS2</td><td align="left">suppressor of cytokine signaling 2</td><td align="center">0.04</td><td align="center">0.0001</td><td align="center">0.17</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="center">32</td><td align="left">205266_at</td><td align="left">LIF</td><td align="left">leukemia inhibitory factor (cholinergic differentiation factor)</td><td align="center">0.04</td><td align="center">0.0003</td><td align="center">0.17</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="center">33</td><td align="left">203372_s_at</td><td align="left">SOCS2</td><td align="left">suppressor of cytokine signaling 2</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.17</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="center">34</td><td align="left">208891_at</td><td align="left">DUSP6</td><td align="left">dual specificity phosphatase 6</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.17</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">35</td><td align="left">223377_x_at</td><td align="left">CISH</td><td align="left">cytokine inducible SH2-containing protein</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.16</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">36</td><td align="left">223961_s_at</td><td align="left">CISH</td><td align="left">cytokine inducible SH2-containing protein</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.14</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">37</td><td align="left">221223_x_at</td><td align="left">CISH</td><td align="left">cytokine inducible SH2-containing protein</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.13</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">38</td><td align="left">208893_s_at</td><td align="left">DUSP6</td><td align="left">dual specificity phosphatase 6</td><td align="center">0.02</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.13</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">39</td><td align="left">230170_at</td><td align="left">OSM</td><td align="left">oncostatin M</td><td align="center">0.02</td><td align="center">0.0002</td><td align="center">0.13</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">40</td><td align="left">208892_s_at</td><td align="left">DUSP6</td><td align="left">dual specificity phosphatase 6</td><td align="center">0.02</td><td align="center">0.0010</td><td align="center">0.05</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.0001</td><td align="center">0.03</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Common genes identified as significantly changed (p &#x0003c; 0.001) in a paired analysis and in a non-paired block analysis.</p><p><sup>1</sup>FDR &#x02013; False Discovery Rate</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The up-regulated genes identified after IL-2 deprivation in both primary and immortalised cells included <italic>SQSTM1, ECOP, YY1AP1, RPS24, TMEM1, LRRC8D, C1orf63, ASAH1, SLC25A46 </italic>and <italic>MIA3</italic>, some of which have been associated with cellular growth control.</p><p>The SQSTM1 protein, previously known as p62 protein, interacts with the ubiquitinated proteins to mediate their clearance and is an important scaffold molecule in the RANK-NF-kappaB signalling pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. In addition, while the p62 protein is also a ligand for Lck kinase of the Src protein-tyrosine kinase family that is involved in T-cell receptor-dependent activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], K&#x000f6;ller et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] stress the role of Lck in transient T cell unresponsiveness, mediated by a selective IL-2 deficiency. Thus, SQSTM1 may play an important role in cell growth, especially because it may facilitate cell survival through signalling cascades for example those that result in Akt activation, by interaction with protein kinase C, as shown in human neuronal cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>].</p><p>Interestingly, the product of the <italic>ECOP </italic>gene, which was found here to be up-regulated, has also been previously shown to be involved in NF-kappa B-related regulation of cellular growth. ECOP (EGFR-Co-amplified and over-expressed protein) has been implicated as a key regulator in the NF-kappaB signalling, and it has been postulated that high-level, amplification-mediated <italic>ECOP </italic>expression, such as that occurring in tumours with amplified EGFR, could contribute to resistance to apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p><p>The identified genes may as well be associated with other cell proliferation pathways. For example, a product of the <italic>YYAP1 </italic>gene, called YY1-associated protein, a co-activator of the YY1 (Yin Yang 1) transcription factor (YYAP1), had been initially identified as a long splice variant of HCC (hepatocellular carcinoma)-specific protein encoded by the <italic>HCCA2 </italic>gene (HCC-associated gene 2). An over-expression of <italic>HCCA2 </italic>has been found to lead to a cell cycle arrest at G0/G1 phase and to an inhibition of cell proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>].</p><p>For the other up-regulated genes distinguished in this study, we could not identify links to the known mechanisms of cell cycle arrest, but some of the genes have been previously associated with different cancers. An over-expression of <italic>ASAH1 </italic>has been found in different malignant tumours, including prostate cancer, head and neck squamous cell cancers and T-cell large granular lymphocyte (LGL) leukaemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. An inhibition of acid ceramidase, the product of <italic>ASAH1</italic>, the over-expression of which in cancer cells has been implicated in drug resistance, is suggested as an efficient and promising novel treatment strategy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. The ribosomal protein gene <italic>RPS24 </italic>has been associated with hepatocellular carcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The MIA3 (TANGO) protein has been identified as a tumour suppressor in malignant melanoma and in colon and hepatocellular carcinomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>].</p><p>Out of genes encoding for the suggested crucial regulators of T lymphocyte quiescence, such as TOB and members of the KLF and FOXO transcription factors' families, as well as TSC-22 and Dyrk1, which had previously been found to be overexpressed in resting T cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], we only found the <italic>FOXO3 </italic>gene to be slightly, but significantly up-regulated after IL-2 withdrawal. This discrepancy might be explained by differences between the different cell models employed (mouse vs. human) and by different experimental settings. On the other hand, the activity of these transcription factors may be regulated posttranscriptionally, so that their mRNA levels may not necessarily reflect their activity. Thus, the expression of some of the known FOXO target genes was examined and found to be affected following IL-2 withdrawal. <italic>IL7R</italic>, the FOXO1 target gene was up to 4-fold overexpressed in the primary T lymphocytes, but not in immortalised T cells. <italic>CDKN1B </italic>(<italic>p27)</italic>, another FOXO target in human, mouse and C. elegans models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>], encoding a cell-cycle regulatory protein, presented slightly, but significantly increased expression. Similarly, <italic>Pink1</italic>, a recently identified FOXO target, the product of which helps to protect lymphocytes from apoptosis after growth factor deprivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>], was among genes of significantly elevated expression in our model of cell-cycle exit. Studies of Murphy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] on C. elegans model pointed at metallothionein genes as possible FOXO targets. In the present study, several metallothionein genes (<italic>MT1H</italic>, <italic>MT1X</italic>, <italic>MT1G</italic>, <italic>MT2A</italic>, <italic>MT1M</italic>, <italic>MT1E</italic>, <italic>MT1F</italic>) were overexpressed (2.6 to 3.8 times) following IL-2 withdrawal. In addition, we show here, that <italic>Cyclin D </italic>expression, reported to be downregulated by FOXO and KLF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], decreased after IL-2 withdrawal. However, some genes reported by other research groups as human FOXO targets, such as <italic>p130 </italic>gene, <italic>Cyclin G2 </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>], or <italic>IGF1R</italic>, <italic>BCL-2BP</italic>, or <italic>Sestrin 1 </italic>found to be FOXO3a-inducible genes in mouse T cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>], as well as most of the KLF targets summarised by Tsachanis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] and Yusuf [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], were unaffected by IL-2 deprivation in our experimental model.</p><p>A set of genes identified as significantly down-regulated 8 hours following IL-2 withdrawal included <italic>PIM1, BCL2, IL-8, HBEGF, DUSP6, OSM, CISH, SOCS2, LIF </italic>and <italic>IL13</italic>. It is notable that some of the identified genes, namely <italic>PIM1, BCL2, DUSP6, CISH and SOCS2 </italic>were previously demonstrated to be the IL-2 target genes or the regulators of IL-2 signalling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. In addition, it is clear that <italic>PIM1, CISH </italic>and suppressors of cytokine signalling (<italic>SOCS</italic>) are implicated in the biological actions of IL-2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>], and that IL-2 was found to regulate mRNA levels of <italic>SOCS2, CISH, DUSP5 </italic>and <italic>DUSP6 </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. It has also been demonstrated that OSM can quickly up-regulate <italic>CISH </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. The coordinated repression of <italic>OSM </italic>and <italic>CISH </italic>that we showed in T cells following IL-2 withdrawal is consistent with these observations.</p><p>To perform a functional analysis of the up- and down-regulated genes, the 158 genes selected in the non-paired comparison between IL-2-deprived and non-deprived lymphocytes were first analysed by Gene Ontology (GO) Categories (see Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>. Table A3 for gene ontology analysis of genes selected in a non-paired sample comparison between IL-2-deprived and non-deprived lymphocytes). The number of genes changed in each category was compared with the expected quantity of genes and the greatest enrichment was found in two molecular function (MF) classes, GO:0016868, intramolecular transferase activity, phosphotransferases; (observed/expected ratio = 43.9) and GO:0005126, hematopoietin/interferon-class (D200-domain) cytokine receptor binding, (observed/expected ratio = 26.3) and two biological process (BP) classes, GO:0007259, JAK-STAT cascade (observed/expected ratio = 16.7) and GO:0009968, negative regulation of signal transduction, (observed/expected ratio = 6.8). Secondly, a gene set analysis was performed by comparing the overall significance of gene groups defined by GO categories. Out of the 2348 GO classes 317 were found to be significantly affected by IL-2 withdrawal, as shown by at least one of the three tests used to assess the significance of the differences. The selected GO categories are shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>. The LS/KS permutation tests, which find gene sets that have more differentially expressed genes among the classes than expected by chance, identified 206 significant gene-sets. Efron-Tibshirani's test, which uses 'maxmean' statistics to identify differentially expressed gene-sets, found 231 significant gene-sets (under 200 permutations). Eleven out of the 215 cellular component categories, 69 of 545 molecular function (MF) categories and 237 of 1588 biological process (BP) categories were significant. Thirty-nine GO categories with p &#x0003c; 0.005 in all of the three applied gene group significance tests were identified (see Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>: Table A4 for overall significance of expression changes following IL-2 deprivation in gene groups defined by GO categories).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Selected Gene Ontology GO categories significantly affected by genes deregulated following IL-2 deprivation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><bold>GO category</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>GO categories</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>GO term</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>LS permutation p-value</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>KS permutation p-value</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Efron-Tibshirani's GSA test</bold><break/><bold>p-value</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Up-regulated genes</bold><break/><bold>(p &#x0003c; 0.01)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Down-regulated genes</bold><break/><bold>(p &#x0003c; 0.01)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">GO:0004907</td><td align="center">MF</td><td align="left">interleukin receptor activity</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>IL12RB1, IL7R</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>IL2RA, IL12RB2, IL17RB IL1RAP</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0019955</td><td align="center">MF</td><td align="left">cytokine binding</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>IL12RB1, IL7R</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>IL2RA, IL12RB2, IL17RB IL1RAP</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0004896</td><td align="center">MF</td><td align="left">hematopoietin/interferon-class (D200-domain) cytokine receptor activity</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0000988</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>IL12RB1, IL7R</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>IL2RA, IL12RB2, IL17RB IL1RAP</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0007259</td><td align="center">BP</td><td align="left">JAK-STAT cascade</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0001056</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>SOCS1, SOCS2, SOCS3, OSM, STAT4</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0006959</td><td align="center">BP</td><td align="left">humoral immune response</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0006364</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>BCL2, CD55, CFHR1, TNF, LTA, CFH, BCL3, GPI</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0050900</td><td align="center">BP</td><td align="left">leukocyte migration</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0047229</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>MYH9</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>IL8, TNF, CKLF, ITGB2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0017040</td><td align="center">MF</td><td align="left">ceramidase activity</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0049829</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>ASAH1</italic></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0018108</td><td align="center">BP</td><td align="left">peptidyl-tyrosine phosphorylation</td><td align="center">0.0001871</td><td align="center">0.0032075</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>CLK4</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>OSM, SOCS1, IL5, ITGB2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0006672</td><td align="center">BP</td><td align="left">ceramide metabolic process</td><td align="center">0.0004208</td><td align="center">0.0030228</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>ASAH1</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>UGCG, CLN8</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0007260</td><td align="center">BP</td><td align="left">tyrosine phosphorylation of STAT protein</td><td align="center">0.0004601</td><td align="center">0.0046325</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>OSM, SOCS1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0030218</td><td align="center">BP</td><td align="left">erythrocyte differentiation</td><td align="center">0.0013289</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>FOXO3, BCL6</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>SFXN1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0042379</td><td align="center">MF</td><td align="left">chemokine receptor binding</td><td align="center">0.001562</td><td align="center">0.0008411</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>IL8, CCL3, CKLF</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="center">GO:0048660</td><td align="center">BP</td><td align="left">regulation of smooth muscle cell proliferation</td><td align="center">0.003213</td><td align="center">0.0021998</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>HBEGF</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Three independent tests: LS, KS and Efron-Tibshirani GSA were applied to select significantly affected gene classes.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The same analytical procedure applied to the database of biological pathways (Biocarta, human database) resulted in 54 significantly up-regulated gene sets. Selected pathways affected by IL-2 withdrawal are shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>. Both analyses, GO and Biocarta, confirmed the consistent up-regulation of the genes belonging to the JAK-STAT pathway.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>A selection of significantly impacted pathways (BioCarta) in T lymphocytes following IL-2 deprivation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Pathway description</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Biocarta Pathway</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>LS permutation</bold><break/><bold>p-value</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>KS permutation</bold><break/><bold>p-value</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Efron-Tibshirani's GSA test p-value</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Up-regulated genes </bold><break/><bold>(p &#x0003c; 0.01)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Down-regulated genes</bold><break/><bold>(p &#x0003c; 0.01)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Visceral Fat Deposits and the Metabolic Syndrome</td><td align="left">h_vobesityPathway</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0001273</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>NR3C1</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>TNF, HSD11B1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cells and Molecules involved in local acute inflammatory response</td><td align="left">h_LairPathway</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0007952</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>ITGB1, ITGAL</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>IL8, TNF, ICAM1, ITGA4</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Adhesion and Diapedesis of Lymphocytes</td><td align="left">h_lympathway</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0029985</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>ITGB1, ITGAL</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>IL8, ICAM1, ICAM2, ITGA4</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Adhesion and Diapedesis of Granulocytes</td><td align="left">h_granulocytesPathway</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0032844</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>IL-8, TNF, CD54, ICAM2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cytokine Network</td><td align="left">h_cytokinePathway</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.0297027</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>IL13, IL8, LTA, IL-5</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL-2 Receptor Beta Chain in T cell Activation</td><td align="left">h_il2rbPathway</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.030315</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>CISH, IL2RA, SOCS3, BCL2, AKT1, JAK3</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Induction of apoptosis through DR3 and DR4/5 Death Receptors</td><td align="left">h_deathPathway</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">0.06</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>BCL2, TRADD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL22 Soluble Receptor Signaling Pathway</td><td align="left">h_il22bppathway</td><td align="center">0.0000955</td><td align="center">0.00001</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>SOCS3, JAK3</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Selective expression of chemokine receptors during T-cell polarization</td><td align="left">h_nktPathway</td><td align="center">0.0000994</td><td align="center">0.0000936</td><td align="center">0.03</td><td align="center"><italic>IL12RB1, CCR4</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>ILRB2, CCL3, IL5</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cytokines and Inflammatory Response</td><td align="left">h_inflamPathway</td><td align="center">0.0001717</td><td align="center">0.078942</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>IL13, IL8, TNF, LTA, IL5</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">NO2-dependent IL 12 Pathway in NK cells</td><td align="left">h_no2il12Pathway</td><td align="center">0.0006013</td><td align="center">0.0135205</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>IL12RB1, CD2</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>IL12RB2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Regulation of MAP Kinase Pathways Through Dual Specificity Phosphatases</td><td align="left">h_dspPathway</td><td align="center">0.0007988</td><td align="center">0.1717258</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>DUSP6, DUSP1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">PTEN dependent cell cycle arrest and apoptosis</td><td align="left">h_ptenPathway</td><td align="center">0.0015749</td><td align="center">0.0100088</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>FOXO3, ITGB1, MAPK1</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>AKT1, PDK1, SOS1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ceramide Signaling Pathway</td><td align="left">h_ceramidePathway</td><td align="center">0.0016286</td><td align="center">0.005673</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>MAPK1</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>BCL2, TRADD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Th1/Th2 Differentiation</td><td align="left">h_th1th2Pathway</td><td align="center">0.001734</td><td align="center">0.0676275</td><td align="center">0.07</td><td align="center"><italic>IL12RB1</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>IL2RA, IL12RB2</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Dendritic cells in regulating TH1 and TH2 Development</td><td align="left">h_dcPathway</td><td align="center">0.0023595</td><td align="center">0.0493208</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">p53 Signaling Pathway</td><td align="left">h_p53Pathway</td><td align="center">0.0026524</td><td align="center">0.1802796</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>BCL2, CDK2, CDKN1A</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Telomeres, Telomerase, Cellular Aging, and Immortality</td><td align="left">h_telPathway</td><td align="center">0.0367325</td><td align="center">0.3499152</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td></td><td align="center"><italic>BCL2, AKT1</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phospholipids as signalling intermediaries</td><td align="left">h_edg1Pathway</td><td align="center">0.0404929</td><td align="center">0.1894782</td><td align="center">&#x0003c; 0.005</td><td align="center"><italic>ASAH1</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>AKT1</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Testing of 288 Biocarta human pathways identified 54 out of 288 investigated gene-sets that passed the 0.005 significance threshold in at least one test (38 gene-sets in LS/KS test and 36 in Efron-Tibshirani's test).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Our data demonstrate for the first time that IL-2 withdrawal induces a coordinate repression of the same set of genes that have been found to be induced during T cell activation as IL-2 targets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. A similar "symmetry" has been previously shown in human fibroblasts, where approximately half of the genes of the early response to serum stimulation were correspondingly repressed at the cell cycle exit after mitogen deprivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>A few previous studies have shown that some mRNAs that are expressed in resting T and B lymphocytes become repressed following cell activation, and it was suggested that cell quiescence is under an active transcriptional control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Similarly, as shown recently, exit from the cell cycle of human fibroblasts is under control of a "quiescence program" dependent upon a set of genes that enforce the non-dividing state, and ensure the reversibility of the cell cycle arrest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Our data support the idea of cell cycle arrest as an active state, controlled by some up-regulated genes.</p><p>While in vitro T lymphocytes deprived of a growth factor would eventually undergo apoptosis, in vivo a small proportion of antigen-activated cells would exit to G<sub>0 </sub>and become quiescent. Cellular quiescence is thought to be an indispensable state for the maintenance of lymphocyte homeostasis following immune response, and therefore it is an important barrier against tumorigenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. Some autoimmune and chronic inflammatory disorders involving an excessive lymphocyte proliferation, were found to be associated with increased risks of lymphoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. Thus, it is very likely that a deregulated expression of genes responsible for cellular quiescence may contribute to the development of some lymphoid malignancies.</p><p>To assess whether T cells adopt quiescent, memory cell phenotype upon IL-2 withdrawal in our model, we compared the gene expression patterns obtained with those described by other researchers as characterising memory vs. na&#x000ef;ve vs. effector T cells. Two molecules known to facilitate T cell homing to lymphoid tissues, SELL (CD62L) and CCR7 are expressed predominantly by na&#x000ef;ve and memory T cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>], but <italic>CCR7 </italic>expression seems not to be affected by growth factor withdrawal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. In our model of cell cycle exit the <italic>SELL </italic>gene was up-regulated in primary T cell lines, while <italic>CCR7</italic>, was unchanged in primary T cells and slightly down-regulated in immortalised T cells after IL-2 deprivation. Out of other genes identified by Holmes et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] as up-regulated in memory T cells, T cells deprived of IL-2 overexpressed <italic>SMAD3</italic>, <italic>TRIM66 </italic>and <italic>NAP1L3</italic>. There was also an increased expression of <italic>IL7R</italic>, thought to be expressed in memory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>] and na&#x000ef;ve [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] T cells, but this was found not significant by the qRT-PCR (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) when analysed for all T cells, possibly because this was truth only in primary T cells. The <italic>CD58 </italic>(<italic>LFA3</italic>) gene, encoding an adhesion molecule known to be expressed on activated and memory T cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>], was indeed highly expressed in actively growing cells and consistently up-regulated after IL-2 withdrawal in our experimental system.</p><p>Holmes et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] reported <italic>Granzyme B </italic>and <italic>KLRD1 </italic>expression to be induced in activated T cells. Our experiments showed that growth factor-deprived T cells presented decreased <italic>Granzyme B </italic>expression, while <italic>KLRD1 </italic>expression was slightly upregulated, but only in primary T cells. A hierarchical clustering of some genes outlined by Holmes et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] is shown in an Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>: Figure A1.</p><p>Haining et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>] demonstrated a gene expression profile common for CD8 and CD4 memory T cells. We showed that some of the genes of this profile were significantly changed at cell cycle exit; there was an increased expression of <italic>S100A4</italic>, <italic>S100A11</italic>, <italic>ANXA1</italic>, <italic>ANXA2</italic>, <italic>CRIP1 </italic>and <italic>CASP1</italic>, which, according to Haining et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>], are up-regulated in memory T cells, and a reduced expression of <italic>Granzyme A</italic>, downregulated in memory cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>].</p><p>In summary, T cells withdrawn from cell cycle gained some crucial characteristics of memory T cells. Nevertheless, the cell cycle exit signature that we describe here is different from memory T cell gene expression signatures published so far.</p><p>Further studies will reveal whether there is a common mechanism of quiescence for different cell types, such as the "common quiescence program" in fibroblasts stimulated to exit to G<sub>0 </sub>by different stimuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Interestingly, it has been found recently that a group of genes required for cell cycle exit in human fibroblasts following serum deprivation, were coordinately repressed in many types of human cancers, and repression of these genes predicted an increased risk of cancer progression and death in breast cancer patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Our studies on a model of human primary and immortalised IL-2-dependent T lymphoblasts extended these observations and brought new insights into the understanding of molecular events important in cell cycle exit, deregulation of which may relate to cancer development.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Cell cycle exit of growth factor-deprived primary and immortalised T lymphocytes is characterised by a gene expression signature, comprising 13 up-regulated and 40 down-regulated genes. Some of these genes are implicated in the mechanisms of cell growth control and show deregulated expression in different tumours. The gene set identified in the non-paired analysis was enriched in transcription, cell cycle, cell growth, proliferation and differentiation, cell adhesion, and immune function genes. Cells at cell cycle exit seem to be under an active transcriptional control. Upon IL-2 withdrawal, some genes become repressed, including those known to be induced during T-cell activation, while others become up-regulated. The identification of genes involved in cell cycle exit and quiescence provides new hints for further studies on the molecular mechanisms regulating the non-dividing state of a cell, the mechanisms closely related to cancer development and to many biological processes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Cell sources and cell sample preparation</title><p>Primary, IL-2-dependent T lymphoblast cell lines ("6", "43" and "j") were generated and propagated as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. Briefly, peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) derived from three healthy donors ("6", "43" and "j") were suspended in a standard medium (RPMI 1640, 10&#x02013;12% FCS, 50 &#x003bc;g/ml gentamycin [Sigma]), activated for 24 h with 20 &#x003bc;g/ml of wheat germ agglutinin (Pharmacia) and subsequently cultured in the standard medium supplemented with 20 U/ml of recombinant (r) IL-2 (R&#x00026;D). Flow cytometry cell surface analysis showed that the three primary T lymphoblast cell populations were composed of T cells exclusively, as they expressed all the pan-T markers, and a subset of the cells also expressed CD4 or CD8 surface molecules (unpublished data).</p><p>Viable cells were assessed every 3&#x02013;7 days by the trypan blue exclusion test and resuspended to the concentration of 0.5&#x02013;2.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>cells/ml in a fresh standard medium supplemented with rIL-2. The number of population doublings (PD) was calculated according to the formula:</p><p><disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="1471-2164-10-261-i1.gif"/></disp-formula></p><p>The cells "6", "43" and "j" were collected after 4&#x02013;5, 7&#x02013;8 and 6&#x02013;7 PD, respectively. The samples of the three primary cell lines were analysed as biological replicates.</p><p>Spontaneously immortalised IL-2-dependent T cell lines were derived from normal spleen (line 5) and from PBMC derived from a Nijmegen Breakage Syndrome patient (line S9), as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. Samples of the immortalised cell lines were collected in three biological replicates each.</p><p>The differential gene expression analysis was performed in cell samples collected directly from the IL-2-containing cultures (samples: 6/0, 43/0, j/0, line 5/0 and S9/0) and after 8-hrs incubation of the lymphoblasts in a standard medium without IL-2, following triple thorough washing of the cells in a standard medium (samples: 6/8, 43/8, j/8, line 5/8 and S9/8). In the cultures deprived of IL-2 for 8 hours, no apoptosis was observed in the primary T lymphoblast lines, and in the immortalised cell lines a negligible proportion of cells had the characteristics of early apoptotic cells, as detected by flow cytometry following Annexin-V staining with the use of the Annexin-V-FLUOS Staining Kit of ROCHE (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). But S-phase depletion and G1/S block were observed, as evaluated by flow cytometry with the use of the BD Cycletest Plus (Becton Dickinson) (unpublished data).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Percentages of apoptotic and necrotic cells in cultures of IL-2-dependent primary (j, 43) and immortalised (line 5, S9) T lymphoblasts (0 h) and at different time points after IL-2 withdrawal (2 h, 8 h, 24 h), analysed by flow cytometry following Annexin-V staining.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Cell lines</td><td align="center" colspan="2">0 h<sup>1</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="2">2 h</td><td align="center" colspan="2">8 h</td><td align="center" colspan="2">24 h</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="8"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">A<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center">N<sup>3</sup></td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">N</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">N</td><td align="center">A</td><td align="center">N</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">j</td><td align="center">0.2<sup>4</sup></td><td align="center">2.1</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">1.1</td><td align="center">0.4</td><td align="center">2.2</td><td align="center">0.5</td><td align="center">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="center">43</td><td align="center">0.5</td><td align="center">3.0</td><td align="center">0.7</td><td align="center">2.0</td><td align="center">0.4</td><td align="center">2.2</td><td align="center">0.7</td><td align="center">3.0</td></tr><tr><td align="center">line 5</td><td align="center">2.3</td><td align="center">4.0</td><td align="center">3.8</td><td align="center">2.3</td><td align="center">4.6</td><td align="center">2.0</td><td align="center">8.1</td><td align="center">3.8</td></tr><tr><td align="center">S9</td><td align="center">5.4</td><td align="center">1.3</td><td align="center">6.7</td><td align="center">1.3</td><td align="center">8.4</td><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">6.9</td><td align="center">1.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>hours after IL-2 withdrawal</p><p><sup>2</sup>A &#x02013; apoptosis</p><p><sup>3</sup>N &#x02013; necrosis</p><p><sup>4</sup>percentage; mean of two replicates</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Microarray procedures</title><p>Total RNA was isolated using Nucleospin RNA II kit (Macherey-Nagel, Germany). RNA quality was assessed using the Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer and RNA 6000 Nano Chip Kit (Agilent Technologies).</p><p>The Affymetrix GeneChip Human Genome U133 Plus 2.0 arrays, which measure the expression level of over 47,000 transcripts and variants, including 38,500 well-characterised human genes, were used. cDNA synthesis was carried out from 5 &#x003bc;g of RNA (One-Cycle cDNA Synthesis Kit, Affymetrix). After purification (GeneChip Sample Cleanup Module), 7 &#x003bc;l of double-stranded cDNA were used for biotinylated cRNA synthesis (IVT Labeling Kit, Affymetrix). Labeled cRNA was purified using a GeneChip Sample Cleanup Module, fragmented and hybridised with genome array. Washing, staining with streptavidin-phycoerythrin conjugate and scanning of the arrays in Affymetrx GeneChip 3000 scanner were performed as recommended by the Affymetrix Gene Expression Analysis Technical Manual.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>All 18 arrays were normalised by the GC-RMA algorithm using a Bioconductor gcrma package. We filtered out all genes with small amplitude of differences (less than 10% of samples with at least 1.5-fold difference in either direction from the median gene expression among all samples). The filtered dataset comprised of 18770 probe-sets. The full dataset has been deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus repository (accession no GSE13909).</p><p>Differentially expressed genes were identified by a random-variance t-test, with the statistical significance threshold set at p &#x0003c; 0.001. A stringent significance cut-off was used to limit the number of false positive genes obtained (at this threshold no more than 19 false positives are expected in each analysis). A global test of the differences in expression profiles between the classes was also performed by sample permutation. Simultaneously, we assessed a False Discovery Rate for each probeset using the Benjamini-Hochberg method.</p><p>To examine the effects of IL-2 withdrawal, samples were compared either according to the type of the cell line (primary/immortalised) in a block design or in a paired sample t-test analysis (for this analysis the replicates of the same sample were averaged).</p><p>For cluster analysis, genes identified in the non-paired analysis were used to obtain a heatmap plot with dendrograms, using Ward's hierarchical cluster algorithm (Bioconductor).</p><p>Gene Ontology classes for the resulting lists of genes were compared to the number of genes expected, considering the number of genes on the microarray in each category. GO classes and parent classes with at least 5 observations in the selected subset and with an observed vs expected ratio of at least 2 were analysed.</p><p>The statistical significance of global gene expression changes in gene ontology categories and BioCarta pathways was assessed by LS/KS permutation tests and the Efron-Tibshirani's GSA maxmean test. All data analyses were performed using the BRB-ArrayTools (developed by Dr. Richard Simon and BRB Array Tools development team) or by Bioconductor packages.</p></sec><sec><title>Real time RT-PCR validation of gene expression</title><p>Based on the microarray results, the following genes were selected for validation by the real-time RT-PCR technique: <italic>DUSP6</italic>, <italic>ASAH1</italic>, <italic>HBEGF</italic>, <italic>MT1F</italic>, <italic>MT1X</italic>, <italic>IL7R</italic>, <italic>IL8</italic>, <italic>CLK4</italic>, <italic>C3orf59</italic>, <italic>SOCS2</italic>, <italic>OSM </italic>and <italic>CISH</italic>. Specific primers were designed using Primer Express v.2.0 software (Applied Biosystems). Detailed primer sequences are available on request.</p><p>The cDNA was synthesised with the High-Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit (Applied Biosystems) using 1 &#x003bc;g of total RNA as a template, and Oligo-dT-Primers (Applied Biosystems), according to the manufacturer's instructions. The real-time (= quantitative, q) RT-PCR reactions were performed with Power SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems) using the 7000 Real-Time PCR system (Applied Biosystems). Reaction mixtures (25 &#x003bc;l) were subjected to a two-step program: 95&#x000b0;C for 10 minutes followed by 40 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 15 s and 60&#x000b0;C for 1 minute. The data were analysed using ABI PRISM 7000 SDS Software. The relative fold difference in gene expression was calculated by the &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct method using the <italic>ACTB </italic>gene as a normalisation control. The statistical significance of the fold change was assessed by the ANOVA test (Statistica package).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>BP: biological process; GO: gene ontology; IL: interleukin; MF: molecular function; PBMC: peripheral blood mononuclear cells; r: recombinant.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>MCh conceived of the study and participated in its design and coordination, carried out RNA isolation, analysed data and interpreted the study, drafted, wrote and edited the manuscript. JKS conceived of the study and participated in its design and coordination, carried out cell cultures, analysed data and interpreted the study, drafted and wrote the manuscript. MG carried out real-time PCR verification of gene expression, participated in drafting the manuscript. MO-W performed microarray gene expression profiling. MJ performed the biostatistical analyses, participated in drafting the manuscript. AP participated in the biostatistical analyses. BJ participated in the design of the study. JS conceived of the study and participated in its design and coordination. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional File 1</title><p><bold>Table A1. Genes differentiating between samples before and after IL-2 withdrawal identified by a non-paired sample T-test</bold>. Genes selected at the nominal univariate comparison level of 0.001.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-10-261-S1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional File 2</title><p><bold>Table A2. Genes differentiating between samples before and after IL-2 withdrawal identified by a paired sample T-test</bold>. Genes selected at the nominal univariate comparison level of 0.001.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-10-261-S2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional File 3</title><p><bold>Table A3. Gene Ontology (GO) analysis of genes selected in a non-paired sample comparison between IL-2-deprived and non-deprived lymphocytes</bold>. The number of genes changed in each category was compared with the number of expected occurrences. Only GO classes and parent classes with at least 5 observations in the selected subset and with an "observed vs. expected" ratio of at least 2 were shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-10-261-S3.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional File 4</title><p><bold>Table A4. Assessment of overall significance of expression changes following IL-2 deprivation in gene groups defined by Gene Ontology categories</bold>. Three independent tests: LS, KS and Efron-Tibshirani GSA were applied to select significantly affected gene classes.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-10-261-S4.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional File 5</title><p><bold>Figure A1. Hierarchical clustering analysis of selected memory T cell genes</bold>. The analysis based on the expression values of some of the genes identified by Holmes et. al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] to characterise memory T cells. Samples before IL-2 withdrawal are in the light-blue columns, samples after IL-2 withdrawal in the navy-blue columns. Primary samples are in the yellow column, immortalised samples are in the green one.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2164-10-261-S5.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Prof. Leendert Looijenga, PhD, for the critical reading of the manuscript. The study was supported by the grant no 2 P05A 150 29 (to JKS, MCh, MG, and JS) and in part by the grant 2 P05A 022 30 (to BJ) of the Polish Ministry of Science and Higher Education.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teague</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hildeman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedl</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrack</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation changes the spectrum but not the diversity of genes expressed by T cells</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>12691</fpage><lpage>12696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10535984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.22.12691</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ropke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladstone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Borregaard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledbetter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Svejgaard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Odum</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apoptosis following interleukin-2 withdrawal from T cells: evidence for a regulatory role of CD18 (beta 2-integrin) molecules</article-title><source>Tissue Antigens</source><year>1996</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8883302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-0039.1996.tb02617.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akbar</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Borthwick</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickremasinghe</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Panayoitidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bofill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krajewski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interleukin-2 receptor common gamma-chain signaling cytokines regulate activated T cell apoptosis in response to growth factor withdrawal: selective induction of anti-apoptotic (bcl-2, bcl-xL) but not pro-apoptotic (bax, bcl-xS) gene expression</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8617294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eji.1830260204</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-A</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannun</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Merida</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual role of ceramide in the control of apoptosis following IL-2 withdrawal</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1998</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>3528</fpage><lpage>3533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9531315</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hieronymus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Blank</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruenke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalden</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CD 95-independent mechanisms of IL-2 deprivation-induced apoptosis in activated human lymphocytes</article-title><source>Cell Death Differ</source><year>2000</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10822277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.cdd.4400684</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devireddy</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional program of apoptosis induction following interleukin 2 deprivation: identification of RC3, a calcium/calmodulin binding protein, as a novel proapoptotic factor</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>4532</fpage><lpage>4541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12808095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.23.13.4532-4541.2003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Blank</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hieronymus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Berden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalden</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extranuclear detection of histones and nucleosomes in activated human lymphoblasts as an early event in apoptosis</article-title><source>Ann Rheum Dis</source><year>2004</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1135</fpage><lpage>1144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15308524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ard.2003.011452</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asselin-Labat</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Biola-Vidamment</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecoeuche</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zennaro</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertoglio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallardy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GILZ, a new target for the transcription factor FoxO3, protects T lymphocytes from interleukin-2 withdrawal-induced apoptosis</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2004</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15031210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2003-12-4295</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurnick</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibroblasts mediate T cell survival: a proposed mechanism for retention of primed T cells</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1990</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>1873</fpage><lpage>1876</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2258711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.172.6.1873</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gombert</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Borthwick</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bofill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Beverley</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Janossy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbar</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibroblasts prevent apoptosis of IL-2-deprived T cells without inducing proliferation: a selective effect on Bcl-XL expression</article-title><source>Immunology</source><year>1996</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8958053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2567.1996.d01-759.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbar</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Girdlestone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Orteu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Borthwick</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Amft</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheel-Toellner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interferon-beta mediates stromal cell rescue of T cells from apoptosis</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>1999</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1041</fpage><lpage>1050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10092109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1521-4141(199903)29:03&#x0003c;1041::AID-IMMU1041&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-#</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pajalunga</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Puggioni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Crescenzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-proliferation as an active state: conceptual and practical implications</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1415</fpage><lpage>1418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17581276</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coppock</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scandalis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilleran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preferential gene expression in quiescent human lung fibroblasts</article-title><source>Cell Growth Differ</source><year>1993</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8396966</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of differential expression of genes in hepatocellular carcinoma by suppression subtractive hybridization combined cDNA microarray</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2007</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17786358</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coller</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new description of cellular quiescence</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e83</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16509772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040083</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzachanis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafuente</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Boussiotis</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrinsic and extrinsic regulation of T lymphocyte quiescence</article-title><source>Leuk Lymphoma</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1959</fpage><lpage>1967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15370239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1042819042000219494</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A transcriptional program mediating entry into cellular quiescence</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e91</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17559306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.0030091</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glynne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghandour</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodnow</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>B-lymphocyte quiescence, tolerance and activation as viewed by global gene expression profiling on microarrays</article-title><source>Immunol Rev</source><year>2000</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11043780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-065X.2000.00614.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duke</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IL-2 addiction: withdrawal of growth factor activates a suicide program in dependent T cells</article-title><source>Lymphokine Res</source><year>1986</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2946903</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Layfield</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disruption of ubiquitin-mediated processes in diseases of the brain and bone</article-title><source>Biochem Soc Trans</source><year>2008</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18481983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST0360469</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>N&#x000e9;morin</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Duplay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence that Lck-mediated phosphorylation of p56dok and p62dok may play a role in CD2 signaling</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>14590</fpage><lpage>14597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10799545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.19.14590</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;ller</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiener</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Aringer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Graninger</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Meuer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Samstag</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional and molecular aspects of transient T cell unresponsiveness: role of selective interleukin-2 deficiency</article-title><source>Clin Exp Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12699409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2249.2003.02150.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joung</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p62 modulates Akt activity via association with PKCzeta in neuronal survival and differentiation</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2005</year><volume>334</volume><fpage>654</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16011831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2005.06.138</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ECop (EGFR-coamplified and overexpressed protein), a novel protein, regulates NF-kappaB transcriptional activity and associated apoptotic response in an IkappaBalpha-dependent manner</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2495</fpage><lpage>2502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15735698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1208496</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatocellular carcinoma-associated gene 2 interacts with MAD2L2</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biochem</source><year>2007</year><volume>304</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17541814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11010-007-9512-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Meacham</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Elojeimy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahdy</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielawska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielawski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Obeid</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannun</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The functional effects of acid ceramidase overexpression in prostate cancer progression and resistance to chemotherapy</article-title><source>Cancer Biol Ther</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1455</fpage><lpage>1460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17881906</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elojeimy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>McKillop</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Zawahry</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Meacham</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahdy</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielawska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannun</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of acid ceramidase in resistance to FasL: therapeutic approaches based on acid ceramidase inhibitors and FasL gene therapy</article-title><source>Mol Ther</source><year>2007</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1259</fpage><lpage>1263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17426710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.mt.6300167</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Irby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kothapalli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrington</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Loughran</surname><given-names>TP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular profiling of LGL leukemia reveals role of sphingolipid signaling in survival of cytotoxic lymphocytes</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2008</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>770</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18477771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2007-11-121871</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huwiler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zangemeister-Wittke</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting the conversion of ceramide to sphingosine 1-phosphate as a novel strategy for cancer therapy</article-title><source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source><year>2007</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17560117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.critrevonc.2007.04.010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Elojeimy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahdy</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeidan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielawska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bielawski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Zawahry</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannun</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinchik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Szulc</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavassoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acid ceramidase inhibition: a novel target for cancer therapy</article-title><source>Front Biosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2293</fpage><lpage>2298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17981711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2741/2843</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosserhoff</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TANGO is a tumor suppressor of malignant melanoma</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>2812</fpage><lpage>2820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17044017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.22242</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arndt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosserhoff</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced expression of TANGO in colon and hepatocellular carcinomas</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2007</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17786351</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusuf</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fruman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of quiescence in lymphocytes</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12860529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1471-4906(03)00141-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hacker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Erlacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Villunger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FOXO3a-dependent regulation of Puma in response to cytokine/growth factor withdrawal</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>203</volume><fpage>1657</fpage><lpage>1663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16801400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20060353</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FOXO transcription factors at the interface between longevity and tumor suppression</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>7410</fpage><lpage>7425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16288288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.onc.1209086</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The search for DAF-16/FOXO transcriptional targets: approaches and discoveries</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2006</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>910</fpage><lpage>921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16934425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exger.2006.06.040</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weidinger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Klagge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Karger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forkhead box-O transcription factor: critical conductors of cancer's fate</article-title><source>Endocr Relat Cancer</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>917</fpage><lpage>929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18775975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1677/ERC-08-0153</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FOXO3a-dependent regulation of Pink1 (Park6) mediates survival signaling in response to cytokine deprivation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>5153</fpage><lpage>5158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19276113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0901104106</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beadling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA array analysis of interleukin-2-regulated immediate/early genes</article-title><source>Med Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12459040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-9433-1-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovanen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenwald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Giltnane</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Staudt</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of gamma c-family cytokine target genes. Identification of dual specificity phosphatase 5 (DUSP5) as a regulator of mitogen activated protein kinase activity in interleukin-2 signaling</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>5205</fpage><lpage>5213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12435740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M209015200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovanen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytokines and immunodeficiency diseases: critical roles of the gamma(c)-dependent cytokines interleukins 2, 4, 7, 9, 15, and 21, and their signaling pathways</article-title><source>Immunol Rev</source><year>2004</year><volume>202</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15546386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0105-2896.2004.00203.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovanen</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Shami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rovella</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pise-Masison</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Radonovich</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Munson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of IL-2 target genes: identification of chromosomal clusters of expressed genes</article-title><source>Int Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1009</fpage><lpage>1021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/intimm/dxh283</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Behrmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Haan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermanns</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller-Newen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaper</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Principles of interleukin (IL)-6-type cytokine signalling and its regulation</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2003</year><volume>374</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12773095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20030407</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisenburger</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An update of the epidemiology of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma</article-title><source>Clin Lymphoma</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14715098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3816/CLM.2003.n.025</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ekstr&#x000f6;m-Smedby</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology and etiology of non-Hodgkin lymphoma&#x02013;a review</article-title><source>Acta Oncol</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16644568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02841860500531682</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malumbres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbacid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>To cycle or not to cycle: a critical decision in cancer</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2001</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11902577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35106065</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khaled</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Durum</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lymphocide: cytokines and the control of lymphoid homeostasis</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12415306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri931</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schluns</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefrancois</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytokine control of memory T-cell development and survival</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12669018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri1052</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Memory T cells have gene expression patterns intermediate between naive and effector</article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>5519</fpage><lpage>5523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0501437102</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>McMichael</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Callan</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular signatures distinguish human central memory from effector memory CD8 T cell subsets</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>5895</fpage><lpage>5903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16237082</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chtanova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weininger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertoni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chappaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sallusto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolph</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identyfication of T cell-restricted genes, and signatures for different T cell responses, using a comprehensive collection of mircroarray datasets</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>7837</fpage><lpage>7847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16339519</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerdiles</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beisner</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinoco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dejean</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Castrillon</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>DePinho</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedrick</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foxo1 links homing and survival of naive T cells by regulating L-selectin, CCR7 and interleukin 7 receptor</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19136962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1689</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaech</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wherry</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Konieczny</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Surh</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective expression of the interleukin 7 receptor identifies effector CD8 T cells that give rise to long-lived memory cells</article-title><source>Nat Imm</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1191</fpage><lpage>1198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni1009</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaech</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kersh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and functional profiling of memory CD8 T cell differentiation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>851</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12526810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(02)01139-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haining</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Subrmanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wherry</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichbaum</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pretz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelosanto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smutko</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaech</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadler</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of an evolutionarily conserved transcriptional signature of CD8 memory differentiation that is shared by T and B cells</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>1859</fpage><lpage>1868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18641323</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siwicki</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rymkiewicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Blachnio</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rygier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzniar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ploski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Janusz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skurzak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chrzanowska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spontaneously immortalized T lymphocytes from Nijmegen Breakage Syndrome patients display phenotypes typical for lymphoma cells</article-title><source>Leuk Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17900685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.leukres.2007.08.011</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siwicki</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Loden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Landberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term cultured IL-2-dependent T cell lines demonstrate p16 overexpression, normal pRb/p53, and upregulation of cyclins E or D2</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2000</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10832057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0531-5565(00)00088-7</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 