<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PONE-RA-10473R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Nutrition</subject><subject>Computational Biology/Sequence Motif Analysis</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics/Cancer Genetics</subject><subject>Mathematics/Statistics</subject><subject>Molecular Biology/Bioinformatics</subject><subject>Oncology/Gastrointestinal Cancers</subject><subject>Pathology/Molecular Pathology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transitions at CpG Dinucleotides, Geographic Clustering of <italic>TP53</italic> Mutations and Food Availability Patterns in Colorectal Cancer</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>TP53</italic> in Colorectal Cancer</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verginelli</surname><given-names>Fabio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bishehsari</surname><given-names>Faraz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Napolitano</surname><given-names>Francesco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mahdavinia</surname><given-names>Mahboobeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cama</surname><given-names>Alessandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Malekzadeh</surname><given-names>Reza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miele</surname><given-names>Gennaro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raiconi</surname><given-names>Giancarlo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tagliaferri</surname><given-names>Roberto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mariani-Costantini</surname><given-names>Renato</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Oncology and Neurosciences, &#x0201c;G. d'Annunzio&#x0201d; University, and Center of Excellence on Aging (CeSI), &#x0201c;G. d'Annunzio&#x0201d; University Foundation, Chieti, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Digestive Disease Research Center (DDRC), Shariati Hospital, University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Mathematics and Informatics, University of Salerno, Salerno, Italy</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Physical Sciences, University of Naples, Naples, Italy</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>Irene Oi-Lin</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">The University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>rmc@unich.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: FV AC RT RMC. Performed the experiments: FV FB FN MM. Analyzed the data: FV FB FN MM AC GM GR RT RMC. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: FV AC RM GM GR RT RMC. Wrote the paper: FV FB FN MM RM GR RT RMC.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e6824</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Verginelli et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Colorectal cancer is mainly attributed to diet, but the role exerted by foods remains unclear because involved factors are extremely complex. Geography substantially impacts on foods. Correlations between international variation in colorectal cancer-associated mutation patterns and food availabilities could highlight the influence of foods on colorectal mutagenesis.</p></sec><sec><title>Methodology</title><p>To test such hypothesis, we applied techniques based on hierarchical clustering, feature extraction and selection, and statistical pattern recognition to the analysis of 2,572 colorectal cancer-associated <italic>TP53</italic> mutations from 12 countries/geographic areas. For food availabilities, we relied on data extracted from the Food Balance Sheets of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. Dendrograms for mutation sites, mutation types and food patterns were constructed through Ward's hierarchical clustering algorithm and their stability was assessed evaluating silhouette values. Feature selection used entropy-based measures for similarity between clusterings, combined with principal component analysis by exhaustive and heuristic approaches.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion/Significance</title><p>Mutations clustered in two major geographic groups, one including only Western countries, the other Asia and parts of Europe. This was determined by variation in the frequency of transitions at CpGs, the most common mutation type. Higher frequencies of transitions at CpGs in the cluster that included only Western countries mainly reflected higher frequencies of mutations at CpG codons 175, 248 and 273, the three major <italic>TP53</italic> hotspots. Pearson's correlation scores, computed between the principal components of the datamatrices for mutation types, food availability and mutation sites, demonstrated statistically significant correlations between transitions at CpGs and both mutation sites and availabilities of meat, milk, sweeteners and animal fats, the energy-dense foods at the basis of &#x0201c;Western&#x0201d; diets. This is best explainable by differential exposure to nitrosative DNA damage due to foods that promote metabolic stress and chronic inflammation.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The <italic>TP53</italic> gene (OMIM no. 191117), which encodes a tumor-suppressor protein that drives multiple cellular responses to stress, including cell-cycle arrest, DNA repair, apoptosis, metabolism and autophagy, is frequently mutated in cancer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Vousden1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Sengupta1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Crighton1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Royds1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Matoba1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Bensaad1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>. <italic>TP53</italic> mutations are mostly missense and cluster in exons 5&#x02013;8, the evolutionarily-conserved region of the DNA-binding domain that contains &#x02248;90&#x00025; of the known mutations and all mutation hotspots at CpG dinucleotides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Hainaut1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Olivier1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Soussi1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Petitjean1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Petitjean2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. Laboratory models and data from tumors with established environmental risk factors show that <italic>TP53</italic> mutation patterns reflect primary mutagenic signatures of DNA damage by carcinogens, vulnerability of nucleotide positions in DNA secondary structure, efficiency of repair processing, and selection for loss of trans-activation properties <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Petitjean1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Petitjean2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Pfeifer1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Hussain1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Hainaut2">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Wright1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Olivier2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Colorectal cancer (CRC), worldwide one of the most common malignancies, is mainly attributed to dietary risk factors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Potter1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Lichtenstein1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Bingham1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Kolonel1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Johnson1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Parkin1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>. <italic>TP53</italic> mutations are found in 50-60&#x00025; of all CRCs and are thought to originate in precancerous lesions, where aberrantly proliferating colonocyte progenitors are directly exposed to dietary residue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Fearon1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Pinto1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>. Nevertheless the <italic>TP53</italic> mutation pattern typical of CRC cannot be easily correlated to diet, because it is characterized by a striking preponderance of G:C&#x0003e;A:T transitions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Soussi1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Hussain1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Olivier2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. These are the most frequent base substitutions induced by reactive oxygen species, byproducts of normal aerobic metabolism generated at high levels in all inflammatory processes and after exposure to a wide variety of carcinogens and toxicants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Wagner1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Feig1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Kreutzer1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Marnett1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ohshima1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Iacopetta1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Russo1">&#x0005b;33&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Iacopetta2">&#x0005b;34&#x0005d;</xref>. Furthermore CRC development appears to depend on whole-life nutrition pattern <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>, and <italic>TP53</italic> mutations may occur years before CRC diagnosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Fearon1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Baker1">&#x0005b;35&#x0005d;</xref>. Thus the time-frame for the estimation of diet may not fully capture the period relevant for mutagenesis and carcinogenesis. This is complicated by the relatively limited variation in dietary habits within single populations, by biases in reporting and recording dietary intakes and by the problematic assessment of exposures to food-borne carcinogens and toxicants, natural and generated in foods production, processing, preservation, and preparation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Day1">&#x0005b;36&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Johansson1">&#x0005b;37&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Asbeck1">&#x0005b;38&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ferrari1">&#x0005b;39&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Huycke1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Goldman1">&#x0005b;41&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Jgerstad1">&#x0005b;42&#x0005d;</xref>. Adding to complexity, intestinal mutagenesis may be modified by nutrient/nutrient, nutrient/microflora, nutrient/cell metabolism, nutrient/gene and nutrient/DNA repair interactions, and affected by epigenetic modifications, transit time of dietary residue, inflammatory and endocrine responses, body mass and energy consumption through physical activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Huycke1">&#x0005b;40&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ishibe1">&#x0005b;43&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Slattery1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Collins1">&#x0005b;45&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Gunter1">&#x0005b;46&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Slattery2">&#x0005b;47&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Arasaradnam1">&#x0005b;48&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>Geography strongly impacts on the ecological, cultural and economic factors that determine food systems and diets. CRCs from patients embedded in geographically diverse populations and cultures reflect substantially different dietary exposures, extended over the whole-life course and unbiased by estimation errors <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Kolonel1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. Thus food-related mutational signatures could be highlighted through the analysis of geographic variation in CRC-associated <italic>TP53</italic> mutations. To test such hypothesis, we analyzed 2,572 <italic>TP53</italic> mutations associated with primary CRCs from 12 countries or geographic areas. The mutations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s006">Database S1</xref>) were extracted from the <italic>TP53</italic> database of the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC) (R10 update, July &#x02013; 2005, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-p53.iarc.fr/Somatic.html">http://www-p53.iarc.fr/Somatic.html</ext-link>), with the addition of an Iranian series <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Petitjean2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Mahdavinia1">&#x0005b;49&#x0005d;</xref>. To investigate correlations between geographic clustering of <italic>TP53</italic> mutations and foods, we relied on the food balance sheets (FBS) of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://faostat.fao.org/site/368/DesktopDefault.aspx?PageID=368">http://faostat.fao.org/site/368/DesktopDefault.aspx?PageID=368</ext-link>), that provide unique comprehensive pictures of the patterns of national food supply, useful for international comparisons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Food1">&#x0005b;50&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-SerraMajem1">&#x0005b;51&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Tornaletti1">&#x0005b;52&#x0005d;</xref>. Food availability patterns (FPs) for the countries/geographic areas in the <italic>TP53</italic> database were derived from the mean <italic>per caput</italic> supplies, in percent of the total caloric value, of each major food group available for human consumption during the reference year 1990 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s004">Dataset S1</xref>). The datamatrices generated for mutation sites (MS), mutation types (MT) and FP (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s005">Datamatrices S1</xref>) were investigated for geographic variation by hierarchical clustering (HC). Factors underlying HC were defined by feature analysis (FA) through principal component analysis (PCA). Pearson's correlation scores were computed between the principal components of the mutation type, food availability pattern and mutation site datamatrices. These analyses demonstrated significant correlations between transitions at CpGs and both mutation sites as well as availabilities of meat, milk, sweeteners and animal fats. Our results could be best explainable with differential exposure to nitrosative DNA damage due to the consumption of energy-dense foods that promote metabolic stress and chronic low-grade inflammation.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Geographic variation in mutation site and type</title><p>Panels A&#x02013;B and C&#x02013;D of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g001">Figure 1</xref> respectively show hierarchical clustering (HC) by country/geographic area for <italic>TP53</italic> mutation sites (MS), based on 2,542 exonic mutations, and types (MT), based on 2,572 mutations in exons and intron-exon boundaries. The MS and MT trees showed similar structures, each with two major geographic clusters, one including only Western countries (I-MS, I-MT), the other Asia and parts of Europe (II-MS, II-MT). The main difference consisted in the position of West and Central Europe in II-MS and I-MT, respectively. Stability of clusters was assessed by silhouette values. Silhouette plots for different thresholds, applied to each dendrogram, were compared to assess the reliability of the clustering solutions. In both cases the tree structure showed two stable clusters. The low silhouette value of MT was related to the poor stability of the &#x0201c;Spain&#x0201d; branch, attributable to either I-MT or II-MT. The MS and MT tree structures were correlated by two-tailed Mantel test (r&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.581, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0006824-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Hierarchical clusterings for <italic>TP53</italic> mutation sites, <italic>TP53</italic> mutation types and food patterns.</title><p>Hierarchical clusterings (HC) by country/geographic area and silhouette plots for: A&#x02013;B, <italic>TP53</italic> mutation sites (MS); C&#x02013;D, <italic>TP53</italic> mutation types (MT); E&#x02013;F, food patterns (FP).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.g001"/></fig><fig id="pone-0006824-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Mantel test correlation between <italic>TP53</italic> mutation sites and <italic>TP53</italic> mutation types.</title><p>Mantel test shows correlation between the distance matrices of mutation sites (MS) and mutation types (MT), with regression line parameter: r&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.581, c&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.015; R<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.338, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.001 after 10,000 permutations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.g002"/></fig><p>By multivariate FA we next investigated the factors that determined clustering for MS (<italic>i.e</italic>., codons) and MT (<italic>i.e</italic>., mutation types), respectively using heuristic or exhaustive approaches. Feature selection aimed at identifying the minimum subset of features necessary to generate the clustering structure obtained using all the features. Sequential forward feature selection with two different rankings, respectively based on the number of mutations recorded for each codon (feature) and on the PC coefficients of each feature, was used to analyze the MS datamatrix by heuristic approach (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0006824-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Feature selection by heuristic approach for the mutation sites data.</title><p>Similarity values are on the y axis; number of features (<italic>i.e.</italic>, codons) on the x axis, respectively ranked in decreasing order of weight (number of mutations, panel A), and decreasing order of the first 11 PC coefficients of each feature (where 11 was the number of PCs contributing 100&#x00025; of the data variance, panel B). Panel C lists (in order of number) the codons (features) with highest variance in the mutation sites (MS) data, selected by weight ranking (23/173 codons) and by PC coefficients ranking (22/173 codons). Overall 19 codons, including the five <italic>TP53</italic> mutation hotspots (highlighted in yellow), were selected by both methods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.g003"/></fig><p>Stable MS clustering was obtained with 23 weight-ranked or 22 PCA-ranked codons, in both cases including the five <italic>TP53</italic> mutation hotspots (<italic>i.e</italic>., CpG codons 175, 245, 248, 273, 282) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Soussi1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Hussain1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Olivier2">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>, out of 173 mutated codons in the datamatrix. The variance contributed by the PCs of the MS datamatrix and their eigenvalues are shown in panels A and D of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g004">Figure 4</xref>, respectively. Total MS variance was explained by 11 components. Four components contributed 80&#x00025; of the variance, and the first component, which accounted for 31&#x00025;, had highly significant PC coefficients for the features corresponding to the five CpG hotspots, as detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s001">File S1</xref> and in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s002">Figure S1</xref>, panel A.</p><fig id="pone-0006824-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Scree and Kaiser's tests applied to the analysis of variance by PCA of the datamatrices for mutation sites, mutation types and food patterns.</title><p>Results obtained using Scree test are shown in panels A&#x02013;C. Total mutation sites (MS) variance (panel A) is explained by 11 components, of which only 9 are visualized, being the Scree test cut at the 98&#x00025; level. Four components contribute 80&#x00025; of the MS variance, the first accounting for 31&#x00025;. Total mutation types (MT) variance (B) is explained by 4 components, the first of which, by far the most relevant, contributes 65&#x00025; of variance. Total food patterns (FP) variance (C) is explained by 3 components, the first of which contributes 87.3&#x00025; of variance. Results obtained using Kaiser's test are shown in panels D&#x02013;F. The first 11 PCs for mutation sites (MS) (A), the first 3 PCs for mutation types (MT) (B) and the first 4 PCs for food patterns (FP) (C) have eigenvalues above 1 (red line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.g004"/></fig><p>Exhaustive multivariate FA of the MT datamatrix is reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t002">2</xref>. In decreasing order, the most relevant features were G:C&#x0003e;A:T at CpGs, followed by A:T&#x0003e;C:G<sup>,</sup> G:C&#x0003e;A:T and G:C&#x0003e;C:G. The variance contributed by each PC of the MT datamatrix and their eigenvalues are shown in panels B and E of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g004">Figures 4</xref> respectively. Total MT variance was explained by 4 components, the first of which accounted for 65&#x00025;, and, as detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s001">File S1</xref> and in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s002">Figure S1</xref>, panel D, the highest PC feature loading among the 8 mutation types corresponded to transitions at CpGs. Other mutations, including transitions at non-CpGs, were associated to minor fractions of variance.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0006824-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Worst-case exhaustive feature analysis of the mutation types datamatrix.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0006824-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0006824.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">|S|&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;number of selected features (j)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feature (i)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1. A:T&#x0003e;C:G</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2. A:T&#x0003e;G:C</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3. A:T&#x0003e;T:A</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4. FS</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5. G:C&#x0003e;A:T</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6. G:C&#x0003e;A:T at CpG</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.92</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.80</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.80</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.79</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.77</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.80</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.81</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7. G:C&#x0003e;C:G</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8. G:C&#x0003e;T:A</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Worst similarity values for each subset S of the MT features, including the selected feature in the left column, are computed using the exhaustive multivariate feature analysis. Bold characters highlight the worst similarity values of the features that most influence cluster structure. Entry (i,j) reports the minimum similarity value obtained using the i-th feature together with any other j-1 features. For example, feature A:T&#x0003e;C:G gives a similarity value that is at least 0.38 when coupled with any 6 of the features in the left column.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0006824-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Best-case exhaustive feature analysis of the mutation types datamatrix.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0006824-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0006824.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Column 1(Feature)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Column 2 (Features that paired with feature in column 1 give the same clustering obtained with all features)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A:T&#x0003e;C:G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G:C&#x0003e;A:T at CpG</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A:T&#x0003e;G:C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A:T&#x0003e;T:A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G:C&#x0003e;A:T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G:C&#x0003e;A:T at CpG</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G:C&#x0003e;A:T at CpG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A:T&#x0003e;C:G and/or G:C&#x0003e;A:T and/or G:C&#x0003e;C:G</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G:C&#x0003e;C:G</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G:C&#x0003e;A:T at CpG</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G:C&#x0003e;T:A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><p>Exhaustive multivariate feature analysis is used to highlight pairs of MT features giving similarity value equal to 1. Features in column 1 give similarity 1 if and only if coupled with one of the features in column 2. For example, feature A:T&#x0003e;C:G gives a similarity value 1 when coupled with G:C&#x0003e;A:T at CpGs. Relevance of individual features in column 1 is based on the number of other features in column 2 with which it can yield unitary value after pairing. The most relevant feature is G:C&#x0003e;A:T at CpGs, followed by A:T&#x0003e;C:G<sup>,</sup> G:C&#x0003e;A:T and G:C&#x0003e;C:G.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The frequency box-plots of the mutations at the 19 codons with highest weights and highest PCA variance coefficients in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g005">Figure 5</xref>, panel A, showed higher mutation frequencies at the three major hotspot codons 175, 248, and, particularly, 273, in I-MS versus II-MS. This reflected higher frequencies of transitions at CpGs in I-MT (range: 46.1&#x02013;61.2&#x00025;) versus II-MT (range: 41.2&#x02013;43.3&#x00025;) in the frequency box-plots of the 8 mutation types in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g005">Figure 5</xref>, panel B. Such most relevant features were used to geographically visualize MS and MT variation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g006">Figure 6</xref>, panels A&#x02013;B). Highlighted groupings of countries/geographic areas were similar to the MS and MT clusters in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g001">Figure 1</xref>, obtained by HC using all the features. Overall these results indicate that in CRC <italic>TP53</italic> transition mutagenesis at CpGs is modulated by geography-related factors. This might reflect differences in exposure(s) to specific food-associated mutagenic process(es) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Hu1">&#x0005b;53&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0006824-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Box-plots of feature relevance for mutation sites, mutation types and food patterns.</title><p>In each panel, box plots pertaining to clusters I versus II of mutation sites (MS), mutation types (MT) and food patterns (FP) obtained by hierarchical clustering are color-coded in red (cluster I) and blue (cluster II), respectively. Panel A: frequency box-plots of mutations at the 19 codons with highest weights and highest PCA variance coefficients (identified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Higher mutation frequencies at the three major CpG hotspot codons 175, 248, and 273 in I-MS versus II-MS are evident. Panel B: frequency box-plots of the 8 mutation types, showing higher frequencies of transitions at CpGs in I-MT (range: 46.1&#x02013;61.2&#x00025;) versus II-MT (range: 41.2&#x02013;43.3&#x00025;). Panel C: box-plots of the mean percent of the total available caloric value from each major food group in the relevant countries/geographic areas, showing lower cereals for the countries/geographic areas in I-FP versus those in II-FP, balanced by higher meat, milk, sweeteners and animal fats.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.g005"/></fig><fig id="pone-0006824-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Geographic visualization of the most relevant features evidenced in the box-plots.</title><p>Selected features of the mutation sites (MS, A), mutation types (MT, B) and food availability patterns (FP, C) datamatrices were mutations at the three major <italic>TP53</italic> hotspot codons 175, 248, and 273 for MS; G:C&#x0003e;A:T mutations at CpGs for MT; meat/milk/sweeteners/animal fats (added), cereals (subtracted) for FP. Feature frequencies were summed and projected in yellow to red color range onto the geographic profiles of the relevant countries/geographic areas.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Geographic variation in food supply patterns</title><p>To address this issue, we analyzed the FP datamatrix by HC and FA through PCA. HC for FP was based on the mean <italic>per caput</italic> supply values, in percent of total available calories, of each major food group in the relevant countries/geographic areas during the reference year 1990 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>. HC yielded two major clusters, I-FP, with Western countries and Japan, and II-FP, with South and East Asia plus Iran (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g001">Figure 1</xref>, panels E&#x02013;F). The clusterization of Japan in I-FP had a low silhouette value and contrasted with the previous assignments of Japan to clusters II-MS and II-MT. To verify Japan's assignment, we generated all the possible subsets of the 13 FP features (food groups), <italic>i.e</italic>., 8,192 subsets. HC trees, cut to obtain two clusters, were then generated based on each of these subsets. Dendrograms were classified as A or B when Japan clusterized respectively in II-FP or I-FP, and as C, when different from A and B. Overall 2,405 clusterings, classified as A, assigned Japan to cluster II-FP with Iran and South and East Asia; 4,178, classified as B, assigned Japan to cluster I-FP, with Western countries; and 1,609 were classified as C, being different from A and B. The histograms in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s003">Figure S2</xref>, panels A&#x02013;B, that visualize the number of times that each of the 13 features was present when type A or B clusterings respectively were obtained, readily show that feature cereals was almost always absent in type A clusterings and almost always present in type B clusterings. Thus Japan joined I-FP only because of the low availability of cereals.</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t003">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t004">4</xref> show the results of exhaustive FA of the FP datamatrix. In decreasing order, the most relevant features were cereals, milk, and meat. PCA showed that total FP variance was explained by 3 components, the first of which accounted for a major fraction of 87.3&#x00025; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g004">Figure 4</xref>, panels C and F). The variance of this component, which, in loading order, included the features cereals, meat, milk, sweeteners, animal fats (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s001">File S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s002">Figure S1</xref>, panel G), explained the tree structure, determined by lower cereals and higher meat, milk, sweeteners and animal fats in I-FP relative to II-FP, as shown in panels C and F of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g004">Figure 4</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0006824-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Worst-case exhaustive feature analysis of the food patterns datamatrix.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0006824-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0006824.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">|S|&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;number of selected features (j)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feature (i)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1. Animal fats</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2. Animal products</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3. Cereals</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4. Fish/seafood</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5. Fruit</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6. Meat</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7. Milk</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8. Oilcrops</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>9. Pulses</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10. Starchy roots</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11. Sweeteners</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12. Vegetable oils</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13. Vegetables</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><p>Worst similarity values for each subset S of the FP features, including the selected feature in the left column, are computed using the exhaustive multivariate feature analysis. Bold characters highlight the worst similarity values of the features that most influence cluster structure (cereals). Entry (i,j) reports the minimum similarity value obtained using the i-th feature together with any other j-1 features. For example, feature &#x0201c;animal products&#x0201d; (i&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;2) gives a similarity at least equal to 0.71 combined with any other remaining 9 features (j&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;10).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0006824-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Best-case exhaustive feature analysis of the food patterns datamatrix.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0006824-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0006824.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Column 1 (Feature)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Column 2 (Features that paired with feature in column 1 give the same clustering obtained with all features)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal fats</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereals, Meat, Milk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal products</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereals, Meat, Oilcrops, Vegetable Oils</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereals</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish/Seafood</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereals, Meat,Milk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruit</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereals, Milk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal fats, Cereals, Fish/Seafood, Milk, Oilcrops, Starchy roots, Vegetable oils</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Milk</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All but Sweeteners</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oilcrops</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal Products, Cereals, Meat, Milk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulses</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereals, Milk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starchy roots</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereals, Meat, Milk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweeteners</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereals</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetable oils</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cereals, Meat, Milk</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetables</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal products, Cereals, Milk</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><p>Exhaustive multivariate feature analysis is used to highlight pairs of FP features giving similarity value equal to 1. Features in column 1 give similarity equal to 1 if and only if coupled with one of the features in column 2. For example, feature cereals (i&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;3) gives a similarity that is always equal to 1 alone or together with any set of other features. Relevance of individual features in column 1 is based on the number of other features in column 2 with which it can yield unitary value after pairing. The most relevant features are cereals, milk, and meat.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Correlations between mutation pattern and food supply pattern</title><p>The data from the MS, MT and FP datamatrices were projected on the 1-dimensional space spanned by their respective PCs. Pairwise Pearson correlations were then computed for the three datamatrices in all the projected spaces. <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t005">Tables 5</xref> to <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t006"/><xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t007">7</xref> show the correlation scores, and the corresponding <italic>P</italic>-values, obtained for the first 3 PCs of each datamatrix, that, except for MS, accounted for most of the variance. Pearson's correlation between the PCs for MT and for FP (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t005">Table 5</xref>) showed that the first PC for MT was correlated with the first PC for FP, with r&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;&#x02212;0.60 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.039). Availabilities of meat, milk, sweeteners and animal fats were directly correlated to transitions at CpGs, availability of cereals to transitions at non-CpGs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s001">File S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s002">Figure S1</xref>, panels D and G). As detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s001">File S1</xref> and in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s002">Figure S1</xref>, other less important correlations involved second and third PCs that accounted for minor fractions of variance. With the same analysis, the first PCs for MS and for MT resulted again strongly correlated, with r&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;&#x02212;0.87 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;0.0002, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t006">Table 6</xref>), which supported Mantel's test results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g002">Figure 2</xref>). However, in spite of the correlation between MT and FP, there were no significant correlations between the PCs of MS and FP (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t007">Table 7</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0006824-t005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Pearson's correlation scores between the PCs of mutation types and food patterns.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0006824-t005-5" xlink:href="pone.0006824.t005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCs</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<sup>th</sup> PC (MT)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<sup>nd</sup> PC (MT)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<sup>rd</sup> PC (MT)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1<sup>th</sup> PC (FP)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;0.6003&#x0002a;</bold> &#x0005b;<italic>0.0391</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2534 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.4268</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.6194&#x0002a;</bold> &#x0005b;<italic>0.0317</italic>&#x0005d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2<sup>nd</sup> PC (FP)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;0.6021&#x0002a;</bold> &#x0005b;<italic>0.0383</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.1735 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.5897</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4654 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.1273</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3<sup>rd</sup> PC (FP)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1724 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.5921</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.6050&#x0002a;</bold> &#x0005b;<italic>0.0371</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.1058 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.7434</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><p>Pearson's correlation scores computed between the principal components (PC) of mutation types (MT) and food availability patterns (FP), with the corresponding <italic>P</italic>-values (square brackets). Significant correlations are highlighted in bold and the corresponding r-coefficient values are marked with an asterisk (&#x0002a;).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0006824-t006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Pearson's correlation scores between the PCs of mutation types and mutation sites.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0006824-t006-6" xlink:href="pone.0006824.t006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCs</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<sup>th</sup> PC (MT)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<sup>nd</sup> PC (MT)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<sup>rd</sup> PC (MT)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1<sup>th</sup> PC (MS)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;0.8742&#x0002a;</bold> &#x0005b;<italic>0.0002</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0908 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.7790</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0118 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.9709</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2<sup>nd</sup> PC (MS)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0975 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.7630</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.1414 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.6612</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0568 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.8609</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3<sup>rd</sup> PC (MS)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0069 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.9830</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2340 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.4642</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3828 <bold>&#x0005b;</bold><italic>0.2194</italic><bold>&#x0005d;</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt106"><p>Pearson's correlation scores computed between the principal components (PC) of mutation types (MT) and mutation sites (MS), with the corresponding <italic>P</italic>-values (square brackets). Significant correlations are highlighted in bold and the corresponding r-coefficient values are marked with an asterisk (&#x0002a;).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0006824-t007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.t007</object-id><label>Table 7</label><caption><title>Pearson's correlation scores between the PCs of mutation sites and food patterns.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0006824-t007-7" xlink:href="pone.0006824.t007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCs</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1<sup>th</sup> PC (MS)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<sup>nd</sup> PC (MS)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3<sup>rd</sup> PC (MS)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1<sup>th</sup> PC (FP)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4176 &#x0005b;<italic>0.1767</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4246 &#x0005b;<italic>0.1688</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4168 &#x0005b;<italic>0.1777</italic>&#x0005d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2<sup>nd</sup> PC (FP)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3858 &#x0005b;<italic>0.2155</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1226 &#x0005b;<italic>0.7042</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.2474 &#x0005b;<italic>0.4382</italic>&#x0005d;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3<sup>rd</sup> PC (FP)</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.2826 &#x0005b;<italic>0.3735</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4014 &#x0005b;<italic>0.1960</italic>&#x0005d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.1824 &#x0005b;<italic>0.5705</italic>&#x0005d;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><p>Pearson's correlation scores computed between the principal components (PC) of mutation sites (MS) and food availability patterns (FP), with the corresponding <italic>P</italic>-values (square brackets). Significant correlations are highlighted in bold and the corresponding r-coefficient values are marked with an asterisk (&#x0002a;).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Scatter plots with superimposed linear regression showing the global trend of correlations were built for the countries/geographic areas as projected on the 2-dimensional spaces spanned by the first PCs of MS and MT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g007">Figure 7</xref>) and of MT and FP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g008">Figure 8</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g007">Figure 7</xref>, Italy, Iran, South and East Asia and West and Central Europe had relatively lower frequencies of mutations at CpG hotspot codons, compensated by higher frequencies of mutations at all other sites (see also box-plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Mutation frequencies at CpG hotspots increased in other countries, with highest frequencies in Australia and UK. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g008">Figure 8</xref>, transitions at CpGs correlated with countries/geographic areas characterized by higher availabilities of energy-dense, Western-style foods, while South and East Asia, Iran, Japan and, to a lesser extent, Italy, where cereals were higher and meat, milk, sweeteners and animal fats lower, had lower frequencies of such mutations.</p><fig id="pone-0006824-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Scatter plot of the correlation between mutation sites and types according to countries/geographic areas.</title><p>Scatter plot of the countries/geographic areas in the <italic>TP53</italic> database projected on the 2-dimensional space spanned by the first principal components of mutation sites (Mutation Site PC2) and mutation types (Mutation Type PC1). Italy, Iran, South and East Asia and West and Central Europe have relatively lower frequencies of mutations at CpG hotspot codons, compensated by higher frequencies of mutations at all other sites (see also box-plots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Mutation frequencies at CpG hotspots increase in other countries, with highest frequencies in Australia and UK. A linear regression shows the global trend of the correlation (r&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;&#x02212;0.8742).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.g007"/></fig><fig id="pone-0006824-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0006824.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Scatter plot of the correlation between mutation types and food patterns according to countries/geographic areas.</title><p>Scatter plot of the countries/geographic areas in the <italic>TP53</italic> database projected on the 2-dimensional space spanned by the highest coefficient features of the first principal component (PC) of food availability pattern (FP), <italic>i.e</italic>., cereals, meat, milk, sweeteners, animal fats, and of the first PC of mutation type (MT), <italic>i.e</italic>., G:C&#x0003e;A:T at CpGs. A linear regression shows the global correlation trend.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.g008"/></fig><p>Overall, variation in the frequency of transitions at CpGs reflected variation in the availabilities of the energy-dense foods that form the basis of &#x0201c;Western-style&#x0201d; diets and that are linked to overweight and obesity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Potter1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Bingham1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Kolonel1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Johnson1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. Transitions at non-CpGs balanced decreases in transitions at CpGs in the countries/geographic areas where cereals compensated for lower availabilities of such foods.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Several studies addressed the issue of CpG transition mutagenesis in cancer, with particular regard to <italic>TP53</italic> mutations in CRC. Being exonic CpGs constitutively hyper-methylated, C to T mutations at coding CpGs in <italic>TP53</italic> should be scored as direct transitions from hypermutable 5-methylcytosine to thymine <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Tornaletti2">&#x0005b;54&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-You1">&#x0005b;55&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Esteller1">&#x0005b;56&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-RideoutWM1">&#x0005b;57&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Pfeifer2">&#x0005b;58&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Pfeifer3">&#x0005b;59&#x0005d;</xref>. Dietary folate is a defined environmental determinant of genomic methylation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Friso1">&#x0005b;60&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Kim1">&#x0005b;61&#x0005d;</xref>. Laboratory models and data on CRCs in patients carrying a germline methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase (<italic>MTHFR</italic>) gene variant that results in reduced plasma and serum folate suggest that low folate, by inducing global hypomethylation, may decrease <italic>TP53</italic> transition mutagenesis at CpGs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ulrich1">&#x0005b;62&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Quinlivan1">&#x0005b;63&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Arasaradnam2">&#x0005b;64&#x0005d;</xref>. Folate-rich foods include fresh vegetables, pulses (legumes) and relatively unprocessed cereals <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Paul1">&#x0005b;65&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-USDA1">&#x0005b;66&#x0005d;</xref>. Little is known about DNA methylation variation among individuals and populations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Bernstein1">&#x0005b;67&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Bock1">&#x0005b;68&#x0005d;</xref>. We did not find any correlation between availability of vegetables or pulses and <italic>TP53</italic> mutation pattern, while cereals, relatively unprocessed in most Asian countries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Drewnowski1">&#x0005b;69&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ghassemi1">&#x0005b;70&#x0005d;</xref>, inversely correlated with transitions at CpGs. Thus folate availability may not account for our results. This conclusion agrees with studies showing that, in absence of interacting genetic effects, folate alone does not influence <italic>TP53</italic> mutation patterns in CRC (although it may affect TP53 protein expression) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Slattery1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Curtin1">&#x0005b;71&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Schernhammer1">&#x0005b;72&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>The hypermutability of endogenous 5-methylcytosine does not <italic>per se</italic> explain the unique role of transitions at CpGs in geographic clustering of <italic>TP53</italic> mutations <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-RideoutWM1">&#x0005b;57&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Pfeifer2">&#x0005b;58&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Pfeifer3">&#x0005b;59&#x0005d;</xref>. However transitions at CpGs in <italic>TP53</italic> are efficiently induced by nitrosative DNA damage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ohshima1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Pfeifer2">&#x0005b;58&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Pfeifer3">&#x0005b;59&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Wink1">&#x0005b;73&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Goodman1">&#x0005b;74&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Sawa1">&#x0005b;75&#x0005d;</xref>. Nitric oxide (NO), a critical signalling molecule implicated in the regulation of peristalsis, gut vasomotor functions and mucosal inflammation, may contribute to transition mutagenesis at CpGs acting directly at 5-methylcytosines, by nitrosative deamination in oxidizing environments, and, indirectly, at guanines, by base alkylation after conversion to nitrate, bacterial reduction to nitrite and endogenous formation of N-nitroso compounds <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Wink1">&#x0005b;73&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Goodman1">&#x0005b;74&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Sawa1">&#x0005b;75&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Wink2">&#x0005b;76&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Grisham1">&#x0005b;77&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Cross1">&#x0005b;78&#x0005d;</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Gal1">&#x0005b;79&#x0005d;</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Lala1">&#x0005b;80&#x0005d;</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Lewin1">&#x0005b;81&#x0005d;</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Hughes1">&#x0005b;82&#x0005d;</xref>. Mutagenesis at CpGs may be facilitated by NO-induced inhibition of DNA repair <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Sawa1">&#x0005b;75&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Lala1">&#x0005b;80&#x0005d;</xref>. Furthermore, NO promotes apoptosis via <italic>TP53</italic> and therefore exerts a critical selective pressure for <italic>TP53</italic> mutation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Forrester1">&#x0005b;83&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ambs1">&#x0005b;84&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ambs2">&#x0005b;85&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Mihara1">&#x0005b;86&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>NO is produced at mutagenic concentrations by inducible NO synthase (iNOS), the widespread enzyme isoform upregulated by inflammatory cytokines <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Wink2">&#x0005b;76&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Hughes1">&#x0005b;82&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Yerushalmi1">&#x0005b;87&#x0005d;</xref>. It has already been suggested that the excess of <italic>TP53</italic> transitions at CpGs found in cancers arising on a chronic inflammatory background, such as CRC in ulcerative colitis and bladder cancer associated with <italic>Schistosomiasis</italic>, results from nitrosative stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Goodman1">&#x0005b;74&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Warren1">&#x0005b;88&#x0005d;</xref>. Moreover transitions at CpGs are strongly related to iNOS expression in both CRC and adenocarcinoma of Barrett's esophagus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ambs3">&#x0005b;89&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Vaninetti1">&#x0005b;90&#x0005d;</xref>. Arginine, the substrate for NO synthesis and a potential CRC-related dietary factor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Yerushalmi1">&#x0005b;87&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Castillo1">&#x0005b;91&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Zell1">&#x0005b;92&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Gerner1">&#x0005b;93&#x0005d;</xref>, is contained in a variety of protein-rich foods of animal and vegetable origin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Paul1">&#x0005b;65&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-USDA1">&#x0005b;66&#x0005d;</xref> and may not <italic>per se</italic> explain why variation in the frequency of transitions at CpGs correlated with variation in the availabilities of meat, milk, sweeteners and animal fats. However it is known that these energy-dense foods promote a pro-inflammatory milieu that increases iNOS expression and NO production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Cross1">&#x0005b;78&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Broughton1">&#x0005b;94&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Joseph1">&#x0005b;95&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-LopezGarcia1">&#x0005b;96&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Giugliano1">&#x0005b;97&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Innis1">&#x0005b;98&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Kallio1">&#x0005b;99&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Devaraj1">&#x0005b;100&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Arulampalam1">&#x0005b;101&#x0005d;</xref>. In addition red meat is a major exogenous source of nitrogen compounds and haem, which contribute to N-nitrosation in the intestinal environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Bingham2">&#x0005b;102&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Tricker1">&#x0005b;103&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Rhodes1">&#x0005b;104&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Cross2">&#x0005b;105&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Cross3">&#x0005b;106&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Oates1">&#x0005b;107&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-MacFarlane1">&#x0005b;108&#x0005d;</xref>. Such considerations are supported by the fact that our data point to a key role of the ubiquitously methylated major <italic>TP53</italic> hotspot codons 175, 248 and 273 in geographic clustering. In fact, the vast majority of the mutations at these 3 codons reported in human cancer are compatible with nitrosative deamination <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Soussi1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Petitjean2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Iacopetta1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Tornaletti2">&#x0005b;54&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Goodman1">&#x0005b;74&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Magewu1">&#x0005b;109&#x0005d;</xref>. Moreover, transitions at codon 248 were experimentally induced with an NO-releasing compound <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Souici1">&#x0005b;110&#x0005d;</xref> while mutations at codon 273 were found to be strongly associated with diets high in red meat and fat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Slattery1">&#x0005b;44&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>In conclusion, we recognize the difficulties inherent in interpreting causes and mechanisms responsible for CRC-associated <italic>TP53</italic> mutations, which are the end result of complex cascades of events. It is important to keep in mind the limitations of our analyses, based on a single, albeit large, database of mutations. Furthermore FAO FBS, the only standardized comprehensive food data available for international comparisons, approximate food supply patterns. Nevertheless, geographic variation in CRC-associated <italic>TP53</italic> mutation patterns appears to be due to transitions at CpGs and mainly related to differential mutation frequencies at the major <italic>TP53</italic> hotspots. This could be explainable by differential exposure to nitrosative DNA damage, linked to the consumption of foods promoting metabolic stress and chronic low-grade inflammation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Databases, Datasets and Datamatrices</title><p>We analyzed 2,572 mutations in <italic>TP53</italic> exons 5&#x02013;8 retrieved from primary CRCs, including 2,475 from 12 countries or geographic areas, extracted from the <italic>TP53</italic> database of the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC) (R10 update, July 2005, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-p53.iarc.fr/Somatic.html">http://www-p53.iarc.fr/Somatic.html</ext-link>), and 97 from Iran <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Petitjean2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Mahdavinia1">&#x0005b;49&#x0005d;</xref>. Mutations in adenomas, metastatic CRC and cell lines were excluded, as their spectrum could differ from that of primary CRC <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Hao1">&#x0005b;111&#x0005d;</xref>. Analyses were based on 2,542 mutations in coding regions for MS, and on 2,572 (<italic>i.e</italic>., all) mutations for MT (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s006">Database S1</xref>). Mutations were grouped according to country or geographic area, the latter including geographically and ethnically related countries with low mutation numbers. Countries and number of mutations for MS and MT, were: Australia (including 6 mutations from New Zealand), MS:302, MT:302; USA, MS:233, MT:237; France, MS:215, MT:221; Italy, MS:181, MT:182; Spain, MS:181, MT:182; UK (including 3 mutations from Ireland), MS:131, MT:134; Iran, MS:94, MT:97; Japan, MS:323, MT:326. Geographic areas were: West and Central Europe (Germany, Austria, Switzerland, The Netherlands, Luxembourg), MS:174, MT:178; South and East Asia (China, Hong Kong, Taiwan, Singapore), MS:315, MT:318; Norway-Denmark, MS:162, MT:162; Sweden-Finland, MS:231, MT:233. Mutations from Brazil, Chile, Israel, Turkey, Korea and Eastern European countries listed in the R10 update of the IARC <italic>TP53</italic> database were excluded because of low numbers.</p><p>The FP dataset (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s004">Dataset S1</xref>) was extracted from the FAO FBS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Food1">&#x0005b;50&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-SerraMajem1">&#x0005b;51&#x0005d;</xref> compiled for the reference year 1990 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://faostat.fao.org/site/368/DesktopDefault.aspx?PageID=368">http://faostat.fao.org/site/368/DesktopDefault.aspx?PageID=368</ext-link>), as used in reference <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>. Year selection tended to exclude the most recent and current international variations in food availabilities and nutrition, as CRC develops over several years and is mostly diagnosed in patients aged 65 years or older <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Parkin2">&#x0005b;112&#x0005d;</xref>, while the IARC <italic>TP53</italic> database compiles mutations since 1989 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Petitjean2">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. The FP dataset included the following major food groups: animal fats, animal products, cereals, fish/seafood, fruit, meat, milk, oilcrops, pulses (legumes), starchy roots, sweeteners, vegetable oils and vegetables. For the purpose of this study alcohol was excluded, being much of the data on average availability of alcoholic drinks not informative and potentially confounding, due to large inter-individual variability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World2">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. Spices and stimulants, which account for low percentages of the total available daily energy supply, were also excluded. Statistical analyses were therefore conducted using the estimated percent (&#x00025;) contribution of each considered food group to mean <italic>per caput</italic> daily energy availability <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>. Weighted average availabilities were calculated for geographic areas by adjusting for the 1990 population size of each included country. The MS, MT and FP datamatrices were normalized converting absolute numbers into frequencies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s005">Datamatrices S1</xref>).</p><p>All standard techniques, including hierarchical clustering (HC), principal components analysis (PCA), Pearson correlation and linear regression, were used in their implementations from Matlab (2007b, The Mathworks and Matlab Statistics Toolbox).</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Statistical Pattern Recognition</title><p>Statistical pattern recognition allowed the integrated analysis of the MS, MT, and FP datamatrices to investigate relations between <italic>TP53</italic> mutation sites, <italic>TP53</italic> mutation types, and food supply patterns. The first analytical step consisted in clustering the 12 analyzed coutries/geographic areas by HC with respect to the data contained in the MS, MT and FP datamatrices. The stability of the obtained clusterings was assessed using the silhouette values. The similarities between the obtained clustering solutions, represented by dendrograms, were assessed using an entropy-based similarity measure. Feature analysis and selection, which is the process of studying the contribution of single features, or subsets of features, to dataset properties, was the next relevant processing step. Exact feature analysis can be performed testing the ability of each single subset of features to maintain a chosen property. In practice, this is feasible only when the number of features is low. In comparing the MT and FP datasets, because of the relatively low number of features, such exhaustive analysis could be carried out. With regard to the MS dataset, the number of possible subsets of features was too high, and therefore a heuristic approach, <italic>i.e</italic>., sequential forward selection, was used to select feature subsets. The principal components and the relative weights of the features were used as ranking criteria. Results were visualized on geographic maps with the relevant areas colored according to the most relevant features. Finally, multivariate correlations between the datasets were computed exploiting their PC projections. All these analytical steps are detailed below.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Hierarchical clustering</title><p>Distance matrices for MS, MT and FP were computed by pairwise comparison between <italic>TP53</italic> countries/geographic areas using the squared Euclidean distance. Dendrograms were constructed through Ward's hierarchical clustering algorithm <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Ward1">&#x0005b;113&#x0005d;</xref>. Stability of clusters was assessed evaluating the silhouette values <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Kaufman1">&#x0005b;114&#x0005d;</xref> that measure how close each point in one cluster is to the points in the neighboring clusters. This measure ranges from &#x0002b;1, indicating points very distant from neighboring clusters, through 0, indicating points not distinctly in one cluster or another, to &#x02212;1, indicating points probably assigned to the wrong cluster.</p><p>Matrices for MS, MT and FP were tested for correlation by Mantel's test <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Mantel1">&#x0005b;115&#x0005d;</xref>. The program Mantel version 3.1 was used to estimate Pearson correlation coefficients. Significance was assessed by 10,000 random permutations.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Feature selection</title><p>Feature selection involved the use of a similarity measure between hierarchical clusterings, visualized as dendrograms, respectively built on the entire feature set and on the feature subset(s) to be tested. The higher the similarity, the higher the rank of the chosen feature subset. The entropy-based similarity measure used is defined below.</p><p>Two clusterings are identical if there is one-to-one correspondence between their clusters. The more a cluster of one clustering is filled with objects from different clusters of the other clustering (disorder), the less is the concordance between clusterings. All the information needed to summarize this phenomenon is the corresponding confusion matrix. Given two clusterings, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e001.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e002.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula><bold>,</bold> where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e003.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is made of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e004.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> clusters and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e005.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e006.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> clusters, the confusion matrix <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e007.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e008.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e009.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is an <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e010.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> matrix, in which the entry <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e011.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> reports the number of objects in the cluster <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e012.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e013.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> falling into the cluster <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e014.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e015.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Entropy is the obvious tool to measure such disorder. If <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e016.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e017.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-th row of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e018.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e019.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e020.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-th column of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e021.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, then <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e022.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> measures the disorder of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e023.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-th cluster of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e024.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> with respect to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e025.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e026.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> measures the disorder of the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e027.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>-th cluster of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e028.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> with respect to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e029.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>A way to compute the similarity between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e030.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e031.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the mean entropy of the clusters of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e032.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> versus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e033.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, where the <italic>a priori</italic> probability of a cluster <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e034.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e035.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, can be approximated as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e036.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, giving the formula:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e037"/></disp-formula>expressing the similarity of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e038.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> versus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e039.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, while the similarity of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e040.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> versus <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e041.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be obtained with the analogue formula on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e042.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, which turns to be <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e043.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The measure of similarity between clusterings is in the trade-off between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e044.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e045.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. We define the final similarity measure:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e046"/></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e047.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e048.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, can be used to set the acceptable level of &#x02018;sub-clusteringness&#x02019; of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e049.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> with respect to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e050.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. When <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e051.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, no importance is given to the fragmentation level of the clusters in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e052.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. When <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e053.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> only exact matching between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e054.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e055.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> will produce a maximum for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e056.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>Basing on such similarity measure between clusterings, useful comparisons between dendrograms can be easily performed. Given a solution obtained from a dendrogram (the target solution), it is possible to assess how much such solution can be approximated by another dendrogram.</p><p>Given a dendrogram <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e057.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, let <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e058.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> be the clustering solution obtained applying a cutting threshold <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e059.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e060.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. We define <italic>complete threshold set</italic> for a dendrogram any minimal set of threshold values, applying which all the possible clusterings for the dendrogram can be obtained. We indicate any such set for a dendrogram <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e061.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e062.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. It can be easily shown that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e063.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e064.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the number of nodes in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e065.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>Given a dendrogram <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e066.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, a target solution <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e067.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be derived applying a cutting threshold. The similarity between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e068.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and another dendrogram, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e069.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, can be approximated using the dendrogram similarity procedure.</p><p>Dendrogram similarity procedure <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e070.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula><disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e071"/></disp-formula>for each <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e072.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e073.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></p><p>Build <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e074.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the confusion matrix between <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e075.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e076.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula><disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e077"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e078"/></disp-formula>return <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e079.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula></p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Exhaustive approach to feature selection for the MT and FP datamatrices</title><p>Feature analysis studies the properties of single features or subsets of features of the analyzed data. Exact feature analysis can be performed testing the properties of each possible subset of features. In this study, the property of interest was the ability to maintain the groups obtained in the clustering analysis phase. Such exhaustive approach was successfully performed on the MT and FP datamatrices.</p><p>Given a set of features <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e080.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and a scoring function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e081.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the exhaustive feature analysis approach consists in computing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e082.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. We performed this analysis using the features of the MT and FP datamatrices in turn for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e083.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e084.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e085.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, where T is the solution obtained in the clustering analysis phase of the data and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e086.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the dendrogram built using the features subset <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e087.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>The results of exhaustive feature analysis are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t002">2</xref> for the MT datamatrix and in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t003">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t004">4</xref> for the FP datamatrix. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t001">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t003">3</xref> the entry <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e088.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> reports the worst score obtained using <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e089.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e090.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e091.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t002">Tables 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0006824-t004">4</xref> the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e092.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula><italic>-th</italic> entry reports the set of features <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e093.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> such that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e094.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Heuristic approach to feature selection for the MS datamatrix</title><p>Being the number of MS feature subsets equal to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e095.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, we used the sequential forward selection approach for MS feature selection. A filter method was used.</p><p>Given a feature set <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e096.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and a scoring function <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e097.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, a ranking of features can be obtained computing and sorting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e098.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Let such ordered set be: <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e099.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>Instead of producing all possible subsets of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e100.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, we produce the sets <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e101.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> such that:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e102"/></disp-formula><disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e103"/></disp-formula></p><p>Substituting <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e104.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e105.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in the exhaustive approach completes the definition of the heuristic approach.</p><p>We used this method with two different rankings, respectively based on the number of mutations recorded for each codon (feature); and on the sum of the first 11 Principal Components (PCs) coefficients of each feature (where 11 was the number of PCs contributing 100&#x00025; of the data variance). Panels A and B of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0006824-g003">Figure 3</xref> report the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e106.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> values obtained for the two different ranking functions. Panel C of the same Figure compares the best feature sets (minimal stable subsets giving <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0006824.e107.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>).</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Geographic visualization of feature relevance</title><p>Geographic visualizations of the most relevant features of the MS, MT and FP datamatrices were obtained by respectively summing feature frequencies (for MS and MT) and <italic>per caput</italic> supply of each food group expressed as &#x00025; of the total available calories, as detailed above <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Food1">&#x0005b;50&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-World1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref> (for FP). Resulting values were projected into yellow to red color range onto the geographic profiles of the countries and geographic areas contributing to the <italic>TP53</italic> mutation database.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Correlation analyses</title><p>To perform a multivariate correlation analysis between the PCs of MS, MT and FP, we exploited their projections on the respective PCs. Both the Scree and the Kaiser <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0006824-Kaiser1">&#x0005b;116&#x0005d;</xref> tests provided clear support for extracting the first 11 components for MS. When applied to MT, these tests supported the extraction of 4 and 3 PCs respectively, being the eigenvalue of the fourth PC near the lower limit value (<italic>i.e</italic>., 0.9). For FP the Scree and Kaiser tests indicated 3 and 4 PCs, respectively. Pairwise Pearson correlations were then computed between the PCs in all the projected spaces.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0006824.s001"><label>File S1</label><caption><p>Coefficient loadings of the three most relevant PCs of mutation sites (MS), mutation types (MT) and food patterns (FP) and Pearson's correlation scores computed between the PCs of MS, MT and FP.</p><p>(0.04 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0006824.s001.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0006824.s002"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>Coefficient loadings of the first three PCs of the mutation sites, mutation types and food patterns datamatrices. Coefficient loadings of the three most relevant principal components (PCs) of the mutation sites (MS, A&#x02013;C), mutation types (MT, D&#x02013;F) and food availability patterns (FP, G&#x02013;I) datamatrices are projected on their 1-dimensional space (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0006824.s001">File S1</xref> for discussion).</p><p>(0.71 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0006824.s002.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0006824.s003"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>Assignment of Japan to clusters I or II in cluster analysis for food availability patterns. The food category &#x0201c;cereals&#x0201d; determined clusterization of Japan with Western countries for food availability patterns. Histograms visualize the number of times that each of the 13 features was present in the 2,405 clusterings classified as type A, i.e, where Japan joined Iran and South and East Asia in cluster II-FP (A), or in the 4,178 clusterings classified as type B, i.e, where Japan joined Western countries in cluster I-FP (B). It is readily evident that feature 3 (cereals) was almost always absent in type A clusterings and almost always present in type B clusterings. This reflects the estimated low mean per caput supply of cereals available for human consumption in Japan, compared to the countries/geographic areas in the II-FP cluster (i.e., Iran and South and East Asia). Features 1 to 13 represent the following food categories: 1, animal fats; 2, animal products; 3, cereals; 4, fish/seafood; 5, fruit; 6, meat; 7, milk; 8, oilcrops; 9, pulses (legumes); 10, starchy roots; 11, sweeteners; 12, vegetable oils; 13, vegetables.</p><p>(0.15 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0006824.s003.tif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0006824.s004"><label>Dataset S1</label><caption><p>1990 Food Balance Sheet data - Estimated mean per caput supply of each major food group available for human consumption in the <italic>TP53</italic> database countries, as extracted from the Food Balance Sheets (FBS) of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), year 1990.</p><p>(0.02 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0006824.s004.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0006824.s005"><label>Datamatrices S1</label><caption><p>Normalized datamatrix for <italic>TP53</italic> mutation sites (MS) and mutation types (MT) assigned to 12 countries/geographic areas and normalized datamatrix for the estimated food availability patterns (FP) of the 12 countries/geographic areas in the <italic>TP53</italic> database. Data from 2,572 <italic>TP53</italic> exons 5&#x02013;8 mutations associated with primary CRCs were retrieved from the <italic>TP53</italic> database of the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC), R10 update, July - 2005, and from Mahdavinia et al., J Cell Physiol. 2008; 216(2):543&#x02013;550.</p><p>(0.07 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0006824.s005.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0006824.s006"><label>Database S1</label><caption><p>List of 2,572 <italic>TP53</italic> exons 5&#x02013;8 mutations reported in association with primary colorectal cancers, including 2,475 from 11 countries/geographic areas, extracted from the <italic>TP53</italic> database of the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC), R10 update, July 2005, and 97 from Iran (Mahdavinia et al., J Cell Physiol. 2008;216:543&#x02013;550).</p><p>(0.61 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0006824.s006.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We acknowledge the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC) and the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), for their investment in the collection and free distribution of the data that made the present study possible. We also thank Dr. Angela Polito, Human Nutrition Unit, National Research Institute for Food and Nutrition (<italic>INRAN</italic>), Rome, Italy, for assisting with FAO data.</p><p>Links: TP53 database of the International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC), http://www-p53.iarc.fr/Somatic.html; Food Balance Sheets (FBS) of the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO), http://faostat.fao.org/site/368/DesktopDefault.aspx?PageID&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;368.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0006824-Vousden1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vousden</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Live or let die: the cell's response to p53.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><volume>2(8)</volume><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12154352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Sengupta1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>P53: traffic cop at the crossroads of DNA repair and recombination.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15688066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Crighton1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crighton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Prey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Syed</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>DRAM, a p53-induced modulator of autophagy, is critical for apoptosis.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>126</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16839881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Royds1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Royds</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Iacopetta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>P53 and disease: when the guardian angel fails.</article-title><source>Cell Death Differ</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16557268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Matoba1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matoba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Patino</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wragg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>P53 regulates mitochondrial respiration.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>312</volume><fpage>1650</fpage><lpage>1653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16728594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Bensaad1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bensaad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vousden</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>P53: new roles in metabolism.</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17481900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Hainaut1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hainaut</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>P53 and human cancer: the first ten thousand mutations.</article-title><source>Adv Cancer Res</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10549356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Olivier1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eeles</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The IARC TP53 database: new online mutation analysis and recommendations to users.</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12007217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Soussi1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soussi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishioka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Reassessment of the TP53 mutation database in human disease by data mining with a library of TP53 missense mutations.</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><volume>25</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15580553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Petitjean1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petitjean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Achatz</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Borresen-Dale</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hainaut</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>TP53 mutations in human cancers: functional selection and impact on cancer prognosis and outcomes.</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>2157</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17401424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Petitjean2"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petitjean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishioka</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavtigian</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Impact of mutant p53 functional properties on TP53 mutation patterns and tumor phenotype: lessons from recent developments in the IARC TP53 database.</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17311302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Pfeifer1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Denissenko</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Formation and repair of DNA lesions in the p53 gene: relation to cancer mutations?</article-title><source>Environ Mol Mutagen</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9585258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Hussain1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Molecular epidemiology and carcinogenesis: endogenous and exogenous carcinogens.</article-title><source>Mutat Res</source><volume>462</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10767641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Hainaut2"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hainaut</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Tumor-specific mutations in p53: the acid test.</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11786899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Wright1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Reimers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Reschke</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Hypermutable bases in the p53 cancer gene are at vulnerable positions in DNA secondary structures.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>5641</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12384517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Olivier2"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron de Fromentel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hainaut</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>TP53 mutation spectra and load: a tool for generating hypotheses on the etiology of cancer.</article-title><source>IARC Sci Publ</source><volume>157</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15055300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-World1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Cancer Research Fund/American Institute for Cancer Research</collab><year>1997</year><article-title>Food, nutrition and the prevention of cancer: a global perspective.</article-title><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>AICR press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Potter1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Colorectal cancer: molecules and populations.</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>916</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10359544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Lichtenstein1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Verkasalo</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Iliadou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaprio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Environmental and heritable factors in the causation of cancer&#x02013;analyses of cohorts of twins from Sweden, Denmark, and Finland.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>343</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10891514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Bingham1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Riboli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Diet and cancer&#x02013;the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14993902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Kolonel1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolonel</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Altshuler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The multiethnic cohort study: exploring genes, lifestyle and cancer risk.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15229477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Johnson1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Review article: nutrition, obesity and colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17593063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-World2"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Cancer Research Fund/American Institute for Cancer Research</collab><year>2007</year><article-title>Food, nutrition, physical activity, and the prevention of cancer: a global perspective.</article-title><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>AICR press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Parkin1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pisani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Global cancer statistics, 2002.</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15761078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Fearon1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fearon</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>A genetic model for colorectal tumorigenesis.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2188735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Pinto1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Wnt control of stem cells and differentiation in the intestinal epithelium.</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><volume>306</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15925592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Wagner1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Endogenous oxidative damage of deoxycytidine in DNA.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>89</volume><fpage>3380</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1565630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Feig1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feig</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Sowers</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Reverse chemical mutagenesis: identification of the mutagenic lesions resulting from reactive oxygen species-mediated damage to DNA.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>6609</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7517554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Kreutzer1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreutzer</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Essigmann</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Oxidized, deaminated cytosines are a source of C &#x02192; T transitions <italic>in vivo</italic>.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>3578</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9520408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Marnett1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marnett</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Oxyradicals and DNA damage.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Ohshima1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohshima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatemichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Chemical basis of inflammation-induced carcinogenesis.</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><volume>417</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12921773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Iacopetta1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacopetta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>TP53 mutation in colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Hum Mutat</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12619112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Russo1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Iacopetta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Soussi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>TP53-CRC Collaborative Study Group. The TP53 colorectal cancer international collaborative study on the prognostic and predictive significance of p53 mutation: influence of tumor site, type of mutation, and adjuvant treatment.</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>7518</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16172461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Iacopetta2"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iacopetta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Soussi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Functional categories of TP53 mutation in colorectal cancer: results of an international collaborative study.</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>842</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16524972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Baker1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Preisinger</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jessup</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Paraskeva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Markowitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>P53 gene mutations occur in combination with 17p allelic deletions as late events in colorectal tumorigenesis.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>7717</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2253215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Day1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>McKeown</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Epidemiological assessment of diet: a comparison of a 7-day diary with a food frequency questionnaire using urinary markers of nitrogen, potassium and sodium.</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11369735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Johansson1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wikman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahr&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallmans</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Underreporting of energy intake in repeated 24-hour recalls related to gender, age, weight status, day of interview, educational level, reported food intake, smoking habits and area of living.</article-title><source>Public Health Nutr</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>919</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11527517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Asbeck1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asbeck</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mast</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bierwag</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Westenh&#x000f6;fer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Acheson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Severe underreporting of energy intake in normal weight subjects: use of an appropriate standard and relation to restrained eating.</article-title><source>Public Health Nutr</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12372163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Ferrari1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Slimani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciampi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trichopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Naska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Evaluation of under- and overreporting of energy intake in the 24-hour diet recalls in the European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition (EPIC).</article-title><source>Public Health Nutr</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>1329</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12639236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Huycke1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huycke</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaskins</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Commensal bacteria, redox stress, and colorectal cancer: mechanisms and models.</article-title><source>Exp Biol Med (Maywood)</source><volume>229</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15229352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Goldman1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Food mutagens.</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><volume>133</volume><fpage>965S</fpage><lpage>973S</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12612183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Jgerstad1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000e4;gerstad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Skog</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Genotoxicity of heat-processed foods.</article-title><source>Mutat Res</source><volume>574</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15914214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Ishibe1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishibe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Understanding the interaction between environmental exposures and molecular events in colorectal carcinogenesis.</article-title><source>Cancer Invest</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11458819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Slattery1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slattery</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Diet activity, and lifestyle associations with p53 mutations in colon tumors.</article-title><source>Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12050095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Collins1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Melvin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Nutritional modulation of DNA repair in a human intervention study.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12663512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Gunter1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leitzmann</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Obesity and colorectal cancer: epidemiology, mechanisms and candidate genes.</article-title><source>J Nutr Biochem</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16426829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Slattery2"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slattery</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Defining dietary consumption: is the sum greater than its parts?</article-title><source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18614718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Arasaradnam1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arasaradnam</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Commane</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradburn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>A review of dietary factors and its influence on DNA methylation in colorectal carcinogenesis.</article-title><source>Epigenetics</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18682688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Mahdavinia1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahdavinia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishehsari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Verginelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cumashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lattanzio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>P53 mutations in colorectal cancer from northern Iran: Relationships with site of tumor origin, microsatellite instability and K-ras mutations.</article-title><source>J Cell Physiol</source><volume>216</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18330889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Food1"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</collab><year>2001</year><article-title>Food Balance Sheets: a handbook.</article-title><comment>Rome, FAO press</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-SerraMajem1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serra-Majem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>MacLean</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brul&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekula</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Comparative analysis of nutrition data from national, household, and individual levels: results from a WHO-CINDI collaborative project in Canada, Finland, Poland, and Spain.</article-title><source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Tornaletti1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tornaletti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Complete and tissue-independent methylation of CpG sites in the p53 gene: implications for mutations in human cancers.</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7731703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Hu1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary pattern analysis: a new direction in nutritional epidemiology (2002)</article-title><source>Curr Opin Lipidol</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11790957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Tornaletti2"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tornaletti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Complete and tissue-independent methylation of CpG sites in the p53 gene: implications for mutations in human cancers.</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7731703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-You1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Halangoda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Buettner</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Methylation of CpG dinucleotides in the lacI gene of the Big Blue transgenic mouse.</article-title><source>Mutat Res</source><volume>420</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9838042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Esteller1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esteller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Epigenetics in cancer.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>358</volume><fpage>1148</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18337604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-RideoutWM1"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rideout WM</surname><given-names>WM</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Coetzee</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Olumi</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>5-Methylcytosine as an endogenous mutagen in the human LDL receptor and p53 genes.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>249</volume><fpage>1288</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1697983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Pfeifer2"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>P53 mutational spectra and the role of methylated CpG sequences.</article-title><source>Mutat Res</source><volume>450</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10838140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Pfeifer3"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Mutagenesis at methylated CpG sequences.</article-title><source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source><volume>301</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16570852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Friso1"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Gene-nutrient interactions in one-carbon metabolism.</article-title><source>Curr Drug Metab</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15720206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Kim1"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Nutritional epigenetics: impact of folate deficiency on DNA methylation and colon cancer susceptibility.</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>2703</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16251634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Ulrich1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ulrich</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Samowitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>MTHFR variants reduce the risk of G:C-&#x0003e;A:T transition mutations within the p53 tumor suppressor gene in colon tumors.</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>2462</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16177213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Quinlivan1"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlivan</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shelnutt</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Maneval</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghandour</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase 677C-&#x0003e;T polymorphism and folate status affect one-carbon incorporation into human DNA deoxynucleosides.</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15735068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Arasaradnam2"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arasaradnam</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Commane</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradburn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>A review of dietary factors and its influence on DNA methylation in colorectal carcinogenesis.</article-title><source>Epigenetics</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18682688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Paul1"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Southgate</surname><given-names>DAT</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year><article-title>McCance and Widdowson's The Composition of Foods.</article-title><publisher-loc>Amsterdam/New York/London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>HMSO and Elsevier/North-Holland Biomedical Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-USDA1"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">USDA nutrient database for standard reference, release 20 (accessed 2007) Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nal.usda.gov/fnic/foodcomp">http://www.nal.usda.gov/fnic/foodcomp</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Bernstein1"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The mammalian epigenome.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>128</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17320505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Bock1"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lengauer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Computational epigenetics.</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>24</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Drewnowski1"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drewnowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>The nutrition transition: new trends in the global diet.</article-title><source>Nutr Rev</source><volume>55</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9155216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Ghassemi1"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghassemi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>An accelerated nutrition transition in Iran.</article-title><source>Public Health Nutr</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12027278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Curtin1"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Slattery</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulrich</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Genetic polymorphisms in one-carbon metabolism: associations with CpG island methylator phenotype (CIMP) in colon cancer and the modifying effects of diet.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>1672</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17449906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Schernhammer1"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schernhammer</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Folate and vitamin B(6) intake and risk of colon cancer in relation to p53 expression.</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>135</volume><fpage>770</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18619459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Wink1"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasprzak</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Maragos</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elespuru</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1991</year><article-title>DNA deaminating ability and genotoxicity of nitric oxide and its progenitors.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>254</volume><fpage>1001</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1948068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Goodman1"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofseth</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Nitric oxide and p53 in cancer-prone chronic inflammation and oxyradical overload disease.</article-title><source>Environ Mol Mutagen</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15199542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Sawa1"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohshima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Nitrative DNA damage in inflammation and its possible role in carcinogenesis.</article-title><source>Nitric Oxide</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16099698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Wink2"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanbauer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Grisham</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Laval</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nims</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Chemical biology of nitric oxide: regulation and protective and toxic mechanisms.</article-title><source>Curr Top Cell Regul</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8646847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Grisham1"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grisham</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavlick</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Laroux</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bharwani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Nitric oxide and chronic gut inflammation: controversies in inflammatory bowel disease.</article-title><source>J Investig Med</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>83</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Cross1"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Nitric oxide in inflammatory bowel disease.</article-title><source>Inflamm Bowel Dis</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12792224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Gal1"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wogan</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Mutagenesis associated with nitric oxide production in transgenic SJL mice.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>93</volume><fpage>15102</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8986771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Lala1"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lala</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Role of nitric oxide in carcinogenesis and tumour progression.</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11902565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Lewin1"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandaletova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Red meat enhances the colonic formation of the DNA adduct O6-carboxymethyl guanine: implications for colorectal cancer risk.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>1859</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Hughes1"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Chemistry of nitric oxide and related species.</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><volume>436</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18237624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Forrester1"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forrester</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupold</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapust</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Spillare</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Nitric oxide-induced p53 accumulation and regulation of inducible nitric oxide synthase expression by wild-type p53.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>93</volume><fpage>2442</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8637893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Ambs1"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Interactive effects of nitric oxide and the p53 tumor suppressor gene in carcinogenesis and tumor progression.</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9194524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Ambs2"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Felley-Bosco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogunfusika</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Frequent nitric oxide synthase-2 expression in human colon adenomas: implication for tumor angiogenesis and colon cancer progression.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>58</volume><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9443414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Mihara1"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Erster</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaika</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrenko</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Chittenden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>P53 has a direct apoptogenic role at the mitochondria.</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12667443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Yerushalmi1"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yerushalmi</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Besselsen</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignatenko</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blohm-Mangone</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Padilla-Torres</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The role of NO synthases in arginine-dependent small intestinal and colonic carcinogenesis.</article-title><source>Mol Carcinog</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16329147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Warren1"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Biggs</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>el-Baz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghoneim</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratton</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Mutations in the p53 gene in schistosomal bladder cancer: a study of 92 tumours from Egyptian patients and a comparison between mutational spectra from schistosomal and non-schistosomal urothelial tumours.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1181</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7767983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Ambs3"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogunfusika</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Oser</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Relationship between p53 mutations and inducible nitric oxide synthase expression in human colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9890175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Vaninetti1"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaninetti</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Geldenhuys</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Risch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hainaut</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Inducible nitric oxide synthase, nitrotyrosine and p53 mutations in the molecular pathogenesis of Barrett's esophagus and esophageal adenocarcinoma.</article-title><source>Mol Carcinog</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17849424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Castillo1"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castillo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>DeRojas</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Splanchnic metabolism of dietary arginine in relation to nitric oxide synthesis in normal adult man.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8419922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Zell1"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignatenko</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yerushalmi</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziogas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Besselsen</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Risk and risk reduction involving arginine intake and meat consumption in colorectal tumorigenesis and survival.</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17096347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Gerner1"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerner</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Impact of dietary amino acids and polyamines on intestinal carcinogenesis and chemoprevention in mouse models.</article-title><source>Biochem Soc Trans</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17371270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Broughton1"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broughton</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Total fat and (n-3):(n-6) fat ratios influence eicosanoid production in mice.</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11773513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Joseph1"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Castrillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Laffitte</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangelsdorf</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tontonoz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Reciprocal regulation of inflammation and lipid metabolism by liver X receptors.</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12524534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-LopezGarcia1"><label>96</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez-Garcia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Meigs</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rifai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Major dietary patterns are related to plasma concentrations of markers of inflammation and endothelial dysfunction.</article-title><source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>1029</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15447916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Giugliano1"><label>97</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giugliano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceriello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The effects of diet on inflammation: emphasis on the metabolic syndrome.</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16904534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Innis1"><label>98</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Innis</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Dietary lipids in early development and intestinal inflammatory disease.</article-title><source>Nutr Rev</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>S188</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18240547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Kallio1"><label>99</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kallio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolehmainen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laaksonen</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulkkinen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Atalay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Inflammation markers are modulated by responses to diets differing in postprandial insulin responses in individuals with the metabolic syndrome.</article-title><source>Am J Clin Nutr</source><volume>87</volume><fpage>1497</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Devaraj1"><label>100</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devaraj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang-Polagruto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Polagruto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Keen</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jialal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>High-fat, energy-dense, fast-food-style breakfast results in an increase in oxidative stress in metabolic syndrome.</article-title><source>Metabolism</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18502272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Arulampalam1"><label>101</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arulampalam</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Gastrointestinal inflammation: lessons from metabolic modulators.</article-title><source>J Intern Med</source><volume>263</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18479260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Bingham2"><label>102</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pignatelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malaveille</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Does increased endogenous formation of N-nitroso compounds in the human colon explain the association between red meat and colon cancer?</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8631138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Tricker1"><label>103</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tricker</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>N-nitroso compounds and man: sources of exposure, endogenous formation and occurrence in body fluids.</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer Prev</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9306073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Rhodes1"><label>104</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Inflammation and colorectal cancer: IBD-associated and sporadic cancer compared.</article-title><source>Trends Mol Med</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11796261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Cross2"><label>105</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Haem, not protein or inorganic iron, is responsible for endogenous intestinal N-nitrosation arising from red meat.</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><volume>63</volume><fpage>2358</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12750250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Cross3"><label>106</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Meat-related mutagens/carcinogens in the etiology of colorectal cancer.</article-title><source>Environ Mol Mutagen</source><volume>44</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15199546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Oates1"><label>107</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oates</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Heme in intestinal epithelial cell turnover, differentiation, detoxification, inflammation, carcinogenesis, absorption and motility.</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>4281</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16865768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-MacFarlane1"><label>108</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacFarlane</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Convergence of genetic, nutritional and inflammatory factors in gastrointestinal cancers.</article-title><source>Nutr Rev</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>S157</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18240541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Magewu1"><label>109</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magewu</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Ubiquitous and tenacious methylation of the CpG site in codon 248 of the p53 gene may explain its frequent appearance as a mutational hot spot in human cancer.</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>4225</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8196660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Souici1"><label>110</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souici</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirkovitch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hausel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Keefer</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Felley-Bosco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Transition mutation in codon 248 of the p53 tumor suppressor gene induced by reactive oxygen species and a nitric oxide-releasing compound.</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10657969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Hao1"><label>111</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>XP</given-names></name><name><surname>Frayling</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sgouros</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Willcocks</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>The spectrum of p53 mutations in colorectal adenomas differs from that in colorectal carcinomas.</article-title><source>Gut</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12010886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Parkin2"><label>112</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><comment>Cancer incidence in five continents, vol. VII. IARC Scientific Publications No. 143, Lyon: IARC Press</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Ward1"><label>113</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1963</year><article-title>Hierarchical Grouping to optimize an objective function.</article-title><source>J Am Stat Assoc</source><volume>58</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>244</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Kaufman1"><label>114</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rousseeuw</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Finding groups in data: an introduction to cluster analysis.</article-title><comment>Wiley Press</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Mantel1"><label>115</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Valand</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1970</year><article-title>A technique of non parametric multivariate analysis.</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5480664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0006824-Kaiser1"><label>116</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1960</year><article-title>The application of electronic computers to factor analysis.</article-title><source>Educational and Psychological Measurement</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>151</lpage></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>The study was funded by the Italian Ministry of Education, University and Research (Ministero dell'Istruzione, dell'Universit&#x000e0; e della Ricerca, MIUR) and by the Faculties of Medicine and Pharmacy, G. d'Annunzio University, Chieti, Italy (years 2005-08). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>