<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PONE-RA-13276R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008089</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology/Obesity</subject><subject>Gastroenterology and Hepatology/Hepatology</subject><subject>Pathology/Histopathology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Alleviation of High-Fat Diet-Induced Fatty Liver Damage in Group IVA Phospholipase A<sub>2</sub>-Knockout Mice</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">PLA<sub>2</sub>-Mediated Fatty Liver</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ii</surname><given-names>Hiromi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>Naoki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>Shintaro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>Kae</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>Shinji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>Keiichi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akiba</surname><given-names>Satoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Pathological Biochemistry, Kyoto Pharmaceutical University, Yamashina-ku, Kyoto, Japan</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Novartis Institutes for BioMedical Research, Tsukuba, Japan</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>Ian</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Mayo Clinic, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>akiba@mb.kyoto-phu.ac.jp</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: HI SA. Performed the experiments: HI NY SY KT SH. Analyzed the data: HI SH TS SA. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HI NY KT SH. Wrote the paper: KI SA.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e8089</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Ii et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>Hepatic fat deposition with hepatocellular damage, a feature of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease, is mediated by several putative factors including prostaglandins. In the present study, we examined whether group IVA phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> (IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>), which catalyzes the first step in prostanoid biosynthesis, is involved in the development of fatty liver, using IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice. Male wild-type mice on high-fat diets (20&#x00025; fat and 1.25&#x00025; cholesterol) developed hepatocellular vacuolation and liver hypertrophy with an increase in the serum levels of liver damage marker aminotransferases when compared with wild-type mice fed normal diets. These high-fat diet-induced alterations were markedly decreased in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice. Hepatic triacylglycerol content was lower in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice than in wild-type mice under normal dietary conditions. Although high-fat diets increased hepatic triacylglycerol content in both genotypes, the degree was lower in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice than in wild-type mice. Under the high-fat dietary conditions, IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice had lower epididymal fat pad weight and smaller adipocytes than wild-type mice. The serum level of prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub>, which has a fat storage effect, was lower in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice than in wild-type mice, irrespective of the kind of diet. In both genotypes, high-fat diets increased serum leptin levels equally between the two groups, but did not affect the serum levels of adiponectin, resistin, free fatty acid, triacylglycerol, glucose, or insulin. Our findings suggest that a deficiency of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> alleviates fatty liver damage caused by high-fat diets, probably because of the lower generation of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> metabolites, such as prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub>. IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> could be a promising therapeutic target for obesity-related diseases including non-alcoholic fatty liver disease.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> (PLA<sub>2</sub>) is an enzyme that catalyzes the hydrolysis of glycerophospholipids at the <italic>sn</italic>-2 position, generating free fatty acid (FFA) and lysophospholipid. Among the more than twenty isozymes of mammalian PLA<sub>2</sub>, group IVA PLA<sub>2</sub> (IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>) is a key enzyme responsible for the release of arachidonic acid, a precursor of prostaglandins (PGs) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Schaloske1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>. Our recent study of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal chow diets demonstrated that decreases in hepatic triacylglycerol (TG) content and the size of epididymal adipocytes are observed with a lower serum level of PGE<sub>2</sub> compared with wild-type mice. This suggests that the circulating level of PGE<sub>2</sub> is related to the levels of intracellular TG in the liver and adipose tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Ii1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>. Previous reports showed that the stimulation of rat hepatocytes with PGE<sub>2</sub> and the administration of PGE<sub>2</sub> to rats induce increases in TG level in the cells and the liver, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Prez1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Enomoto1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. Similarly, 15-deoxy-PGJ<sub>2</sub> endogenously generated in mature 3T3-L1 adipocytes has been shown to be responsible for the storage of TG <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Mazid1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>. Considering these findings, it is possible that IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> mediates fat deposition in the liver and adipose tissues through the generation of PGs.</p><p>The accumulation of hepatic TG is a major symptom of alcoholic liver disease. However, hepatic fat deposition resulting from TG accumulation has also been found in the absence of alcohol abuse. Such fatty liver progresses to non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) followed by the development of non-alcoholic steatohepatitis and cirrhosis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Bradbury1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>. NAFLD is closely associated with abdominal obesity, a feature of metabolic syndrome <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Marchesini1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>. Obesity from overeating high-fat (HF) and/or high-caloric foods is characterized by an abnormal increase in adipose tissue mass mainly resulting from the excessive storage of TG within adipocytes. The state of obesity is accompanied by changes in the expression and secretion of adipokines including adiponectin and resistin, and by an increased release of FFA from hypertrophied adipocytes. The alterations in the circulating levels of adipokines and FFA are involved in the accumulation of TG causing liver damage <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Bradbury1">&#x0005b;6&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Adams1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>. Consequently, factors that modulate intracellular TG levels and/or circulating adipokine levels could be targets for the prevention of fatty liver and the development of NAFLD. Considering our recent finding that hepatic TG content is lower in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal chow diets than in wild-type mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Ii1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>, it is possible that a suppression of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> protects against the development of fatty liver under HF dietary conditions.</p><p>Taking this into account, in the present study, we examined the possible involvement of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> in the development of fatty liver using IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets. The current study demonstrated that a deficiency of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> protected mice against HF diet-induced increases in the number of hepatocytes exhibiting cytoplasmic vacuolation and hepatic TG content accompanying liver damage. These findings and further results shown here suggest that IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> is involved in the development of fatty liver damage under HF dietary conditions.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><p>Microscopic views of the liver of wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal or HF diets for 8 or 16 weeks are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figure 1</xref>. The results reveal an apparent cytoplasmic vacuolation of hepatocytes around the central vein in wild-type mice fed HF diets for 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) or 16 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figure 1B</xref>) weeks compared with wild-type mice fed normal diets for 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) or 16 weeks (data not shown). The degree of hepatic vacuolation increased with the period of feeding. In wild-type mice fed HF diets for 16 weeks, a markedly high level of cytoplasmic vacuolation of hepatocytes around the portal vein was observed compared with that in cells around the central vein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). The vacuolated area was not stained with periodic acid-Schiff, which stains glycogen (data not shown). In contrast to wild-type mice fed HF diets, we found that cytoplasmic vacuolation of hepatocytes around the central and portal veins was strikingly suppressed in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets for 8 weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). Even after 16 weeks of HF feeding, IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice exhibited considerably reduced hepatic vacuolation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). Under normal dietary conditions, slight cytoplasmic vacuolation was observed in hepatocytes of wild-type mice; however, this was not the case for IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). This observation in mice fed normal diets was consistent with the results shown in our recent paper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Ii1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0008089-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008089.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Microscopic views of the liver in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice.</title><p>Wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout (KO) mice were fed normal (N) or high-fat (HF) diets for 8 (A) or 16 (B) weeks and fasted. Representative liver sections stained with hematoxylin-eosin are shown. IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> deficiency suppressed the hepatic fat deposition under the HF feeding. CV, central vein; PV, portal vein. Original magnification, &#x000d7;4 and &#x000d7;20.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0008089.g001"/></fig><p>The histological results shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figure 1</xref> suggest that a deficiency of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> decreases HF diet-induced fat deposition in the liver, leading us to measure hepatic TG content under HF dietary conditions. Consistent with the histological results, hepatic TG content was apparently greater in wild-type mice fed HF diets for 8 weeks than in wild-type mice fed normal diets, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g002">Figure 2</xref>. In IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal diets, hepatic TG content was lower than that in wild-type mice, as reported in our recent paper <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Ii1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>. Although HF diets also increased hepatic TG content in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice, the level was significantly lower than that in HF diet-fed wild-type mice, and almost at the level found in normal diet-fed wild-type mice. The degree of the HF diet-induced increase in hepatic TG content was lower in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice than in wild-type mice.</p><fig id="pone-0008089-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008089.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Hepatic triacylglycerol content in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice.</title><p>Wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice were fed normal (N) or high-fat (HF) diets for 8 weeks and fasted. Triacylglycerol content in the liver was measured (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;5&#x02013;7). IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> deficiency suppressed the accumulation of hepatic triacylglycerol under the HF feeding. &#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.005 versus wild-type mice fed normal diets, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 versus wild-type mice fed normal diets, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01 versus wild-type mice fed HF diets.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0008089.g002"/></fig><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008089-t001">Table 1</xref>, the weights of the body, liver, and epidermal fat pads increased in wild-type mice fed HF diets for 8 or 16 weeks compared with respective wild-type mice fed normal diets. While no significant difference in these weights was observed between IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal and HF diets for 8 weeks, HF feeding for 16 weeks increased these weights. However, these weights in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets were lower than those in wild-type mice fed HF diets. Under the dietary conditions, there was no significant difference in the amounts of food intake between the two genotype mice fed HF diets for 16 weeks (wild-type, 2.77&#x000b1;0.18 g/day; IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout, 2.90&#x000b1;0.27 g/day, n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;5), or between those fed normal diets for 16 weeks (wild-type, 3.68&#x000b1;0.18 g/day; IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout, 3.89&#x000b1;0.10 g/day, n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;7). Consistent with the change in liver weights, macroscopic views of the liver revealed visible hypertrophy in wild-type mice fed HF diets for 16 weeks compared with wild-type mice fed normal diets, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g003">Figure 3</xref>. However, such hypertrophy was suppressed in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Furthermore, the epididymal fat pads were visibly smaller in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets than in wild-type mice (data not shown). Similarly, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g004">Figure 4</xref>, microscopic views of epididymal fat pads revealed that the adipocytes of epididymal fat pads were larger in wild-type mice fed HF diets for 8 weeks than in wild-type mice fed normal diets. Although HF diets also increased adipocyte size in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice, the adipocytes under the HF dietary conditions were smaller in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice than in wild-type mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Similar results were observed after 16 weeks of HF feeding (data not shown).</p><fig id="pone-0008089-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008089.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Macroscopic views of the liver in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice.</title><p>Wild-type (WT) and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout (KO) mice were fed normal (N) or high-fat (HF) diets for 16 weeks and fasted. Representative photographs of the liver in each mouse are shown. IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> deficiency suppressed the hepatic hypertrophy induced by HF feeding.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0008089.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone-0008089-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008089.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Microscopic views of epididymal fat pads in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice.</title><p>Wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout (KO) mice were fed normal or high-fat (HF) diets for 8 weeks and fasted. Representative epididymal fat pad sections stained with hematoxylin-eosin are shown. Original magnification, &#x000d7;4. IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> deficiency suppressed the expansion of epididymal adipocytes induced by HF feeding.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0008089.g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0008089-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008089.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Weights of the body, epidermal fat pads, and liver, and serum levels of biochemical parameters under high-fat dietary conditions.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0008089-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0008089.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body weight (g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver weight (g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fat pad weight (g)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FFA (mEq/l)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PL (mg/dl)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LPC (&#x000b5;M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (U/l)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST (U/l)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 weeks of feeding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT (N)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1&#x000b1;1.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235&#x000b1;24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">377&#x000b1;26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46&#x000b1;5.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156&#x000b1;24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT (HF)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.1&#x000b1;3.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7&#x000b1;0.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#x000b1;0.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226&#x000b1;35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">455&#x000b1;80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107&#x000b1;25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157&#x000b1;26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO (N)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3&#x000b1;1.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2&#x000b1;0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">288&#x000b1;7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">418&#x000b1;&#x000b1;39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36&#x000b1;4.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154&#x000b1;31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO (HF)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5&#x000b1;1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2&#x000b1;0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#x000b1;0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">275&#x000b1;21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">478&#x000b1;53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x000b1;4.9<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138&#x000b1;40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 weeks of feeding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT (N)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.9&#x000b1;2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178&#x000b1;22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">407&#x000b1;23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#x000b1;19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165&#x000b1;26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WT (HF)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.8&#x000b1;0.7<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6&#x000b1;0.4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0&#x000b1;0.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">361&#x000b1;35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">575&#x000b1;33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">350&#x000b1;77<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">366&#x000b1;71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO (N)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2&#x000b1;1.1<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">c</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4&#x000b1;0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">c</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8&#x000b1;0.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173&#x000b1;32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419&#x000b1;18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104&#x000b1;58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215&#x000b1;10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO (HF)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2&#x000b1;2.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9&#x000b1;0.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5&#x000b1;0.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#x000b1;0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188&#x000b1;8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411&#x000b1;14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87&#x000b1;21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134&#x000b1;21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Wild-type (WT) and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout (KO) mice fed normal (N) or high-fat (HF) diets for 8 or 16 weeks were fasted and subjected to each measurement (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;4&#x02013;6). FFA, free fatty acid; PL, phospholipids; LPC, lysophosphatidylcholine; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>a</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 versus wild-type mice fed normal diets.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>b</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 versus wild-type mice fed HF diets.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>c</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.005 versus wild-type mice fed normal diets.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Under the dietary conditions where HF diets taken for 8 weeks induced fat deposition in the liver and adipose tissues of wild-type mice but not IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g001">Figures 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g002">2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g004">4</xref>), no significant change in the serum levels of TG was observed as follows: wild-type mice fed normal diets, 60.8 mg/dl&#x000b1;3.6; wild-type mice fed HF diets, 72.0 mg/dl&#x000b1;3.5; IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal diets, 70.8 mg/dl&#x000b1;3.3; IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets, 75.0 mg/dl&#x000b1;15.5; n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;3&#x02013;5. Similar results were observed after 16 weeks of feeding (data not shown). Furthermore, there was no difference between the serum levels of FFA for the two genotypes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008089-t001">Table 1</xref>). HF diets taken for 8 weeks also did not affect the serum level of glucose (wild-type mice fed normal diets, 135 mg/dl&#x000b1;9; wild-type mice fed HF diets, 118 mg/dl&#x000b1;13; IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal diets, 122 mg/dl&#x000b1;15; IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets, 111 mg/dl&#x000b1;7; n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;4&#x02013;5). Under our experimental conditions, there were no differences in the serum levels of insulin after 8 weeks of HF feeding as follows: wild-type mice fed normal diets, 0.84 ng/ml&#x000b1;0.21; wild-type mice fed HF diets, 1.14 ng/ml&#x000b1;0.14; IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal diets, 1.22 ng/ml&#x000b1;0.10; IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets, 0.94 ng/ml&#x000b1;0.33; n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;4&#x02013;5. HF diets taken for 16 weeks also did not affect the serum level of insulin (data not shown). In contrast, while no significant change in the serum level of phospholipids or lysophosphatidylcholine was observed in the two genotype mice fed HF diets for 8 weeks, HF diets taken for 16 weeks increased these serum levels in wild-type mice but not IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008089-t001">Table 1</xref>). Consistent with this, the profiles of lipoproteins shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g005">Figure 5</xref> reveal that wild-type mice fed HF diets for 16 weeks had higher serum levels of low-density lipoprotein (LDL) and high-density lipoprotein (HDL) than wild-type mice fed normal diets, but a change in the serum level of very low-density lipoprotein (VLDL) was scarcely observed. In IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets, the serum level of LDL but not HDL was reduced compared with those in wild-type mice fed HF diets. Although TG content of these lipoproteins was concomitantly measured, there was no difference between the four groups (data not shown). Furthermore, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008089-t002">Table 2</xref>, we confirmed that the serum level of PGE<sub>2</sub> was significantly lower in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice than in wild-type mice under the dietary conditions.</p><fig id="pone-0008089-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008089.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Lipoprotein profiles under HF dietary conditions.</title><p>Wild-type (WT) and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout (KO) mice were fed normal or HF diets for 16 weeks and fasted. The serum levels of VLDL, LDL, and HDL were analyzed. Each trace represents the mean (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;4&#x02013;6). IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> deficiency reduced the increased serum level of LDL by HF feeding.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0008089.g005"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0008089-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008089.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Serum levels of PGE<sub>2</sub> in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0008089-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0008089.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PGE<sub>2</sub> (ng/ml)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild-type mice (N)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.29&#x000b1;1.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild-type mice (HF)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.32&#x000b1;1.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO mice (N)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52&#x000b1;0.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">a</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KO mice (HF)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88&#x000b1;0.41<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">b</xref></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>Wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout (KO) mice were fed normal (N) or high-fat (HF) diets for 16 weeks and fasted. The serum levels of PGE<sub>2</sub> were measured (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;3&#x02013;5).</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>a</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 versus wild-type mice fed normal diets.</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label>b</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 versus wild-type mice fed HF diets.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The elevation of serum aminotransferase level, as a marker of liver damage, is correlated with NAFLD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Clark1">&#x0005b;9&#x0005d;</xref>. In agreement with this, we show here that the serum level of alanine aminotransferase (ALT) was significantly higher in wild-type mice fed HF diets for 8 weeks than in wild-type mice fed normal diets, and the serum levels of both ALT and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) were markedly increased after 16 weeks of HF feeding (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0008089-t001">Table 1</xref>). However, no elevation of these aminotransferase levels was observed in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice even under HF dietary conditions. Considering the correlation of hepatic fat deposition with liver damage, it is likely that the protection against the HF diet-induced elevation of serum aminotransferase levels in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice is due to the reduced hepatic vacuolation and TG content.</p><p>It is conceivable that changes in the levels of adipokines including adiponectin, leptin, and resistin influence the accumulation of intracellular lipids in the liver <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Kadowaki1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Yu1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>. Taking this into account, we determined the serum levels of adipokines in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal or HF diets. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g006">Figure 6A</xref>, HF diets taken for 8 weeks did not affect the serum levels of adiponectin in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice. In contrast, HF diets increased the serum levels of leptin in both genotypes, with no difference exhibited between the levels in the two groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). Furthermore, no significant difference was observed in the serum levels of resistin among the four groups under our experimental conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0008089-g006">Figure 6C</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0008089-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0008089.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Serum levels of adipokines in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice.</title><p>Wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout (KO) mice were fed normal (N) or high-fat (HF) diets for 8 weeks and fasted. The serum levels of adiponectin (A), leptin (B), and resistin (C) were measured (n&#x0200a;&#x0003d;&#x0200a;4&#x02013;6). &#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 versus wild-type mice fed normal diets, &#x0002a;&#x0002a;<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 versus IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal diets. No significant differences in the serum levels of adipokines were detected between the two genotypes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0008089.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>Fatty liver with hepatocellular damage occurs in parallel with the accumulation of hepatic TG, which is associated with abdominal obesity. The present study showed that HF feeding of wild-type mice increased hepatocellular vacuolation, hepatic TG content, and serum aminotransferase levels with increases in adipose tissue mass and the number of hypertrophic adipocytes, indicating that HF diet-fed wild-type mice exhibited fatty liver damage with adipose fat deposition. The amounts of hepatic and adipose fats are regulated by several factors including FFA, insulin, adipokines, and PGs. Among these factors, PGs are generated by the cyclooxygenase pathway of the arachidonic acid cascade, the first step of which is mainly catalyzed by IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Schaloske1">&#x0005b;1&#x0005d;</xref>. Previous reports showed that PGE<sub>2</sub> and 15-deoxy-PGJ<sub>2</sub> accelerate the deposition of fats in hepatocytes and adipocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Prez1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Mazid1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Vassaux1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>. Furthermore, the administration of PGE<sub>2</sub> to rats increases hepatic TG content <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Enomoto1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. In addition to PGs, arachidonic acid metabolites of the 12-lipoxygenase pathway, such as 12-hydroxyeicosatetraenoic acid, are suggested to mediate inflammation occurring with fat deposition in adipose tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Nunemaker1">&#x0005b;13&#x0005d;</xref>. Considering the role of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> in the arachidonic acid cascade, it is possible that hepatic fat deposition could be ameliorated when the production of such arachidonic acid metabolites is suppressed by the inhibition of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>. Consistent with our expectations, the present study clearly showed that in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice with lower serum levels of PGE<sub>2</sub>, a lack of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> alleviated the HF diet-induced hepatic fat deposition with hepatocellular damage, and reduced adipose accumulation. Our findings suggest that an inhibition of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> prevents the HF diet-induced development of fatty liver damage. This notion is consistent with a recent observation that the administration of a cyclooxygenase-2 inhibitor to HF diet-fed rats prevents fat deposition in the liver and adipose tissues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Hsieh1">&#x0005b;14&#x0005d;</xref>.</p><p>The present study further shows that HF diet-fed wild-type mice exhibited fatty liver damage with higher serum levels of phospholipids, lysophosphatidylcholine, and LDL. However, in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice, a deficiency of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> reduced the HF diet-induced increase in these serum levels as well as fatty liver damage. These findings seem to indicate that the suppressed increase in LDL levels in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets probably results from suppressing the HF diet-induced development of fatty liver damage. In addition, the changes in the serum levels of phospholipids and lysophosphatidylcholine may be correlated with the serum levels of LDL.</p><p>Obesity with fat deposition in abdominal adipose tissues is implicated in the accumulation of hepatic TG through an increased influx of FFA into hepatocytes from hypertrophied adipocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Marchesini1">&#x0005b;7&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Adams1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, and/or through alterations of the secretion of adipokines including adiponectin and resistin that regulate, respectively, fat burning and fat storage in the liver <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Adams1">&#x0005b;8&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Kadowaki1">&#x0005b;10&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Yu1">&#x0005b;11&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Kusminski1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. However, under our experimental conditions, wild-type mice on HF diets exhibited no change in the serum levels of not only FFA, adiponectin, and resistin, but also TG, glucose, or insulin, despite hepatic and adipose fat deposition. Thus, HF diet-fed wild-type mice developed fatty liver and adipose accumulation in the absence of significant features of metabolic disorders. This suggests that the HF diet-induced hepatic fat deposition is mediated in part by the direct deposition of dietary fats, as in the case of adipose tissues, in wild-type mice. Our recent <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Ii1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref> and the present studies showed that hepatic TG content was lower in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice than in wild-type mice under normal dietary conditions, suggesting a physiological role of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> in the regulation of TG accumulation in the liver. Furthermore, HF diet-induced increase in hepatic TG content was partially suppressed in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice compared with wild-type mice, the reduced level being almost at the level observed in wild-type mice fed normal diets. It is, consequently, possible that since IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> is physiologically involved in the regulation of TG content in the liver, a lack of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> somewhat prevents hepatic TG deposition even caused by excess dietary fat intake, thereby resulting in the alleviation of large hepatic vacuolation. It has been suggested that PGE<sub>2</sub> plays a role in hepatocellular TG accumulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Prez1">&#x0005b;3&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Enomoto1">&#x0005b;4&#x0005d;</xref>. In IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice, serum PGE<sub>2</sub> levels were indeed reduced. However, other IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> metabolites, such as other eicosanoids and lysophospholipids, are also probably reduced in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice. Therefore, IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> metabolites responsible for the accumulation of hepatic TG are unclear at present. Meanwhile, a recent study showed that an HF diet-induced increase in the mass of visceral adipose tissues precedes the development of fatty liver accompanied with no significant change in the serum levels of FFA, TG, or adiponectin in moderately obese mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Akagiri1">&#x0005b;16&#x0005d;</xref>. Furthermore, fatty liver has been shown to occur through adipose accumulation with adipocyte hypertrophy and slightly decreased serum adiponectin levels, but without impaired glucose tolerance or any change in the serum levels of FFA, TG, glucose, insulin, or leptin in mice with an adipose-specific STAT3 (signal transducer and activator of transcription 3) disruption resulting in leptin resistance in adipocytes, even under normal dietary conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Cernkovich1">&#x0005b;17&#x0005d;</xref>. This observation suggests that adipose accumulation and/or lower circulating adiponectin levels can cause the development of fatty liver in the absence of high dietary fats and metabolic disorders. Taking these findings and the notion mentioned above into account, the present results also suggest that the protection against the development of fatty liver damage in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets may be ascribable, in part, to the tendency towards a decreased adipose tissue mass with smaller adipocytes. However, to clarify the precise roles of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> in the liver and adipose tissues, further studies with liver- or adipose-specific IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice are needed.</p><p>Regarding the role of PGs in an increase in adipose tissue mass, PGE<sub>2</sub> accelerates the deposition of intracellular TG by suppressing the production of cAMP that induces lipolysis through the activation of hormone-sensitive lipase in human and rat adipocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Vassaux1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>. Furthermore, 15-deoxy-PGJ<sub>2</sub> endogenously generated in mature 3T3-L1 adipocytes participates in the accumulation of TG probably through the activation of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-&#x003b3; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Mazid1">&#x0005b;5&#x0005d;</xref>. These findings suggest roles for PGE<sub>2</sub> and 15-deoxy-PGJ<sub>2</sub> in the hypertrophy of mature adipocytes. In addition, PGI<sub>2</sub> and 15-deoxy-PGJ<sub>2</sub> play roles in the differentiation of preadipocytes into mature adipocytes resulting in adipocyte hyperplasia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Vassaux1">&#x0005b;12&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Kliewer1">&#x0005b;18&#x0005d;</xref>. In contrast, PGF<sub>2&#x003b1;</sub> inhibits preadipocyte differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Reginato1">&#x0005b;19&#x0005d;</xref>. Thus, PGs exhibit various effects on adipogenesis <italic>in vitro</italic>. A previous study demonstrated that the differentiation of 3T3-L1 preadipocytes is inhibited by the knockdown of group VIA PLA<sub>2</sub> or group VIB PLA<sub>2</sub>, other isozymes of intracellular PLA<sub>2</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Su1">&#x0005b;20&#x0005d;</xref>, suggesting the contribution of the isozymes to the generation of PGs responsible for preadipocyte differentiation. Recently, we reported that adipose tissue mass and adipocyte size are reduced in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed normal diets compared with wild-type mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Ii1">&#x0005b;2&#x0005d;</xref>, with similar results being observed in the present study. Furthermore, we show here that under the HF dietary conditions, IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice with lower serum levels of PGE<sub>2</sub> had lower adipose tissue mass and smaller adipocytes than wild-type mice, suggesting that the lower adipose tissue mass in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice fed HF diets probably results from the smaller adipocytes. Collectively, IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> may also be involved in adipose accumulation through the generation of PGs responsible for adipocyte hypertrophy.</p><p>The development of NAFLD is associated with the lower circulating levels of adiponectin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Hui1">&#x0005b;21&#x0005d;</xref>, hepatic fat deposition being presumably due, in part, to the decreased fat burning effects of adiponectin in the liver. Consistent with this notion, a previous study showed that the administration of adiponectin to obese <italic>ob/ob</italic> mice, resulting in its higher concentration in serum, has beneficial effects on fatty liver <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Xu1">&#x0005b;22&#x0005d;</xref>. This suggests that adiponectin itself or factors that regulate the production of adiponectin can be potent therapeutic molecular targets for the prevention of fatty liver. As inhibitory regulators of adiponectin production, PGD<sub>2</sub>, PGJ<sub>2</sub>, and 15-deoxy-PGJ<sub>2</sub> are shown to suppress the expression of adiponectin in 3T3-L1 adipocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Peeraully1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>. In contrast, the serum levels of adiponectin decrease in lipocalin-type PGD synthase-knockout mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Ragolia1">&#x0005b;24&#x0005d;</xref>, suggesting a contribution of PGD<sub>2</sub> to the production of adiponectin. Among the inhibitory and stimulatory effects of PGs, the former may be involved in the decrease in adiponectin level observed in obesity and NAFLD. In the present study, however, there was no difference between serum adiponectin levels in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice, irrespective of the kind of diet, although the deficient mice were resistant to the HF diet-induced development of fatty liver damage. At present, the reasons for the lack of change in serum adiponectin levels in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice are unclear. Other PLA<sub>2</sub> isozymes might be involved in the generation of PGs responsible for regulating the expression of adiponectin. Alternatively, a deficiency of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> might result in decreases in the levels of both inhibitory and stimulatory PGs on the production of adiponectin. Meanwhile, the serum levels of leptin correlate positively with adipose accumulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Friedman1">&#x0005b;25&#x0005d;</xref>. Consistent with this, we show here that HF diets increased the serum levels of leptin with adipose accumulation in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice. However, a deficiency of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> did not affect the HF diet-induced increase in serum leptin levels. Considering the beneficial effects of leptin on fatty liver <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Huang1">&#x0005b;26&#x0005d;</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Fishman1">&#x0005b;27&#x0005d;</xref>, the changes in serum leptin levels under the HF dietary conditions probably do not explain the reduced fatty liver damage in IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice. Previous studies showed that the expression of leptin is inhibited by PGD<sub>2</sub>, PGJ<sub>2</sub>, and 15-deoxy-PGJ<sub>2</sub> in 3T3-L1 adipocytes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Peeraully1">&#x0005b;23&#x0005d;</xref>, but stimulated by PGE<sub>2</sub> in mouse adipose tissues in primary culture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Fain1">&#x0005b;28&#x0005d;</xref>. As in the case of adiponectin mentioned above, the possible involvement of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> in the generation of PGs that regulate the production of leptin is unclear at present. To further clarify the role of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> in the expression of adiponectin and leptin in adipocytes and colocalized inflammatory cells, experiments with preadipocytes and macrophages derived from IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice are underway in our laboratory.</p><p>Resistin has been implicated in the pathogenesis of obesity-mediated insulin resistance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Kusminski1">&#x0005b;15&#x0005d;</xref>. Increased serum levels of resistin are related to the histological severity of NAFLD in human subjects <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Pagano1">&#x0005b;29&#x0005d;</xref>. A previous study demonstrated that hepatic TG content tended to be lower in resistin-deficient mice <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Banerjee1">&#x0005b;30&#x0005d;</xref>. These findings suggest that higher serum levels of resistin are a cause of the development of fatty liver. In the present study, no significant difference was observed in the serum levels of resistin in wild-type and IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice. This observation is consistent with the lack of changes in the serum levels of insulin and glucose in both genotypes under the HF dietary conditions. Under our experimental conditions, fatty liver damage in wild-type mice probably develops in the absence of insulin resistance.</p><p>In summary, the present study demonstrates that a deficiency of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> protected mice against the HF diet-induced development of fatty liver damage with adipose accumulation. The alleviation of fatty liver damage is probably associated with the decreased generation of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> metabolites including PGs. To our knowledge, this is the first report to suggest the possible involvement of IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub> in hepatic fat deposition progressing to NAFLD under HF dietary conditions.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Mice</title><p>Homozygous IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice with a C57BL/6 background (more than N19 generations) were generated by the cross breeding of heterozygous IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice, which were a generous gift from Dr. T. Shimizu and Dr. N. Uozumi (Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, the University of Tokyo) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Uozumi1">&#x0005b;31&#x0005d;</xref>. Male IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout and wild-type mice (6 weeks of age) were kept under a 12 h light/dark cycle, and given normal (5.3&#x00025; fat) or HF (D12108: 20&#x00025; fat and 1.25&#x00025; cholesterol, Research Diets Inc.) diets for 8 or 16 weeks. For measurement of food consumption, mice were housed individually in cages with wire-screen floors and no bedding. Preweighed food was placed in food cups attached to the cage floor with spring clips. Food intake was then measured daily for 3 days before the end of HF feeding period by weighting the food with careful monitoring of any spillage. This study was approved by the Experimental Animal Research Committee at Kyoto Pharmaceutical University.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Histological Analysis</title><p>The animals were fasted for 20 h, and body weights were measured before the collection of the blood and tissues. Mice were deeply anesthetized with pentobarbital (0.3 mg/g body weight, intraperitoneal administration). After the blood was collected from the inferior vena cava, mice were perfused transcardially with saline using a peristaltic pump. The liver and epidermal fat pads were isolated and weighed. The isolated tissues were fixed in 10&#x00025; buffered formaldehyde and embedded in a paraffin block for microtome slicing into 4-&#x000b5;m thick sections. The tissue sections were deparaffinized and stained with hematoxylin-eosin or periodic acid-Schiff. The stained sections were photographed using a microscope (model IX71, Olympus, Tokyo, Japan) with a digital camera.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Measurement of Biochemical Parameters and Analysis of Lipoproteins in Serum</title><p>Collected blood samples from the inferior vena cava were placed for 30 min at room temperature, and the supernatants were obtained as serum after centrifugation. The serum levels of TG, glucose, ALT, and AST were measured with an automatic analyzer (DRI-CHEM 7000, Fujifilm Medical, Tokyo, Japan). The serum levels of FFA, phospholipids, lysophosphatidylcholine, insulin, adiponectin, leptin, and resistin were quantified with commercial assay kits (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Osaka, Japan; Sceti Medical Labo K.K., Tokyo, Japan; R&#x00026;D Systems, Inc., Minneapolis, MN). For the determination of the serum levels of PGE<sub>2</sub>, the serum from mice were collected and treated with indomethacin (10 &#x000b5;g/ml). PGE<sub>2</sub> was extracted from the samples by solid phase extraction on a C18 cartridge. The concentrations of PGE<sub>2</sub> were analyzed with a commercial ELISA kit (R&#x00026;D Systems, Inc.) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Lipoproteins in the serum were analyzed with a liquid chromatography system equipped with a reactor for a postcolumn reaction to automatically measure the total amounts of cholesterol of separated lipoproteins.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Measurement of Hepatic TG</title><p>The liver (100 mg wet tissue) was homogenized in an ice-cold 0.05&#x00025; butylhydroxytoluene solution. After lipids were extracted from the liver according to the method of Folch <italic>et al</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0008089-Folch1">&#x0005b;32&#x0005d;</xref> with a slight modification, TG content in each sample was measured with a commercial assay kit (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Osaka, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Values are expressed as the mean &#x000b1; SEM. Data were analyzed with Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr. T. Shimizu and Dr. N. Uozumi (Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, the University of Tokyo) for kindly providing breeding groups of heterozygous IVA-PLA<sub>2</sub>-knockout mice.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0008089-Schaloske1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaloske</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> superfamily and its group numbering system.</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>1761</volume><fpage>1246</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16973413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Ii1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Group IVA phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> is associated with the storage of lipids in adipose tissue and liver.</article-title><source>Prostaglandins Other Lipid Mediat</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18282778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Prez1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aspichueta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochoa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chico</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The 2-series prostaglandins suppress VLDL secretion in an inflammatory condition-dependent manner in primary rat hepatocytes.</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><volume>176</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>171</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Enomoto1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enomoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikejima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Enomoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishiura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Kupffer cell-derived prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub> is involved in alcohol-induced fat accumulation in rat liver.</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>G100</fpage><lpage>G106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10898751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Mazid1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazid</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jisaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Endogenous 15-deoxy-&#x00394;<sup>12,14</sup>-prostaglandin J<sub>2</sub> synthesized by adipocytes during maturation phase contributes to upregulation of fat storage.</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>580</volume><fpage>6885</fpage><lpage>6890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17150216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Bradbury1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Lipid metabolism and liver inflammation. I. Hepatic fatty acid uptake: possible role in steatosis.</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source><volume>290</volume><fpage>G194</fpage><lpage>G198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Marchesini1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marchesini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bugianesi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Forlani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerrelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Nonalcoholic fatty liver, steatohepatitis, and the metabolic syndrome.</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>917</fpage><lpage>923</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12668987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Adams1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Angulo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindor</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease.</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><volume>172</volume><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15795412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Clark1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brancati</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>The prevalence and etiology of elevated aminotransferase levels in the United States.</article-title><source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><volume>98</volume><fpage>960</fpage><lpage>967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12809815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Kadowaki1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadowaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Adiponectin and adiponectin receptors in insulin resistance, diabetes, and the metabolic syndrome.</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>116</volume><fpage>1784</fpage><lpage>1792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16823476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Yu1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Adipocyte signaling and lipid homeostasis: sequelae of insulin-resistant adipose tissue.</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>1042</fpage><lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15920027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Vassaux1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vassaux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaillard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Darimont</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ailhaud</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Negrel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Differential response of preadipocytes and adipocytes to prostacyclin and prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub>: physiological implications.</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>131</volume><fpage>2393</fpage><lpage>2398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1330499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Nunemaker1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunemaker</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimble</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>12-Lipoxygenase-knockout mice are resistant to inflammatory effects of obesity induced by Western diet.</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab</source><volume>295</volume><fpage>E1065</fpage><lpage>E1075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18780776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Hsieh1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>COX-2-mediated inflammation in fat is crucial for obesity-linked insulin resistance and fatty liver.</article-title><source>Obesity</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>1150</fpage><lpage>1157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19247274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Kusminski1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kusminski</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>McTernan</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Role of resistin in obesity, insulin resistance and Type II diabetes.</article-title><source>Clin Sci</source><volume>109</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16104844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Akagiri1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akagiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>A mouse model of metabolic syndrome; Increase in visceral adipose tissue precedes the development of fatty liver and insulin resistance in high-fat diet-fed male KK/Ta mice.</article-title><source>J Clin Biochem Nutr</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18385833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Cernkovich1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cernkovich</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Combs</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harp</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Adipose-specific disruption of signal transducer and activator of transcription 3 increases body weight and adiposity.</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>149</volume><fpage>1581</fpage><lpage>1590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18096662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Kliewer1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kliewer</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenhard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Willson</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>A prostaglandin J<sub>2</sub> metabolite binds peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor &#x003b3; and promotes adipocyte differentiation.</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8521498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Reginato1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reginato</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Krakow</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Prostaglandins promote and block adipogenesis through opposing effects on peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor &#x003b3;.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>273</volume><fpage>1855</fpage><lpage>1858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Su1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancuso</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bickel</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Small interfering RNA knockdown of calcium-independent phospholipases A<sub>2</sub> &#x000ae; or &#x000a9; inhibits the hormone-induced differentiation of 3T3-L1 preadipocytes.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>279</volume><fpage>21740</fpage><lpage>21748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15024020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Hui1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kench</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriketos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Beyond insulin resistance in NASH: TNF-&#x003b1; or adiponectin?</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15239085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Xu1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Keshaw</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>The fat-derived hormone adiponectin alleviates alcoholic and nonalcoholic fatty liver diseases in mice.</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12840063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Peeraully1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peeraully</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sievert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Trayhurn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Prostaglandin D<sub>2</sub> and J<sub>2</sub>-series (PGJ<sub>2</sub>, &#x00394;<sup>12</sup>-PGJ<sub>2</sub>) prostaglandins stimulate IL-6 and MCP-1, but inhibit leptin, expression and secretion by 3T3-L1 adipocytes.</article-title><source>Pflugers Arch</source><volume>453</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16924534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Ragolia1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ragolia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaia</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Maesaka</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Accelerated glucose intolerance, nephropathy, and atherosclerosis in prostaglandin D<sub>2</sub> synthase knock-out mice.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>280</volume><fpage>29946</fpage><lpage>29955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15970590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Friedman1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Halaas</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Leptin and the regulation of body weight in mammals.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>395</volume><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9796811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Huang1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dedousis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopaschuk</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Doherty</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Liver triglyceride secretion and lipid oxidative metabolism are rapidly altered by leptin <italic>in vivo</italic>.</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>147</volume><fpage>1480</fpage><lpage>1487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16339207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Fishman1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzumdar</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Atzmon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Resistance to leptin action is the major determinant of hepatic triglyceride accumulation <italic>in vivo</italic>.</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17099068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Fain1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fain</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Leffler</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahouth</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Eicosanoids as endogenous regulators of leptin release and lipolysis by mouse adipose tissue in primary culture.</article-title><source>J Lipid Res</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>1689</fpage><lpage>1694</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11013312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Pagano1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Soardo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Milocco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Basan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Increased serum resistin in nonalcoholic fatty liver disease is related to liver disease severity and not to insulin resistance.</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>1081</fpage><lpage>1086</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16394091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Banerjee1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangwala</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhoades</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Regulation of fasted blood glucose by resistin.</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>303</volume><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14976316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Uozumi1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uozumi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kume</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagase</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Role of cytosolic phospholipase A<sub>2</sub> in allergic response and parturition.</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>390</volume><fpage>618</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9403692</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0008089-Folch1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Folch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloane-Stanley</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1957</year><article-title>A simple method for the isolation and purification of total lipides from animal tissues.</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>226</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13428781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work was supported by a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research from, and by the Open Research Program of, the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan, and by Takeda Research Foundation (Japan). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>