<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkp762</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkp762</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Nucleic Acid Enzymes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evolutionarily conserved proteins MnmE and GidA catalyze the formation of two methyluridine derivatives at tRNA wobble positions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moukadiri</surname><given-names>Isma&#x000ef;l</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>Silvia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Piera</surname><given-names>Julio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vel&#x000e1;zquez-Campoy</surname><given-names>Adri&#x000e1;n</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rk</surname><given-names>Glenn R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Armengod</surname><given-names>M.-Eugenia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>Laboratorio de Gen&#x000e9;tica Molecular, <sup>2</sup>Laboratorio de Mol&#x000e9;culas Org&#x000e1;nicas, Centro de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Pr&#x000ed;ncipe Felipe, 46012-Valencia, <sup>3</sup>Fundaci&#x000f3;n Arag&#x000f3;n I + D and Institute of Biocomputation and Physics of Complex Systems (BIFI), Universidad de Zaragoza, 50009-Zaragoza, Spain and <sup>4</sup>Department of Molecular Biology, Ume&#x000e5; University, S90187, Sweden</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: <phone>+34 96 328 9680</phone>; Fax: <fax>+34 96 328 9701</fax>; Email: <email>armengod@cipf.es</email></corresp></author-notes><!--For NAR both ppub and collection dates generated for PMC processing 1/27/05 beck--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><month>11</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>37</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>7177</fpage><lpage>7193</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>8</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2009. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The wobble uridine of certain bacterial and mitochondrial tRNAs is modified, at position 5, through an unknown reaction pathway that utilizes the evolutionarily conserved MnmE and GidA proteins. The resulting modification (a methyluridine derivative) plays a critical role in decoding NNG/A codons and reading frame maintenance during mRNA translation. The lack of this tRNA modification produces a pleiotropic phenotype in bacteria and has been associated with mitochondrial encephalomyopathies in humans. In this work, we use <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> approaches to characterize the enzymatic pathway controlled by the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex. Surprisingly, this complex catalyzes two different GTP- and FAD-dependent reactions, which produce 5-aminomethyluridine and 5-carboxymethylamino-methyluridine using ammonium and glycine, respectively, as substrates. In both reactions, methylene-tetrahydrofolate is the most probable source to form the C5-methylene moiety, whereas NADH is dispensable <italic>in vitro</italic> unless FAD levels are limiting. Our results allow us to reformulate the bacterial MnmE&#x02022;GidA dependent pathway and propose a novel mechanism for the modification reactions performed by the MnmE and GidA family proteins.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Transfer RNAs (tRNAs) are by far the most heavily and diversely modified of all cellular RNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). Modifications are introduced posttranscriptionally by specific enzymes and are critical for the fine-tuning of tRNA functions. Many of these modifications frequently appear in the anticodon wobble position (position 34) and are pivotal in the mRNA decoding process by stabilizing correct codon&#x02013;anticodon interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>). Modifications at wobble uridines are classified into two groups according to their chemical structures and decoding properties: 5-hydroxyuridine derivatives (xo<sup>5</sup>U) with an oxygen atom directly bonded to the C5 atom of the uracil base, and 5-methyluridine derivatives (xm<sup>5</sup>U) with a methylene carbon directly bonded to the C5 atom. The last ones are mostly found in tRNAs that decode two-family box triplets ending in A or G, and include 2-thiouridine derivatives (xm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U) and 2&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-methyluridine derivatives (xm<sup>5</sup>Um). Modified nucleosides of the xm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U type restrict the wobble capacity of uridine because the thiolation at position 2 of U34 stabilize the C3&#x02032;-endo puckering conformation of the ribose, which facilitates the base paring with purines (A or G) and prevents misreading of codons ending in U or C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). The xm<sup>5</sup> modification seems to be critical for decoding NNG/A codons by stabilizing U&#x02022;G pairing at the wobble position as well as improving reading of the NNA codons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3 B4 B5 B6 B7 B8 B9">3&#x02013;9</xref>). The lack of these modifications produces translational frameshifting and a pleiotropic phenotype in bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>), whereas it has been associated with mitochondrial encephalomyopathies in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>) and mitochondrial dysfunction in a human cell line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). Interestingly, some proteins involved in the biosynthesis of the xm<sup>5</sup>(s<sup>2</sup>)U type nucleosides are evolutionarily conserved from bacteria to humans, so that the use of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> to ascertain the biochemical and functional roles of such proteins may guide the study of their eukaryotic counterparts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>).</p><p>In <italic>E. coli</italic>, proteins MnmE and GidA form an &#x003b1;2&#x003b2;2 heterotetrameric complex that controls the formation of 5-carboxymethylaminomethyluridine (cmnm<sup>5</sup>U) in the wobble position of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i1.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i2.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i3.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i4.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i5.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i6.jpg"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12 B13 B14">12&#x02013;14</xref>). In certain tRNAs (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i7.jpg"/></inline-formula>,<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i8.jpg"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i9.jpg"/></inline-formula>), the cmnm<sup>5</sup> group may be demodified to 5-aminomethyl (nm<sup>5</sup>) and subsequently methylated in an <italic>S</italic>-adenosyl-<sc>l</sc>-methionine (AdoMet) dependent step to produce methylaminomethyl (mnm<sup>5</sup>). Both reactions are carried out by the same enzyme called MnmC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). Protein MnmA, together with the cysteine desulfurase IscS and sulfur transfer mediators TusA-E, is required for the thiolation at position 2 of the uridine that occurs in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i10.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i11.jpg"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gkp762i12.jpg"/></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Modifications at the 2- and 5-positions occur independently of each other. Meanwhile, the function of MnmA and MnmC in tRNA modification is rather well understood, the precise role of proteins MnmE and GidA remains unknown and it is unclear how many steps precede the formation of the cmnm<sup>5</sup> group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). <fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Model prior to the present study for the U34 modification pathway in tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> and tRNA<sup>Glu</sup>. The first stage in the modification of U34 at position 5 is mediated by the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>), which catalyzes the production of a still unknown intermediate group (X) using GTP, FAD and a THF derivative. Glycine is subsequently incorporated by an unidentified transferase to build cmnm<sup>5</sup>U. Finally, cmnm<sup>5</sup>U is first demodified to nm<sup>5</sup>U and subsequently methylated in an AdoMet-dependent step to mnm<sup>5</sup>U by the bifunctional enzyme MnmC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>). U34 may undergo thiolation at position 2 (s<sup>2</sup>) mediated by MnmA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>). Modifications in the 2- and 5-positions occur independently of each other. Therefore, 2-thiouridine derivatives are present in tRNA obtained from <italic>mnmE</italic>, <italic>gidA</italic> and <italic>mnmC</italic> mutants. In this work, tRNA was completely digested to nucleosides by nuclease P1 and alkaline phosphatase before HPLC analysis. This allowed us to follow accumulation of nucleosides s<sup>2</sup>U, nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in modification assays where <italic>in vivo</italic> synthesized tRNA was used as substrate. Alternatively, tRNA was digested with nuclease P1, but not alkaline phosphatase, before TLC analysis, producing 5&#x02032;-monophosphate nucleosides. C2, C3 and C4 are the designations given to 5&#x02032;-monophosphate nucleosides identified in our TLC experiments (pnm<sup>5</sup>U, pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U and pmnm<sup>5</sup>U), where <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed tRNA was mostly used as substrate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkp762f1"/></fig></p><p>Results obtained <italic>in vivo</italic> have shown that both the MnmE GTPase activity as well as the GidA FAD-binding activity is necessary for tRNA modification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19 B20 B21">19&#x02013;21</xref>). Biochemical and structural studies indicated that MnmE binds 5&#x02032;-formyl-tetrahydrofolate, which was proposed to be the one-carbon group donor in the modification reaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). Data obtained from mutants where different steps of the tetrahydrofolate (THF) pathway were interrupted indicated that the C5-methylene moiety of mnm<sup>5</sup>U or cmnm<sup>5</sup>U is derived from this pathway, although apparently not from 5-formyl-THF or methyl-THF (T. Suzuki and T. Suzuki, 22nd tRNA workshop, Sweden, 2007). Therefore, the one-carbon group donor remains uncertain. In contrast, glycine was reported to be directly incorporated into the cmnm-group of cmnm<sup>5</sup>U <italic>in vivo</italic> (T. Suzuki and T. Suzuki, 22nd tRNA workshop, Sweden, 2007). Curiously, taurine (&#x003c4;) is incorporated into human mitochondrial tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> and tRNA<sup>Leu(UUR)</sup> in place of cmnm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). This led to the hypothesis that proteins of the MnmE and GidA families jointly catalyze the formation of an unknown intermediate in the modification pathway of the wobble uridine, whereas the subsequent activity of a taurine or glycine transferase would be responsible for construction of the &#x003c4;m<sup>5</sup> group in humans, or the cmnm<sup>5</sup> group in yeast and bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). However, there is no evidence for this independent, second step. For example, no bacterial or yeast mutants have been isolated where the putative intermediate produced by the MnmE and GidA proteins accumulates. Therefore, the possibility that the complex formed by these proteins drives all the reaction steps in the cmnm<sup>5</sup>/&#x003c4;m<sup>5</sup>-side chain synthesis cannot be ruled out.</p><p>In this work, we use both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> approaches to characterize the MnmE&#x02022;GidA-dependent pathway. Our results indicate that the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex catalyzes two different tRNA modification reactions by which the nm and cmnm groups are incorporated into position 5 of the wobble uridine, without participation of any more proteins.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Bacterial strains, plasmids, growth conditions and protein techniques</title><p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains and plasmids used in this study are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>. Deletion of the <italic>mnmC</italic> and <italic>folE</italic> genes was performed by targeted homologous recombination as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>) using primers shown in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>. Deletion of the target gene was confirmed by PCR. The N-terminal FLAG-tagged <italic>mnmC</italic> gene was amplified by PCR from genomic DNA of MC1000 <italic>E. coli</italic> strain using the specific primers FLAG-MnmC(F) (<underline>GACTATAAAGACGACGACGACAAA</underline>AAACACTACTCCATACAACC, FLAG sequence underlined) and FLAG-MnmC(R) (TTACCCCGCCTTAACCGCTTTACCCTTCAAC), and cloned into pBAD TOPO TA under the P<sub>araC</sub> promoter, producing pIC1253. LBT (Luria&#x02013;Bertani broth containing 40 mg/ml thymine) and LAT (LBT containing 20 g of Difco agar per litre) were used for routine cultures and plating of <italic>E. coli</italic>. When required, antibiotics were added at the following concentrations: 100 &#x000b5;g/ml of ampicillin, 12.5 &#x000b5;g/ml of tetracycline, and 25 &#x000b5;g/ml of kanamycin. Cell growth was monitored by measuring the optical density (OD) of the cultures at 600 nm. Recombinant proteins were purified according to standard procedures. Unless otherwise specified, protein MnmE and FLAG-GidA was purified from a <italic>gidA::</italic>Tn<italic>10</italic> mutant (strain IC5923) and <italic>mnmE::kan</italic> mutant (strain IC5924), respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>MnmE&#x02022;GidA heterotetramer formation</title><p>To obtain the MnmE&#x02022;GidA heterotetramer, 10 &#x000b5;M final concentration of the MnmE and FLAG-GidA proteins were mixed in 40 &#x000b5;l of the following buffer: 50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl (pH 7.5), 50 mM KCl, 10 mM magnesium acetate, 5 mM DTT, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 3% glycerol. The mix was incubated at room temperature (20&#x02013;22&#x000b0;C) for &#x0223c;2 h.</p></sec><sec><title>Isothermal titration calorimetry assay</title><p>Binding affinity of THF derivatives to MnmE was determined by isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) in a MicroCal VP-ITC isothermal titration calorimeter (MicroCal, Northampton, MA, USA). Calorimetric experiments consisted of the titration of a 20&#x02013;30 &#x000b5;M MnmE solution with a 300&#x02013;450 &#x000b5;M solution of the THF derivative at 25&#x000b0;C in 50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl pH 7.5, 100 mM KCl, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 2 mM &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol. To obtain the <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub>, the data were fitted using software developed at the BIFI and implemented in Origin 7.0 (OriginLab).</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription of <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA<sup>Lys</sup></title><p>Unmodified <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> was prepared by <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription of BstNI-digested plasmid (pUC19-tRNA<sup>Lys</sup>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>) using the Riboprobe T7-transcription kit (PROMEGA). Each reaction was performed in a final volume of 50 &#x000b5;l containing 40 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl buffer, pH 7.9, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2 mM spermidine, 10 mM NaCl, 10 mM DTT, 50 U of recombinant RNasin ribonuclease inhibitor, 2.5 mM each ribonucleotide (or 2.5 mM each rATP, rGTP and rCTP, 0.1 mM rUTP and 125 &#x000b5;Ci [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]-rUTP [20 &#x000b5;Ci/&#x000b5;l, 800 mCi/mmol], when radiolabeled tRNA was required), 2 &#x000b5;g of BstNI-digested plasmid, 50 U of T7-RNA polymerase and RNase-free water. The mix was incubated under mild agitation for 3 h at 37&#x000b0;C. At the end of the incubation period, DNA template was digested by addition of a few units of RNase-free DNase Q1 followed by an extra incubation at 37&#x000b0;C for 5 min. Finally, 100 &#x000b5;l of 0.3 M sodium acetate were added to the tube, and the radiolabeled tRNA was extracted with an equal volume (150 &#x000b5;l) of water-saturated phenol&#x02013;chloroform&#x02013;isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1), ethanol-precipitated and dried. The transcribed tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> was resuspended in RNase-free water and the removal of unincorporated nucleotides was performed using Micro Bio-Spin 6 Chromatography Columns (Sephadex G25 column, BioRad).</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of bulk tRNA from <italic>E. coli</italic></title><p>Bacterial strains were grown in LBT broth at 37&#x000b0;C to about 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>8</sup> cells/ml. The cells were lysed, and total RNA was prepared (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>), dissolved in R200 buffer (100 mM Tris&#x02013;H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, pH 6.3, 15% ethanol, 200 mM KCl), and applied to a Nucleobond column (AX500) equilibrated with the same buffer. The column was washed with 6 ml of R200 and 2 ml of R650 buffer (same as R200 buffer except that the KCl concentration was 650 mM). tRNA was eluted with 7 ml of buffer R650 and precipitated with 0.7 volume of cold isopropanol, washed twice with 70% ethanol, dried, dissolved in water and quantified in a NanoDrop spectrophotometer. Note that LB broth is deficient in selenium; therefore, MnmE/GidA-specific tRNAs isolated from strains grown in this medium mostly carry sulphur at position 2.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA enzymatic activity</title><p>To perform the modification <italic>in vitro</italic> of labelled tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> by the <italic>E. coli</italic> MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex, the following mix was made, unless otherwise specified, in 100 &#x000b5;l final volume: 30 000 c.p.m. (counts per minute) of radioactive tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> in Buffer A (100 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl pH 8, 100 mM Ammonium acetate, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5% Glycerol, 5 mM DTT, 0.5 mM FAD, 0.5 mM NADH, 0.5 mM NADPH, 2 mM GTP, 1 mM methylene-THF and 10 &#x000b5;g BSA). Glycine, alanine and serine were used at 2 mM. All cofactor solutions were freshly prepared just before use and protected from light. The enzymatic reaction was started by addition of the purified enzymes (2 &#x000b5;M final concentration, unless otherwise specified). A blank without enzymes was always included in each series of experiments. The reaction mixture was incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 40 min with mild agitation. Then, the radiolabeled tRNA was phenol extracted, ethanol precipitated and digested with nuclease P1. The resulting nucleotides (1 &#x000b5;l portions) were analyzed by bidimensional thin layer chromatography (2D-TLC) on cellulose plates using isobutyric acid/concentrated ammonia/water (66:1:33 [v:v:v]) as the first dimension solvent (solvent A, 4 h), and 100 mM sodium phosphate buffer, pH 6.8/(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>/n-propanol (100/60/2, v/w/v) (solvent B, 4 h) or isopropanol/concentrated HCl/water (68/18/14, v/v/v) (solvent C, 6 h 30 min) as the second dimension solvent.</p><p>To perform the modification <italic>in vitro</italic> of total tRNA by MnmE&#x02022;GidA, we used the same procedure as above with the following modifications: the reaction mix was prepared in 200 &#x000b5;l of final volume and contained 40 &#x000b5;g of total tRNA purified from strain IC5653 (an <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> double mutant). At the end of the reaction, tRNA was phenol extracted, ethanol precipitated, degraded to nucleotides with nuclease P1 and, finally, treated with bacterial alkaline phosphatase. The resulting hydrolysate was analyzed by HPLC using a Develosil C30 column (250 &#x000d7; 4.6 mm; Phenomenex Ltd). The chromatographic conditions for gradient elution were essentially as described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>). Given that total tRNA was extracted from a strain where the 2-thiouridylase MnmA protein is active, absorbance could be monitored at 314 nm to maximize the detection of thiolated nucleosides.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of the MnmC enzymatic activity</title><p>The tRNA previously modified by MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex was phenolysed, ethanol precipitated and incubated with 2 &#x003bc;M FLAG-MnmC protein in 200 &#x000b5;l (total volume) of MnmC buffer {50 mM Tris&#x02013;Cl (pH 8.0), 50 mM Ammonium acetate, 40 &#x003bc;M [<italic>methyl</italic>-<sup>14</sup>C]AdoMet (60 mCi/mmole) or 0.5 mM cold SAM, 0.5 mM FAD, 5% glycerol}. After 40 min of incubation at 37&#x000b0;C, the tRNA was recovered by phenolization and ethanol precipitation, and digested by nuclease P1 (and by <italic>E. coli</italic> alkaline phosphatase when appropriated). The resulting products were analyzed by 2D-TLC on a cellulose plate (or by reverse-phase HPLC) as described earlier.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Study of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA modification activity using <italic>in vitro</italic> synthesized tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> and TLC analysis</title><p>To determine whether the recombinant MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex displays tRNA modification activity, we developed an <italic>in vitro</italic> modification assay where the independent contribution of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex and its putative substrates and cofactors could be assessed. Basically, the reaction mix contained recombinant proteins, <sup>32</sup>P-labeled tRNA<sup>Lys</sup>, GTP, FAD and NADH/NADPH. In addition, we included methylene-THF as the first-choice carbon donor because its affinity for MnmE, while similar to that of the remaining THF derivatives (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> &#x0223c; 1 &#x000b5;M) as determined by ITC, displays a slightly more favourable enthalpy, suggestive of a better interaction (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). After incubation of the reaction mix, the tRNA was hydrolyzed by nuclease P1 and analyzed by 2D-TLC. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> shows that a major spot corresponding to nucleotide pU was obtained in the absence of any protein (panels A1 and B1), and that one additional compound (C1) appeared after addition of either MnmE or FLAG-GidA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, panels A2 and B2). Interestingly, when the assay was performed in the presence of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex, a new compound, named C2, was also detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, panels A3 and B3). Formation of C2, but not C1, was absolutely dependent on the presence of FAD and GTP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figure S1</ext-link>), which suggests that only C2 is related to the MnmE&#x02022;GidA pathway. <table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Affinity of MnmE to THF derivatives as determined by ITC<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">THF derivative</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> (&#x003bc;M)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>G</italic> (<italic>K</italic>cal/mol)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;<italic>H</italic> (<italic>K</italic>cal/mol)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<italic>T</italic> &#x00394;<italic>S</italic> (<italic>K</italic>cal/mol)</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6S/6R) 5-formyl-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6S) 5-formyl-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6R) 10-formyl-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6S) 5-methyl-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6R) 5,10-methylene-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6S) THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;8.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p><sup>a</sup>Data in this table indicate that all derivatives were bound by MnmE in a favorable and spontaneous way (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> and &#x00394;G values were similar), although the binding for 10-formyl-THF and methyl-THF was the less favorable. Assuming that either there is no protonation or this is equal for all ligands, binding of methylene-THF exhibits a slightly more favorable enthalpy than the remainder.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The complex MnmE&#x02022;GidA catalyzes the formation of two nucleotides, C2 and C3, on <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed tRNA<sup>Lys</sup>. Autoradiograms of tRNA hydrolysates resulting from <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reactions performed in buffer A in the presence (+) or absence (&#x02212;) of the indicated components. (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Correspond to the autoradiograms of the TLC analysis in solvents A/C and A/B, respectively. Positions of modified 5' phosphate nucleotides C1, C2 and C3 are indicated. Circles in dotted lines show the migration of the canonical nucleotides used as UV markers. Identical results to those shown in panels A1, B1, A2 and B2 were obtained in the presence of glycine (data not shown). In this article, we show that C2 and C3 correspond to nm<sup>5</sup>U 5&#x02032;-monophosphate (pnm<sup>5</sup>U) and cmnm<sup>5</sup>U 5&#x02032;-monophosphate (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U), respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkp762f2"/></fig></p><p>Next, we analyzed the role of glycine in the <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reaction. Addition of this amino acid, but not alanine or serine, led to disappearance of C2 and production of a new compound, designated C3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, panels A4 and B4, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>). Formation of C3 was also dependent on inclusion of both GTP and FAD in the reaction mix (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figure S2</ext-link>). According to reference maps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>), C3 corresponds to cmnm<sup>5</sup>U 5&#x02032;-monophosphate (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U), but C2 cannot be assigned.</p></sec><sec><title>MnmC converts nucleotides C2 and C3 (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U) to mnm<sup>5</sup>U 5&#x02032;-monophosphate (pmnm<sup>5</sup>U)</title><p>MnmC is a bifunctional enzyme whose C-terminal domain catalyzes demodification of cmnm<sup>5</sup>(s<sup>2</sup>)U to nm<sup>5</sup>(s<sup>2</sup>)U, whereas its N-terminal domain independently methylates nm<sup>5</sup>(s<sup>2</sup>)U to form the final product mnm<sup>5</sup>(s<sup>2</sup>)U (16; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Therefore, considering that cmnm<sup>5</sup>U and nm<sup>5</sup>U are substrates for MnmC, we decided to use this enzyme to investigate the nature of compounds C2 and C3 (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U) generated by the MnmE&#x02022;GidA activity. tRNA<sup>Lys</sup>, previously modified <italic>in vitro</italic> by MnmE&#x02022;GidA (in the presence or not of glycine), was incubated with protein FLAG-MnmC, in a buffer containing FAD and SAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). Subsequently, the tRNA was hydrolyzed using nuclease P1 and the resulting nucleotides were analyzed by TLC. Interestingly, C2 and most of C3 (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U) disappeared, whereas two new compounds migrating as pmnm<sup>5</sup>U (C4) and pm<sup>5</sup>U (C5), according to previous chromatographic diagrams (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>), were generated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A, compare panels 2 and 3 with 4 and 5, respectively). Synthesis of m<sup>5</sup>U could be explained if our MnmC preparation contained traces of TrmA, which catalyzes the SAM-dependent methylation of the uracil in position 54 in all <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNAs. Note that the compound labeled with an asterisk in panel 4 of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A is already present in other chromatograms, with variable relative intensity. Thus, we think it is a product of either an unusual cleavage or tRNA degradation. <fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>MnmC converts C2 and C3 to C4 (mnm<sup>5</sup>U 5&#x02032;-monophosphate, pmnm<sup>5</sup>U). 2D-TLC autoradiograms of tRNA hydrolysates resulting from <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reactions. Solvent system A/C was used for the TLC analysis. (<bold>A</bold>) [&#x003b1;-<sup>32</sup>P]-UTP-labelled <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> was incubated in buffer A (<bold>A1</bold>), modified by the addition of MnmE&#x02022;GidA to form C2 (pnm<sup>5</sup>U) in the absence of glycine (<bold>A2</bold>), or C3 (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U<bold>)</bold> in the presence of this amino acid (<bold>A3</bold>). C2 and C3 were converted to compound C4 (pmnm<sup>5</sup>U) by MnmC (<bold>A4</bold> and <bold>A5</bold>) (<bold>B</bold>) Cold <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> was incubated in buffer A with 40 &#x003bc;M [<italic>methyl</italic>-<sup>14</sup>C]AdoMet (<bold>B1</bold>). Addition of MnmE&#x02022;GidA (in the absence of glycine) produces C2 (pnm<sup>5</sup>U), which is not visible in this step because both the tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> as well as the methyl group added to U34 are not radiolabeled (<bold>B2</bold>). Incubation of the resulting tRNA with MnmC, FAD and [<italic>methyl</italic>-<sup>14</sup>C]AdoMet produces pmnm<sup>5</sup>U (<bold>B3</bold>). (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) Total tRNA from an <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> mutant or a wild-type strain, respectively, were treated as in (B), and the products resulting from the MnmC activity are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkp762f3"/></fig></p><p>Conversion of C3 to pmnm<sup>5</sup>U (C4) by MnmC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A, panels 3 and 5) is in agreement with our prediction that C3 is pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U. Conversion of C2 to pmnm<sup>5</sup>U (C4) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A, panels 2 and 4) suggests that C2 is pnm<sup>5</sup>U since it works as a substrate for MnmC but does not exhibit the chromatographic mobility of pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U. If so, this is surprising because it has never before been reported that nm<sup>5</sup>U may be a direct product of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex activity.</p><p>To further explore the capability of MnmC to work on the C2 nucleotide produced by MnmE&#x02022;GidA, we proceeded as follows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). Five micrograms of unlabeled <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> were incubated in buffer A with MnmE&#x02022;GidA and [<italic>methyl</italic>-<sup>14</sup>C]AdoMet, in the absence of glycine, to form C2 (pnm<sup>5</sup>U), according to our previous results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A, panel 2). In this case, production of pnm<sup>5</sup>U could not be detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B, panel 2) because the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed tRNA used as substrate was unlabelled, and [<italic>methyl</italic>-<sup>14</sup>C]AdoMet does not work as a methyl donor in the formation of nm<sup>5</sup>U by MnmE&#x02022;GidA. Then, the tRNA modified by the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex was incubated with MnmC, FAD and [<italic>methyl</italic>-<sup>14</sup>C]AdoMet, hydrolyzed and analyzed by TLC. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B, panel 3, a radioactive compound whose migration characteristics correspond to those of pmnm<sup>5</sup>U could be detected. Moreover, 15 &#x000b5;g of total tRNA isolated from either an <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> double mutant (strain IC5653; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C) or a wild-type strain (MG1655; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>D) were treated in the same way as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B. Addition of MnmC, FAD, and <sup>14</sup>C-radiolabeled SAM to total tRNA previously modified <italic>in vitro</italic> by the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex (in the absence of glycine, i.e. under conditions where only the nucleotide corresponding to C2, pnm<sup>5</sup>U, is formed) produced compounds whose migration characteristics are those of pmnm<sup>5</sup>U and pmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C and D). The tRNAs isolated from the wild-type strain that are substrates for MnmE&#x02022;GidA/MnmC are mostly modified, which may explain the less amount of labeled products obtained in this case (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>C and D). Altogether these experiments support that MnmC transforms nucleotide C2 (pnm<sup>5</sup>U), produced by MnmE&#x02022;GidA in the absence of glycine, to pmnm<sup>5</sup>U.</p></sec><sec><title>Ammonium ion or glycine may be used by the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex to synthesize nm<sup>5</sup>U or cmnm<sup>5</sup>U, respectively</title><p>If compound C2 is pnm<sup>5</sup>U, we wondered whether ammonium is the source of its amine group, given that the nucleotide is synthesized in the absence of glycine. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> shows that removal of ammonium acetate from the reaction buffer prevents formation of C2 (compare panels B and C). It is important to note that stimulation of the MnmE GTPase activity (which is essential for the modifying function of this protein; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>) requires potassium or ammonium ions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). In the <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reaction, potassium ions are present, at least, 10 mM due to the addition of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex (whose formation is carried out in a buffer containing 50 mM KCl). This concentration might be suboptimal for efficient stimulation of the MnmE GTPase activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>), explaining that elimination of ammonium from the reaction mix impairs the <italic>in vitro</italic> tRNA modification reaction. However, when ammonium acetate was substituted by potassium acetate, the modification reaction does not work either, given that C2 (pnm<sup>5</sup>U) is not produced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D). The same result was obtained when sodium acetate was the substituent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>E). Interestingly, when ammonium ions are removed but glycine is added, C3 (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U), but not C2 (pnm<sup>5</sup>U), is formed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>F). Considering that the synthesis of both nucleotides requires the presence of GTP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figures S1 and S2</ext-link>), we conclude that 10 mM KCl is enough to stimulate the MnmE activity and that ammonium may be used by the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex to synthesize the nm<sup>5</sup> group. Moreover, given that C3 (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U) may be obtained when glycine, but not ammonium, is present in the buffer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>F), we propose that C2 (pnm<sup>5</sup>U) is not an intermediate in the C3 (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U) formation and that synthesis of both compounds is mediated by MnmE&#x02022;GidA through different and independent pathways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). Strikingly, only compound C3 (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U) is produced when ammonium and glycine are simultaneously present in the reaction mix (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, panels A4 and B4). Therefore, we think that the glycine-dependent reaction is competitively more effective under the conditions used in these assays. <fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Ammonium ion is indispensable to form C2 (pnm<sup>5</sup>U) but not C3 (pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U). 2D-TLC autoradiograms of tRNA hydrolysates resulting from <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reactions performed in buffer C (same as buffer A, but without ammonium acetate) supplemented (+) or not (&#x02212;) with the indicated components. Salts were added to buffer C at 100 mM, but note that potassium ions are always present at, at least, 10 mM after the addition of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex. Solvent system A/C was used for the TLC analysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkp762f4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>A new model of the U34 modification pathway. As in the old model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) the modifications at the 2- and 5-positions occur independently of each other. C2, C3 and C4 are the designations given to 5&#x02032;-monophosphate nucleosides identified in our TLC experiments (pnm<sup>5</sup>U, pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U, and pmnm<sup>5</sup>U).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkp762f5"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Reverse-phase HPLC analysis of total <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA modified <italic>in vitro</italic> by the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex</title><p>To confirm the TLC data and further investigate how proteins MnmE, GidA and MnmC work, we performed the <italic>in vitro</italic> modification assay using total tRNA purified from a double mutant <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> instead of the <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed tRNA<sup>Lys</sup>. In this case, the resulting tRNA was analyzed, after digestion with nuclease P1 and alkaline phosphatase, by HPLC, using some purified nucleosides as controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>A). Previous HPLC analysis of tRNA purified from null <italic>mnmE</italic> or <italic>gidA</italic> mutants (where protein MnmA is active) revealed accumulation of s<sup>2</sup>U and disappearance of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in the corresponding chromatograms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>). In this work, we observed that s<sup>2</sup>U remained accumulated after performing the <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reaction in the absence of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>B). However, when this complex was added to a reaction mix containing ammonium but not glycine, s<sup>2</sup>U was converted into nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>C). Note that ammonium was indispensable for this conversion since s<sup>2</sup>U remained accumulated in the absence of the cation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>D). Moreover, when the reaction mix contained glycine but not ammonium, s<sup>2</sup>U was partially converted into cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, whereas no production of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>E). Altogether these results support the idea that the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex catalyzes the <italic>in vitro</italic> biosynthesis of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA through two independent reactions and without participation of other proteins. <fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>HPLC analysis of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA activity. (<bold>A</bold>) Elution times and UV spectra of the reference ribonucleosides. (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>In vitro</italic> modification reaction performed in the absence of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex. (<bold>C</bold>) As in B, but adding MnmE&#x02022;GidA. (<bold>D</bold>) As in C except ammonium acetate was removed from buffer. (<bold>E</bold>) As in (D), but adding glycine. (<bold>F</bold>) As in (C) (i.e. in buffer A, which contains ammonium acetate), but adding glycine. (<bold>G</bold> and <bold>H</bold>) Bulk tRNA from <italic>mnmC::kan</italic> and <italic>mnmC1</italic> mutants, respectively. <italic>AU</italic>, absorbance units.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkp762f6"/></fig></p><p>Curiously, both cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U were detected after the simultaneous addition of ammonium and glycine to the reaction mix (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>F). This result differs from that obtained when the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex activity was analyzed using <italic>in vitro</italic> synthesized tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> and TLC. In such a case, pcmnm<sup>5</sup>U was the only product detected when both ammonium and glycine were included in the reaction (compound C3 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, panels A4 and B4), in spite of we detected formation of pnm<sup>5</sup>U (C2) if only ammonium was present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, panels A3 and B3). Thus, it seems that the glycine-dependent reaction is competitively more effective when the <italic>in vitro</italic> synthesized tRNA<sup>Lys</sup> is the substrate. Considering that this tRNA is completely unmodified, in contrast to the total tRNA purified from the <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>), it is tempting to speculate that some tRNA modification(s) outside the 5-position of U34 modulate the efficiency of the reactions mediated by the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex.</p><p>To firmly establish the identities of the nucleosides resulting from the <italic>in vitro</italic> MnmE&#x02022;GidA activity, we again analyzed their ability to be used as substrates by the bifunctional enzyme MnmC. As expected, MnmC converted the peaks assigned to nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U into mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3</ext-link>, compare panels B and D with C and E, respectively).</p><p>To further demonstrate that nm<sup>5</sup>U is not an intermediate in the synthesis of cmnm<sup>5</sup>U mediated by MnmE&#x02022;GidA, the bulk tRNA purified from an <italic>mnmC2</italic> mutant (where nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U accumulates) was used as substrate for an <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reaction mediated by MnmE&#x02022;GidA in the presence of glycine (with or without ammonium) and, as expected, no conversion of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U to cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U was observed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4</ext-link>). In addition, we used total tRNA extracted from an <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> mutant as substrate in a reaction catalyzed by MnmE&#x02022;GidA in the presence of ammonium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). After phenol extraction and ethanol precipitation, the resulting tRNA, which carried nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>B), was mixed with MnmE&#x02022;GidA and glycine (in the presence or absence of ammonium). The HPLC pattern of the tRNA remained unaltered after this second reaction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>C), supporting that nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U is not a substrate for MnmE&#x02022;GidA. <fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>The nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U nucleoside is not an intermediate in the biosynthetic pathway of cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U. Bulk tRNA from an <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> double mutant (<bold>A</bold>) was incubated with MnmE&#x02022;GidA in buffer A to form nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (<bold>B</bold>). After phenol extraction and ethanol precipitation, the resulting tRNA was incubated with MnmE&#x02022;GidA and glycine in buffer A, with or without ammonium acetate (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkp762f7"/></fig></p><p>Finally, we thought that if the MnmE&#x02022;GidA activity is able to introduce the nm<sup>5</sup> group at the wobble uridine, the modified nucleoside should be found in the tRNA isolated from a null <italic>mnmC</italic> mutant. As expected, HPLC analysis of tRNA from an <italic>mnmC::kan</italic> strain revealed the presence of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, in addition to cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, in the hydrolysates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>G). Curiously, this nucleoside was previously not identified in tRNA from an <italic>mnmC1</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>), which we now know carries a nonsense mutation in the <italic>mnmC</italic> gene. Here, we have carefully analyzed the tRNA extracted from mutant <italic>mnmC1</italic> and detected the presence of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>H). Whether such a discrepancy may be due to the different growth medium used in each case is a question that remains to be explored.</p></sec><sec><title>Involvement of FAD and NADH in the tRNA modification reaction</title><p>Mutations affecting the FAD-binding domain of GidA impair tRNA modification <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>). Here, we have shown that FAD is essential for the <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reaction (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figures S1 and S2</ext-link>). It was previously postulated that GidA-bound reduced FAD is required for the last step in the synthesis of the cmnm<sup>5</sup>-group, and that GidA-bound FAD receives its electrons from NADH, given that GidA binds NADH but not NADPH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). Curiously, we have found that NADH (or NADPH) does not seem to be necessary for the synthesis <italic>in vitro</italic> of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U if FAD is present at a high concentration (1 mM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>A and B). Note that appropriate control experiments indicate that nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U do not accumulate if FAD is removed, though NADH or NADPH remains in the reaction mix. Synthesis of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U is drastically reduced when FAD is used at 2 &#x000b5;M (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>C and D). However, under such conditions, the addition of NADH (but not NADPH) at 0.5 mM substantially improves the nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U synthesis, mainly of the last one (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>C and D). These results suggest that NADH may play a critical role in tRNA modification depending on cell FAD concentrations. <fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>NADH is dispensable for <italic>in vitro</italic> tRNA modification unless FAD levels are limiting. The effect of FAD, NADH and NADPH on the nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U formation, in bulk tRNA purified from a double <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> mutant, was monitored by HPLC analysis. The MnmE and GidA proteins were previously dialysed against TBS buffer (50 mM Tris&#x02013;HCl pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl and 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>). (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) Formation of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (ammonium acetate, but not glycine, is present in the reaction mix) and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (glycine, but not ammonium acetate, is present in the mix), respectively, when FAD (1 mM) was added in the absence of exogenous NADH and NADPH (thin line) and when NADH or NADPH was added at 0.5 mM in the absence of FAD (bold line). (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) Formation of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U, respectively, when FAD is added to 2 &#x000b5;M, in the absence of NADH and NADPH (bold line), or in the presence of NADH (0.5 mM, thin line). NADPH (0.5 mM) did not improve the production of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U when FAD was used at 2 &#x000b5;M (data not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkp762f8"/></fig></p><p>Curiously, it has been reported that TrmFO, a GidA paralogue involved in the FAD-, NADPH- and methylene-THF-dependent methylation of uridine at position 54 of tRNAs, is able to catalyze the <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reaction in the absence of NADPH (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Given that NADPH is thought to be required for FAD reduction, the mentioned finding was attributed to copurification of the enzyme with the oxidized and reduced forms of flavin. In this respect, it should be mentioned that we have used dialyzed proteins to perform the experiments shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>. Considering the relatively low affinity of GidA for FAD (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> &#x0223c; 3 &#x000b5;M; our own unpublished results) and NADH (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> &#x0223c; 11 &#x000b5;M; 32), we find it unlikely that the dialyzed GidA protein used in our experiments carried these cofactors.</p></sec><sec><title>MnmE&#x02022;GidA uses methylene-THF to form the C5-methylene moiety of nm<sup>5</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>U</title><p>While studying the requirements for the <italic>in vitro</italic> synthesis of nm<sup>5</sup>U by MnmE&#x02022;GidA, we observed that removal of methylene-THF from the reaction mix did not affect the accumulation of the modified nucleoside. This suggests that MnmE copurifies with the one-carbon unit donor, a behavior that has also been observed for TrmFO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>). To overcome this difficulty and further investigate the carbon donor used by MnmE&#x02022;GidA, we first constructed a <italic>folE::cat</italic> mutant. <italic>folE</italic> encodes GTP cyclohydrolase I, which is the first enzyme of the <italic>de novo</italic> THF pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). HPLC analysis of tRNAs purified from the <italic>folE::cat</italic> mutant revealed the disappearance of nucleoside mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and accumulation of s<sup>2</sup>U, in relation to the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). This finding supports that THF works as the one-carbon unit donor in the MnmE&#x02022;GidA modification pathway. Then, strain <italic>folE::cat</italic> was independently transformed with plasmids expressing proteins GST-MnmE and FLAG-GidA with the aim to purify both proteins from cells where THF is presumably very limited, since only some folate-related salvage pathway may be active (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). Finally, an <italic>in vitro</italic> modification assay was performed with bulk tRNA extracted from an <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> double mutant and proteins purified from the <italic>folE::cat</italic> strain. The relative accumulation of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and s<sup>2</sup>U observed under different concentrations of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex and folate derivatives is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>. Curiously, when no external source of folate is included in the reaction mix (see entry &#x02018;Proteins/No folates&#x02019; in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>), nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U still accumulates if the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex is added to 2 &#x000b5;M (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>, column A). This suggests that the amount of protein MnmE that is added to the mix still provides a concentration of the one-carbon unit donor that is enough to lead the <italic>in vitro</italic> modification of tRNA. Accordingly, when the concentration of MnmE&#x02022;GidA in the mix is reduced from 2 to 0.35 &#x000b5;M (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>, column B), no significant conversion of s<sup>2</sup>U to nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U is observed in the absence of exogenous folate. Moreover, if under such conditions, the folate derivative is added to 50 &#x000b5;M, major increases of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U are only seen with methylene-THF, THF or methyl-THF. These results help us to discard 5-formyl-, 10-formyl- and methenyl-THF as the one-carbon unit donor. However, given that no one-carbon unit is carried by THF, it is possible that our preparation of this compound contained traces of the true one-carbon unit donor, which may be methylene-THF or methyl-THF. We assume that traces of one of them are also present in the other one, explaining that the <italic>in vitro</italic> reaction works with both substrates. The use of the folate derivative at 1 &#x000b5;M (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>, column C) still led to the production of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in the case of THF, methylene-THF and methyl-THF, with methylene-THF appearing to be slightly more effective. A further decrease in the concentration of these derivatives did not lead to conclusive results since the efficiency of the reaction was drastically reduced (data not shown), probably because the affinity of MnmE for them is in the low micromolar range (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). <table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Levels of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U and s<sup>2</sup>U in mutants of the THF pathway</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U/s<sup>4</sup>U<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">s<sup>2</sup>U/s<sup>4</sup>U<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BW25113 (wt)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>folE::cat</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>metF::kan</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>glyA::kan</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF2"><p><sup>a</sup>The numbers are calculated as the absorbance of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U or s<sup>2</sup>U relative to the absorbance of s<sup>4</sup>U at 314 nm and represent the mean values of at least two independent experiments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Synthesis of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U in the presence of different THF derivatives</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reaction mix<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">A<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF4"><sup>b</sup></xref><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">B<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF4"><sup>b</sup></xref><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">C<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF4"><sup>b</sup></xref><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U/s<sup>4</sup>U</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">s<sup>2</sup>U/s<sup>4</sup>U</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U/s<sup>4</sup>U</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">s<sup>2</sup>U/s<sup>4</sup>U</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U/s<sup>4</sup>U</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">s<sup>2</sup>U/s<sup>4</sup>U</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No proteins/No folates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0246</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0248</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0244</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins/No folates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0178</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0271</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins/methylene-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0459</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0498</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0457</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins/THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0486</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0465</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0357</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0072</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins/5 formyl-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0264</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0279</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins/10 formyl-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0274</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0033</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0269</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins/methyl-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0503</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0422</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0063</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0225</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0114</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins/methenyl-THF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0222</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0034</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0314</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF3"><p><sup>a</sup>tRNA purified from an <italic>mnmE gidA</italic> double mutant and buffer A were used for performing the <italic>in vitro</italic> modification reaction in the presence of the components specified in the column. MnmE and GidA were used at a final concentration of 2 &#x000b5;M (A) and 0.35 &#x000b5;M (B and C). Folates were used at a final concentration of 1 mM (A), 50 &#x000b5;M (B) and 1 &#x000b5;M (C).</p></fn><fn id="TF4"><p><sup>b</sup>The numbers are calculated as the absorbance of nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U or s<sup>2</sup>U relative to the absorbance of s<sup>4</sup>U at 314 nm. Bold numbers are used to highlight the highest values. nd, not done.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p><italic>glyA</italic> and <italic>metF</italic> mutations block the synthesis of 5-formyl-THF and methyl-THF, respectively. Considering that the <italic>in vivo</italic><sup>13</sup>C incorporation from glycine to mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U takes place in <italic>glyA</italic> and <italic>metF</italic> mutants similarly to the wild-type strain, it was suggested that 5-formyl-THF and methyl-THF are not the direct substrates to form the C5-methylene moiety of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U (T. Suzuki and T. Suzuki, 22nd tRNA workshop, Sweden, 2007). We have verified such a proposal, finding that mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U accumulates in <italic>glyA</italic> and <italic>metF</italic> null mutants at the wild-type level (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). These results, together with those shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>, prompt us to conclude that methylene-THF is the one-carbon unit donor in the modification reaction catalyzed by MnmE&#x02022;GidA. If so, data from <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref> also suggest that there is no substrate inhibition with THF and methyl-THF since nm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup>U accumulates even when both compounds are added at 1 mM (final concentration) and, according to our hypothesis, methylene-THF should be a minor contaminant in the respective preparations. This behaviour is different from that described for TrmFO, whose methylene-THF-dependent activity is inhibited by concentrations of THF higher than 2 &#x000b5;M (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>). Given that the affinity of MnmE for all THF derivatives tested is similar (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), we think that either the binding to methylene-THF is kinetically favored or the affinity for this derivative significantly increases when MnmE is bound to its partners.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>To characterize the enzymatic pathway of mnm<sup>5</sup>U biosynthesis in <italic>E. coli</italic>, we have purified proteins MnmE, GidA and MnmC and checked their ability to modify tRNA <italic>in vitro</italic>. Our results show, for the first time, that the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex catalyses the synthesis of nm<sup>5</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>U in tRNA through two independent reactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3</xref>A and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), in which ammonium and glycine are the source of the amino and carboxymethylamino moiety, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). The identity of the nucleosides synthesized by the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex <italic>in vitro</italic> (nm<sup>5</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>U) was confirmed by the fact that, in a buffer containing FAD and SAM, they were transformed to mnm<sup>5</sup>U by a recombinant MnmC protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figure S3</ext-link>). <italic>In vivo</italic> results also indicated that nm<sup>5</sup>U is a direct product of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA activity because a peak corresponding to this nucleoside could be clearly identified in the HPLC analysis of total tRNA extracted from an <italic>mnmC</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>G and H). It should be emphasized that nm<sup>5</sup>U is a final product, and not a stable intermediate, of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA activity since it is not a substrate for this complex both <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figure S4</ext-link>) as well as <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>G and H; note in these panels that nm<sup>5</sup>U accumulates in an <italic>mnmC</italic> mutant where the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex is active). Therefore, the pathway controlled by MnmE and GidA may be reformulated as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> and, more schematically, 9A.</p><p>We have previously shown that the GTPase activity of MnmE and the FAD-binding ability of GidA are required for tRNA modification <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>). Here, we demonstrate that the two <italic>in vitro</italic> reactions catalyzed by MnmE&#x02022;GidA are GTP- and FAD-dependent (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Figures S1 and S2</ext-link>), suggesting that the synthesis of nm<sup>5</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>U share a similar mechanism.</p><p>Biochemical and structural studies previously indicated that MnmE binds 5&#x02032;-formyl-THF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). Consequently, a tRNA modification mechanism based on the formyl transfer onto C5 of the wobble uridine was proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>). However, we have found here that MnmE exhibits a similar affinity for different THF derivatives, including 5&#x02032;-formyl-THF (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), which questions the role of this compound as the one-carbon unit donor in the modification reaction. We have analyzed the nucleoside composition of tRNA extracted from mutants where the THF pathway is inactivated at different stages. Our data support the idea that the C5-methylene moiety of xm<sup>5</sup>(s<sup>2</sup>)U nucleosides is derived from the THF pathway, since s<sup>2</sup>U accumulates in a <italic>folE</italic> mutant, although not from 5-formyl- or methyl-THF, since the level of mnm<sup>5</sup>s<sup>2</sup> in <italic>glyA</italic> and <italic>metF</italic> mutants is similar to that of the wild-type strain (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Moreover, we have performed <italic>in vitro</italic> modification assays in the presence of different THF derivatives (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Our data indicate that neither 5-formyl-, 10-formyl- or methenyl-THF is likely to be the one-carbon unit donor in the modification reaction. Altogether, these results prompt us to conclude that methylene-THF is the source of the C5 methylene moiety of nm<sup>5</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>U.</p><p>We have shown that NADH is dispensable for the <italic>in vitro</italic> function of MnmE&#x02022;GidA unless FAD levels are limiting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). This suggests that FAD undergoes an oxidation-reduction cycle during synthesis of nm<sup>5</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>U (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>B). In such a cycle, FAD receives electrons from other participant in the reaction and, subsequently, donates them to some reaction intermediate. Probably, there is a spontaneous oxidation of the reduced FAD during the <italic>in vitro</italic> modification that may explain, together with the low affinity of GidA for FAD (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> &#x0223c; 3 &#x000b5;M, our own unpublished results), the low efficiency of the reaction when FAD is used at 2 &#x000b5;M. Under these circumstances, addition of NADH would facilitate production of the reduced FAD, improving the second step of the FAD cycle associated with the reduction of some reaction intermediate. Based on these considerations, we propose a novel catalytic mechanism for the nm<sup>5</sup>U and cmnm<sup>5</sup>U modification process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>C), where a general acid of MnmE&#x02022;GidA converts the methylene-THF into a reactive iminium ion (step 1), in analogy to the reaction catalyzed by thymidylate synthase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). This allows the addition of the amine or carboxymethylamine group to the methylene group at N5 of THF (step 2). Then, FAD-bound GidA performs a dehydrogenation reaction (step 3), facilitating the nucleophilic attack by the C5 atom of U34 (step 4), which has been activated, again in analogy with the thymidilate synthase reaction, through the attack at the C6 position of U34 by a general acid of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex. Later, FADH<sub>2</sub> serves as the reducing agent of the Schiff&#x02019;s base (step 7). This step is followed by the liberation of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA complex and production of cmnm<sup>5</sup>U and nm<sup>5</sup>U. Our model involves that the THF-binding domain of MnmE and the FAD-binding domain of GidA should be close to the C5 position of the wobble uridine of tRNA. The structural rearrangements of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA heterotetramer that are coupled to the GTPase cycle of MnmE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>) and to the FAD binding of GidA (our own unpublished results) might help in the construction of the active center. Further biochemical and structural studies will be required to clarify the detailed mechanism of the MnmE&#x02022;GidA-dependent reactions. <fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>The MnmE&#x02022;GidA tRNA modification pathway. (<bold>A</bold>) A schematic of the new formulation for the MnmE&#x02022;GidA pathway. (<bold>B</bold>) Hypothetical FAD-dependent steps in the MnmE&#x02022;GidA-mediated reaction. (<bold>C</bold>) The proposal chemical mechanism for the MnmE&#x02022;GidA catalyzed reactions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkp762f9"/></fig></p><p>MnmE and GidA, but not MnmC, are conserved proteins from bacteria to humans. The MnmE and GidA homologues in yeast (MSS1 and MTO1) and humans (GTPBP3 and MTO1) are nucleus-encoded proteins involved in modification of mitochondrial tRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38 B39 B40 B41">38&#x02013;41</xref>). The lack of MnmC determines that, in yeast, the final product of the MSS1/MTO1 pathway is cmnm<sup>5</sup>U. In humans, taurine is incorporated into tRNAs in place of glycine, producing &#x003c4;m<sup>5</sup>U (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>). Both nucleosides are probably synthesized in mitochondria by the MnmE and GidA homologues without the participation of other proteins, through a reaction similar to that described here. If so, the complex formed by the human homologues should be able to use taurine in place of glycine. It should be noted that GTPBP3 largely conserves the MnmE properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>), which supports our proposal that the tRNA modification reaction catalyzed by the eukaryotic homologues should be basically similar to that performed by the <italic>E. coli</italic> proteins. The presence of nm<sup>5</sup>(s<sup>2</sup>)U in mitochondrial tRNA has not been reported so far. However, in the light of our results, we think this issue should be further explored.</p></sec><sec><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/gkp762/DC1">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p></sec><sec><title>FUNDING</title><p>Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovaci&#x000f3;n and Generalidad Valenciana (BFU2004-05819, BFU2007-66509, ACOMP/2009/348 and AP-079/09 to M.-E.A.); the Swedish Science Research Council (Project BU-2930); the Carl Trygger Foundation (to G.R.B.). Funding for open access charge: Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovaci&#x000f3;n (grant BFU2007&#x02013;66509 to M.-E.A.).</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>[Supplementary Data]</title></caption><media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="gkp762_index.html"/><media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gkp762_1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank R. Moser (Merck-Eprova AG) and K. Tamura for their generous gifts of tetrahydrofolate derivatives and plasmid pUC-tRNA<sup>Lys</sup>, respectively. We also thank T. G. Hagervall, J. N&#x000e4;svall and J. Timoneda for helpful discussions; and G. J&#x000e4;ger and K. Nilsson for their technical advices. I.M. was a recipient of a Bancaixa Research Contract and short-term fellowships from the Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovaci&#x000f3;n and Generalidad Valenciana. S.P. and A.V.-C. were supported by a fellowship from the Ministerio de Ciencia e Innovaci&#x000f3;n and a Research Contract from Fundaci&#x000f3;n Arag&#x000f3;n I + D, respectively.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><comment>Bj&#x000f6;rk,G. and Hagervall,T. (2005) Transfer RNA modification. In Curtiss,R. III, B&#x000f6;ck,A., Ingraham,J.I., Kaper,J.B., Maloy,S., Neidhardt,F.C., Riley,M.M., Squires, C.L. and Wanner,B.L. (eds), <italic>Escherichia coli and Salmonella: Cellular and Molecular Biology</italic>, [Online] <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ecosal.org">http://www.ecosal.org</ext-link>. ASM Press, Washington DC</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agris</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bringing order to translation: the contributions of transfer RNA anticodon-domain modifications</article-title><source>EMBO Rep.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18552770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weixlbaumer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohtsuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimazaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modified uridines with C5-methylene substituents at the first position of the tRNA anticodon stabilize U&#x02022;G wobble pairing during decoding</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>18801</fpage><lpage>18811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18456657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagervall</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced misreading of asparagine codons by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> tRNALys with hypomodified derivatives of 5-methylaminomethyl-2-thiouridine in the wobble position</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9811540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagervall</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000f8;rensen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The modification of the wobble base of tRNAGlu modulates the translation rate of glutamic acid codons in vivo</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9826503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbonavicius</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagervall</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rk</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvement of reading frame maintenance is a common function for several tRNA modifications</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>4863</fpage><lpage>4873</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11532950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasukawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Akira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Codon-specific translational defect caused by a wobble modification deficiency in mutant tRNA from a human mitochondrial disease</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>15070</fpage><lpage>15075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15477592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rk</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bystr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A conserved modified wobble nucleoside (mcm5s2U) in lysyl-tRNA is required for viability in yeast</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17592039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Esberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rk</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bystr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eukaryotic wobble uridine modifications promote a functionally redundant decoding system</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3301</fpage><lpage>3312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18332122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human mitochondrial diseases associated with tRNA wobble modification deficiency</article-title><source>RNA Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17132941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villarroya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Esteve</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguado</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Ferrandis</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Victor</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cebolla</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of human GTPBP3, a GTP-binding protein involved in mitochondrial tRNA modification</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>7514</fpage><lpage>7531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18852288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elseviers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrullo</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> mutants deficient in biosynthesis of 5-methylaminomethyl-2-thiouridine</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1984</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3521</fpage><lpage>3534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6427754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagervall</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloskey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rk</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transfer RNA(5-methylaminomethyl-2-thiouridine)-methyltransferase from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 has two enzymatic activities</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1987</year><volume>262</volume><fpage>8488</fpage><lpage>8495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3298234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moukadiri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rk</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Armengod</surname><given-names>M-E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Further insights into the tRNA modification process controlled by proteins MnmE and GidA of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>5892</fpage><lpage>5905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17062623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bujnicki</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oudjama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Roovers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Owczarek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Caillet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Droogmans</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a bifunctional enzyme MnmC involved in the biosynthesis of a hypermodified uridine in the wobble position of tRNA</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1236</fpage><lpage>1242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15247431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roovers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oudjama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaminska</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Purta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Caillet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Droogmans</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bujnicki</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence-structure-function analysis of the bifunctional enzyme MnmC that catalyses the last two steps in the biosynthesis of hypermodified nucleoside mnm5s2U in tRNA</article-title><source>Proteins</source><year>2008</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>2076</fpage><lpage>2085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18186482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kambampati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauhon</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MnmA and IscS are required for in vitro 2-thiouridine biosynthesis in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1109</fpage><lpage>1117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12549933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanistic insights into sulfur relay by multiple sulfur mediators involved in thiouridine biosynthesis at tRNA wobble positions</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Vicente</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Villarroya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguado</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Knecht</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Armengod</surname><given-names>M-E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The GTPase activity and C-terminal cysteine of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> MnmE protein are essential for its tRNA modifying function</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>28378</fpage><lpage>28387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12730230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Vicente</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Villarroya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellado</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Pay&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rk</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Armengod</surname><given-names>M-E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of mutagenesis in the switch I region and conserved arginines of Escherichia coli MnmE protein, a GTPase involved in tRNA modification</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>30660</fpage><lpage>30670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15983041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Inanaga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nureki</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Numata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conserved cysteine residues of GidA are essential for biogenesis of 5-carboxymethylaminomethyluridine at tRNA anticodon</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>2009</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19446527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scrima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vetter</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Armengod</surname><given-names>M-E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittinghofer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure of the TrmE GTP-binding protein and its implications for tRNA modification</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15616586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saigo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taurine as a constituent of mitochondrial tRNAs: new insights into the functions of taurine and human mitochondrial diseases</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>6581</fpage><lpage>6589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12456664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yukawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shindo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondria-specific RNA-modifying enzymes responsible for the biosynthesis of the wobble base in mitochondrial tRNAs: implications for the molecular pathogenesis of human mitochondrial diseases</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>1613</fpage><lpage>1624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15509579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Datsenko</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One-step inactivation of chromosomal genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 using PCR products</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>6640</fpage><lpage>6645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10829079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Himeno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Asahara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro study of <italic>E. coli</italic> tRNA(Arg) and tRNA(Lys) identity elements</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1992</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2335</fpage><lpage>2339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1375736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emilsson</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurland</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth rate dependence of transfer RNA abundance in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>1990</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>4359</fpage><lpage>4366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2265611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gehrke</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribonucleoside analysis by reversed-phase high-performance liquid chromatography</article-title><source>J Chromatogr.</source><year>1989</year><volume>471</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2670985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Droogmans</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roovers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of enzymatic activity of transfer RNA modification enzymes using radiolabeled tRNA substrates</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>425</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17673079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scrima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittinghofer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dimerisation-dependent GTPase reaction of MnmE: how potassium acts as GTPase-activating element</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2940</fpage><lpage>2951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16763562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of GTPase activity of TrmE, a member of a novel GTPase superfamily, from <italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic></article-title><source>J. Bacteriol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>7078</fpage><lpage>7082</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11092873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scrima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vers&#x000e9;es</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittinghofer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structures of the conserved tRNA-modifying enzyme GidA: implications for its interaction with MnmE and substrate</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>380</volume><fpage>532</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18565343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishimasu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishitani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwashita</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nureki</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atomic structure of a folate/FAD-dependent tRNA T54 methyltransferase</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>8180</fpage><lpage>8185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19416846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbonavicius</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Skouloubris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Myllykallio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a novel gene encoding a flavin-dependent tRNA:m5U methyltransferase in bacteria: evolutionary implications</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>3955</fpage><lpage>3964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16027442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbonavicius</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brochier-Armanet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Skouloubris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Myllykallio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosjean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro detection of the enzymatic activity of folate-dependent tRNA (Uracil-54,-C5)-methyltransferase: evolutionary implications</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>425</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17673080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Cr&#x000e9;cy-Lagard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>El Yacoubi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Garza</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Noiriel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of bacterial and plant folate synthesis and salvage: predictions and validations</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>245</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17645794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finer-Moore</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Santi</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroud</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lessons and conclusions from dissecting the mechanism of a bisubstrate enzyme: thymidylate synthase mutagenesis, function, and structure</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12525151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decoster</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vassal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mss1, a nuclear-encoded mitochondrial GTPase involved in the expression of cox1 subunit of cytochrome-coxidase</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1993</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8392589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colby</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzagoloff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MTO1 codes for a mitochondrial protein required for respiration in paromomycin-resistant mutants of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>27945</fpage><lpage>27952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9774408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A human mitochondrial GTP binding protein related to tRNA modification may modulate phenotypic expression of the deafness-associated mitochondrial 12S rRNA mutation</article-title><source>Mol. Cell Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>7701</fpage><lpage>7711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12370316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of the putative nuclear modifier gene MTO1 involved in the pathogenesis of deafness-associated mitochondrial 12 S rRNA A1555G mutation</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>27256</fpage><lpage>27264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cabedo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Maci&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Villarroya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Escudero</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Vicente</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Knecht</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Armengod</surname><given-names>M-E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> trmE (mnmE) gene, involved in tRNA modification, codes for an evolutionarily conserved GTPase with unusual biochemical properties</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>7063</fpage><lpage>7076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10601028</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>