<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2229-9-144</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995436</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-9-144</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cytosolic N-terminal arginine-based signals together with a luminal signal target a type II membrane protein to the plant ER</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Boulaflous</surname><given-names>Aur&#x000e9;lia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>aboulaflous@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Saint-Jore-Dupas</surname><given-names>Claude</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Claude.Saint-Jore@univ-rouen.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Herranz-Gordo</surname><given-names>Marie-Carmen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>carmen.herranz@ibmp-ulp.u-strasbg.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Pagny-Salehabadi</surname><given-names>Sophie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Sophie.Pagny@univ-rouen.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Plasson</surname><given-names>Carole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Carole.plasson@univ-rouen.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Garidou</surname><given-names>Fr&#x000e9;d&#x000e9;ric</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>frederic.garidou@univ-rouen.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7"><name><surname>Kiefer-Meyer</surname><given-names>Marie-Christine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Marie-Christine.Kiefer-Meyer@univ-rouen.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8"><name><surname>Ritzenthaler</surname><given-names>Christophe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>christophe.ritzenthaler@ibmp-ulp.u-strasbg.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9"><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>Lo&#x000ef;c</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>lfaye@crihan.fr</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A10"><name><surname>Gomord</surname><given-names>V&#x000e9;ronique</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>vgomord@crihan.fr</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Laboratoire GLYCAD, IFRMP 23, Universit&#x000e9; de Rouen, 76821 Mont Saint Aignan Cedex, France</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Institut de Biologie Mol&#x000e9;culaire des plantes, 12 rue du G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;ral Zimmer, 67084 Strasbourg Cedex, France</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2009 Boulaflous et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Boulaflous et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/9/144"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>In eukaryotic cells, the membrane compartments that constitute the exocytic pathway are traversed by a constant flow of lipids and proteins. This is particularly true for the endoplasmic reticulum (ER), the main "gateway of the secretory pathway", where biosynthesis of sterols, lipids, membrane-bound and soluble proteins, and glycoproteins occurs. Maintenance of the resident proteins in this compartment implies they have to be distinguished from the secretory cargo. To this end, they must possess specific ER localization determinants to prevent their exit from the ER, and/or to interact with receptors responsible for their retrieval from the Golgi apparatus. Very few information is available about the signal(s) involved in the retention of membrane type II protein in the ER but it is generally accepted that sorting of ER type II cargo membrane proteins depends on motifs mainly located in their cytosolic tails.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Here, using <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>glucosidase I as a model, we have identified two types of signals sufficient for the location of a type II membrane protein in the ER. A first signal is located in the luminal domain, while a second signal corresponds to a short amino acid sequence located in the cytosolic tail of the membrane protein. The cytosolic tail contains at its N-terminal end four arginine residues constitutive of three di-arginine motifs (RR, RXR or RXXR) independently sufficient to confer ER localization. Interestingly, when only one di-arginine motif is present, fusion proteins are located both in the ER and in mobile punctate structures, distinct but close to Golgi bodies. Soluble and membrane ER protein markers are excluded from these punctate structures, which also do not colocalize with an ER-exit-site marker. It is hypothesized they correspond to sites involved in Golgi to ER retrotransport.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Altogether, these results clearly show that cytosolic and luminal signals responsible for ER retention could coexist in a same type II membrane protein. These data also suggest that both retrieval and retention mechanisms govern protein residency in the ER membrane. We hypothesized that mobile punctate structures not yet described at the ER/Golgi interface and tentatively named GERES, could be involved in retrieval mechanisms from the Golgi to the ER.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>In eukaryotic cells, the membrane compartments that constitute of the exocytic pathway are traversed by a constant flow of lipids and proteins. This is particularly true for the endoplasmic reticulum (ER), the main "gateway of the secretory pathway" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], where biosynthesis of sterols, lipids, membrane-bound and soluble proteins, and glycoproteins occurs. Maintenance of the resident proteins in this compartment implies they have to be distinguished from the secretory cargo. To this end, they must possess specific ER localization determinants to prevent their exit from the ER, and/or to interact with receptors responsible for their retrieval from the Golgi apparatus. The tetrapeptide H/KDEL is the best characterized signal contributing to the accumulation of most soluble protein in the ER lumen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Specific recognition of this tetrapeptide sequence by the ERD2-like receptor, in post-ER compartments, initiates the formation of COPI-coated vesicles, which transport the H/KDEL-containing soluble proteins selectively from the Golgi back to the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><p>Retrieval mechanisms from the Golgi to the ER are also responsible for ER location of some type I and II transmembrane proteins, in animals cells by interaction with subunits of the COPI machinery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref> for membrane protein topology). Indeed, sorting of ER membrane residents depends on the specific interaction of motifs mainly located in their cytoplasmic tails. For instance, many type I membrane proteins located in the ER bear a di-lysine motif (K(X)KXX) in their C-terminal cytosolic tail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. In addition, the efficiency of a di-lysine motif for ER localisation of transmembrane proteins in cells has also been described in mammals, yeasts and plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], suggesting a conservation of the machinery. The di-lysine motifs can either act as direct retention signals or through a retrieval mechanism from the Golgi often associated with the acquisition of Golgi-specific carbohydrate modifications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Some sequence flexibility can be observed concerning the dibasic motif(s) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], in particular, lysine residues within non-type I membrane proteins are sometimes substituted by arginine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Moreover, the amino acids (aa) flanking the di-lysine motif are important; since serine or alanine residues generally favor efficient retention while the proximity of glycine or proline residues completely disrupts ER retention capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Finally, di-lysine ER-retention/retrieval signals require a strict spacing relative to the C-terminus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p><p>On the other hand, some ER-resident membrane proteins contain a di-arginine motif acting as a retention/retrieval signal in animal cells. This motif is made of either two consecutive arginine residues located at position 2-3, 3-4, 4-5 with respect to the N-terminus of the protein or of arginine residues separated by an amino acid and located at position 2-4, 3-5. This motif was first described in yeast for signal-mediated retrieval of type II membrane proteins from the Golgi to the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. It is now generally admitted that di-arginine motifs are much more frequent than di-lysine motifs. They are found in a variety of cytosolic positions, including loops, at the C- and N- terminal end of type I and II membrane proteins respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Like the di-lysine motif, the di-arginine motif efficiency is influenced by surrounding residues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Structural analysis of N-linked glycans revealed a Golgi-to-ER retrograde transport mechanism for ER membrane glycoproteins containing a di-arginine motif indicating they act as ER retrieval signals as described for most di-lysine motifs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p><p>Several other motifs have occasionally been described for ER retention of membrane proteins in eukaryotic cells. For instance the diphenylalanine (FF) motif, present in type I proteins of the p24 family, is essential for COPI coat protein interactions triggering Golgi to ER retrograde transport [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Similarly, Cosson et <italic>al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] identified a new COPI-binding motif containing a critical aromatic residue involved in ER retrieval.</p><p>In addition to retrieval mechanisms, the strict retention of ER-resident proteins has also been investigated. It was shown for Sec12p (a type II ER membrane protein), that the TMD is responsible for recycling whereas the cytosolic tail is involved in strict retention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. ER residency by direct retention can be also accomplished by oligomerization of protein subunits into large complexes, <italic>via </italic>their transmembrane and/or the luminal domains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. It is important to note that both mechanisms, retention and retrieval, are not exclusive and can function either in parallel or in combination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p><p>In plants, few molecular signals responsible for protein residency in the ER have been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. For soluble proteins, K/HDEL is largely predominant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. For type I membrane proteins, signals include C-terminal di-lysine motifs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>], the aromatic aa-enriched ER retrieval signal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and the length of the TMD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. To our knowledge, so far, no information is available concerning signals responsible for type II membrane protein residency in the plant ER.</p><p>Alpha-glucosidase I is the first enzyme involved in the N-glycan maturation. This glycosidase removes the distal &#x003b1;-1,2-linked glucose residue from the oligosaccharide precursor, just after its transfer "en bloc" on the nascent protein. The function and consequently the location of this type II membrane protein in the ER is essential for plant development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>].</p><p>In a previous study, we have shown that <italic>A. thaliana </italic>glucosidase I (<italic>At</italic>GCSI) is located exclusively in the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. This localization is consistent with a trimming of the first glucose residue from the precursor oligosaccharide. Here, the analysis of the N-terminus of this glycosidase has allowed the identification of two independent types of signals conferring ER residency to a type II membrane protein. Thus, di-arginine-based motifs initially located in the cytosolic face of <italic>At</italic>GCSI are sufficient to confer ER residency of a membrane reporter protein. As the presence of a second type of signal in the luminal part of <italic>At</italic>GCSI is also sufficient for ER retention, we propose that the arginine-based motifs may act as salvage signals to localize the full-length protein in this compartment.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>The cytosolic tail of <italic>At</italic>GCSI contains ER targeting information</title><p>The cytosolic region of many membrane proteins residing in the mammalian and yeast ER contains signals which facilitate either their strict retention in the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] or their retrieval from the Golgi to the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. In plants, only very few studies refer to the characterization of cytosolic motifs responsible for membrane protein retention in the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>].</p><p>With the aim to identify a conserved ER targeting motif in the cytosolic tails of the different GCSI cloned so far, we aligned their sequences (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The size of GCSI cytosolic tail is very different from one species to another varying from 11 aa in <italic>Neurospora crassa </italic>to 62 aa in <italic>Oriza sativa</italic>. However, in each case, the cytosolic tail is very polar, arginine and lysine residues being largely represented. In particular, arginine blocks near the N-terminal end are identified in six out of twelve GCSI sequences. This block was shown to contain ER trafficking information in human GCSI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of the cytosolic tail sequence and transmembrane domain length of glucosidases I cloned from different species</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Organism</th><th align="right">Cytosolic tail sequence</th><th align="right">TMD length</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic><break/><underline>AJ278990</underline></td><td align="right"><monospace>MTGAS<bold>RR</bold>SA<bold>R</bold>G<bold>R</bold>I<bold>K</bold>SSSLSPGSDEGSAYPPSI<bold>RR</bold>G<bold>K</bold>G<bold>K</bold>ELVSIGAFKTNL<bold>K</bold></monospace></td><td align="right">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Oryza sativa</italic><break/>BAB86175.1</td><td align="right"><monospace>MSGGGGSSSV<bold>RR</bold>PVAAA<bold>R</bold>S<bold>R</bold>SGPEPDA<bold>RR</bold>AAAAAAAAAAAAA<bold>RRR</bold>G<bold>R</bold>GDHGPL<bold>R</bold>LMEVSPRN</monospace></td><td align="right">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Neurospora crassa</italic><break/>CAC18158.1</td><td align="right"><monospace>MAPPPP<bold>R</bold>QP<bold>R</bold>Q</monospace></td><td align="right">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Strongylocentrotus Purpuratus</italic><break/>XP_797552.1</td><td align="right"><monospace>&#x0003e;MAA<bold>R</bold>T<bold>R</bold>IADSGGGA<bold>R</bold>S<bold>R</bold>ET<bold>K</bold>T<bold>K</bold>P<bold>K</bold>SGNGAQS<bold>R</bold>NNETQSSS<bold>K</bold>N</monospace></td><td align="right">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Danio rerio</italic><break/><italic>XP_696318.1</italic></td><td align="right"><monospace>MG<bold>RRRKR</bold>VATGDGVPSP<bold>RK</bold>EE<bold>K</bold>APAPP<bold>RK</bold>E<bold>KKKK</bold>TDIG<bold>K</bold></monospace></td><td align="right">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Apis melifera</italic><break/>XP_623340.1</td><td align="right"><monospace>MSILNISITVLCIAIATWFSY<bold>K</bold>GYLET<bold>R</bold>VNTPYDI<bold>KK</bold>LVTIS</monospace></td><td align="right">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic><break/>XP_972740.1</td><td align="right"><monospace>MA<bold>R</bold>Q<bold>RR</bold>TQGAADPN<bold>K</bold>GTNSSSSNGSNSTNN<bold>R</bold>SS<bold>K</bold>STS</monospace></td><td align="right">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Enchytraeus japonensis</italic><break/>BAE93517.1</td><td align="right"><monospace>MA<bold>KKK</bold>VP<bold>R</bold>E<bold>K</bold>NHSGGTT<bold>RR</bold>TSESSSNNHADS<bold>KR</bold>QI<bold>R</bold>I<bold>K</bold>LNE<bold>KRKR</bold>QEPGS<bold>K</bold></monospace></td><td align="right">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic><break/>NP_502053.1</td><td align="right"><monospace>MH<bold>R</bold>EHEEMHQPS<bold>RRRR</bold>PP<bold>R</bold>EVE<bold>R</bold>PSATI<bold>R</bold>YEPVAEPEPWCSFCSWD</monospace></td><td align="right">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Homo sapiens</italic><break/>NP_006293.2</td><td align="right"><monospace><underline>MA<bold>R</bold>GE<bold>RRRR</bold>A</underline>VPAEGV<bold>R</bold>TAE<bold>R</bold>AA<bold>R</bold>GGPG<bold>RR</bold>DG<bold>R</bold>GGGP<bold>R</bold></monospace></td><td align="right">21</td></tr><tr><td/><td align="right">-60 -50 -40 -30 -20 -10 -1</td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Numbers below the cytosolic tail sequences indicate the position from the transmembrane domain (TMD). Bold letters highlight the importance of arginine (R) and lysine (K) residues. Note underlined sequence from <italic>H. sapiens </italic>retains a reporter membrane protein in the ER in plant cell.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><italic>At</italic>GCSI is an ER type II membrane protein, composed of a 51 aa cytosolic tail (CT), a 18 aa transmembrane domain (TMD) and a large 783 aa C-terminal domain (CD) oriented in the lumen of the ER and containing the catalytic site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). As illustrated (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2AB</xref>), we have shown in a previous work that the first 90 aa (CT+TMD+ 30 aa of the stem) located at the N-terminal end of the <italic>At</italic>GCSI, are sufficient to retain a reporter protein in the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. The <italic>At</italic>GCSI cytosolic domain of 51 aa contains six arginine residues including four arginines located at position 6, 7, 10 and 12 and a doublet at the position 33,34 relative to the N-terminal end.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Schematic representation of the fusion proteins analyzed in this study</bold>. <italic>At</italic>GCSI: full-length <italic>A. thaliana </italic>&#x003b1;-glucosidase I fused to GFP. &#x00394;13GCSI: GCSI minus the first 13 N-terminal aa (MTGASRRSARGRI-). GCS150: the first 150 aa of GCSI fused to GFP. GCS90: the first 90 aa of GCSI fused to GFP or mRFP. &#x00394;13GCS150: GCS150 minus the first 13 N-terminal aa. &#x00394;13GCS90: GCS90 minus the first 13 N-terminal aa. Hs10-&#x00394;13GCS90: the first 10 N-terminal aa of <italic>Homo sapiens </italic>GCSI (MARGERRRRA-) fused at the N-terminus of &#x00394;13GCS90. XYLT35: the first 35 aa of <italic>A. thaliana </italic>&#x003b2;-1,2-xylosyltransferase fused to GFP or mRFP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum60</italic>: the first 35 aa of XYLT fused to the first 60 aa of the luminal domain of GCSI (Pro91 to Cys150) and to GFP. XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum81</italic>: the first 35 aa of XYLT fused to the first 81 aa of luminal domain of GCSI (Arg70 to Cys150) and to GFP. GCS13-XYLT35: the 13 first N-terminal aa of GCSI fused to XYLT35. ST-mRFP: the first 52 aa of a rat &#x003b1;-2,6-sialyltransferase (ST) fused to mRFP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>]. mRFP-HDEL: mRFP under the control of the sporamine signal peptide and the HDEL ER retention sequence. CT: cytosolic tail; TMD: transmembrane domain; CD: C-terminal domain.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>The 13 first N-terminal amino acids of <italic>At</italic>GCSI contain ER targeting information</bold>. CLSM analysis of transgenic tobacco BY-2 cells showing cortical views (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>C</bold>) or cross sections (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>D</bold>). (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>B</bold>) GCS90 accumulates in the ER in BY-2 suspension-cultured cells. (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>D</bold>) &#x00394;13GCS90 accumulates into the Golgi apparatus. Bars = 8 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-2"/></fig><p>To define more precisely the sequence in the cytosolic tail of <italic>At</italic>GCSI containing ER location information, the first 13 aa located at the N-terminal end of GCS90 were deleted and the resulting chimeric protein was named &#x00394;13GCS90 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). This truncation removed potential dibasic motifs RR or RXR that might function in ER localization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>], while others (RR or KXK) remained in the cytosolic tail of this fusion protein. When expressed in tobacco BY-2 cells or leaf epidermal cells, &#x00394;13GCS90 was found into bright spots (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2CD</xref>) that colocalized with the Golgi marker ST-mRFP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A-C</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] but no longer localized with the mRFP-HDEL ER marker (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). These results indicate that the first 13 aa of <italic>At</italic>GCSI are required for GCS90 accumulation in the ER.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Arginine-rich ER targeting sequences are conserved for GCSI between kingdoms</bold>. CLSM analysis of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum </italic>leaf epidermal cells expressing GFP fusions alone (left panels), or co-expressing GFP fusions and either the ER marker mRFP-HDEL (middle panels), or the Golgi marker ST-mRFP (right panels). &#x00394;13GCS90 (<bold>A</bold>-<bold>C</bold>) is exclusively located in the Golgi and perfectly co-localizes with ST-mRFP (<bold>C</bold>). XYLT35 is also located in the Golgi (<bold>D</bold>-<bold>F</bold>); [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. When GCS13-XYLT35 (<bold>G</bold>) is co-expressed with mRFP-HDEL, the ER appears in yellow and the Golgi remains green (<bold>H</bold>) whereas when GCS13-XYLT35 is co-expressed with ST-mRFP the Golgi is yellow and the ER is green (<bold>I</bold>) showing GCS13-XYLT35 has a dual location in the ER and in the Golgi. Interestingly, when the first 13 N-terminal amino acids of GCS90 are replaced by the first 10 N-terminal amino acids of the human GCSI, Hs10&#x00394;13GCS90 is located exclusively in the ER (<bold>J</bold>) as illustrated from colocalization with mRFP-HDEL (<bold>K</bold>) and the absence of overlap for GFP and RFP signals when it is co-expressed with ST-mRFP (<bold>L</bold>). This together with data presented <bold>Table 1 </bold>suggests that arginine-rich ER targeting sequences are conserved for GCSI between kingdoms. Bars = 8 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-3"/></fig><p>In order to determine whether this 13 aa peptide sequence affects the targeting a Golgi-resident membrane protein, it was fused to the Golgi marker XYLT35 to give GCS13-XYLT35 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). As illustrated in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D-F</xref>, XYLT35 resides exclusively in the Golgi apparatus and it was previously shown to preferentially accumulate in the medial Golgi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. In contrast, GCS13-XYLT35 was found as a bright network (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G-I</xref>) that colocalized with the mRFP-HDEL ER marker (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3H</xref>) and was very similar to the pattern observed for GCS90 (compare to Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2AB</xref>). In addition to this strong ER labeling, a few bright spots were also occasionally observed when GCS13-XYLT35 was expressed (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3H</xref>). These spots proved to be dynamic and colocalized partially with the late Golgi marker ST-mRFP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4I</xref>) indicating location in the early Golgi (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3I</xref>), [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>].</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>The N-terminal arginine residues of <italic>At</italic>GCSI contain ER localization information</bold>. CLSM analysis of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum </italic>leaf epidermal cells expressing GFP fusions alone (left panels), or co-expressing GFP fusions and the ER marker mRFP-HDEL (middle panels), or co-expressing GFP fusions together with the Golgi marker ST-mRFP (right panels). GCS90 (<bold>A</bold>) co-localizes with mRFP-HDEL (<bold>B</bold>, ER in yellow) but not with ST-mRFP (<bold>C</bold>, ER in green, Golgi in red). When the four arginine residues in position 6, 7, 10 and 12 are replaced by alanine or leucine residues, R/A GCS90 (<bold>D</bold>-<bold>F</bold>) or R/L GCS90 (<bold>G</bold>-<bold>I</bold>) accumulates exclusively in the Golgi showing that arginine residues are involved in <italic>At</italic>GCSI ER localization. Bars = 8 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-4"/></fig><p>In conclusions, we show here that the first 13 aa of <italic>At</italic>GCSI are necessary to retain the GCS90 fusion protein in the ER and sufficient to relocate a medial Golgi marker mainly to the ER and to a lesser extent the early-Golgi.</p></sec><sec><title>A cytosolic arginine-rich sequence is an ER targeting signal in plants</title><p>In order to further investigate whether another arginine-rich sequence could replace the 13 N-terminal aa of <italic>At</italic>GCSI responsible for ER retention, this peptide was replaced by the first 10 amino-terminal residues of human GCSI and the resulting fusion was named Hs10&#x00394;13GCS90 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). After transient expression in tobacco leaf epidermal cells, Hs10&#x00394;13GCS90 localized in the ER (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3J-L</xref>), thus demonstrating that the N-terminal arginine-rich cytosolic sequence of human GCSI is functional in plants. Similarly, the C-terminal arginine-rich cytosolic tail of <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>calnexin, a type I membrane protein changed the localization of the type II &#x00394;13GCS90 from the Golgi to the ER (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>)</p></sec><sec><title>Arginine residues in the cytosolic tail of <italic>At</italic>GCSI contain ER localization information</title><p>In order to define whether arginine residues within the first 13 aa of GCS90 play a key role in ER targeting, these residues were first replaced by either leucine or alanine residues using site-directed mutagenesis (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> for the construct details) and the resulting fusion proteins were expressed in tobacco cells.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Sub-cellular localization of GCS90 after arginine (R) substitutions in the cytosolic tail.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Mutants </th><th align="right">Cytosolic domain</th><th align="right">Sub-cellular localization </th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td/><td align="right">6 7 10 12</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left">GCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T G A S <bold>R R </bold>S A <bold>R </bold>G <bold>R </bold>I K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">ER</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x00394;13GCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">Golgi</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hs10&#x00394;13GCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M A R G E <bold>R R R R </bold>A K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">ER</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GCS13-XYLT35</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T A G A S <bold>R R </bold>S A <bold>R </bold>G <bold>R </bold>I-10aa</monospace></td><td align="right">ER + GA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CNX11-XYLT35</td><td align="right"><monospace>M N D <bold>R R </bold>P Q <bold>R </bold>K <bold>R </bold>P A-10aa</monospace></td><td align="right">ER + GA</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">R/L<sub>6-7</sub>GCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T G A S L L S A <bold>R </bold>G <bold>R </bold>I K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">ER + punctate structures</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R/L<sub>10-12</sub>GCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T G A S <bold>R R </bold>S A L G L I K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">ER + punctate structures</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R/L<sub>6-12</sub>GCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T G A S L <bold>R </bold>S A <bold>R </bold>G L I K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">ER + punctate structures</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R/L<sub>6-10</sub>GCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T G A S L <bold>R </bold>S A L G <bold>R </bold>I K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">ER +GA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R/L<sub>7-12</sub>GCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T G A S <bold>R </bold>L S A <bold>R </bold>G L I K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">Golgi +ER</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R/L<sub>7-10</sub>GCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T G A S <bold>R </bold>L S A L G <bold>R </bold>I K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">Golgi</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R/AGCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T G A S A A S A A G A I K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">Golgi</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R/LGCS90</td><td align="right"><monospace>M T G A S L L S A L G L I K S S S L-32aa</monospace></td><td align="right">Golgi</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>GCS90 is exclusively located in the ER (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>) and perfectly co-localizes with the ER marker mRFP-HDEL (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>), but not with the late Golgi marker ST-mRFP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). When arginine residues, in position 6, 7 10 and 12 (R<sub>6</sub>, R<sub>7</sub>, R<sub>10 </sub>and R<sub>12</sub>, respectively) were all replaced by alanine residues, GCS90 mutant (R/AGCS90) was found to accumulate exclusively in the Golgi apparatus as illustrated from its co-localization with ST-mRFP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D-F</xref>). The same effects on sub-cellular localization were observed for R/L GCS90 after substitution of the four arginine residues by leucines, (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4G-I</xref>). These observations indicate that four arginines in position 6-7-10 and 12 present in the cytosolic tail of <italic>At</italic>GCSI encode information necessary for ER residency of membrane reporter protein.</p><p>To further dissect this cytosolic signal, an exhaustive pair-wise leucine scanning mutagenesis of all four arginine residues was performed and results related to the location of the mutants in tobacco leaf epidermal cells are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. All mutations affected the localization of GCS90. Thus, R/L<sub>6-7</sub>GCS90 and R/L<sub>10-12</sub>GSC90 were found in the ER (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A, I</xref>) and in additional punctate structures (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B, H</xref>, arrows) that appear distinct from Golgi stacks (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D-F</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5I</xref>). Similar results were obtained for R/L<sub>6-12</sub>GCS90 (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>). Remarkably, the mRFP-HDEL soluble and the GSC90-mRFP membrane ER markers were excluded from these punctate structures (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B-C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5H</xref>). Finally, Constructs in which mutated arginine residues were distant by more than two aa (R/L<sub>6-10</sub>; R/L<sub>7-12</sub>; R/L<sub>7-10</sub>) all displayed a strict Golgi (illustrated with R/L<sub>7-10</sub>, Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3GH</xref>) or a dual Golgi-ER pattern (illustrated with R/L<sub>6-10 </sub>Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3CD</xref>; or with R/L<sub>7-12 </sub>Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3EF</xref>,). These findings indicate that a cytosolic RR or RXR or RXXR motif is sufficient to confer ER residency to a membrane reporter protein.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Punctate structures do not accumulate ER resident proteins and are distinct from Golgi stacks</bold>. When arginine residues are mutated by pairs, R/L<sub>6-7</sub>GCS90 (<bold>A</bold>-<bold>I</bold>) and R/L<sub>10-12</sub>GCS90 (<bold>G</bold>-<bold>K</bold>) are located in the ER (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>G</bold>). Co-expression with soluble ER marker mRFP-HDEL (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>H</bold>) or membrane (<bold>C</bold>) ER marker GCS90-mRFP reveals those markers are excluded from the punctate structures that appear in green (arrows). Punctate structures are closely associated to Golgi stacks labelled with the <italic>cis</italic>-Golgi marker Man99-mRFP (<bold>D</bold>), the medial Golgi marker XYLT35-mRFP (<bold>E</bold>) or <italic>trans</italic>-Golgi marker ST-mRFP (<bold>F</bold>, <bold>I</bold>). When the constructs highlighting punctate structures are co-expressed together with the ER marker mRFP-HDEL and the Golgi marker ST-mRFP, the ER and the punctate structures appear in yellow (<bold>J</bold>). When zooming, micrograph suggests punctate structures can be closed to the ER (<bold>K</bold>, top and bottom arrows). Zone I corresponds to the co-localization area between a punctate structure and a Golgi whereas zone II corresponds to the Golgi only (<bold>K</bold>, insert). Arrows indicate the punctate structures.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Towards the characterization of punctate structures labeled after arginine substitution</title><p>Considering that fusion proteins harboring only one di-arginine motif: RR, RXR or RXXR accumulate in the ER and in punctate structures associated with the Golgi, the next challenge was to identify the nature of these fluorescent punctate structures from which the ER markers are excluded. Coexpression of R/L<sub>10-12</sub>GCS90 with an ER and a Golgi marker simultaneously, revealed that the punctate structures are closely associated but nevertheless distinct and smaller than Golgi stacks (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5JK</xref> and insert). Interestingly, units formed by association of one dictyosome and one punctate structure move together along the ER and never dissociate (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). Considering these observations, we propose that punctate structures are small intermediate domains located between the ER and the Golgi, from which ER resident soluble or membrane proteins are excluded (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>).</p><p>Based on the observation that punctate structures are strongly associated with the Golgi and move together with the Golgi stacks along the ER cortical network, we speculated first that they could correspond to ER-exit-sites (ERES) initially described by daSilva et <italic>al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>].</p><p>It was previously shown that a GTP-locked form of Sar1p accumulates to ERES [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>] and exerts a dominant negative effect on protein secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. When Sar1p-mRFP or Sar1p-GTP-mRFP were expressed alone, they were both located to the cytoplasm and to the ER (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6AB</xref>, <bold>respectively</bold>) but the ER morphology was different. Indeed, Sar1p GTP blocking ER exit, R/LGCS90 was found in the ER and in the Golgi when expressed together with the GTP-locked form of Sar1p (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>), and, as a consequence, the ER membranes turned into a lamellar sheet. In addition, Sar1p-GTP-mRFP and GCS90 perfectly co-localised (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D-F</xref>). To test if the small punctate structures were sensitive to an ER exit blockage, R/L<sub>6-7</sub>GCS90 and R/L<sub>10-12</sub>GCS90 were co-expressed with Sar1p-GTP-mRFP (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6G-I</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6J-L</xref>). Interestingly, no punctate structures were observed showing that the presence of punctate structures depends on active COPII machinery.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Sar1p-GTP regulates ER to Golgi traffic of GCS90 and induces the disappearance of the punctate structures</bold>. CLSM analysis of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum </italic>leaf epidermal cells expressing GFP-fusions simultaneously with Sar1p variants. Sar1p-mRFP (<bold>A</bold>) and Sar1p-GTP-mRFP (<bold>B</bold>) are accumulated at the ER. Because Sar1p-GTP-mRFP blocks ER exit, membrane proteins accumulate in the ER and the ER membrane morphology turns into fenestrated sheets (<bold>B</bold>). In presence of Sar1p-GTP-mRFP, the Golgi fusion R/LGCS90 is blocked in the ER (<bold>C</bold>, compare with pattern presented <bold>Figure 5G</bold>). When GCS90 (<bold>D</bold>-<bold>F</bold>), R/L<sub>6-7</sub>GCS90 (<bold>G</bold>-<bold>I</bold>) or R/L<sub>10-12</sub>GCS90(<bold>J</bold>-<bold>L</bold>) are co-expressed with Sar1p-GTP-mRFP, the expression patterns remain unchanged, (compare to <bold>Figure 7G-I, A-C </bold>and <bold>D-F</bold>, respectively), except that the punctate structures have disappeared. Bars = 8 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-6"/></fig><p>The drug BFA blocks COPI-mediated retrograde transport. Thus, if the punctate structures were sensitive to BFA, this would suggest they are likely to be involved in retrograde Golgi to ER traffic. To test this hypothesis, cells co-expressing R/L<sub>6-7</sub>GCS90 or R/L<sub>10-12</sub>GCS90 and mRFP-HDEL were incubated for 2 h in the presence of BFA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7G-I</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7M-O</xref> respectively). In both cases, the ER turned into a lamellar pattern and the punctate structures disappeared (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7J-L</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7P-R</xref>). As a control, we have observed BFA-induced redistribution of R/LGCS90 in the ER (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A-F</xref>). Together, these results indicate that inhibition of COPI-mediated retrograde transport by BFA abolishes the formation of punctate structures.</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Punctate structures diappear when COPI-mediated retrograde transport is inhibited with BFA</bold>. CLSM analysis of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum </italic>leaf epidermal cells co-expressing GFP-fusions and mRFP-HDEL. Control cells co-expressing R/LGCS90 and mRFP-HDEL show green Golgi stacks and a red ER (-BFA, panels <bold>A</bold>-<bold>C</bold>). When cells are treated with BFA for 2 h, Golgi membranes are reabsorbed in the ER and the ER appears in yellow (+BFA, panels <bold>D</bold>-<bold>F</bold>). When cells co-expressing R/L<sub>6-7</sub>GCS90 (<bold>G</bold>-<bold>L</bold>) or R/L<sub>10-12</sub>GCS90 (<bold>M</bold>-<bold>R</bold>) and mRFP-HDEL are treated with BFA for 2 h, punctate structures disappear (<bold>J</bold>-<bold>L </bold>and <bold>P</bold>-<bold>R </bold>respectively).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-7"/></fig><p>In conclusion, different GCS90 mutants harboring only one RR, RXR or RXXR motif accumulate in the ER and in punctate structures that do not contain ER soluble or membrane resident proteins, move together with the Golgi, but are not formed in the presence of Sar1p-GTP and disappear in the presence of BFA. Based on these results, our hypothesis is that these punctate structures could be involved in Golgi to ER retrograde transport.</p></sec><sec><title>A luminal sequence in <italic>At</italic>GCSI also contains ER retention information</title><p>We have shown above that cytosolic arginine-motifs are sufficient to confer ER-residency to a Golgi reporter protein and their removal changes the localization of GCS90 from the ER to the Golgi. However, we observed that the deletion of the first N-terminal 13 aa from the full-length sequence of <italic>At</italic>GCSI (&#x00394;13GCSI- Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>), does not modify the location of the <italic>At</italic>GCSI. The accumulation of &#x00394;13GCSI in the ER shows that the arginine motifs are not necessary for ER residency of the full-length <italic>At</italic>GCSI protein and suggests that other ER retention signals must exist.</p><p>After successive deletion at the C-terminal end of &#x00394;13GCSI, we have shown that, in contrast with the Golgi location of &#x00394;13GCS90, the &#x00394;13GSC150 containing the first 150 aa of At GCSI minus the first 13 aa (&#x00394;13CT+TMD+81 aa of the stem) is detected exclusively in the ER (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref>). In order to identify the sequence responsible for ER localisation of &#x00394;13GCSI, the first 13 aa of the GCS150 were deleted and the resulting fusion protein (&#x00394;13GCS150) was expressed <italic>in N. tabacum </italic>leaf epidermal cells, where it was found exclusively in the ER (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref>), and perfectly co-localized with mRFP-HDEL (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C</xref>). In contrast, in the same conditions, &#x00394;13GCS90 was detected exclusively in the Golgi apparatus (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8EF</xref>). ER-specific targeting information is therefore contained within the <italic>At</italic>GCSI luminal domain, between the Pro 91 and Cys150.</p><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>The N-terminal arginine motifs are not the unique determinants responsible for ER retention of <italic>At</italic>GCSI</bold>. When expressed in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum </italic>leaf epidermal cells &#x00394;13GCS150-GFP is located in the ER (<bold>B</bold>) A as it was observed for the GCS150 (<bold>A</bold>) and confirmed after co-expression with the ER marker mRFP-HDEL (<bold>C</bold>). In contrast, &#x00394;13GCS90-GFP is targeted to the Golgi apparatus (<bold>E</bold>) where it colocalizes with the Golgi marker ST-mRFP (<bold>D</bold>) whereas GCS90 is accumulated in the ER (<bold>D</bold>). Bars: 8 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-8"/></fig><p>To further investigate the ER targeting capacity of its luminal domain, an 81 aa long peptide corresponding to the N-terminal part of <italic>At</italic>GCSI luminal domain (from Arg70 to Cys150) was fused at the C-terminal end of the medial-Golgi marker XYLT35 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9D-F</xref>, and the resulting fusion protein was named XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum81</italic>). A shorter 60 aa peptide corresponding to the luminal domain of <italic>At</italic>GCSI from Pro91 to Cys150, was fused to XYLT35 to generate XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum60 </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Both fusions were expressed in tobacco leaf epidermal cells. In agreement with its medial-Golgi localization, XYLT35 accumulated specifically in the Golgi (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9A-C</xref>), whereas both XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum81 </italic>and XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum60</italic>, where detected in the ER (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">9D-F, G-I</xref>). Therefore, in addition to arginine-based motifs in its cytosolic tail, <italic>At</italic>GCSI contains additional information in its luminal domain from residues Pro91 and Cys 150 that is sufficient to confer ER localization.</p><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><bold>A luminal domain of <italic>At</italic>GCSI is sufficient for targeting a Golgi marker into the ER</bold>. (<bold>A</bold>-<bold>C</bold>) XYLT35 and ST-mRFP are targeted to the Golgi when expressed in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum </italic>leaf epidermal cells. (<bold>D</bold>-<bold>F</bold>, <bold>G</bold>-<bold>I</bold>) XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum81 </italic>or XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum60 </italic>where co-expressed with ST-mRFP. Both fusion proteins containing a 81 or a 60 aa long luminal domain of <italic>At</italic>GCSI fused to the Golgi marker XYLT35 (XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum81 </italic>and XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum60 </italic>respectively) are targeted to the ER. Bars = 8 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-9"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Introduction of soluble or type I membrane proteins in the ER, is mediated by a cleavable N-terminal signal peptide. Then, ER protein localization is governed by different signals and mechanisms. It is well documented that soluble ER-resident proteins bear at their C-terminal end a H/KDEL tetrapeptide that ensure their retrieval from the Golgi apparatus to the ER when they escape to this organelle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]<italic>via </italic>the binding to a receptor named ERD2-like [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>] located throughout Golgi and in the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. In contrast, molecular signals responsible for the targeting of type I membrane proteins in the ER are not so well understood, especially in plant cells. For instance, a 17 aa TMD derived from human lysosomal protein LAMP1 was shown to mediate retention of GFP in the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. In addition, C-terminal dilysine motifs confer ER localization to type I membrane proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Finally, a C-terminal &#x003a6;XXK/R/D/E&#x003a6; motif (where &#x003a6; is a large hydrophobic aa residue) is necessary and sufficient for the localization of type III membrane &#x00394;<sup>12 </sup>oleate desaturase FAD2 to the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>For type II membrane proteins, the TMD acts as a non-cleavable signal sequence (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>) and we have recently shown that in plant cell, the 16 aa TMD of soybean mannosidase I (ManI) is sufficient to retain GFP in the ER and the <italic>cis</italic>-Golgi whereas the 18 aa TMD of <italic>At</italic>GCSI is not responsible for the residency of this glucosidase in the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. Here we investigated the signals that mediate ER localization of <italic>At</italic>GCSI, a type II membrane enzyme playing a key role in seed development, as shown by characterization of the GCSI <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>mutant which produces shrunken seeds where embryo development is blocked at the heart stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>].</p><sec><title>A cytosolic di-arginine motifs is sufficient for ER residency of a type II membrane protein</title><p>Based on the demonstration that the 13 first N-terminal aa of <italic>At</italic>GCS1 cytosolic sequence contain ER targeting information (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), we have substituted the four arginine residues in the sequence MTAGAS<underline>RR</underline>SA<underline>R</underline>G<underline>R</underline>I- with alanine or leucine residues. This mutation completely abolishes the ER retention capacity of this sequence, as R/LGCS90 and R/AGCS90 were found in the Golgi, thus demonstrating the key role of arginine residues. In addition, this 13 aa peptide was sufficient to relocalize, the medial Golgi marker XYLT35 to the ER when fused at its N-terminal end. A competition between the di-arginine motifs mediating ER localization and the TMD length of XYLT35 (23 aa), more consistent with a Golgi location, could explain why part of GCS13-XYLT35 is also detected in the Golgi apparatus.</p><p>In order to identify the minimal requirement for the ER targeting motif, the four arginine residues were mutated in pairs and it was found that two arginine residues organized as RR, RXR or RXXR motif were sufficient to confer ER residency. Consequently, three distinct di-arginine motifs sufficient for ER retention co-exist in the cytosolic tail of GCSI. In mammalian cells, N-terminal arginine residues were also shown to serve as ER signals for some type II membrane proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. For instance, the first 16 aa of human Iip33 (MH<bold>RRR</bold>S<bold>R</bold>SC<bold>R</bold>EDQKPV-) target not only Iip33 but also other type II membrane proteins to the ER and the minimal requirement for efficiency of this sequence is the presence of a diarginine RR or RXR motif [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. On the other hand, in the first 10 aa of human GCSI (MA<bold>R</bold>GE<bold>RRRR</bold>A-), a triple arginine (RRR) carries ER accumulation information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Finally, a comparison of the GCSI sequences available has shown that di-arginine motifs at the N-terminal end of these ER resident proteins are highly conserved (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>].</p><p>In mammals, arginine-rich or di-lysine ER-localization signals require a strict spacing relative to the N/C terminus and from the membrane. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. This could also explain why, too close to the transmembrane domain of <italic>At</italic>GCSI, the RR motif at position 21,22 does not confer ER localization (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). A similar situation was described when a deleted version of <italic>A. thaliana </italic>mannosidase II (ManII) containing a 10 aa cytosolic tail (MP<bold>RKR</bold>TLVVN-) was targeted to the Golgi only, despite an RXR motif in the sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. These examples suggest that position of the di-arginine motif(s) relative to the N-terminal end and/or the TMD is certainly important to consider in plants too.</p><p>Interestingly, in mammalian cells, in contrast to KK-signals, functional arginine-rich signals are found in a variety of cytosolic positions, including intracellular loops and the N- and C- termini in type II and type I membrane proteins, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]. Here, we have identified a sequence similar to the GCSI arginine-rich sequence, in the C-terminal cysosolic tail of the type I membrane protein <italic>A. thaliana </italic>calnexin (ND<bold>RR</bold>PQ<bold>R</bold>X<bold>R</bold>PA-) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>] and we have shown that this sequence has the capacity to relocate a type II Golgi protein to the ER. These results are consistent with previous data showing that the last 78 C-terminal aa of calnexin, including a 43 aa CT, a 22 aa TMD and 13 aa in the lumen, were sufficient to target GFP to the ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. All together these results suggest that cytosolic arginine-rich motifs might have a similar role for residency of type II and some type I ER membrane proteins in the ER of plant cells.</p></sec><sec><title>The luminal domain of <italic>At</italic>GCSI also contains ER targeting information</title><p>While performing successive deletions in order to identify a minimal ER targeting sequence in <italic>At</italic>GCSI, we have observed that when the 13 N-terminal aa were removed from the full length protein, &#x00394;13GCSI was still located in the ER. This result clearly shows that the arginine-rich cytosolic tail is not the only ER determinant in <italic>At</italic>GCSI. A series of deletions at the C-terminal end of &#x00394;13GCSI led us to identify a luminal sequence containing ER targeting information. When fused to XYLT35, a 60 aa luminal sequence from Pro91 to Cys150 of <italic>At</italic>GCSI is able to almost perfectly relocate this medial Golgi marker into the ER. This is the first time that an ER localization signal is shown to be contained in the luminal domain of a plant membrane protein. As mentioned above, the Golgi labeling occasionally observed with this fusion protein might be due to a competition between the ER localization sequence from <italic>At</italic>GCSI and the TMD length of XYLT35 more adapted to Golgi than ER location.</p><p>As shown here for <italic>At</italic>GCSI, some mammalian and yeast membrane proteins also contain two ER retention/retrieval signals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. For instance, in human GCSI, the CT bears a triple-arginine ER-targeting motif and the luminal domain contains an ER retention domain which is yet to be characterized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. In conclusion, at least for ER resident membrane proteins, the presence of several sequences containing ER targeting information seems to be common. Interestingly, different motifs also probably suggest a hierarchy of these signals and different targeting mechanisms and the importance for those proteins to be kept securely in the ER.</p></sec><sec><title>Several mechanisms participate to <italic>At</italic>GCSI retention in the ER</title><p>In mammalian cells, studies have shown that both retrieval and retention mechanisms govern the localization of ER membrane proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Of these two mechanisms, retrieval is better understood, and retrieval signals have been identified in the cytosolic tails of type I and type II ER resident membrane proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>]. In plants, very few data are available on retrieval of ER membrane proteins. Contreras et <italic>al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>] have shown that a KK motif in the C-terminal cytoplasmic tail of type I p24 protein is able to interact with components of the COPI machinery and to recruit ARF1 <italic>in vitro</italic>. McCartney et <italic>al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] have highlighted a dominant negative mutant of ARF1 affect the transient localisation in the Golgi of a chimera protein containing a -YNNKL motif in its cytoplasmic tail. However, mechanisms by which membrane proteins containing an arginine motif are targeted to the ER remain to be investigated. GCS90 and derivated constructs appear as excellent tools to study these mechanisms in plant cell.</p><p>The situation is complicated by the fact that retrieval mediated by arginine or lysine-motifs involves distinct machinery. For instance, a mammalian &#x003b1;-COPI isoform interacts with the KKXX motif but not with the RXR motif [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>] and there is also evidence suggesting a COPI-independent ER retrieval pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>]. On the other hand, some membrane proteins, such as the type II membrane protein Sec12p are retrieved by interaction of their TMD with the receptor rer1p [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>]. Thus, the questions concerning distinct protein sorting machineries and/or mechanisms for the different ER retrieval motifs remain to be addressed.</p><p>In addition to retrieval, a mechanism of retention <italic>sensu stricto </italic>has been described, especially for soluble ER residents. Indeed, it is now generally accepted that soluble reticuloplasmins are retained in the ER lumen of mammalian cells mainly by a mechanism of strict retention. However, when they escape this first mechanism, the ER resident proteins are retrotransported from the Golgi back to the ER by a second mechanism involving a H/KDEL C-terminal sequence and a membrane receptor named ERD2. Some data are also in favor of the presence of these two mechanisms to explain retention of reticuloplasmins in the plant ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><p>Although one could argue that ER retention is due to the absence of positive signals required for an efficient ER exit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>], it is likely that specific retention signals or features are also necessary to prevent massive access of ER-resident membrane proteins into forward carriers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>].</p><p>ER retention of type I and type II membrane proteins can be accomplished by direct association of protein subunits to give large oligomeric complexes <italic>via </italic>their TMD and/or luminal domain, as previously described in the kin-recognition model for Golgi-located membrane proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>]. This type of mechanism may be functional in the ER retention of subunit components of the hetero-oligomeric oligosaccharyltransferase complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>]. When expressed in COS cells, ER targeting information in the luminal domain of human GCSI appears to direct ER localization by retention rather than by retrieval. Evidence includes the fact that N-linked Man<sub>9</sub>-GlcNAc<sub>2 </sub>is the major glycan released from the recombinant enzyme [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. On the other hand, the co-purification of &#x003b1;-glucosidase I from either bovine mammary glands or calf liver with a large 320-350 kDa protein complex is consistent with homotetramer formation responsible for ER retention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>].</p><p>Although there is now evidence that both protein retrieval and retention mechanisms operate at the ER-Golgi interface, the question concerning the relative roles played by these different mechanisms in determining the residency of ER membrane proteins is still largely unresolved. The following targeting model could be put forward for <italic>At</italic>GCSI. We have shown that, at least, two ER localization signals are present in <italic>At</italic>GCSI and we propose that these signals correspond to different targeting mechanisms. As illustrated Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>, <italic>At</italic>GCSI would form homo- or heterooligomers (<italic>via </italic>the luminal region) that are excluded from ER domains where ERES are formed. When <italic>At</italic>GCSI monomers escaping these large complexes, are transported by default simultaneously with membrane proteins containing export signals to the Golgi <italic>via </italic>a COPII-mediated transport, <italic>At</italic>GCSI molecules arriving in the <italic>cis</italic>-Golgi interact with putative di-arginine specific receptors mediating their COPI-dependent retrotransport to the ER. The presence of punctate structures in some of the GCSI mutants is also in favor of an arginine-based retrieval.</p><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p><bold>Schematic representation of mechanisms involved in the location of type II membrane protein in the plant ER</bold>. Two mechanisms for ER localization of GCSI are proposed, one being complementary of the other. First, <italic>At</italic>GCSI resides in ER subdomains where it forms homo or hetero-oligomers with an unknown partner and is excluded from the ER export sites (ERES) (<bold>I</bold>). When <italic>At</italic>GCSI molecules escape these complexes, they move to the ERES (<bold>II</bold>) and are transported from the ER to the Golgi in a COPII dependent manner. Once in the Golgi, the COPI machinery would recognize <italic>At</italic>GCSI's cytosolic tail (<bold>III</bold>). Retrograde transport would then occur at Golgi-ER export sites (GERES) to target <italic>At</italic>GCSI back to the ER where it would form new complexes with its partners (<bold>IV</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-10"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Preliminary evidence for Golgi-ER exit sites (GERES)</title><p>In contrast to mammalian cells, transport of proteins in plants between the ER and the Golgi does not rely on the cytoskeleton but nevertheless requires energy and is regulated by various proteins such as the GTPases Sar1 and ARF1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. Forward transport of proteins is initiated in specific regions of the ER membrane called ERES (ER Exit Sites) that were visualized using fluorescent protein fusions to plant homologues of the proteins involved in the COPII-coat formation in mammalian cells, for instance Sar1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], Sec23 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>], Sec24 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>] and Sec13 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. Very recently, ERES were shown to be induced not only by membrane cargo but also by specific exit sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>]. Regarding <italic>At</italic>GCSI, when one out of the three di-arginine motifs is present in the cytosolic tail of a GCS90, fluorescence is detected not only in the ER but also in punctate structures close to- and moving with the Golgi stacks along ER tracks. Both soluble and membrane ER markers are excluded from these punctate structures. We propose that they correspond to a Golgi/ER intermediate compartment. Interestingly, we have shown that punctate structures do not colocalize with Sar1 WT and are not observed in the presence of Sar1p-GTP. However, as expected, Sar1p-GTP-mRFP exerts a dominant negative effect on protein secretion and retains the Golgi construct R/LGCS90 in the ER, showing that ER exit of R/LGCS90 is COPII-regulated, as it was previously shown for many other membrane or soluble proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. Moreover, in our expression system, punctate structures disappeared in the presence of BFA. In the same way, BFA prevented cargo-induced recruitment of Sar1p-YFP at the ERES (ERD2-GFP being the cargo) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. It remains to be elucidated whether is due to the loss of Golgi stacks or blockage of ER exit sites, the fact that punctate structures could not be seen after BFA treatment. However, these results strongly support that the punctate structures are involved in Golgi to ER traffic, therefore we propose that those structures that do not colocalize with Sar1 as described for ERES, could well be Golgi-ER Export Sites (GERES).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><italic>Arabidopsis </italic>alpha glucosidase I (<italic>At</italic>GCSI) is the first enzyme involved in the N-glycan maturation. We have previously shown that the function and consequently the location of this type II membrane protein in the ER is essential for <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>].</p><p>As illustrated Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>, we have identified two independent types of signals conferring ER residency in the <italic>At</italic>GCSI sequence. Three distinct di-arginine motifs co-existing in the cytosolic tail of <italic>At</italic>GCSI and a 60 aa luminal sequence are independently sufficient for ER retention. Interestingly, the presence of these different types of signals suggests that both retrieval and retention mechanisms govern the localization of <italic>At</italic>GCSI in the ER membrane. When only one out of the three di-arginine motifs is present, <italic>At</italic>GCSI accumulates not only in the ER but also in punctate structures not yet characterised at the ER/Golgi interface and tentatively named GERES. We hypothesised that GERES correspond to Golgi to ER export sites involved at least in arginine-based retrieval mechanisms from the Golgi back to the ER.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Glucosidase I-GFP fusions</title><p>The binary vector pBLTI121-sGFP was generated by inserting cDNA encoding sGFP without the ATG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>] as a <italic>Spe</italic>I and <italic>Stu</italic>I fragment into the binary plant transformation vector pBLTI121 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The full length <italic>At</italic>GCSI cDNA was amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using forward primer FGCSI (CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGCCGT) and reverse primer RGCSI (CG<underline>GGATCC</underline>GAAAAATAGGATAATCTTC) and sub-cloned into pBLTI121-GFP as a <italic>Kpn</italic>I or <italic>BamH</italic>I fragment.</p><p>The different glucosidase-GFP fusions were then generated by PCR using the <italic>At</italic>GCSI as template and were all fused at the N-terminal end of GFP using <italic>Kpn</italic>I and <italic>Spe</italic>I restriction sites into pBLTI121-GFP. Thirteen different GFP fusions were made. They are schematized in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> and the primers used are detailed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>. GSC150 and GCS90 correspond to the first 150 and 90 aa of <italic>At</italic>GCSI respectively fused to GFP. &#x00394;13GCS90 and &#x00394;13GCS150 derivate from GCS150 and GCS90, respectively, where the first 13 aa were deleted. Directed mutagenesis led to the replacement of the arginine residues located at the position 6, 7, 10 and/or 12 with leucine or alanine residues and the constructs were named R/LGCS90-GFP, R/AGCS90-GFP, R/L<sub>6-7</sub>GCS90-GFP, R/L<sub>10-12</sub>GCS90-GFP, R/L<sub>6-10</sub>GCS90-GFP, R/L<sub>6-12</sub>GCS90-GFP, R/L<sub>7-10</sub>GCS90-GFP and R/L<sub>7-12</sub>GCS90-GFP.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Oligonucleotides used to generate GFP fusions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Primer</th><th align="left">5'-3' sequence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td/><td align="left">At glucosidase I as template</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RGCS150</td><td align="left">G<underline>ACTAGT</underline>ACACAAATGCCGCATAAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RGCS90</td><td align="left">G<underline>ACTAGT</underline>AAAAGGAGTGATAACCCT</td></tr><tr><td align="left">F&#x00394;13GCS90/150</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGAAATCATCATCATTATCTCCC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FR/L4</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGC<bold>CTTCTG</bold>AGCGCG<bold>CTT</bold>GGT<bold>CTA</bold>ATCAAATCATCA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FR/A4</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGC<bold>GCTGCG</bold>AGCGCG<bold>GCT</bold>GGT<bold>GCA</bold>ATCAAATCATCA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FR/L6-7</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGC<bold>CTTCTG</bold>AGCGCGCGT</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FR/L10L12</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGCCGTCGGAGCGCG<bold>CTT</bold>GGT<bold>CTA</bold>ATCAAATCATCA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FR/L6L10</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGC<bold>CTT</bold>CGGAGCGCG<bold>CTT</bold>GGTCGAATCAAATCATCA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FR/L6L12</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGC<bold>CTT</bold>CGGAGCGCGCGTGGT<bold>CTA</bold>ATCAAATCATCA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FR/L7L10</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGCCGT<bold>CTG</bold>AGCGCG<bold>CTT</bold>GGTCGAATCAAATCATCA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FR/L7L12</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGCCGT<bold>CTG</bold>AGCGCGCGTGGT<bold>CTA</bold>ATCAAATCATCA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fhs10GCS90</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGGCTCGGGGCGAGCGGCGGCGCCGCGCAAA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FGCS(70-150)</td><td align="left">GG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CGGCTAGTTCGTCACGGG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FGCS(91-150)</td><td align="left">GGGGTACCCCTGCTCCGAAAGTCATG</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td/><td align="left">&#x003b2;1,2xylosyltransferase as template</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FGCS13XYLT35</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGACCGGAGCTAGCCGTCGGAGCGCGCGTGGTCGAATCAGTAAACGGAATCCGAAG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FCNX11XYLT35</td><td align="left">CGG<underline>GGTACC</underline>CCATGAATGATCGTAGACCGCAAAGGAAACGCCCAAGTAAACGGAATCCGAAG-3'</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RXYLT35</td><td align="left">GG<underline>ACTAGT</underline>TGAAAACGACGATGAGTG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FXYLT35'</td><td align="left">GC<underline>TCTAGA</underline>GCATGAGTAAACGGAATCCG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RXYLT35'</td><td align="left">GG<underline>GGTACC</underline>TGAAAACGACGATGAGTG</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The <italic>BamH</italic>I, <italic>Spe</italic>I or <italic>Kpn</italic>I restriction sites used for vector construction are underlined. Triplet codons for leucine or alanine are given in bold.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Finally, the N-terminal 13 aa of <italic>At</italic>GCSI were replaced by the N-terminal 10 aa of human hippocampus glucosidase I [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>] to obtain hs10GCS90-GFP. The reverse primer RGCS150 was used to generate GCS150-GFP and &#x00394;13GCS150, and the oligonucleotide RGCS90 was common to all the other fusions ending at aa 90.</p></sec><sec><title>&#x003b2;-1,2-xylosyltransferase-derivated GFP fusions</title><p>To obtain the fusion protein GCS13-XYLT35 or CNX11-XYLT35, nucleotides coding for the first N-terminal 13 aa of <italic>At</italic>GCSI or last C-terminal 11 aa of <italic>A. thaliana </italic>calnexin were fused to the 5' end of XYLT35 after PCR amplification and using XYLT35 cDNA as template [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Primers contain respectively a <italic>Kpn</italic>I or a <italic>Spe</italic>I site (underlined, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) to permit the cloning into pBLTI121-GFP.</p><p>Two cDNAs encoding 81 and 60 aa of the luminal predicted domain of <italic>At</italic>GCSI were fused to the 3' end of XYLT35. To generate the fusion proteins XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum81 </italic>and XYLT35-GCS<italic>lum60</italic>, the first N-terminal 35 aa of XYLT were first subcloned into pBLTI121-GFP, at the N-terminal end of GFP. Then, XYLT35 was amplified by PCR using primers FXYLT35' and RXYLT35' detailed in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, and a <italic>Xba</italic>I or <italic>Kpn</italic>I restriction site (underlined) was used to clone XYLT35 into pBLTI121-GFP. Finally, the 81 or 60 aa of predicted luminal domain of <italic>At</italic>GCSI, aa 70 to aa 150 or aa 91 to 150, were subcloned between XYLT35 and GFP using PCR reaction with <italic>At</italic>GCSI cDNA as template and forward primer FGCS80 or FGCS60 (see table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> for primer details) and reverse primer R150 (see above) with respectively <italic>Kpn</italic>I or <italic>BamH</italic>I site (underlined) to sub-clone into pBLTI121.</p></sec><sec><title>ER and Golgi red fluorescent markers</title><p>Monomeric red fluorescent protein (mRFP) was cloned in pCAMBIA binary vector under the control of sporamine signal peptide at the 5'end and the ER targeting sequence HDEL at the 3' end. ST-mRFP, described in Saint-Jore-Dupas et <italic>al</italic>., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] was amplified by PCR using forward primer FST and reverse primer RST (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) and sub-cloned into pCAMBIA as a <italic>Kpn</italic>I or <italic>SacI </italic>fragment. For the XYLT35mRFP, MAN99mRFP and the GCS90mRFP, we have then substituted the GFP from the XYLT35, MAN99 and GCS90 constructs by the mRFP using the <italic>Spe</italic>I and <italic>Sac</italic>I endonucleases.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated tobacco BY-2 cell transformation</title><p>pBLTI121-GFP fusions were transferred into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens </italic>(strain LBA4404) by heat shock [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>]. Transgenic <italic>Agrobacterium </italic>were selected onto YEB medium (per liter, beef extract 5 g, yeast extract 1 g, sucrose 5 g, MgSO4-7H2O 0.5 g) containing kanamycin (100 mg.mL<sup>-1</sup>) and gentamycin (10 mg.mL<sup>-1</sup>) and were used to transform <italic>Nicotiana tabacum </italic>(<italic>c.v. Bright Yellow-2</italic>) BY-2 cells, as described in Gomord et <italic>al</italic>., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>]. Transformed tobacco cells were selected in the presence of cefotaxime (250 mg.mL<sup>-1</sup>) and kanamycin (100 mg.mL<sup>-1</sup>). After screening by fluorescence microscopy and, calli expressing the GFP fusions were used to initiate suspension cultures of transgenic cells.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transient expression in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic></title><p>PBLTI121-GFP, pVKH18-En6-mRFP, Sar binary plasmid and pCAMBIA-mRFP fusions transformed <italic>A. tumefaciens </italic>(strain GV3101 pMP90) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>] were cultured in kanamycin/spectinomycin and gentamycin containing YEB at 28&#x000b0;C until the stationary phase (approximately 20 h), washed and resuspended in infiltration medium (MES 50 mM pH5.6, glucose 0.5%(w/v), Na3PO4 2 mM, acetosyringone (Aldrich) 100 mM from 10 mM stock in absolute ethanol. The bacterial suspension was pressure injected into the abaxial epidermis of plant leaves using a 1-mL plastic syringe by pressing the nozzle against the lower leaf epidermis. Plants were incubated for 2-3 days at 20-25&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>BFA treatment</title><p>Tobacco cells were incubated in 50 &#x003bc;m.mL<sup>-1 </sup>BFA (Sigma, from 10 mg.mL<sup>-1 </sup>stock in DMSO) for 2 h before confocal analysis as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Confocal Laser Scanning Microscopy analysis</title><p>Cells expressing GFP were imaged using a Leica TCS SP2 AOBS confocal laser scanning microscope (CLSM) with a 488-nm argon ion laser line and the fluorescence was recorded by a photomultiplier set up for 493-538 nm. Dual-color imaging of cells co-expressing GFP and mRFP was performed using simultaneously a 488-nm argon ion laser line with the lowest laser power and a HeNe 594 nm laser line. Fluorescence signals were separated using the acousto-optical beam splitter (AOBS) and GFP emission was detected in photomultiplier 2 (493-538 nm) whereas mRFP was collected in photomultiplier 3 (600-630 nm). Appropriate controls were performed to exclude the possibility of cross talk between the two fluorophores before the image acquisitions.</p></sec><sec><title>Accession numbers</title><p>[EMBL: <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="Z18242">Z18242</ext-link> (<italic>A. thaliana </italic>calnexin; Huang et <italic>al</italic>., 1993); EMBL: <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="X87237">X87237</ext-link> (<italic>H. sapiens </italic>glucosidase I; Kalz-F&#x000fc;ller et <italic>al</italic>., 1995); EMBL:<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AJ278990">AJ278990</ext-link> (A. <italic>thaliana </italic>glucosidase I; Boisson et <italic>al</italic>., 2001); EMBL:<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF272852">AF272852</ext-link> (A. <italic>thaliana &#x003b2;</italic>-1,2-xylosyltransferase; Pagny et <italic>al</italic>., 2003)].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>List of abbreviations</title><p>CD: C-terminal domain; CT: cytosolic tail; ER: endoplasmic reticulum; GCS: glucosidase; GFP: green fluorescent protein; MAN: mannosidase; mRFP: monomeric red fluorescent protein; ST: sialyltransferase; TMD: transmenbrane domain; XYLT: xylosyltransferase.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>AB carried out the molecular genetic studies, and made a substantial contribution to the confocal microscopy analysis and interpretation of data. CSJD made a substantial contribution to the confocal microscopy analysis and interpretation of data. MCHG, SPS, CP, FG, MCKM and VG carried out the molecular genetic studies, and made contributions to construct design. AB, CSJD, CR, LF and VG have been involved in drafting the manuscript or revising it critically for important intellectual content. GV has given final approval of the version to be published. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>ER membrane protein biosynthesis and topology</bold>. (<bold>A</bold>) Type II membrane proteins are synthesized with an internal start-transfer sequence that is blocked in the membrane during the translation of the protein in the ER lumen. (<bold>B</bold>) In contrast, type I membrane proteins are synthesized with a cleavable hydrophobic signal peptide at their N-terminal ends for introduction in the ER (similar to what happens to a soluble protein) and a stop transfer sequence that corresponds to the transmembrane domain.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-S1.PPT" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>The arginine-rich cytosolic domain of type I calnexin targets the type II Golgi marker XYLT35 to the ER when fused at its N-terminal end</bold>. (<bold>A</bold>)<italic> Arabidopsis thaliana </italic>calnexin (a type I membrane protein) contains a C-terminal cytosolic, 11 amino acid long-, arginine-rich-peptide that has never been characterized especially for targeting efficiency (yellow rectangle). This RRXXRXR peptide is very similar to the one found at the cytosolic N-terminal end of type II <italic>A. thaliana </italic>glucosidase I. (<bold>B</bold>) To determine if the arginine-rich motif from calnexin could mediate the targeting of a type II membrane protein in the ER, it was fused to the N-terminal end of the Golgi marker XYLT35 (CNX11-XYLT35, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). When transiently expressed in tobacco leaf epidermal cells, CNX11-XYLT35 (left) was found mainly in the ER (middle) and in part in the Golgi (right), exactly as observed for GCS13-XYLT35 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3G-I</xref>). Bars = 8 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-S2.PPT" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>The spacing between arginine residues is important to confer ER retention</bold>. CLSM analysis of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum </italic>leaf epidermal cells co-expressing GFP-fusions together with either the ER marker mRFP-HDEL (left panel) or the Golgi marker ST-mRFP (right panel). R/L<sub>6-12</sub>GCS90 is located to the ER and to punctate structures that do not contain the ER soluble protein mRFP-HDEL (<bold>A</bold>) and are closely associated to the Golgi stacks (<bold>B</bold>). In contrast, R/L<sub>6-10</sub>GCS90 and R/L<sub>7-12</sub>GCS90 colocalize with mRFP-HDEL (<bold>C </bold>and <bold>E </bold>respectively) and with ST-mRFP (<bold>D </bold>and <bold>F </bold>respectively). These data show that the LRXXLXR and RLXXRXL motifs are not efficient to target GCS90 to the ER exclusively. Finally, R/L<sub>7-10</sub>GCS90 is found exclusively in the Golgi (<bold>H</bold>) and not in the ER (<bold>G</bold>). In conclusion, arginine residue spacing and their position relative to the N-terminal end are important for ER targeting efficiency. Bars = 8 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-S3.PPT" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p><bold>Punctate structures and Golgi move together along the ER</bold>. Tobacco leaf epidermal cells coexpressing R/L<sub>6-7</sub>GCS90-GFP and XYLT35-mRFP.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-9-144-S4.AVI" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by CNRS, the Universit&#x000e9; of Rouen, the Minist&#x000e8;re de l'&#x000e9;ducation nationale, de la recherche et de la technologie (MENRT) for a PhD grant to A. Boulaflous and the "Agence National de la recherche" (ANR-ERGO) for a research grant to C. Saint-Jore-Dupas. We thank F. Brandizzi and C. Hawes (Oxford Brookes University) for making available the binary plasmid containing ST-mRFP fusion. We thank D. Evans (Oxford Brookes University) for precious comments on the writing of the manuscript. All the microscopy experiments were performed at the "Plateforme d'Imagerie cellulaire de Haute-Normandie-PRIMACEN" at the University of Rouen.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vitale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Denecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>The endoplasmic reticulum-gateway of the secretory pathway</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.11.4.615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10213782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pelham</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><article-title>The retention signal for soluble proteins of the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>1990</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0968-0004(90)90303-S</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2077689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Denecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Rycke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Botterman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Plant and mammalian sorting signals for protein retention in the endoplasmic reticulum contain a conserved epitope</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1992</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2345</fpage><lpage>2355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1376250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Napier</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowke</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelham</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><article-title>Immunological evidence that plants use both HDEL and KDEL for targeting proteins to the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1992</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1383243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gomord</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Denmat</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitchette-Lain&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Satiat-Jeunemaitre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>The C-terminal HDEL sequence is sufficient for retention of secretory proteins in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) but promotes vacuolar targeting of proteins that escape the ER</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>1997</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1997.11020313.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9076996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gomord</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Protein retention and localization in the endoplasmic reticulum and the golgi apparatus</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><year>1999</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0300-9084(99)80118-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10433115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelham</surname><given-names>HRB</given-names></name><article-title>Ligand-induced redistribution of the human KDEL receptor from the Golgi complex to the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1992</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(92)90476-S</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1310258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Harter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Mechanisms of vesicle formation: insights from the COP system</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(99)80063-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10449336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pagny</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabanes-Macheteau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillikin</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Leborgne-Castel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerouge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Boston</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomord</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Protein recycling from the Golgi apparatus to the endoplasmic reticulum in plants and its minor contribution to calreticulin retention</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.12.5.739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10810147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cosson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Letourneur</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Coatomer (COPI)-coated vesicles: role in intracellular transport and protein sorting</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(97)80023-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9261053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teasdale</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><article-title>Signal-mediated sorting of membrane proteins between the endoplasmic reticulum and the golgi apparatus</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.12.1.27</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8970721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of a consensus motif for retention of transmembrane proteins in the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1990</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3153</fpage><lpage>3162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2120038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benghezal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasteneys</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><article-title>The C-terminal dilysine motif confers endoplasmic reticulum localization to type I membrane proteins in plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>1201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.12.7.1179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10899983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCartney</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanoa</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>McNew</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><article-title>Membrane-bound fatty acid desaturases are inserted co-translationally into the ER and contain different ER retrieval motifs at their carboxy termini</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2004</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.01949.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14690501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kabu&#x000e2;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashikov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oelmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerardy-Schahn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Endoplasmic reticulum retention of the large splice variant of the UDP-galactose transporter is caused by a dilysine motif</article-title><source>Glycobiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/glycob/cwi085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15932921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><article-title>Retrieval of transmembrane proteins to the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.121.2.317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8468349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunbrack</surname><given-names>RL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Strominger</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><article-title>Signals for retention of transmembrane proteins in the endoplasmic reticulum studied with CD4 truncation mutants</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1991</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>1918</fpage><lpage>1922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.88.5.1918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2000396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gaynor</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>te Heesen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Emr</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><article-title>Signal-mediated retrieval of a membrane protein from the Golgi to the ER in yeast</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.127.3.653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7962050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Townsley</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelham</surname><given-names>HRB</given-names></name><article-title>The KKXX signal mediates retrieval of membrane proteins from the Golgi to the ER in yeast</article-title><source>Eur J Cell Biol</source><year>1994</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7957309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hardt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bause</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Lysine can be replaced by histidine but not by arginine as the ER retrieval motif for type I membrane proteins</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2002</year><volume>291</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2002.6515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11866428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><article-title>Short cytoplasmic sequences serve as retention signals for transmembrane proteins in the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>718</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(89)90105-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2527615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shikano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Membrane receptor trafficking: evidence of proximal and distal zones conferred by two independent endoplasmic reticulum localization signals</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>5783</fpage><lpage>5788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1031748100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bakke</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobberstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>MHC class II-associated invariant chain contains a sorting signal for endosomal compartments</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1990</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(90)90137-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2121367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lotteau</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Teyton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peleraux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Quaranta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><article-title>Intracellular transport of class II MHC molecules directed by invariant chain</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1990</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/348600a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2250716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Michelsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwappach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Hide and run. Arginine-based endoplasmic-reticulum-sorting motifs in the assembly of heteromultimeric membrane proteins</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.embor.7400480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16065065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thibodeau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>A three-amino-acid-long HLA-DRbeta cytoplasmic tail is sufficient to overcome ER retention of invariant-chain p35</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2005</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>4679</fpage><lpage>4687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.02592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16188937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name><surname>Welling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>A Phosphorylation-dependent Export Structure in ROMK (Kir 1.1) Channel overrides an endoplasmic reticulum localization signal</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>35281</fpage><lpage>35289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M504836200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16118216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schutze</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><article-title>An N-terminal double-arginine motif maintains type II membrane proteins in the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1994</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1696</fpage><lpage>1705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8157008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hardt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalz-Fuller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Volker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bause</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>(Arg)3 within the N-terminal domain of glucosidase I contains ER targeting information but is not required absolutely for ER localization</article-title><source>Glycobiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/glycob/cwg013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12626409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Orci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravazzola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amherdt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lottspeich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><article-title>A major transmembrane protein of Golgi-derived COPI-coated vesicles involved in coatomer binding</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>1239</fpage><lpage>1248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.135.5.1239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8947548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz-Zapater</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aniento</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Sorting signals in the cytosolic tail of membrane proteins involved in the interaction with plant ARF1 and coatomer</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2004</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02075.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15125774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cosson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefkir</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Demolliere</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Letourneur</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>New COP1-binding motifs involved in ER retrieval</article-title><source>Embo J</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>6863</fpage><lpage>6870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/17.23.6863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Endoplasmic reticulum localization of Sec12p is achieved by two mechanisms: Rer1p-dependent retrieval that requires the transmembrane domain and Rer1p-independent retention that involves the cytoplasmic domain</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.134.2.279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8707815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoe</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Slusarewicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabouille</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Watzele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Kin recognition between medial Golgi enzymes in HeLa cells</article-title><source>Embo J</source><year>1994</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8313901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cocquerel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wychowski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubuisson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>A retention signal necessary and sufficient for endoplasmic reticulum localization maps to the transmembrane domain of hepatitis C virus glycoprotein E2</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1998</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>2183</fpage><lpage>2191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9499075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cocquerel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Duvet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cacan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wychowski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubuisson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>The transmembrane domain of hepatitis C virus glycoprotein E1 is a signal for static retention in the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1999</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>2641</fpage><lpage>2649</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10074109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cocquerel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wychowski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Minner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Penin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubuisson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Charged residues in the transmembrane domains of hepatitis C virus glycoproteins play a major role in the processing, subcellular localization, and assembly of these envelope proteins</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2000</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>3623</fpage><lpage>3633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.74.8.3623-3633.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10729138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Opat</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gleeson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><article-title>Medial Golgi but not late Golgi glycosyltransferases exist as high molecular weight complexes. Role of luminal domain in complex formation and localization</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>11836</fpage><lpage>11845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.16.11836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10766809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanton</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Traffic between the plant endoplasmic reticulum and Golgi apparatus: to the Golgi and beyond</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2006.09.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17010656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barrieu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chrispeels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><article-title>Delivery of a secreted soluble protein to the vacuole <italic>via </italic>a membrane anchor</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>961</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.120.4.961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10444079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Frangne</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marc-Martin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Paris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>The destination for single-pass membrane proteins is influenced markedly by the length of the hydrophobic domain</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1077</fpage><lpage>1092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.000620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boisson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomord</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Audran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubreucq</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Granier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerouge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Caboche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepiniec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Arabidopsis glucosidase I mutants reveal a critical role of N-glycan trimming in seed development</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1010</fpage><lpage>1019</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/20.5.1010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11230125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gillmor</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Poindexter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorieau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Palcic</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Alpha-glucosidase I is required for cellulose biosynthesis and morphogenesis in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>1003</fpage><lpage>1013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200111093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11901167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saint-Jore-Dupas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nebenf&#x000fc;hr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulaflous</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Follet-Gueye</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Plasson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Driouich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomord</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Plant <italic>N</italic>-Glycan processing enzymes employ different targeting mechanisms for their spatial arrangement along the secretory pathway</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3182</fpage><lpage>3200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.036400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17138701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ciczora</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Callens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Montpellier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartosch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosset</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Op de Beeck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubuisson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Contribution of the charged residues of hepatitis C virus glycoprotein E2 transmembrane domain to the functions of the E1E2 heterodimer</article-title><source>J Gen Virol</source><year>2005</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>2793</fpage><lpage>2798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.81140-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16186234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zerangue</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwappach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><article-title>A new ER trafficking signal regulates the subunit stoichiometry of plasma membrane K(ATP) channels</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1999</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0896-6273(00)80708-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10197533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pagny</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouissoni&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Follet-Gueye</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Driouich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schachter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomord</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Structural requirements for <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>&#x003b2;-1,2-xylosyltransferase activity and targeting to the Golgi</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0960-7412.2002.01604.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12943552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>daSilva</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Snapp</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Denecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippincott-Schwartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Endoplasmic reticulum export sites and Golgi bodies behave as single mobile secretory units in plant cells</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1753</fpage><lpage>1771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.022673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15208385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Saint-Jore</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutuzov</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><article-title>Organization of transport from endoplasmic reticulum to Golgi in higher plants</article-title><source>Biochem Soc Trans</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/0300-5127:0280505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10961949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>A dominant negative mutant of sar1 GTPase inhibits protein transport from the endoplasmic reticulum to the Golgi apparatus in tobacco and Arabidopsis cultured cells</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2000</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.2000.00823.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10972878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Phillipson</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimpl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>daSilva</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Crofts</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Movafeghi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Denecke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Secretory bulk flow of soluble proteins is efficient and COPII dependent</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2005</fpage><lpage>2020</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.13.9.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11549760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name><name><surname>Elamawi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bubeck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepperkok</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritzenthaler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><article-title>Dynamics of COPII vesicles and the Golgi apparatus in cultured <italic>Nicotiana tabacum </italic>BY-2 cells provides evidence for transient association of Golgi stacks with endoplasmic reticulum exit sites</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1513</fpage><lpage>1531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.104.026757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bar-Peled</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Conceicao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frigerio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Raikhel</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><article-title>Expression and regulation of aERD2, a gene encoding the KDEL receptor homolog in plants, and other genes encoding proteins involved in ER-Golgi vesicular trafficking</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.7.6.667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bassham</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Raikhel</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><article-title>Transport proteins in the plasma membrane and the secretory system</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(96)80018-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelham</surname><given-names>HRB</given-names></name><article-title>A human homologue of the yeast HDEL receptor</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1990</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/348162a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2172835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Raikhel</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><article-title>The Arabidopsis endoplasmic reticulum retention receptor functions in yeast</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1993</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>11433</fpage><lpage>11437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.90.23.11433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8248265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boevink</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Oparka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Santa Cruz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Betteridge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Stacks on tracks: the plant Golgi apparatus traffics on an actin/ER network</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>1998</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1998.00208.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9750355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saint-Jore</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Evins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Batoko</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Redistribution of membrane proteins between the Golgi apparatus and endoplasmic reticulum in plants is reversible and not dependent on cytoskeletal networks</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2002</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0960-7412.2002.01252.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11874578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>The Lec23 chinese hamster ovary mutant is a sensitive host for detecting mutations in {alpha}-glucosidase I that give rise to congenital disorder of glycosylation IIb (CDG IIb)</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>49894</fpage><lpage>49901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M410121200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15383536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gassmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoll</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Biermann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosbacher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaupmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>The RXR-type endoplasmic reticulum-retention/retrieval signal of GABAB1 requires distant spacing from the membrane to function</article-title><source>Mol Pharmacol</source><year>2005</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15805225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoberer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gl&#x000f6;ssl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mach</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinkellner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of Arabidopsis thaliana Golgi alpha-mannosidase II, a key enzyme in the formation of complex N-glycans in plants</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><comment><italic>Erratum in</italic>: Plant J 2006.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02648.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16460512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schoberer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vavra</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mach</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinkellner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Arginine/lysine residues in the cytoplasmic tail promote ER export of plant glycosylation enzymes</article-title><source>Traffic</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0854.2008.00841.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18939950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><article-title>Primary structure and characterization of an <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana </italic>calnexin-like protein</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1993</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>6560</fpage><lpage>6566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8454626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Irons</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>The first 238 amino acids of the human lamin B receptor are targeted to the nuclear envelope in plants</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2003</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erg102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12598565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>S&#x000f6;nnichsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000fc;llekrug</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen Van</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Diekmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mieskes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Retention and retrieval: both mechanisms cooperate to maintain calreticulin in the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1994</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>2705</fpage><lpage>2717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7876339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heine</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Quitsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Storch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehesjoki</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mole</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Braulke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Topology and endoplasmic reticulum retention signals of the lysosomal storage disease-related membrane protein CLN6</article-title><source>Mol Membr Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09687860600967317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17453415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cosson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Letourneur</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Coatomer interaction with di-lysine endoplasmic reticulum retention motifs</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>263</volume><fpage>1629</fpage><lpage>1631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.8128252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8128252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Aniento</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Sorting signals in the cytosolic tail of plant p24 proteins involved in the interaction with the COPII coat</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1779</fpage><lpage>1786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pch200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zerangue</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Malan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dazin</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwappach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Analysis of endoplasmic reticulum trafficking signals by combinatorial screening in mammalian cells</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>2431</fpage><lpage>2436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.051630198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11226256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Girod</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Storrie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Johannes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goud</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepperkok</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Evidence for a COP-I-independent transport route from the Golgi complex to the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/15658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10559986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Rer1p as common machinery for the endoplasmic reticulum localization of membrane proteins</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>9693</fpage><lpage>9698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.18.9693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9275186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Letourneur</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Targeting to the endoplasmic reticulum in yeast cells by determinants present in transmembrane domains</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>33273</fpage><lpage>33278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.50.33273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9837899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schekman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>A primer on vesicle budding</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80722-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10219233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappeler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauri</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><article-title>Protein targeting to endoplasmic reticulum by di-lysine signals involves direct retention in addition to retrieval</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>15080</fpage><lpage>15084</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.21.15080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10329713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Slusarewicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoe</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Kin recognition: A model for the retention of Golgi enzymes</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1993</year><volume>330</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(93)80906-B</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8370450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabouille</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>The role of the membrane spanning domain and stalk region of N-acetylglucosaminyltransferase I in retention, kin recognition and structural maintenance of the Golgi apparatus in HeLa cells</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1975</fpage><lpage>1989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8832420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giraudo</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniotti</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Maccioni</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><article-title>Physical and functional association of glycolipid N-acetyl-galactosaminyl and galactosyl transferases in the Golgi apparatus</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>1625</fpage><lpage>1630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.031458398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11172001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreibich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Retention of subunits of the oligosaccharyltransferase complex in the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>3984</fpage><lpage>3990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.6.3984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10660554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hardt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aparicio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bause</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Analysis of structural signals conferring localisation of pig OST48 to the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>382</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1047</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/BC.2001.130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11530934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hettkamp</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Legler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bause</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Purification by affinity chromatography of glucosidase I, an endoplasmic reticulum hydrolase involved in the processing of asparagine-linked oligosaccharides</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><year>1984</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1984.tb08253.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6235111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pukazhenthi</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijay</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><article-title>Conserved structural features in glycoprotein processing glucosidase I from several tissues and species</article-title><source>Indian J Biochem Biophys</source><year>1993</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8005615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hanton</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Seeking a way out: export of proteins from the plant endoplasmic reticulum</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2006.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16781884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stefano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Renna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanton</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>In tobacco leaf epidermal cells, the integrity of protein export from the endoplasmic reticulum and of ER export sites depends on active COPI machinery</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2006</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02675.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16553898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hanton</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Studying protein export from the endoplasmic reticulum in plants</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>390</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><comment>full_text</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nebenf&#x000fc;hr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunahay</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Frohlick</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Masurkiewicz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Meehl</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Staehelin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><article-title>Stop-and-go movements of plant Golgi stacks are mediated by the acto-myosin system</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>1127</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.121.4.1127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10594100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kalz-F&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieberich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bause</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Cloning and expression of glucosidase I from human hippocampus</article-title><source>Eur J Biochem</source><year>1995</year><volume>231</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1995.tb20706.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7635146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>H&#x000f6;fgen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Willmitzer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Storage of competent cells for <italic>Agrobacterium transformation</italic></article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1988</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>9877</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/16.20.9877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3186459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Gomord</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitchette</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Denmat</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Cunningham C, Porter AJR</person-group><article-title>Production of foreign proteins in tobacco cell suspension culture</article-title><source>Methods in Molecular Biotechnology</source><year>1998</year><volume>3</volume><publisher-name>Totowa: Humana Press Inc.</publisher-name><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><comment>full_text</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koncz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>The promoter of T-DNA gene 5 controls the tissue-specific expression of chimeric genes carried by a novel type of <italic>Agrobacterium </italic>binary vector</article-title><source>Mol General Genet</source><year>1986</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00331014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Runions</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brach</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Photoactivation of GFP reveals protein dynamics within the endoplasmic reticulum membrane</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eri289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16207749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>