<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Cell Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2121</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2121-10-91</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20017961</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2121-10-91</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Oxidative stress promotes autophagic cell death in human neuroblastoma cells with ectopic transfer of mitochondrial PPP2R2B (B&#x003b2;2)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Wan-Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>srnt.tw@yahoo.com.tw</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A2"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Zhi-Xuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>uonera@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Chia-An</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>nily1249@yahoo.com.tw</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Lin </surname><given-names>Ming-Yi </given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>bigcat0204@yahoo.com.tw</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Tung</surname><given-names>Li-Chu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>tlc@ntnu.edu.tw</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A6"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Kang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kangfang@ntnu.edu.tw</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Life Science, National Taiwan Normal University, Taipei, Taiwan</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2009 Cheng et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2009</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cheng et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2121/10/91"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The multifunctional protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A) is a heterotrimeric serine/threonine protein phosphatase composed of a scaffolding, catalytic and regulatory subunits. By modifying various downstream signal transducers, the aberrant expression of the brain-targeted regulatory subunit PPP2R2B is associated with the onset of a panel of neuronal disorders. The alternatively splicing of PPP2R2B encodes two regulatory subunit isoforms that determine cellular distribution of the neuron-specific holoenzyme to mitochondria (B&#x003b2;2) and cytoplasm (B&#x003b2;1), respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Human neuroblastoma cells were transfected with <italic>PPP2R2B </italic>constructs encoding the complete sequences of B&#x003b2;2 and B&#x003b2;1, respectively. The colonies with antibiotic resistance were selected as stable cell lines. Both ectopic B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones exhibited characteristics of autophagy. To test how cells respond to reactive oxygen species generators, the cells were treated with either hydrogen peroxide or t-butyl hydroperoxide and B&#x003b2;2 clones induced cell death. Suppression of autophagy using either RNA interference of the essential autophagy gene or pharmacological inhibitor rescued cell death caused by oxidative stress.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Cells with ectopically expressed mitochondria-targeted regulatory subunit PPP2R2B of the holoenzyme PP2A were shown predisposed to autophagy and oxidative stress induced cell death that is related to apoptosis. The results promised a model for studying the mechanism and function of aberrant PPP2R2B expression in neuronal cells. The work provided a new target for understanding and prevention of neuropathogenesis.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A) regulates cellular proliferation and tissue growth by antagonizing protein kinases and plays an important role in controlling cell cycle checkpoints, regulating nuclear telomerase activity and modulating dephosphorylation of neurofilaments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. It is believed that the enzyme flexibility and the substrate specificity are determined by the regulatory subunit (B) that binds to the ubiquitous catalytic (C) and scaffolding (A) subunits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] to form the heterotrimeric PP2A.</p><p>The regulatory B subunits can be categorized into three distinct families based on their homology, namely B (B55 or PR55), B' (B56 or PR61), B"(PR48/59/72/130) and B' " (PR93/110). Furthermore, each B family is composed of several isoforms from different genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. There is no sequence or structural similarities among the three gene families. The brain-specific regulatory B subunit, PPP2R2B (B&#x003b2;), is widely expressed in the neurons of brain and cerebellum and consists of tryptophan-glutamate repeat-containing &#x003b2;-propeller proteins. The various N termini of B subunit determine enzyme activity, subcellular localizations and neuronal functions of PP2A [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Mainly expressed in Purkinje cells of the cerebellar cortex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] and in tissues of spinocerebellar ataxia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], PPP2R2B is also known in mediating PP2A-regulated dephosphorylation of several substrates; they include vimentin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] and histone-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] as well as microtube-associated protein in neuron cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>The alternative splicing of PPP2R2B generates two major isoforms. They include B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 with two distinct N terminal tails [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The different N termini with 21 and 24 residues of B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 each encode distinctive subcellular signals that target PPP2R2B isoforms to cytoplasm and mitochondria, respectively, and affect cellular phosphatase activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. The up-regulated mitochondrial B&#x003b2;2 was reported promoting apoptosis in response to deprived growth factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], while an elevated expression of cytosolic B&#x003b2;1 due to CAG repeat expansion at the 5' end of the gene causes autosomal dominant disease of spinocerebellar ataxia type 12 (SCA12) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><p>The aberrant expression of brain-specific PPP2R2B affecting PP2A activity has been implicated in cerebellar atrophy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Translocation of PPP2R2B to mitochondria promotes mitochondria fission, apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and neuronal differentiation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Being implicated in neurodegenerative diseases, oxidative stress causes neuron cell damage and reduction of viable cells. How cells with overexpressed PPP2R2B react to environmental stress remains unclear. Mitochondria are the principal targets for reactive oxygen species (ROS). To address this, the work began with generation of stable cell lines by transferring <italic>B&#x003b2;1 </italic>and <italic>B&#x003b2;2</italic>, respectively, into human neuroblastoma SK-N-SH cells. The stable clones targeting ectopic PPP2R2B to mitochondria or cytoplasm exhibit characteristics of autophagy that is distinct from the parental cells. Furthermore, only B&#x003b2;2 clones were sensitive to ROS treatment and susceptible to autophagy-mediated cell death. The resulting apoptosis can be suppressed by chemical inhibitor and RNA interference of the related autophagy gene, and thereby preventing cells from ROS damage-induced cell death. The work illustrates the significance of autophagy in maintaining viabilities of neuronal cells with ectopically transferred PPP2R2B as well as in accelerating pathogenesis when encountered with oxidative stress.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>The establishment of clones targeting B<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>2 to mitochondria and B<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>1 cytoplasma, respectively</title><p>The expression of B family regulatory subunits regulates cell developmental patterns in brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. The antibiotic-resistant clones from human neuroblastoma cells, SK-N-SH, through ectopic transfection of either <italic>B&#x003b2;1 </italic>or <italic>B&#x003b2;2 </italic>cDNA' s driven by cytomegalovirus promoter were established as stable cell lines that can be propagated in serum-supplemented media. In addition to the basal levels in SK-N-SH cells, three isolated clones exhibited increased immune-active signals by sequence-specific B&#x003b2;2 antiserum (B&#x003b2;2#3, B&#x003b2;2#5 and B&#x003b2;2#8, Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>), while two were detected by B&#x003b2;1 antiserum (B&#x003b2;1#1 and B&#x003b2;1#2, Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>). A parallel increase of PP2A activities in the immunoprecipitates was also observed in the selected B&#x003b2;2 (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>) and B&#x003b2;1 (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>) clones that corresponded with their increased sensitivities to antisera in western blot. In contrast to the parental cells, the stable B&#x003b2;2 clones tend to aggregate to form clusters in culture (data not shown).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Both immunoactive B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones acquired enhanced PP2A activity (A)</bold>. Cell lysates of SK-N-SH cells, B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones were probed with signal sequence-specific B&#x003b2;2 antiserum. The blots were detected with ECL system following incubation with secondary HRP-conjugated goat against rabbit antibody. The ectopic expressions of B&#x003b2;2 were detected B&#x003b2;2 (A) clones. Each blot was reprobed with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) antibody to confirm equal loading of the proteins. (B) The PP2A phosphatase activities of B&#x003b2;2 clones were determined by immunoprecipitating cell lysates with B&#x003b2;2 antisera as described in Materials and Methods. <bold>Characterizations of clones B&#x003b2;1#1 and B&#x003b2;1#2 (C) </bold>Cell lysates of SK-N-SH cells, B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones were probed with B&#x003b2;1 antiserum and reprobed with GAPDH antibody to confirm equal loading of the proteins. The blots were detected with ECL system. <bold>(D) </bold>The PP2A phosphatase activities of B&#x003b2;1 clones were determined by immunoprecipitating cell lysates with B&#x003b2;1 antisera as described before. The results represented fold of increase of activity relative to control of SK-N-SH with empty vector shown as average values in three individual experiments. The result represented mean values of three individual determinations; the bars standard errors in three independent experiments as conducted. *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, significance of difference as compared with the control group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-10-91-1"/></fig><p>The strong signals in clones by B&#x003b2;2 antiserum overlapping with mitotracker green marked direct targeting of ectopic B&#x003b2;2 at mitochondria (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>); while little overlay was detected between mitochondria and the increased signal as determined by B&#x003b2;1 antiserum indicated cytoplasm distribution of B&#x003b2;1 in the isolated clones (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). Despite some degree of non-specific staining by the antisera, the results provided evidence that stable clones by targeting cytoplasm with ectopic B&#x003b2;1 and mitochondria with B&#x003b2;2, respectively, can be achieved.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Differential subcellular localization of ectopic B&#x003b2;2 and B&#x003b2;1 by confocal image analysis</bold>. <bold>(A) </bold>Cells were immunostained with antiserum against &#x003b2;2 (<italic>red</italic>) and counter-stained with mitotracker (<italic>green</italic>) and visualized by confocal microscopy. The merged graph showed that &#x003b2;2 was colocalized as yellow colors at mitochondria in clone B&#x003b2;2 #5 and #8. (B) Cells were immunostained with antiserum against &#x003b2;1 (<italic>red</italic>) and mitotracker as before. The merged graph showed that ectopic &#x003b2;1 can be distributed in cytoplasm in clone B&#x003b2;1#1 as compared with SK-N-SH cells. <italic>Bar</italic>, 20 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-10-91-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The enhanced autophagosome formation in clones with ectopic PPP2R2B</title><p>An increased autophagy has been reported in human cells or tissues with neuronal injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. We then assessed whether coordinated regulation of mitochondrial networks and autophagy-regulated cell viability can be recapitulated in clones with acquisition of PPP2R2B functions. As LC3 is modified with the lipid phospatidylethanolamine before being located to autophagosomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], the emitted fluorescence can be used to monitor autophagosome formation in cells through transient transfection with expression vector, green fluorescent protein-tagged light chain 3 (GFP-LC3). The results showed that GFP puncta that represented autophagy development can be detected in both B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones, but not in the parental cells (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Thus, the presence of autophagosome is closely related to ectopically expressed PPP2R2B.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Autophagosome formation expressing GFP-LC3 puncta in B&#x003b2;2 and B&#x003b2;1 clones</bold>. The parental SK-N-SH cells and B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones were transfected with GFP-LC3 plasmid for 48 h and observed under the fluorescence microscope for GFP (<italic>green</italic>) followed by counter-staining with DAPI(<italic>blue</italic>). Puncta fluorescence in GFP-LC3 transfected cells can be detected in cells of both B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones. <italic>Bars</italic>, 20 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-10-91-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sensitivity of peroxide-induced apoptotic cell death is associated with ectopic B<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>2</title><p>The two ROS generators H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>(Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>) and <italic>t</italic>-butyl hydroperoxide (tBHP) (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>) suppressed growth in B&#x003b2;2 clones in dose-dependent manners, while both B&#x003b2;1 clones and SK-N-SH cells with empty vector alone were not affected. Compared with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, the suppression of viable cells was more evident in tBHP that exerted more sensitivity in cells with ectopic B&#x003b2;2. The escalated cell death is proportional to the levels of B&#x003b2;2, in which B&#x003b2;2#8 was more sensitive to peroxide treatment.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Cells growth curves as affected by various concentrations of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>and tBHP</bold>. The exponentially growing SK-N-SH cells or B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones were seeded at a total of 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>cells per 6-cm plate and treated with different concentrations of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>(0, 50 and 100 &#x003bc;M, respectively) (A) or tBHP (0, 50 and 100 nM, respectively) (B). After 48 h of treatment, the cells were trypsinized and counted by trypan blue exclusion assay. The result represented mean values of three individual determinations; the bars standard errors in three independent experiments as conducted. *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, significance of difference as compared with the control group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-10-91-4"/></fig><p>An increase of sub-G<sub>1 </sub>populations was also detected in B&#x003b2;2 clones by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>(Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>) and tBHP (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). The results indicated that the decrease of viable cells can be attributed to apoptotic cell death that was not observed in cells with ectopic B&#x003b2;1. Thus, it is evident that the apoptotic cell death can be attributed to exogenous ROS in SK-N-SH cells with ectopic B&#x003b2;2.</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Both H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>and tBHP increased sub-G<sub>1 </sub>cell populations in different B&#x003b2;2 clones as indicated by cell cycle histograms</bold>. Exponential growing cells were cultured with different concentrations of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>or tBHP for 48 h. The trypsinized cells were analyzed by flow cytometry following staining with propidium iodide. The percentage distribution of cell cycle phases for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>(A, <italic>top</italic>) or tBHP (B, <italic>bottom</italic>) was determined by Cell Quest software. The results represented averages of three independent experiments and the results were average values in three individual experiments as mean &#x000b1; standard errors of three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-10-91-5"/></fig></sec><sec><title>ROS-induced apoptosis in B<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>2 clones can be rescued by autophagy inhibitor, 3-MA and ATG7 siRNA</title><p>Autophagic stress can be morphologically recognized by accumulations of autophagic vacuoles in cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. The autophagy marker protein LC3, a mammalian homolog of the yeast Atg8 protein, is covalently modified and redistributes to acidic vesicular organelles (AVO' s) with covalent lipidation as seen by mobility shift from LC3-I to LC3-II by SDS-PAGE. As shown by the acridine-orange staining (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>) and western blotting with LC-3 antibody (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>), induction of ROS accelerated cellular changes that are consistent with enhanced autophagy as indicated by the induced formation of AVO' s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] and the increased lipidation of LC3 (LC3-II) in addition to the basal level. The effect was reverted by the autophagy inhibitor, 3-MA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>The inhibitor 3-MA suppressed autophagy development in cells with ectopic B&#x003b2;2</bold>. <bold>(A) Autophagosome formation by acridine orange staining</bold>. Cells plated on coverslips in 6-well plates were either pretreated with (+) or without (-) autophagy inhibitor 3-MA before being given 50 nM tBHP for 48 h. The cells were then fixed and stained with acridine orange (<italic>green</italic>) and analyzed by fluorescence microscopy. The formation of autophagosome as shown in puncta fluorescence (<italic>red</italic>) can be suppressed by 3-MA. The presence of autophagy was found mainly in 100% of the cells after treatment, in which more than 100 cells were observed under each condition. <italic>Scales</italic>, 50 &#x003bc;m. Cells as pointed out by arrows were amplified as shown in the inset (2&#x000d7;). (B) <bold>Western blot probed with LC3 antibody </bold>The development of autophagy by tBHP in the presence (+) or absence (-) of 3-MA was analyzed by western blot analysis by incubating the blot with LC3 antibody. Levels of the 18-kDa LC3-I is visualized in both B&#x003b2;2 and B&#x003b2;1 clones. Elevated LC3-II, the 16-kDa form of LC3 specific for membranes of autophagosomes by tBHP in B&#x003b2;2 clones was suppressed by 3-MA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-10-91-6"/></fig><p>With no distinct affect on cell growth <italic>per se</italic>, 3-MA rescued B&#x003b2;2 clones from peroxide-induced cell death (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>) by suppressing formation of apoptotic cells (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B</xref>) in dose dependent manner. Thus, the accelerated autophagy by peroxide injury antagonized cell survival with supplemented mitochondrial PPP2R2B. The ROS-induced growth inhibition became less evident as cells were pretreated with 3-MA. The addition of 3-MA that rescued apoptotic death in B&#x003b2;2 clones reflects the role of autophagy that not only protects cells but initiated apoptotic cell death under oxidative stress.</p><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>The autophagy inhibitor rescued tBHP-induced cell death in B&#x003b2;2 clones</bold>. (A) <bold>Cell growth determination </bold>A total of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>exponentially growing cells were cultured with either 10 or 20 &#x003bc;M of 3-MA before being treated with 50 nM of tBHP for 48 h. The cells were then trypsinized and counted for viable cells by trypan-blue staining. The results represented averages of three independent experiments and error bars standard errors. (B) <bold>tBHP-induced apoptotic cell death can be blocked by 3-MA </bold>Annexin V binding in B&#x003b2;2 clones was determined by flow cytometry 48 h after treatment with 50 nM of tBHP in the presence and absence of 10 or 20 &#x003bc;M of 3-MA, respectively, using SK-N-SH cells as control. The results represented averages of three independent experiments and error bars standard errors. Data are represented as the mean &#x000b1; standard errors of three independent experiments, each performed in duplicate. *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, significance of difference as compared with the control group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-10-91-7"/></fig><p>More work was extended using siRNA-dependent knock-down expression of the essential autophagy gene <italic>ATG7 </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Transfection with ATG7-specific siRNA in B&#x003b2;2 clones down-regulated ATG7 expression (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref>), suppressed cell growth inhibition (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8B</xref>) and interfered development of apoptosis (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8C</xref>) by tBHP, while cells with transfer of the scrambled (SO) siRNA remained unaffected. Moreover, knock-down of ATG7 expression repressed tBHP-induced accumulation of the LC3-II isoform (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8D</xref>), that further corroborated autophagy with the development of apoptosis.</p><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Transfer of ATG7 siRNA blocked tBHP-induced cell death in B&#x003b2;2#5 clone</bold>. A total of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>exponentially growing cells of both B&#x003b2;2#5 and B&#x003b2;1#1 clones were transfected with either scrambled siRNA (SO) control or ATG7 siRNA, treated with tBHP and analyzed. <bold>(A) Knocked-down ATG5 expression by the increased ATG7 siRNA </bold>Cell lysates of B&#x003b2;2#5 clones were probed with ATG7 antibody and reprobed with &#x003b2;-actin antibody to confirm equal loading of the proteins. The blots were then detected with ECL system. <bold>(B) Cell growth </bold>Both B&#x003b2;2#5 and B&#x003b2;1#1 clones were treated with tBHP for 48 h following transfection with either SO control or ATG7 siRNA. The viable cells were determined by trypan-blue staining. <bold>(C) Determination of apoptotic cells </bold>Distribution of annexin V binding in both clones was determined by flow cytometry after 48 h treatment with 50 nM of tBHP. The results represented averages of three independent experiments and error bars standard errors. Data are represented as the mean &#x000b1; standard errors of three independent experiments, each performed in duplicate. *<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05, significance of difference as compared with the control group. <bold>(D) Western blot analysis with LC3 antibody </bold>Development of autophagy by tBHP was analyzed by western blot analysis by incubating the blot with LC3 antibody with &#x003b2;-actin antibody as loading control. The elevated LC3-II as visualized the 16-kDa form of LC3 specific for membranes of the formed autophagosomes by tBHP in B&#x003b2;2 #5 clones was suppressed by the increased concentrations of ATG7 siRNA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2121-10-91-8"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion and Conclusions</title><p>PP2A deregulation has been vastly implicated in the onset of neurodegenerative diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. The mechanisms of PP2A activity responsible for the disrupted neuron function remain unclear and are far from being understood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Intervention of normal brain or cerebellar PP2A function is crucial in the developing neurodegenerative pathology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. In an effort to learn how the increased expression of PPP2R2B isoforms affects cell growth, genes encoding proteins encoding different targeting sequences were transferred into human SK-N-SH cells. The clones with ectopically expressed PPP2R2B can be propagated as stable cell lines. Our work showed that discrete antisera cross-reactivity, in which mitochondria can be stained by B&#x003b2;1 and cytoplasm by B&#x003b2;2, respectively. To understand the function of the ectopic gene in the stable clones, it will be important to further analyze the fractions at subcellular levels.</p><p>The stable clones forming aggregation in culture exhibited autophagy characteristics that are distinct from the parental cells. Autophagy is a lysosome-dependent degradation pathway regulated by extracellular nutrients or trophic factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Cells exhibiting basal rate of autophagy maintain homeostasis and survival of neurons under stress that protects them from pathogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. Despite their relatively slow growth rate compared to the parental cells (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>), clones with ectopic brain-specific subunit PPP2R2B were able to sustain minor increases of autophagosome formation that maintains cell viable. The formation of autophagosome in both B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones (Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>) demonstrated how cells survive when encountered with stress conditions. While heterotrimeric PP2A holoenzyme containing all three regulatory subunit families can affect events ranging from the initiation of DNA replication to vertebrate axis formation to apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], the up-regulated mitochondrial PPP2R2B putatively serves to deregulate protein kinases cascades, thereby making cells autophagic as seen in some neuron disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>].</p><p>Numerous studies suggested a close relationship between dysfunctional mitochondria and autophagy. Mitochondrial perturbation is one of the sources to induce autophagic cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. The disturbance of autophagy-lysosome balance has been recognized as a major cause in numerous neurodegenerative disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. While low levels of autophagy maintains cell viabilities in both stable B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 clones, only the latter was sensitive to peroxide injury by initiating apoptosis (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>) with concomitant increase of AVO' s (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Inhibition of autophagy by the chemical inhibitor, 3-MA, (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>) and RNA interference-mediated knockdown of ATG7 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>) reverted the process. Thus, oxidative stress-induced cell death in B&#x003b2;2 cells as shown in annexin V staining and growth assays demonstrated that the progression of autophagy lead B&#x003b2;2 cells to apoptosis.</p><p>Although autophagy is capable of keeping cells from being damaged, the work provided evidence that, in addition to being protective, the increased autophagy as a result of peroxide injury can be pathogenic resulting from apoptosis. Our work showed that the attenuated autophagy prolonged cell survival by reducing formation of the accumulated autophagosome following peroxide injury. Given the fact that oxidative stress is an origin of disturbing cell homeostasis, it is conceivable that the reduced autophagic source may be an alternative approach to ameliorate harmful effects to neuronal system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Being necessary at basal level for maintaining normal axonal and synaptic structures, particularly in Purkinje neurons, excessive autophagy can be neurotoxic and inhibition by chemical regulators prevents the onset of neurodegeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Further investigation on how excessive autophagy affects cell signaling and growth under oxidative stress will provide more targets to understand the basis of the diseases.</p><p>More evidence indicated that PP2A activity can be regulated by extracellular signals and cell cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. How altered cell signaling in organelles, particularly those in mitochondria that impinge viable neuron cells as a result of increased expression of the regulatory subunit PPP2R2B, provides an interesting topic for developing more effective preventive measures in development of neuron disorders.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Antisera production</title><p>The peptides derived from the N terminus of mitochondria-specific B&#x003b2;2 (CFSRYLPYIFRPPNT) and cytoplasm-specific B&#x003b2;1(MKCFSRYLPYIFRPPNTILSSSCH) were coupled to keyhole limpet hemocyanin, respectively, via the sulfhydryl group of the N-terminal cysteine; the polyclonal antibody sera were generated in rabbits and purified by standard affinity techniques.</p></sec><sec><title>Cytomegalovirus promoter-driven expression constructs containing B&#x003b2;1 or B&#x003b2;2 cDNA and establishment of stable clones from SK-N-SH cells and cell culturing</title><p>The B&#x003b2;1 cDNA was restriction-digested by <italic>Xba </italic>I from the B&#x003b2;1 phagemid (provided by BA Hemmings, Katholieke Universiteit te Leuven, Belgium) containing N-terminus cytoplasm-specific sequence of PPP2R2B and ligated into <italic>Xba</italic>I site of pcDNA3. The B&#x003b2;2 cDNA containing mitochondria-specific sequence of PPP2R2B was restriction-digested from B&#x003b2;2 cDNA library clone by <italic>Xho</italic>I and <italic>Spe</italic>I from the plasmid (provided by S Strack, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa) and ligated into <italic>Xho</italic>I and <italic>Spe</italic>I sites of pcDNA3. Each of the recombinant plasmids was confirmed of their DNA sequences by DNA sequencing from both ends.</p><p>Human neuroblastoma cell line SK-N-SH was acquired from American Type Tissue Collection (Rockville, MD) and grown in DMEM (Invitrogen, Grands Islands, NY). Medium was changed three times a week. Cells were observed with a phase-contrast microscope (Nikon Diaphot-300). SK-N-SH cells were cultured every 5 or 7 days using standard trypsinization procedures to maintain the cell line. All cultured cells were supplemented with L-glutamine, sodium pyruvate, and supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated FCS in the humidified atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 37&#x000b0;C. All cell lines were examined and found to be free of mycoplasma contamination using a MycoTect kit (Invitrogen, Grands Islands, NY). Both hydrogen peroxide and t-butyl hydroperoxide were from Sigma (St. Louis, MO).</p><p>A total of 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>exponentially growing SK-N-SH cells were cultured in 60-cm<sup>2 </sup>flasks and transfected with one microgram of either recombinant B<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>1, B<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>2 construct or the empty vector by Lipofectamine (Invitrogen) in serum-free media following the manufacturer's protocols. After three weeks of culturing and selection with 200 &#x003bc;g/ml of G418 (Invitrogen), the antibiotic-resistant colonies were harvested, and, after limited dilution, the subclones carrying overexpressed B&#x003b2;1 or B&#x003b2;2 isolated. The established clones can be continuously propagated as immortalized cell lines in 10% FCS-supplemented DMEM.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination for cell growth and apoptosis</title><p>Cell growth was measured by trypan blue exclusion assay. Briefly, cells were plated in 12-well culture plates (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>cells/well). After incubation for the time specified, the cells were treated with different concentrations of peroxides for the times as specified. The trypsinized cells suspended in PBS were mixed with trypan blue solution in a 1:1 ratio and the cell numbers counted by a hemocytometer.</p><p>The annexin V-positive cells were determined using Annexin V-FITC Apoptosis Detection Kit (Roche Diagnostics, Indianapolis, IN) according to the supplier's instructions. Each cell line was tested at least three times and apoptotic cells determined quantitatively by flow cytometry.</p></sec><sec><title>Flow cytometry of cell cycle analysis by propidium iodide staining</title><p>To determine phase distribution of DNA content, propidium iodide (PI) staining was performed. Briefly, 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells collected were washed once and fixed in 70% ethanol overnight. After centrifugation at 700 rpm for 5 min at 4&#x000b0;C, cell pellet was stained with 5 &#x003bc;g/ml PI (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) plus 0.5 mg/ml RNaseA in PBS buffer for 15 min at room temperature in the dark. The analysis was performed with FACScan flow cytometer (Becton-Dickinson, Mansfield, MA). Cell cycle distributions were analyzed by Cell-Quest and Modfit software (Becton-Dickinson, Mansfield, MA). The statistics of cell distributions were calculated from three individual experiments.</p></sec><sec><title>PP2A activity assay determination</title><p>The phosphatase activity was conducted by modifying the published work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. Briefly, cell lysates were immune-precipitated with antiserum against &#x003b2;2, &#x003b2;1 or pre-serum depending on the type of clones used. Following precipitation with protein (A/G)-agarose and resuspension in the assay buffer, the collected supernatants were reacted with p-nitrobenzyl phosphate substrate. The optical readings of the assay as determined by spectrophotometer for each cells were subtracted from those by precipitation with pre-serum. Data were converted into percentage by comparing with those of the control parental cells, SK-N-SH with the empty vector.</p></sec><sec><title>Confocal imaging</title><p>Cells were seeded on poly-D-lysine-coated, chambered glasses (20-mm<sup>2</sup>chamber, Nalge Nunc), fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde for 20 min. The cells were incubated with the primary B&#x003b2;1 or B&#x003b2;2 antiserum followed by TRITC-conjugated secondary anti-rabbit antibody. A concentration 10 nM mitotracker green (Molecular Probes) was added to counterstain mitochondria. Pictures of fixed cells were taken on a Zeiss LSM 510 Meta laser scanning confocal microscope at the Optical Molecular Imaging Microscopy Core Facility, National Taiwan University.</p></sec><sec><title>Transfection of the GFP-LC3 construct and examination of puncta fluorescence</title><p>The stables clones B&#x003b2;2 and B&#x003b2;1 derived from SK-N-SH cells were grown on sterile histologic slides, and, after 24 h, transfected with GFP-LC3 construct (gifted by Dr. Wei-Pang Huang, Department of Life Science, National Taiwan University) using a mixture of Lipofectamine (Invitrogen) and plasmid in Opti-MEM medium (Invitrogen) at a ratio of 5 &#x003bc;L Lipofectamine per milliliter of medium per 1 &#x003bc;L plasmid. After 6 h of incubation, cells were placed in regular complete medium and cultured for 1 day. The slides were washed with PBS, and cells fixed in cold methanol. Cells were then washed in PBS twice, and coverslips mounted with glycerol/PBS (3:1) solution. Slides were examined under a fluorescent microscope (Leica). Autophagy was quantified based on the mean numbers of puncta displaying intense staining for three fields (containing at least 50 cells per field) for each experimental condition. The amount of GFP-LC3 dots, each dot signal was detected by eye and the area was measured using the Photoshop 7.0 software (Adobe).</p></sec><sec><title>Detection of AVO' s by acridine orange staining</title><p>Cells were cultured with or without peroxides for 48 hours, washed with PBS, stained with medium containing 0.5 &#x003bc;g/ml of acridine orange for 15 minutes. The media was removed, the cells were washed and fluorescent micrographs taken using an inverted fluorescent microscope.</p></sec><sec><title>Western blot analysis</title><p>Cells cultured in 0.5% serum-supplemented media were washed with PBS and scraped in lysis buffer containing 1% triton X-100, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 1% aprotonin, 5 mM PMSF and 10 &#x003bc;g/ml leupeptin in 20 mM sodium phosphate. Protein concentration was determined by the BCA assay (Pierce Biotechnology, Rockford, IL) and 20 &#x003bc;g of total protein was performed for Western blots analysis. Protein samples were electrophoresed on SDS-polyacrylamide gels, transferred to nitrocellulose filters). The blots wee incubated in fresh blocking solution and probed for 1 h with 1:3,000 dilution of B&#x003b2;1 and B&#x003b2;2 antisera, respectively. Blots were washed twice in PBS-T and then incubated with a 1:4,000 dilution of peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody (Kirkegaard and Perry Laboratories, Inc., Gaithersburg, MD) in PBS-T for 1 h at 22&#x000b0;C. Blots were then again washed twice for 10 min in PBS-T and then detected by ECL illumination system (Amersham).</p></sec><sec><title>RNA interference</title><p>For siRNA transfection, 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells were transfected by nucleofection (Applied Amaxa Biosystems) and cell suspensions mixed with 1 or 5 &#x003bc;g of siRNA for B&#x003b2;2 cells. The cells were diluted in 2 ml DMEM (supplemented with 10% FBS, 100 U/ml penicillin, 0.1 mg/ml streptomycin, and 2 mM L-glutamine) at 37&#x000b0;C. The siRNA corresponding to the human cDNA sequence for ATG7 (5'-CAGTGGATCTAAATCTCAAACTGAT-3') was acquired from Sigma-Aldrich. The control siRNAs (SO) were acquired from Ambion. The ATG7 signal was verified by Western blotting with the anti-ATG7 rabbit polyclonal antibody (Cell Signalling Technology).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistics</title><p>Unless otherwise indicated, results were expressed as compiled means &#x000b1; S.E. from at least three independent experiments. Values of p &#x0003c; 0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>WTC and ZXG participated the biochemical and biology experiments, CAL and MYL conducted isolation of the clones and KF and LCT conceived of the study and research design. KF wrote the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by grant (ORD94-3) from National Taiwan Normal University.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendrix</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cron</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthies</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Goris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Merlevede</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofsteenge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmings</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><article-title>Structure of the 55-kDa regulatory subunit of protein phosphatase 2A: evidence for a neuronal-specific isoform</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1991</year><volume>30</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>3589</fpage><lpage>3597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00229a001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1849734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumby</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><article-title>Brain protein serine/threonine phosphatases</article-title><source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-4388(99)80049-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10395578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Overexpression of the protein phosphatase 2A regulatory subunit Bgamma promotes neuronal differentiation by activating the MAP kinase (MAPK) cascade</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><issue>44</issue><fpage>41525</fpage><lpage>41532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M203767200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12191994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Colbran</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebner</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadzinski</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><article-title>Protein serine/threonine phosphatase 1 and 2A associate with and dephosphorylate neurofilaments</article-title><source>Brain Res Mol Brain Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>49</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-328X(97)00117-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9387859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaucha</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebner</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Colbran</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadzinski</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><article-title>Brain protein phosphatase 2A: developmental regulation and distinct cellular and subcellular localization by B subunits</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>1998</year><volume>392</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-9861(19980323)392:4&#x0003c;515::AID-CNE8&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9514514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaucha</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Colbran</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadzinski</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><article-title>Cloning and characterization of B delta, a novel regulatory subunit of protein phosphatase 2A</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1999</year><volume>460</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(99)01377-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10556517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCright</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Audlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Virshup</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>The B56 family of protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A) regulatory subunits encodes differentiation-induced phosphoproteins that target PP2A to both nucleus and cytoplasm</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><issue>36</issue><fpage>22081</fpage><lpage>22089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.271.36.22081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8703017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Virshup</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>Protein phosphatase 2A: a panoply of enzymes</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(99)00074-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10712915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Griswold-Prenner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamibayashi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruoka</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumby</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Derynck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Physical and functional interactions between type I transforming growth factor beta receptors and B alpha, a WD-40 repeat subunit of phosphatase 2A</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>6595</fpage><lpage>6604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9774674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Luangpirom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hladik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mudrak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Speciale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><article-title>Altered expression levels of the protein phosphatase 2A ABalphaC enzyme are associated with Alzheimer disease pathology</article-title><source>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</source><year>2004</year><volume>63</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15099019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hearn</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><article-title>SCA12: an unusual mutation leads to an unusual spinocerebellar ataxia</article-title><source>Brain Res Bull</source><year>2001</year><volume>56</volume><issue>3-4</issue><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0361-9230(01)00596-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Hearn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><article-title>Why is SCA12 different from other SCAs?</article-title><source>Cytogenet Genome Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><issue>1-4</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000072854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14526180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>HolmesE</surname><given-names>SEFH</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Hearn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Spinocerebellar ataxia type 12 (SCA12): additional evidence for a causative role of the CAG repeat expansion in PPP2R2B</article-title><source>Abstract Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1074</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Hearn</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>McInnis</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorelick-Feldman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleiderlein</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingersoll-Ashworth</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumner</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ananth</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Seltzer</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieria-Saecker</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Epplen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Riess</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><article-title>Expansion of a novel CAG trinucleotide repeat in the 5' region of PPP2R2B is associated with SCA12</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>23</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/70493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10581021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Turowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Myles</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmings</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><article-title>Vimentin dephosphorylation by protein phosphatase 2A is modulated by the targeting subunit B55</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1997</fpage><lpage>2015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10359611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mayer-Jaekel</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohkura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrigno</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Andjelkovic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiomi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmings</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Drosophila </italic>mutants in the 55 kDa regulatory subunit of protein phosphatase 2A show strongly reduced ability to dephosphorylate substrates of p34cdc2</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>1994</year><volume>107</volume><issue>Pt 9</issue><fpage>2609</fpage><lpage>2616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7844174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamibayashi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>The interaction of SV40 small tumor antigen with protein phosphatase 2A stimulates the map kinase pathway and induces cell proliferation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1993</year><volume>75</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(93)90533-V</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8252625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Kanegan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadzinski</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Distinct protein phosphatase 2A heterotrimers modulate growth factor signaling to extracellular signal-regulated kinases and Akt</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><issue>43</issue><fpage>36029</fpage><lpage>36036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M506986200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16129692</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dagda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaucha</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wadzinski</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>A developmentally regulated, neuron-specific splice variant of the variable subunit Bbeta targets protein phosphatase 2A to mitochondria and modulates apoptosis</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><issue>27</issue><fpage>24976</fpage><lpage>24985</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M302832200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12716901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cholfin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobrido</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulst</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Geschwind</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><article-title>The SCA12 mutation as a rare cause of spinocerebellar ataxia</article-title><source>Arch Neurol</source><year>2001</year><volume>58</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1833</fpage><lpage>1835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.58.11.1833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11708992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dagda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cribbs</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Usachev</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>The spinocerebellar ataxia 12 gene product and protein phosphatase 2A regulatory subunit Bbeta2 antagonizes neuronal survival by promoting mitochondrial fission</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><issue>52</issue><fpage>36241</fpage><lpage>36248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M800989200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18940801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><article-title>Autophagic stress in neuronal injury and disease</article-title><source>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</source><year>2006</year><volume>65</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.jnen.0000229233.75253.be</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16772866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dagda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulich</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><article-title>Mitochondrially localized ERK2 regulates mitophagy and autophagic cell stress: implications for Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Autophagy</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>770</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18594198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kabeya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirisako</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kominami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohsumi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>LC3, a mammalian homologue of yeast Apg8p, is localized in autophagosome membranes after processing</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>5720</fpage><lpage>5728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/19.21.5720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11060023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paglin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollister</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Delohery</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sphicas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Domingo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahalom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>A novel response of cancer cells to radiation involves autophagy and formation of acidic vesicles</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>61</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11212227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Seglen</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><article-title>3-Methyladenine: Specific inhibitor of autophagic/lysosomal protein degradation in isolated rat hepatocytes</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA</source><year>1892</year><volume>79</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1889</fpage><lpage>1982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.79.6.1889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedrich</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>J-i</given-names></name><name><surname>Kominami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chait</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><article-title>Essential role for autophagy protein Atg7 in the maintenance of axonal homeostasis and the prevention of axonal degeneration</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><issue>36</issue><fpage>14489</fpage><lpage>14494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0701311104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goedert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Satumtira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamibayashi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sontag</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Reduced binding of protein phosphatase 2A to tau protein with frontotemporal dementia and Parkinsonism linked to chromosome 17 mutations</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2000</year><volume>75</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2155</fpage><lpage>2162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2000.0752155.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11032905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Avila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>MAR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Role of tau protein in both physiological and pathological conditions</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>2004</year><volume>84</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00024.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15044677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duenas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Giunti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular pathogenesis of spinocerebellar ataxias</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2006</year><volume>129</volume><issue>Pt 6</issue><fpage>1357</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awl081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16613893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Codogno</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><article-title>Autophagy and signaling: their role in cell survival and cell death</article-title><source>Cell Death Differ</source><year>2005</year><volume>12</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><fpage>1509</fpage><lpage>1518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.cdd.4401751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16247498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Waguri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanida</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchiyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kominami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Loss of autophagy in the central nervous system causes neurodegeneration in mice</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>441</volume><issue>7095</issue><fpage>880</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16625205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hearn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>SCA12: an unusual mutation leads to an unusual spinocerebellar ataxia</article-title><source>Brain Res Bull</source><year>2001</year><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0361-9230(01)00596-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11719278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jankovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>The role of autophagy-lysosome pathway in neurodegeneration associated with Parkinson's disease</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2008</year><volume>131</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1969</fpage><lpage>1978</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awm318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18187492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cribbs</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Critical role for protein phosphatase 2A heterotrimers in mammalian cell survival</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><issue>46</issue><fpage>47732</fpage><lpage>47739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M408015200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15364932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikehara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Imamura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshiro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikehara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinjo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasumoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>A protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A) inhibition assay using a recombinant enzyme for rapid detection of microcystins</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><year>2008</year><volume>51</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1368</fpage><lpage>1373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxicon.2008.03.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18430448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>