<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gke245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">11266554</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcriptional adaptor and histone acetyltransferase proteins in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and their interactions with CBF1, a transcriptional activator involved in cold-regulated gene expression</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stockinger</surname><given-names>Eric J.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Yaopan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x958ead0.0x98f2a20">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Regier</surname><given-names>Martha K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x958ead0.0x98f2a20">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Triezenberg</surname><given-names>Steven J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x958ead0.0x98f2a20">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thomashow</surname><given-names>Michael F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="N0x958ead0.0x98f29e0">a</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x958ead0.0x98f2a20">Department of Crop and Soil Sciences and <label>1</label>Department of Biochemistry, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI&#x000a0;48824, USA</aff><author-notes><fn id="N0x958ead0.0x98f29e0"><label>a</label><p>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: &#x0002b;1 517 355 2299; Fax: &#x0002b;1 517 353 5174; Email: <email>thomash6&#x00040;msu.edu</email> Present address: Eric J. Stockinger, Department of Horticulture and Crop Science, 209 Williams Hall, The Ohio State University&#x0002f;OARDC, Wooster, OH 44691, USA</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2001</year></pub-date><volume>29</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1524</fpage><lpage>1533</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http:&#x0002f;&#x0002f;www.nar.oupjournals.org&#x0002f;content&#x0002f;vol29&#x0002f;issue7&#x0002f;"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2000</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2001</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2001</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2001 Oxford University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2001</copyright-year><abstract><p>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> CBF transcriptional activators bind to the CRT&#x0002f;DRE regulatory element present in the promoters of many cold-regulated genes and stimulate their transcription. Expression of the CBF1 proteins in yeast activates reporter genes carrying a minimal promoter with the CRT&#x0002f;DRE as an upstream regulatory element. Here we report that this ability of CBF1 is dependent upon the activities of three key components of the yeast Ada and SAGA complexes, namely the histone acetyltransferase (HAT) Gcn5 and the transcriptional adaptor proteins Ada2 and Ada3. This result suggested that CBF1 might function through the action of similar complexes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. In support of this hypothesis we found that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> has a homolog of the <italic>GCN5</italic> gene and two homologs of <italic>ADA2</italic>, the first report of multiple <italic>ADA2</italic> genes in an organism. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 protein has intrinsic HAT activity and can physically interact <italic>in vitro</italic> with both the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2a and ADA2b proteins. In addition, the CBF1 transcriptional activator can interact with the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 and ADA2 proteins. We conclude that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> encodes HAT-containing adaptor complexes that are related to the Ada and SAGA complexes of yeast and propose that the CBF1 transcriptional activator functions through the action of one or more of these complexes.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes id="N0x958ead0.0x98f2aa0" notes-type="data_link"><p>DDBJ&#x0002f;EMBL&#x0002f;GenBank accession nos: AF338768&#x02013;AF338771</p></notes></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The CBF1, CBF2 and CBF3 proteins of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c2">2</xref>), also known as DREB1B, DREB1C and DREB1A (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c4">4</xref>), respectively, are transcriptional regulatory proteins involved in cold-regulated (COR) gene expression. The CBF proteins, which contain AP2&#x0002f;EREBP DNA-binding domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c5">5</xref>), recognize the DNA regulatory element designated the CRT (C-repeat)&#x0002f;DRE (dehydration-responsive element) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c7">7</xref>). The CRT&#x0002f;DRE is present in the promoters of multiple COR and dehydration-inducible genes, including <italic>COR15a</italic>, <italic>COR6.6&#x0002f;KIN2</italic>, <italic>COR47</italic> and <italic>COR78</italic>&#x0002f;<italic>RD29A </italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c8">8</xref>). In plants that are well irrigated and grown at normal temperatures (&#x0223c;20&#x000b0;C) neither the <italic>CBF</italic> genes nor the target <italic>COR</italic> genes are expressed. However, within minutes of transferring plants to low non-freezing temperatures (&#x0223c;4&#x000b0;C) the <italic>CBF</italic> genes are induced, followed at &#x0223c;2 h by expression of the <italic>COR</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c2">2</xref>). Constitutive overexpression of either CBF1 or CBF3 in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants results in constitutive <italic>COR</italic> gene expression and an increase in freezing tolerance without a low temperature stimulus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c9">9</xref>). These results indicate that the CBF proteins and the genes they regulate, the CBF regulon, have important roles in cold acclimation, the process whereby certain plants increase in freezing tolerance in response to low non-freezing temperatures.</p><p> The mechanism by which the CBF proteins activate expression of the <italic>COR</italic> genes is not known. Indeed, very little is known about how any transcriptional activator stimulates transcription in plants. In contrast, studies in yeast and animal systems have revealed two fundamental mechanisms by which transcriptional activators stimulate transcription. One is to help assemble the transcriptional apparatus at target promoters. Many transcriptional activation domains can interact directly with basal transcription factors, including the TATA-binding protein (TBP), TFIIA, TFIIB, TFIIH and components of the RNA polymerase II holoenzyme, and are thought to recruit these proteins to promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c13">13</xref>). A second mechanism is to induce changes in chromatin structure that result in promoters becoming more accessible to RNA polymerase II and other components of the transcriptional apparatus. The changes in chromatin are accomplished by two major classes of protein complexes. One class comprises the SWI&#x0002f;SNF-related complexes, which alter the position of DNA in nucleosomes through a mechanism involving ATP hydrolysis (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c15">15</xref>). The second class comprises proteins that covalently modify the histone proteins in the nucleosome core (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c16">16</xref>). Most prominent among this second class are the histone acetyltransferase (HAT) proteins (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c17">17</xref>), which catalyze the addition of acetyl groups to specific lysine residues present in the N-terminal tails of core histones.</p><p> Expression of the CBF proteins in yeast activates reporter genes carrying a minimal promoter with the CRT&#x0002f;DRE as an upstream regulatory element (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c2">2</xref>). This finding indicates that the CBF proteins can interact with yeast proteins to stimulate transcription. Protein fusion experiments have demonstrated that the C-terminal half of CBF1 functions as an activation domain in both yeast and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (E.J.Stockinger, S.J.Triezenberg and M.F.Thomashow, unpublished results). This region of CBF1 (and homologous regions in CBF2 and CBF3), like many other activation domains from yeast and other eukaryotes, is rich in acidic amino acids. Some acidic activation domains, like those of the yeast activators Gcn4 and Pho4 and the herpes virus activator VP16, recruit HAT-containing complexes to promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c20">20</xref>). The yeast Gcn5 protein is the HAT component of at least two distinct transcriptional adaptor complexes in yeast, designated Ada (mass &#x0223c;0.8 MDa) and SAGA (mass &#x0223c;1.8 MDa), that are capable of acetylating histone H3 in nucleosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c21">21</xref>). These complexes include the transcriptional adaptor proteins Ada2 and Ada3, as well as other complex-specific proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c22">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c25">25</xref>). Transcriptional activation by Gcn4 or Gal4&#x02013;VP16 is significantly reduced in yeast mutants that do not produce either Ada2, Ada3 or Gcn5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c28">28</xref>).</p><p> The goal of this study was to explore the possibility that the CBF proteins might activate gene expression by recruiting HAT-containing adaptor complexes to promoters. Here we demonstrate that the ability of CBF1 to stimulate gene expression in yeast is dependent upon the activities of the Ada2, Ada3 and Gcn5 proteins. Moreover, we show that (i) <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> has homologs of both Ada2 and Gcn5; (ii) the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 protein has HAT activity; (iii) the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 protein can physically interact with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2; (iv) the CBF1 transcriptional activator interacts with the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2 and GCN5 proteins. Taken together, these results indicate that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> encodes HAT-containing adaptor complexes that are related to the Ada and SAGA complexes of yeast and suggest that the CBF1 transcriptional activator functions through the action of one or more of these complexes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>CBF1 activity in yeast</title><p>The yeast strains PSY316 (MAT&#x003b1; <italic>ade2-101 his3-del.200 leu2-3,2-112 lys2 ura3-53</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c26">26</xref>) and its descendant deletion mutant strains PSY316&#x00394;<italic>ada2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c26">26</xref>), PSY316&#x00394;<italic>ada3</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c29">29</xref>) and PSY316&#x00394;<italic>trp1</italic>&#x00394;<italic>gcn5</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c30">30</xref>) were transformed with plasmid pEJS134 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c1">1</xref>) and selected for uracil prototrophy. Plasmid pEJS134 bears two direct repeat copies of the CRT&#x0002f;DRE sequence (5&#x02032;-GATCATTTCATGGCCGACCTGCTTTTT) upstream of the <italic>GAL1</italic> TATA&#x02013;<italic>lacZ</italic> reporter gene and integrates into the <italic>URA3</italic> locus. The resulting strains are listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gke245tb1">1</xref>. Into each of these reporter strain constructs we transformed plasmid pEJS251 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c1">1</xref>), from which CBF1 was expressed under control of the <italic>ADC1</italic> promoter. &#x003b2;-Galactosidase activity was assayed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c31">31</xref>) for three independent colonies from each transformation event.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolation of cDNAs encoding atADA2a, atADA2b and atGCN5</title><p><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cDNA libraries CD4-10 (donated by John Walker to the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Biological Resource Center funded by National Science Foundation&#x0002f;Department of Energy&#x0002f;US Department of Agriculture Collaborative Research in Plant Biology Program grant USDA 92-37105-7675), CD4-14 and CD4-15 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c32">32</xref>) were obtained through the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Biological Resource Center. Oligonucleotides used for PCR or sequencing were synthesized either at the Michigan State University Macromolecular Structure Facility or in the USDA Plant Gene Expression Center in Albany, CA.</p><p> EST clone EST147D16 (GenBank accession no. T76166) was identified through a BLAST search of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> EST database (provided by the National Center for Biotechnology Information) using the yeast Ada2 protein sequence as a query. The EST clone obtained from Tom Newman (Michigan State University, MI) was used as a hybridization probe to isolate a full-length <italic>ADA2a</italic> cDNA clone from the size-selected <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cDNA library CD4-14 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c32">32</xref>).</p><p> The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>ADA2b</italic> gene was initially identified by the EU <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Genome Project sequencing of chromosome 4 (accession no. 2244998; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c33">33</xref>). Forward (5&#x02032;-GCGAGGATCCGC<underline>ATG</underline>GGTCGCTCTCGAGGGAACTTCC; underlining indicates the start codon) and reverse (5&#x02032;-GCGGCGGCCGCACAACACTACACAAGCC<underline>TTA</underline>; underlining indicates the stop codon) primers were used to amplify and clone the predicted open reading frame for the <italic>ADA2b</italic> gene from the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cDNA library CD4-10.</p><p> The cDNA sequence of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homolog of yeast <italic>GCN5</italic> was initially submitted to GenBank (accession no. AF037442; T.Tomihama, K.Shoji and T.Okano, unpublished results). Forward (5&#x02032;-GATTTTCTCAATCACCTTCACTATACTGCT) and reverse (5&#x02032;-CCTACAAAGTAAAAACTTAAACATTCTGAA) primers were used to amplify a cDNA fragment from the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cDNA library CD4-10. Sequencing of this PCR fragment indicated differences from the deposited sequence that implied changes in the frame of the predicted polypeptide. A cDNA fragment spanning the HAT and bromodomains of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>GCN5</italic> was amplified using forward (5&#x02032;-CCAGTGCGGCCGCCATGGTGGAAAAGATGGTGG) and reverse (5&#x02032;-GGCACGCGGCCGCCATGTATTCCCAGTTCCAATG) primers and was then cloned into the <italic>Not</italic>I site of pET28a (Novagen), resulting in plasmid pSTQ431. The insert fragment of pSTQ431 was subsequently used as a hybridization probe to screen the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cDNA library CD4-15 for an independent cDNA clone, pEJS427. The nucleotide sequences of the PCR-derived and library-derived cDNA clones agree completely in all regions of overlap.</p><p> Nucleotide sequences of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cDNAs described above have the following assigned GenBank accession nos: <italic>ADA2a</italic>, AF338769; <italic>ADA2b</italic>, AF338770; <italic>GCN5</italic>, AF338768. The nucleotide sequence of a genomic cosmid fragment encoding <italic>GCN5</italic> has also been deposited as AF338771.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA blot analysis</title><p>RNA blot analysis was performed with 10 &#x000b5;g (per lane) total RNA prepared from roots or leaves of <italic>in vitro</italic> grown plants, or mature rosette leaves of cold acclimated, soil-grown plants. Total <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RNA was isolated essentially as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c34">34</xref>) with an added phenol:chloroform extraction following precipitation with LiCl. Following electrophoresis and blotting to nylon membranes using standard procedures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c35">35</xref>), RNAs were hybridized with radiolabeled cDNA probes encoding atADA2a, atADA2b or atGCN5 and subsequently rehybridized successively with probes for <italic>eIF-4A</italic> and <italic>COR15a</italic>. Cloned cDNA fragments encoding atADA2a, atADA2b or atGCN5 were radiolabeled with <sup>32</sup>P nucleotides either by random priming or by directed priming with internal oligonucleotides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c36">36</xref>). Membranes were hybridized with probes in Church buffer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c37">37</xref>) and washed in 1&#x000d7; SSC, 0.1&#x00025; SDS at 65&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Histone acetylation assays</title><p>DNA fragments encoding the full-length atGCN5(1&#x02013;568) and an N-terminal truncation derivative atGCN5(155&#x02013;568) were subcloned into the His<sub>6</sub>-tagged vector pET-28c (Novagen) and transformed into <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain BL21(DE3). Protein expression was induced for 16 h at 20&#x000b0;C using IPTG (40 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml) in 500 ml of LB medium containing kanamycin (100 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml). Cells expressing the recombinant proteins were collected, washed once with phosphate-buffered saline and resuspended in 15 ml of buffer A (50 mM sodium phosphate pH 7.9, 500&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 10&#x00025; glycerol) containing two tablets of protease inhibitor cocktail (Boehringer Mannheim) and 1 mg&#x0002f;ml pepstatin. Resuspended cells were passed three times through a French press (&#x0223c;8000 p.s.i.) at 4&#x000b0;C. To the French press lysate was added Triton X-100 (to 1&#x00025;), DTT (to 10 mM) and imidazole (to 25 mM). Cell extracts were centrifuged for 15 min at 20 000 <italic>g</italic>. Recombinant GCN5 proteins were purified by incubating 10 ml of the supernatant with 0.8 ml of Ni&#x02013;NTA resin (Qiagen) with gentle shaking for 1.5 h at 4&#x000b0;C. The Ni&#x02013;NTA was washed eight times, 5 min each wash, at 4&#x000b0;C with washing solution (8 ml of buffer A containing 6 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 0.2&#x00025; Triton X-100, 1 mg&#x0002f;ml pepstatin, 50 mg&#x0002f;ml PMSF, 1 mg&#x0002f;ml leupeptin and 2 mg&#x0002f;ml aprotinin). Two additional brief washes with 8 ml of washing solution containing 25 mM imidazole were performed before eluting proteins binding to the Ni&#x02013;NTA with 800 &#x000b5;l of elution buffer (washing solution containing 250 mM imidazole).</p><p> HAT assays were performed in 30 &#x000b5;l reactions containing 50&#x000a0;mM Tris&#x02013;HCl pH 8.0, 10&#x00025; glycerol, 1 mM DTT, 1 mM PMSF, 0.1 mM EDTA, 50 mM NaCl, 10 mM butyric acid, 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g calf thymus histones (Sigma), 200 &#x000b5;Ci &#x0005b;<sup>3</sup>H&#x0005d;acetyl-CoA (NEN) and either 1.8 &#x000b5;g full-length atGCN5, 2.9 &#x000b5;g N-terminal truncated atGCN5 or 2.8 &#x000b5;g purified recombinant human TAF31 (as a negative control). The reaction mixture was incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 30 min, after which the reactions were terminated by adding 20 &#x000b5;l of SDS&#x02013;PAGE loading buffer. Twenty microliters of the terminated reaction mixtures were electrophoresed on 18&#x00025; SDS&#x02013;polyacrylamide gels. Gels were fixed (40&#x00025; methanol, 10&#x00025; acetic acid solution), soaked in autoradiographic enhancer (NEN Life Science Products), vacuum dried and exposed to X-ray film for 2 days.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> protein interaction assays</title><p>Plasmids expressing GST fusion proteins bearing CBF1 or various fragments of atGCN5 (amino acids 1&#x02013;568, 1&#x02013;150 or 155&#x02013;568) were constructed using pGEX vectors (Pharmacia). Recombinant proteins were expressed in <italic>E.coli</italic> strains XA90 or BL21(DE3) CodonPlus following induction with 40&#x02013;60 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml IPTG at 20&#x000b0;C for 20 h. Cells were lysed by French press in buffer B (10 mM Tris pH 7.9, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA and 10&#x00025; glycerol) with a protease inhibitor cocktail (Boehringer Mannheim) and 1 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml pepstatin. Triton X-100 and DTT were added to 1&#x00025; (v&#x0002f;v) and 10 mM final concentration, respectively, and the lysates were rocked at 4&#x000b0;C for 40 min. Following centrifugation at 20 000 <italic>g</italic> for 15 min, 1 ml of the supernatant was shaken together with 60 &#x000b5;l of glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads (Pharmacia) for 90 min at 4&#x000b0;C. The beads were then washed eight times with 1 ml of buffer B containing 10 mM &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol, 0.2&#x00025; Triton X-100, 1 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml pepstatin, 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml PMSF, 1 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml leupeptin and 2 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml aprotinin. To check protein purity, the bead-bound protein was eluted with 2&#x00025; SDS and visualized by silver staining after fractionation by SDS&#x02013;PAGE.</p><p> To express the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2a, ADA2b and GCN5 proteins <italic>in vitro</italic> the corresponding cDNAs were cloned into pET-28 vectors (Novagen). A plasmid expressing luciferase was provided by the manufacturer. Purified plasmid DNAs were used as templates in the TNT T7 transcription&#x0002f;translation system (Promega) containing &#x0005b;<sup>35</sup>S&#x0005d;methionine to radiolabel the expressed protein.</p><p> Depending on the specific experiment, either 1 or 2 &#x000b5;g GST or GST fusion protein bound to glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads was incubated with 4 &#x000b5;l of radiolabeled translation mixture for 1 h at 25&#x000b0;C in 200 &#x000b5;l of binding buffer (40 mM HEPES pH 7.6, 100 mM NaAc, 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EDTA, 10&#x00025; glycerol, 0.2&#x00025; Triton X-100, 1 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml pepstatin, 50 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml PMSF, 1 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml leupeptin and 2 &#x000b5;g&#x0002f;ml aprotinin) plus 8&#x00025; bovine serum. After washing six times with 800 &#x000b5;l of binding buffer (with 300 or 400 mM NaCl) at 4&#x000b0;C or room temperature the bound proteins were eluted with 2&#x00025; SDS and detected by autoradiography after SDS&#x02013;PAGE.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>CBF1 requires Ada2, Ada3 and Gcn5 to activate transcription in yeast</title><p>Our previous studies demonstrated that the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> CBF1 transcription factor induces the expression of reporter genes in yeast that carry the CRT&#x0002f;DRE regulatory element in their promoters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c2">2</xref>). If CBF1 functions in yeast by recruiting the Ada and&#x0002f;or SAGA complexes to promoters its activity should be impaired in strains with null mutations in either <italic>ADA2</italic>, <italic>ADA3</italic> or <italic>GCN5</italic>. To test this hypothesis, CBF1 was expressed in yeast strains carrying the <italic>lacZ</italic> reporter gene under the control of a minimal promoter with the CRT&#x0002f;DRE as an upstream regulatory element. In addition, the strains carried deletions of either <italic>ADA2</italic>, <italic>ADA3 </italic>or <italic>GCN5</italic>. Assays of &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity indicated that the ability of CBF1 to induce expression of the <italic>lacZ</italic> reporter gene was greatly impaired in all three null mutants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f1">1</xref>). The effects of the <italic>ada2</italic>, <italic>ada3</italic> and <italic>gcn5</italic> mutations on CBF1 activity were similar in degree to their effects on the activities of the Gcn4 and VP16 transcriptional activators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c28">28</xref>). The effects of the <italic>ada2</italic>, <italic>ada3</italic> and <italic>gcn5</italic> mutations on CBF1 activity do not reflect a general debilitation of the transcriptional machinery, for the activities of other transcriptional activators such as HAP4 are not affected by mutations in these genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c28">28</xref>; results not shown). Thus, we concluded that CBF1 functions through the action of the Ada2, Ada3 and Gcn5 proteins in yeast.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> has two genes encoding distinct Ada2 proteins</title><p>The observation that CBF1 activity in yeast requires the action of Ada2, Ada3 and Gcn5 raised the possibility that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> might have transcriptional complexes related to Ada and&#x0002f;or SAGA and, more specifically, might encode homologs of Ada2, Ada3 and Gcn5. BLAST searches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c38">38</xref>) of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> EST database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c39">39</xref>) indicated the presence of a cDNA clone encoding an apparent Ada2 homolog (EST clone accession no.&#x000a0;T76166). DNA sequencing and northern blot analysis indicated that the EST clone was missing a significant portion of the 5&#x02032;-end of the Ada2 coding sequence. A cDNA encoding a full-length <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Ada2-like polypeptide was isolated by screening a size-selected cDNA library (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c32">32</xref>) using the partial EST cDNA clone as probe (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f2">2</xref>). We designate the Ada2-like polypeptide atADA2a and the gene <italic>ADA2a</italic>.</p><p> Subsequent to our identification of the cDNA encoding atADA2a, a gene encoding a second putative <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Ada2-like protein was identified by the EU <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Genome Project (GenBank accession no. 2244998; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c33">33</xref>). The gene, which is located on chromosome 4, was predicted to have 11 exons and 10 introns and span &#x0223c;4.6 kb of DNA. Attempts to amplify the corresponding cDNA based on the predicted exons were unsuccessful. However, inspection of the genomic sequence revealed an alternative first exon that included putative coding sequences quite similar to atADA2a. Based on this insight, we successfully amplified fragments from a cDNA library resulting in isolation of a cDNA encoding a second Ada2-like protein. The polypeptide was designated atADA2b and the gene <italic>ADA2b</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f2">2</xref>).</p><p> The deduced atADA2a and atADA2b polypeptides have predicted molecular weights of 62 and 58 kDa, respectively, and share 49&#x00025; amino acid sequence identity. In Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f2">2</xref> the primary structures of ADA2a and ADA2b are aligned with known Ada2 homologs from yeast and humans. Strong similarities between the four polypeptides are found primarily in three separate regions. The most N-terminal region of sequence similarity includes a Cys-rich module and a motif resembling a portion of the myb oncoprotein, both recognized initially in the yeast Ada2 sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c26">26</xref>). The corresponding region of yeast Ada2 is capable of binding <italic>in vitro</italic> to both yeast Gcn5 and the transcriptional activation domain of VP16 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c41">41</xref>). The second region of sequence similarity includes a domain which in yeast Ada2 was sufficient for <italic>in vitro</italic> interaction with yeast Ada3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c41">41</xref>). A third region of sequence similarity is present near the C-terminus; deletions of this region in the yeast homolog had no discernable effect <italic>in vivo</italic> or <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c41">41</xref>). An additional feature of both <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2 polypeptides is the presence of an N-terminal extension absent in the yeast and human Ada2 proteins. This region harbors a cluster of arginine and lysine residues that resembles a typical nuclear localization sequence.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> encodes a Gcn5 homolog with HAT activity</title><p>A BLAST search of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> EST database identified a cDNA sequence encoding a potential homolog of Gcn5 (GenBank accession no. AF037442). The predicted ORF was somewhat shorter than that of the yeast Gcn5 protein. We amplified, cloned and sequenced a putative full-length Gcn5 cDNA fragment from an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cDNA library and used the cDNA as a hybridization probe to screen a second <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cDNA library for an independent cDNA clone. The DNA sequences of both of these cDNAs lacked a cytidylate residue reported at position 519 of the original EST clone and contained an additional adenylate residue between positions 1676 and 1677 of the original sequence. These sequences have been confirmed in a genomic clone of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>GCN5</italic> locus (Y.Mao, M.F.Thomashow and S.J.Triezenberg, unpublished results). These differences in sequence result in a much longer deduced ORF (568 amino acids) than originally reported (418 amino acids). Of the 12 additional differences between our nucleotide sequence and the originally deposited sequence, six result in changes in predicted amino acids.</p><p> Alignments of the putative <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Gcn5 protein, designated atGCN5, with homologs from yeast, humans, <italic>Drosophila</italic> and <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> are presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f3">3</xref>. Two regions of atGCN5 share a high degree of sequence identity with the other Gcn5 proteins. In the HAT domain itself the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homolog is 60&#x00025; identical and 72&#x00025; similar to yeast Gcn5. Nearly all of the key amino acids or clusters essential for yeast Gcn5 activity <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c42">42</xref>) are conserved in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> atGCN5 protein. In addition, the C-terminal region of the atGCN5 polypeptide includes a conserved bromodomain, a domain that is thought to promote protein binding to chromatin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c44">44</xref>). A third feature characteristic of all described metazoan Gcn5 homologs is the presence of a large N-terminal extension absent in the Gcn5 proteins from the lower eukaryotes yeast and <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homolog also has an N-terminal extension, but this region is significantly smaller than, and has no obvious sequence similarity with, the metazoan N-terminal extensions.</p><p> Histone acetylation assays were conducted to determine whether <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> atGCN5 has the HAT activity characteristic of Gcn5 proteins. N-terminal polyhistidine tags were fused to both full-length (amino acids 1&#x02013;568) and N-terminal truncated (amino acids 155&#x02013;568) versions of atGCN5 and the proteins were expressed in <italic>E.coli</italic>. The His-tagged proteins were purified using a Ni&#x02013;NTA affinity matrix and histone acetylation was assayed by incubating the proteins with calf thymus core histones and &#x0005b;<sup>3</sup>H&#x0005d;acetyl CoA. The reaction products were resolved on SDS&#x02013;polyacrylamide gels and the acetylated histones were detected by fluorography. The results indicated that both forms of atGCN5 effectively acetylated histone H3 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f4">4</xref>). Another His-tagged recombinant protein (in this case human TAF32) purified in a similar manner showed no HAT activity, as expected. We conclude that the atGCN5 protein not only resembles a HAT in primary structure but has HAT activity with similar specificity to other Gcn5 proteins. The gene encoding the atGCN5 protein was designated <italic>GCN5</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>ADA2a</italic>, <italic>ADA2b</italic> and <italic>GCN5</italic> are transcribed in leaves and roots</title><p>Transcripts for the <italic>ADA2a</italic>, <italic>ADA2b</italic> and <italic>GCN5</italic> genes of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> were detected in leaf and root tissues at normal growth temperatures (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f5">5</xref>). Low temperature treatment did not affect the transcript levels of the genes in leaf tissue (the slight decrease in <italic>GCN5</italic> transcript levels observed in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f5">5</xref> was not consistently observed).</p></sec><sec><title>The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> atADA2 and atGCN5 polypeptides interact directly</title><p>Protein&#x02013;protein interaction experiments were conducted to determine whether the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> atADA2 polypeptides can interact directly with the atGCN5 protein. To test this, plasmids were constructed to express GST fusion proteins containing either full-length atGCN5(1&#x02013;568), an N-terminal fragment atGCN5(1&#x02013;150) or N-terminally truncated atGCN5(155&#x02013;568). Equivalent amounts of each fusion protein or GST alone were bound to glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads and incubated with <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2a or ADA2b polypeptides that had been expressed and radiolabeled <italic>in vitro</italic>. After washing off non-binding material, polypeptides that bound to the glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads were eluted, fractionated by SDS&#x02013;PAGE and detected by autoradiography. The results presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f6">6</xref> indicate that neither atADA2a nor atADA2b interacted with GST alone or GST fused to the N-terminal portion of atGCN5, but that they both interacted efficiently with GST fused to full-length atGCN5 or N-terminally truncated atGCN5 polypeptide. We conclude that both <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2 proteins interact directly with atGCN5 protein and that the interaction does not require the N-terminal region of the atGCN5 polypeptide.</p></sec><sec><title>CBF1 interacts with atADA2 and atGCN5</title><p>The results presented above raised the possibility that CBF1 might function in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> by recruiting to promoters an adaptor complex(s) that includes the atADA2 and atGCN5 proteins. If true, then CBF1 might directly interact with these proteins. To test this possibility a GST fusion protein bearing the entire CBF1 polypeptide was expressed in <italic>E.coli</italic> and bound to glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> atADA2a, atADA2b and atGCN5 proteins, as well as luciferase as a negative control, were then transcribed and translated <italic>in vitro</italic> in the presence of &#x0005b;<sup>35</sup>S&#x0005d;methionine. The radiolabeled proteins were incubated with the GST&#x02013;CBF1 fusion protein or GST alone as a negative control. After washing, proteins that were bound to the glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads were eluted, fractionated by SDS&#x02013;PAGE and detected by autoradiography. The results presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f7">7</xref> show that all three <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> adaptor proteins were effectively retained on beads carrying the GST&#x02013;CBF1 fusion protein, but not on the matrix containing GST alone. The slight retention observed on the GST matrix could be eliminated using a more stringent wash condition that did not affect protein retention on the GST&#x02013;CBF1 matrix (data not shown). Combinations of atADA2a or atADA2b with atGCN5 did not increase retention of the proteins on the GST&#x02013;CBF1 matrix. The luciferase protein was not retained on the GST&#x02013;CBF1 fusion protein, indicating that CBF1 does not avidly bind proteins in general. Likewise, some of the minor products present in preparations of the radiolabeled proteins (presumably reflecting incomplete translation or partial proteolytic products) were not retained on the CBF1 matrix.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>A recent fundamental advance in understanding transcriptional control mechanisms is the discovery of HAT-containing adaptor complexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c17">17</xref>). These complexes, which are recruited to promoters by transcriptional activators, are thought to remodel chromatin by acetylating specific histones and by making the promoters more accessible to the transcriptional apparatus. Here we present evidence that plants have HAT-containing adaptor complexes that are related to the Ada and SAGA chromatin-modifying complexes of yeast. Specifically, we establish that (i) <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> encodes homologs of the yeast Gcn5 and Ada2 proteins; (ii) the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 protein has HAT activity; (iii) the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 and ADA2 proteins physically interact with each other. Furthermore, we show that the activity of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> transcriptional activator CBF1 is dependent on the activities of the Gcn5, Ada2 and Ada3 proteins in yeast and that CBF1 physically interacts with the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 and ADA2 proteins <italic>in vitro</italic>. These results suggest that CBF1 stimulates transcription, in part, through the recruitment of Ada&#x0002f;SAGA-like chromatin-modifying complexes to the promoters of its target genes.</p><p> The two <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>ADA2</italic> genes encode proteins that strongly resemble the previously described counterparts from yeast and humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c30">30</xref>). Regions of yeast Ada2 implicated in interaction with Gcn5 and with Ada3 are notably conserved in both plant homologs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f2">2</xref>). The most N-terminal region of sequence similarity includes two potential zinc fingers comprising six conserved cysteines in the Cys-x2-Cys &#x02018;ZZ&#x02019; zinc finger configuration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c45">45</xref>) with an additional two flanking conserved histidine residues. This motif is also found in the transcriptional adaptor&#x0002f;co-activator protein p300 and the CREB (cAMP response element-binding protein)-binding protein, CBP. The N-terminal region of yeast Ada2 protein was sufficient for <italic>in vitro</italic> interactions with yeast Gcn5 and with the transcriptional activation domain of VP16 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c40">40</xref>). Deletion of the Cys-rich region from yeast Ada2 reduced co-immunoprecipitation of Gcn5, but had little discernable phenotype <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c41">41</xref>). The N-terminal region of Ada2 also contains one copy of a motif present three times in the DNA-binding domain of the Myb protein family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c46">46</xref>). Deletion of the myb motif did not affect co-precipitation of Gcn5, but nevertheless crippled the ability of Ada2 to support transcriptional activation <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c41">41</xref>). A central region of these proteins also shows considerable sequence similarity. Deletions in this region of the yeast Ada2 protein disrupted the <italic>in vitro</italic> interaction with yeast Ada3 and caused debilitating phenotypes <italic>in vivo</italic>. Despite the considerable sequence similarity in a third region near the C-terminus, deletions in this region of the yeast Ada2 protein had no significant effects <italic>in vivo</italic> or <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c41">41</xref>). Interestingly, the N-termini of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2 proteins, which are very similar to each other, show little similarity with the N-termini of the fungal or human Ada2 proteins. This region of the atADA2 proteins includes a stretch of basic amino acids that resembles nuclear localization sequences. The significance of this difference between the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and other Ada2 proteins is not known.</p><p> The significance of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> having two <italic>ADA2</italic> homologs is also unknown. It is possible that the two genes are functionally redundant. Indeed, both atADA2 proteins can interact with recombinant atGCN5 <italic>in vitro</italic> with similar apparent affinities and no gross differences in expression of the two genes were observed (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f6">6</xref>). However, we cannot yet exclude the possibility that the two atADA2 proteins have different roles. The two genes may be expressed in different cell types within leaves, roots or other tissues or differentially in response to developmental or environmental cues. It is also possible that the two atADA2 proteins may be components of distinct adaptor protein complexes that mediate distinct regulatory signals. Additional experimentation will be required to resolve these issues.</p><p> The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 polypeptide shows significant similarities in amino acid sequence to the HAT catalytic domains and bromodomains of previously described Gcn5 homologs from yeast, <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>, <italic>Drosophila</italic>, mice and humans. Moreover, the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 protein has HAT activity specific for histone H3, the hallmark of the Gcn5 proteins. Thus, the role of atGCN5 in gene regulation is likely to be similar to that proposed for the other Gcn5 proteins; remodeling chromatin to facilitate assembly of the transcriptional apparatus. Interestingly, however, the N-terminal region of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 is notably different from those found in metazoan Gcn5 proteins and is completely absent in the lower eukaryote yeast and <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> Gcn5 proteins. It will be of interest to determine whether this region of atGCN5 interacts with other proteins and affects the nature of the Ada&#x0002f;SAGA-like complex. In animal systems this domain may contribute to recognition of chromatin substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c47">47</xref>) and may also carry other functions relevant to transcriptional activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c19">19</xref>), but no definitive explanation of the function of this domain has yet been elucidated.</p><p> To our knowledge this is the first description of genes encoding plant transcriptional adaptor proteins with putative roles in chromatin remodeling. In maize, an enzyme with histone acetyltransferase activity has been described at the biochemical level and its cDNA sequence reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c49">49</xref>). However, this enzyme is a cytoplasmic type B histone acetyltransferase, which presumably acetylates newly synthesized histone H4 for transport to the nucleus and incorporation into nucleosomes; it is unlikely to mediate chromatin modification for transcriptional regulation. An <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> N-acetyltransferase designated HOOKLESS has also been described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c50">50</xref>). Mutations in the <italic>HOOKLESS</italic> gene result in developmental defects, notably a lack of the differential cell growth that leads to apical hook formation in hypocotyls. The deduced sequence of the HOOKLESS protein indicates that it is a member of the Gcn5-related superfamily of acetyltransferases. However, the protein is more closely related to enzymes that acetylate small metabolites such as spermine than to HAT proteins and thus, again, is unlikely to have a role in modifying chromatin structure and transcriptional activation.</p><p> Sequence homologs of the yeast Ada2 and Gcn5 proteins have been identified in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c30">30</xref>), mouse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c47">47</xref>), <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c51">51</xref>), <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c52">52</xref>) and now <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (this report; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c33">33</xref>). The wide distribution amongst these diverse phyla suggests that these proteins play important roles in transcriptional activation, and perhaps other processes, in all eukaryotes. The precise functions of these proteins in the growth and development of these organisms, however, remain to be clarified. In yeast, mutations in <italic>ADA2</italic> and <italic>GCN5</italic> are not lethal, even though the genes are unique (i.e. are single copy genes). Inactivation of either <italic>ADA2</italic> or <italic>GCN5</italic>, however, produces pleiotropic effects. Yeast carrying null mutations in either of these genes grow slowly, especially in minimal media, and are both cold- and high-temperature-sensitive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c28">28</xref>). Microarray analysis indicated that under standard growth conditions expression of &#x0223c;5&#x00025; of all yeast genes is affected by inactivation of <italic>GCN5</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c53">53</xref>). The affected genes showed no obvious specialization, being involved in a wide range of cell processes. No similar comprehensive analysis has yet been performed in a higher eukaryote. However, it has recently been demonstrated that in mice, homozygous <italic>GCN5</italic> null mutations result in an embryonic lethal phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c55">55</xref>). Interestingly, knockout mutations of the closely related <italic>PCAF</italic> gene had no discernable phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c55">55</xref>). To date, no <italic>ADA2</italic> mutations have been described in higher eukaryotes. The ability to use reverse genetics in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> to test gene function should help to determine whether the <italic>ADA2</italic> and <italic>GCN5</italic> genes of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> participate broadly in controlling gene expression or are involved in specific functions, including the regulation of genes involved in environmental stress tolerance.</p></sec><sec><title>NOTE ADDED IN PROOF</title><p>A report published after submission of this manuscript indicates that <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> encodes proteins related to the p300 and CBP transcriptional coactivator proteins from animals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gke245c56">56</xref>).</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig id="gke245f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p> Transcriptional activation by CBF1 in yeast requires the yeast <italic>ADA2</italic>, <italic>ADA3</italic> and <italic>GCN5</italic> genes. A reporter gene consisting of two CRT&#x0002f;DRE <italic>cis</italic>-acting sequences inserted 5&#x02032; to a <italic>GAL1</italic> minimal promoter&#x02013;<italic>lacZ</italic> gene fusion was integrated into the <italic>URA3</italic> locus of the wild-type parental yeast strain PSY316 and the respective isogenic <italic>ada2</italic>, <italic>ada3</italic> and <italic>gcn5</italic> deletion mutant strains. These strains were transformed with a 2&#x000b5; plasmid carrying the CBF1 coding sequence under control of the constitutive promoter ADC1 and were grown to mid-log phase (OD<sub>590</sub> &#x0003d; 0.6 to 0.8) before cell extracts were assayed for &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity (31). Values for &#x003b2;-galactosidase activity were normalized to total yeast cellular protein. Error bars represent the standard deviation about the mean for three independent yeast cultures.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gke24501"/></fig><fig id="gke245f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> encodes two apparent homologs of the ADA2 proteins of human and yeast. Amino acid sequences for ADA2 homologs from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (a), human (h) and yeast (y) were deduced from cDNA sequences and aligned using the PILEUP program of the GCC sequence analysis package. Amino acids identical in all four sequences are shown as white letters on a black background, whereas amino acids with similar side chains in all four sequences are shown as black letters with a gray background. Three regions of sequence similarity are indicated by black, hatched or gray lines above the sequences, including a Cys-rich region (thick black line) and a myb motif (vertical stripes). Potential nuclear localization signals in both <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2 sequences are boxed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gke24502"/></fig><fig id="gke245f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p> The predicted <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 protein sequence reveals HAT and bromodomains that are similar to regions of GCN5 proteins from other organisms. (<bold>A</bold>, above) Amino acid sequences predicted from cDNA or gene sequences for GCN5 homologs were aligned using the PILEUP program. Prefixes to protein names indicate species: h, human; m, mouse; d, <italic>Drosophila</italic>; a, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>; y, <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>; Tt, <italic>Tetrahymena</italic>. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 sequence is shown in bold. Amino acids identical in all eight sequences are indicated by white letters with a black background; amino acids with similar side chains in all eight sequences are shown on a gray background. The HAT domain is represented by a black bar above the sequences. The Glu residue critical for catalysis by yeast Gcn5 is marked by a black triangle. The bromodomain is represented by a gray bar above the sequences. (<bold>B</bold>, opposite) Schematic representation of regions of sequence similarity among GCN5 homologs. The HAT domain is represented by hatched bars, the bromodomain is denoted by shaded bars and the N-terminal extensions found in animal and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 proteins are shown as open and filled bars, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gke24503"/><graphic xlink:href="gke24503b"/></fig><fig id="gke245f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 selectively acetylates histone H3 <italic>in vitro</italic>. Full-length atGCN5(1&#x02013;568), a truncated form of atGCN5 (comprising residues 155&#x02013;568, which retains the conserved HAT domain) and human TAF32 were expressed as polyhistidine-tagged fusion proteins in <italic>E.coli </italic>and subsequently purified using a Ni&#x02013;NTA affinity matrix. Purified recombinant proteins (1.8 &#x000b5;g full-length atGCN5; 2.9 &#x000b5;g truncated atGCN5; 2.8 &#x000b5;g hTAF32) were incubated for 30 min at 30&#x000b0;C with 20 &#x000b5;g calf thymus core histones in the presence of &#x0005b;<sup>3</sup>H&#x0005d;acetyl-CoA. Following fractionation by 18&#x00025; SDS&#x02013;PAGE, gels were fixed and either stained with Coomassie blue (left) or exposed to X-ray film for fluorography (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gke24504"/></fig><fig id="gke245f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>ADA2a</italic>, <italic>ADA2b</italic> and <italic>GCN5</italic> are transcribed in roots and leaves. Northern filters were prepared with total RNA (20 &#x000b5;g) isolated from roots (R) or leaves (L) of plants grown <italic>in vitro</italic> at 22&#x000b0;C or from leaves of cold acclimated plants grown in soil (Lc). Filters were hybridized with cDNA probes for either <italic>ADA2a</italic>, <italic>ADA2b</italic> or <italic>GCN5</italic> and then stripped and hybridized in succession with cDNA probes for <italic>eIF-4A</italic> and <italic>COR15a</italic>. Autoradiography for the <italic>ADA2a</italic>, <italic>ADA2b</italic>, <italic>GCN5</italic> and <italic>eIF-4A</italic> probes was for 22 h using a single intensifying screen at &#x02013;80&#x000b0;C; exposure for the <italic>COR15a</italic> probe was for 4 h at room temperature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gke24505"/></fig><fig id="gke245f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><italic>In vitro</italic> interaction of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> GCN5 with atADA2a and atADA2b. Portions of the atGCN5 protein were expressed in <italic>E.coli</italic> as GST fusions and bound to glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads. His-tagged atADA2a and atADA2b were expressed and radiolabeled using <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription&#x02013;translation reactions. The translation reactions were incubated with the GST&#x02013;GCN5 fusion proteins, washed and then eluted in a SDS buffer. The bound proteins were detected by autoradiography after fractionation by SDS&#x02013;PAGE. The lanes from left to right contain: 50&#x00025; ADA2 protein input; eluate from GST&#x02013;GCN5(1&#x02013;568); eluate from GST&#x02013;GCN5(155&#x02013;568); eluate from GST&#x02013;GCN5(1&#x02013;150); eluate from GST alone.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gke24506"/></fig><fig id="gke245f7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><italic>In vitro</italic> interaction of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> CBF1 with atADA2a, atADA2b and atGCN5. A GST&#x02013;CBF1 fusion protein and GST alone were expressed in <italic>E.coli</italic> and bound to glutathione&#x02013;Sepharose beads. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ADA2a, ADA2b and GCN5 proteins as well as luciferase (as a negative control) were expressed and radiolabeled using <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription&#x02013;translation reactions. The translation reactions were incubated with GST or the GST&#x02013;CBF1 fusion protein, washed and then eluted in SDS. The bound proteins were detected by autoradiography after fractionation by SDS&#x02013;PAGE. Lanes on the left (50&#x00025; input) contain 50&#x00025; of the radiolabeled protein that was incubated with each GST protein. The middle lanes (GST&#x02013;CBF1) show proteins, singly or in pairs, that were bound and eluted from GST&#x02013;CBF1. Lanes on the right (GST) show proteins bound and eluted from GST alone.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gke24507"/></fig><table-wrap id="gke245tb1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title> Yeast strains</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">Strain<hr/></td><td valign="top">Genotype<hr/></td><td valign="top">Reference<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">PSY316</td><td valign="top">MAT&#x003b1; <italic>ade2-101 his3-del.200 leu2-3,2-112 lys2 ura3-53</italic></td><td valign="top">(26)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">PSY316&#x00394;<italic>ada2</italic></td><td valign="top">MAT&#x003b1; <italic>ade2-101 his3-del.200 leu2-3,2-112 lys2 ura3-53 </italic>&#x00394;<italic>ada2</italic></td><td valign="top">(26)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">PSY316&#x00394;<italic>ada3</italic></td><td valign="top">MAT&#x003b1; <italic>ade2-101 his3-del.200 leu2-3,2-112 lys2 ura3-53 </italic>&#x00394;<italic>ada3</italic></td><td valign="top">(29)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">PSY316&#x00394;<italic>gcn5</italic></td><td valign="top">MAT&#x003b1; <italic>ade2-101 his3-del.200 leu2-3,2-112 lys2 ura3-53</italic>&#x00394;<italic>trp1 </italic>&#x00394;<italic>gcn5</italic></td><td valign="top">(30)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">EJS274</td><td valign="top">MAT&#x003b1; <italic>ade2-101 his3-del.200 leu2-3,2-112 lys2 URA3</italic>::<italic>CRT-lacZ</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">EJS276</td><td valign="top">MAT&#x003b1; <italic>ade2-101 his3-del.200 leu2-3,2-112 lys2 </italic>&#x00394;<italic>ada2 URA3</italic>::<italic>CRT-lacZ</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">EJS278</td><td valign="top">MAT&#x003b1; <italic>ade2-101 his3-del.200 leu2-3,2-112 lys2 </italic>&#x00394;<italic>ada3 URA3</italic>::<italic>CRT-lacZ</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">EJS280</td><td valign="top">MAT&#x003b1; <italic>ade2-101 his3-del.200 leu2-3,2-112 lys2 </italic>&#x00394;<italic>gcn5 </italic>&#x00394;<italic>trp1 URA3</italic>::<italic>CRT-lacZ</italic></td><td valign="top">This work</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><ack><sec><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We gratefully acknowledge gifts of yeast strains, plasmids and experimental advice from Dr Shelley Berger and colleagues (Wistar Institute, Philadelphia) and from Dr Fred Winston, Harvard University. We thank Dr Tom Newman for assistance with searching the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> EST database and for plasmids. Dr Yuri Nedialkov provided the recombinant TAF32 protein used in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gke245f4">4</xref>. Other members of the Thomashow and Triezenberg laboratories are thanked for discussions, experimental assistance and comments on the manuscript. S.J.T. thanks Peter Quail, Jim Tepperman and colleagues at the UDSA Plant Gene Expression Center (Albany, CA) for their gracious hospitality and scientific advice during a sabbatical. This work was supported by NSF grant MCB-9728462 and the Michigan Agricultural Experiment Station.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="gke245c1"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Stockinger</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name>, Gilmour,S.J. and Thomashow,M.F. (1997) <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana CBF1 </italic>encodes an AP2 domain-containing transcriptional activator that binds to the C-repeat&#x0002f;DRE, a <italic>cis</italic>-acting DNA regulatory element that stimulates transcription in response to low temperature and water deficit. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>94</volume>, <fpage>1035</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1040</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9023378</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c2"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Gilmour</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name>, Zarka,D.G., Stockinger,E.J., Salazar,M.P., Houghton,J.M. and Thomashow,M.F. (1998) Low temperature regulation of the <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>CBF family of AP2 transcriptional activators as an early step in cold-induced <italic>COR </italic>gene expression. <source>Plant J.</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>442</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9881163</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c3"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, Kasuga,M., Sakuma,Y., Abe,H., Miura,S., Yamaguchi-Shinozaki,K. and Shinozaki,K. (1998) Two transcription factors, DREB1 and DREB2, with an EREBP&#x0002f;AP2 DNA binding domain separate two cellular signal transduction pathways in drought- and low-temperature-responsive gene expression, respectively, in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. <source>Plant Cell</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1406</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9707537</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c4"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Shinwari</surname><given-names>Z.K.</given-names></name>, Nakashima,K., Miura,S., Kasuga,M., Seki,M., Yamaguchi-Shinozaki,K. and Shinozaki,K. (1998) An <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>gene family encoding DRE&#x0002f;CRT binding proteins involved in low-temperature-responsive gene expression. <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>, <volume>250</volume>, <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9735350</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c5"><label>5.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Riechmann</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name> and Meyerowitz,E.M. (1998) The AP2&#x0002f;EREBP family of plant transcription factors. <source>Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>379</volume>, <fpage>633</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>646</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9687012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c6"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name>, Wilhelm,K.S. and Thomashow,M.F. (1994) The 5&#x02032; region of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic><italic>cor15a</italic> has <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements that confer cold-, drought- and ABA-regulated gene expression. <source>Plant Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>701</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>713</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8193295</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c7"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> and Shinozaki,K. (1994) A novel <italic>cis</italic>-acting element in an <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>gene is involved in responsiveness to drought, low temperature, or high salt stress. <source>Plant Cell</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>264</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8148648</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c8"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Thomashow</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name> (1998) Role of cold-responsive genes in plant freezing tolerance. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>, <volume>118</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9733520</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c9"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Jaglo-Ottosen</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name>, Gilmour,S.J., Zarka,D.G., Schabenberger,O. and Thomashow,M.F. (1998) <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>CBF1</italic> overexpression induces <italic>COR </italic>genes and enhances freezing tolerance. <source>Science</source>, <volume>280</volume>, <fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9525853</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c10"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> and Weintraub,S.J. (1998) Stepwise recruitment of components of the preinitiation complex by upstream activators <italic>in vivo</italic>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>2876</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2883</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9566906</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c11"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, Horn,P.J., Sullivan,S.M., Triezenberg,S.J., Boyer,T.G. and Berk,A.J. (1998) DNA-complex assembly activity required for VP16C transcriptional activation. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>4023</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4031</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632787</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c12"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Gaudreau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Keaveney,M., Nevado,J., Zaman,Z., Bryant,G.O., Struhl,K. and Ptashne,M. (1999) Transcriptional activation by artificial recruitment in yeast is influenced by promoter architecture and downstream sequences. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>96</volume>, <fpage>2668</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2673</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10077568</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c13"><label>13.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nevado</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, Gaudreau,L., Adam,M. and Ptashne,M. (1999) Transcriptional activation by artificial recruitment in mammalian cells. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>96</volume>, <fpage>2674</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2677</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10077569</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c14"><label>14.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name> (1998) Chromatin remodeling machines: similar motors, ulterior motives. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9478131</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c15"><label>15.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Workman</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name> and Kingston,R.E. (1998) Alteration of nucleosome structure as a mechanism of transcriptional regulation. <source>Annu. Rev. Biochem.</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>579</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9759497</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c16"><label>16.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Strahl</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name> and Allis,C.D. (2000) The language of covalent histone modifications. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>403</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10638745</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c17"><label>17.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name> and Allis,C.D. (1998) Roles of histone acetyltransferases and deacetylases in gene regulation. <source>Bioessays</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>615</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>626</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9780836</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c18"><label>18.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name>, Schmid,A., Zavari,M., Lui,L., Berger,S.L. and Horz,W. (1998) Absence of Gcn5 HAT activity defines a novel state in the opening of chromatin at the PHO5 promoter in yeast. <source>Mol. Cell</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>505</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9660934</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c19"><label>19.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name>, Zhou,J., Jambeck,P., Churchill,M.E. and Allis,C.D. (1998) Histone acetyltransferase activity of yeast Gcn5p is required for the activation of target genes <italic>in vivo</italic>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>639</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9499399</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c20"><label>20.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, Steger,D.J., Eberharter,A. and Workman,J.L. (1999) Activation domain-specific and general transcription stimulation by native histone acetyltransferase complexes. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>855</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>863</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9858608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c21"><label>21.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name>, Duggan,L., Cote,J., Roberts,S.M., Brownell,J.E., Candau,R., Ohba,R., Owen-Hughes,T., Allis,C.D., Winston,F., Berger,S.L. and Workman,J.L. (1997) Yeast Gcn5 functions in two multisubunit complexes to acetylate nucleosomal histones: characterization of an Ada complex and the SAGA (Spt&#x0002f;Ada) complex. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>1640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1650</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9224714</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c22"><label>22.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name>, Schieltz,D., Pray-Grant,M.G., Steger,D.J., Reese,J.C., Yates,J.R. and Workman,J.L. (1998) A subset of TAF(II)s are integral components of the SAGA complex required for nucleosome acetylation and transcriptional stimulation. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>94</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9674426</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c23"><label>23.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name>, Schieltz,D., Pray-Grant,M.G., Yates,J.R. and Workman,J.L. (1998) The ATM-related cofactor Tra1 is a component of the purified SAGA complex. <source>Mol. Cell</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>867</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9885573</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c24"><label>24.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogryzko</surname><given-names>V.V.</given-names></name>, Kotani,T., Zhang,X., Schlitz,R.L., Howard,T., Yang,X.J., Howard,B.H., Qin,J. and Nakatani,Y. (1998) Histone-like TAFs within the PCAF histone acetylase complex. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>94</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9674425</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c25"><label>25.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Eberharter</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, Sterner,D.E., Schieltz,D., Hassan,A., Yates,J.R., Berger,S.L. and Workman,J.L. (1999) The ADA complex is a distinct histone acetyltransferase complex in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>Mol.&#x000a0;Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>6621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6631</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gke245c26"><label>26.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name>, Pina,B., Silverman,N., Marcus,G.A., Agapite,J., Regier,J.L., Triezenberg,S.J. and Guarente,L. (1992) Genetic isolation of ADA2: a potential transcriptional adaptor required for function of certain acidic activation domains. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>265</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1638630</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c27"><label>27.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Georgakopoulos</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> and Thireos,G. (1992) Two distinct yeast transcriptional activators require the function of the GCN5 protein to promote normal levels of transcription. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>4145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4152</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1396595</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c28"><label>28.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name>, Silverman,N., Berger,S.L., Horiuchi,J. and Guarente,L. (1994) Functional similarity and physical association between GCN5 and ADA2: putative transcriptional adaptors. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>4807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4815</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7957049</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c29"><label>29.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Pi&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, Berger,S., Marcus,G.A., Silverman,N., Agapite,J. and Guarente,L. (1993) ADA3: a gene, identified by resistance to GAL4-VP16, with properties similar to and different from those of ADA2. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>5981</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5989</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8413201</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c30"><label>30.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Candau</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, Moore,P.A., Wang,L., Barlev,N., Ying,C.Y., Rosen,C.A. and Berger,S.L. (1996) Identification of human proteins functionally conserved with the yeast putative adaptors ADA2 and GCN5. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>602</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8552087</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c31"><label>31.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and Botstein,D. (1983) Construction and use of gene fusions to <italic>lacZ </italic>(&#x003b2;-galactosidase) that are expressed in yeast. <source>Methods Enzymol.</source>, <volume>101</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>180</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6310320</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c32"><label>32.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kieber</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>, Rothenberg,M., Roman,G., Feldmann,K.A. and Ecker,J.R. (1993) CTR1, a negative regulator of the ethylene response pathway in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, encodes a member of the raf family of protein kinases. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>441</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8431946</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c33"><label>33.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Bancroft,I., Bent,E., Love,K., Goodman,H., Dean,C., Bergkamp,R., Dirkse,W., Van Staveren,M., Stiekma,W., Drost,L., Ridley,O., Hudson,S.-A., Patel,K., Murphy,G., Piffanelli,P., Wedler,H., Wedler,E., Wambutt,R., Weitzenegger,T., Pohl,T.M., Terryn,N., Gielen,J., Villarroel,R., De Clerck,R., Van Montague,M., Lecharny,A., Auborg,S., Gy,I., Kreis,M., Lao,N., Kavanagh,T., Hempel,S., Kotter,P., Entian,K.-D., Rieger,M., Schaeffer,M., Funk,B., Mueller-Auer,S., Silvey,M., James,R., Montfort,A., Pons,A., Puigdomenech,P., Douka,A., Voukelatou,E., Miliono,D., Hatzopoulos,P., Piravandi,E., Obermaier,B., Hilbert,H., D&#x000fc;sterh&#x000f6;ft,A., Moores,T., Jones,J.D.G., Eneva,T., Palme,K., Benes,V., Rechman,S., Ansorge,W., Cooke,R., Berger,C., Delseny,M., Voet,M., Volckaert,G., Mewes,H.-W., Klosterman,S., Schueller,C. and Chalwatzis,N. (1998) Analysis of 1.9 Mb of contiguous sequence from chromosome 4 of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>391</volume>, <fpage>485</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>491</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9461215</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c34"><label>34.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Puissant</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> and Houdebine,L.-M. (1990) An improvement of the single-step method of RNA isolation by acid guanidinium thiocyanate-phenol-chloroform extraction. <source>Biotechniques</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1690559</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c35"><label>35.</label><citation citation-type="other"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, Fritsch,E.F. and Maniatis,T. (1989) <italic>Molecular Cloning: A&#x000a0;Laboratory Manual</italic>, 2nd Edn. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold Spring Harbor, NY.</citation></ref><ref id="gke245c36"><label>36.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Feinberg</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name> and Vogelstein,B. (1983) A technique for radiolabelling restriction endonuclease fragments to high specific activity. <source>Anal. Biochem.</source>, <volume>132</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6312838</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c37"><label>37.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name> and Gilbert,W. (1984) Genomic sequencing. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>1991</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1995</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6326095</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c38"><label>38.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Gish,W., Miller,W., Meyers,E. and Lipman,D. (1990) Basic local alignment search tool. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>215</volume>, <fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c39"><label>39.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, de Bruijn,F.J., Green,P., Keegstra,K., Kende,H., McIntosh,L., Ohlrogge,J., Raikhel,N., Somerville,S., Thomashow,M., Retzel,E. and Somerville,C. (1994) Genes galore: a summary of methods for accessing results from large-scale partial sequencing of anonymous <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>cDNA clones. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>, <volume>106</volume>, <fpage>1241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1255</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7846151</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c40"><label>40.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Barlev</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name>, Candau,R., Wang,L., Darpino,P., Silverman,N. and Berger,S.L. (1995) Characterization of physical interactions of the putative transcriptional adaptor, ADA2, with acidic activation domains and TATA-binding protein. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>19337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19344</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7642611</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c41"><label>41.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Candau</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> and Berger,S.L. (1996) Structural and functional analysis of yeast putative adaptors: evidence for an adaptor complex <italic>in vivo</italic>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>271</volume>, <fpage>5237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5245</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8617808</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c42"><label>42.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Liu,L. and Berger,S.L. (1998) Critical residues for histone acetylation by Gcn5, functioning in Ada and SAGA complexes, are also required for transcriptional function <italic>in vivo</italic>. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>653</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9499400</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c43"><label>43.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Jeanmougin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Wurtz,J.M., Le Douarin,B., Chambon,P. and Losson,R. (1997) The bromodomain revisited. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>153</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9175470</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c44"><label>44.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Dhalluin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, Carlson,J.E., Zeng,L., He,C., Aggarwal,A.K. and Zhou,M.M. (1999) Structure and ligand of a histone acetyltransferase bromodomain. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>399</volume>, <fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>496</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10365964</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c45"><label>45.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name>, Blake,D.J., Davies,K.E., Kendrick-Jones,J. and Winder,S.J. (1996) ZZ and TAZ: new putative zinc fingers in dystrophin and other proteins. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>241</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gke245c46"><label>46.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, Ibanez,C., Garcia,A., Graf,T. and Lipsick,J. (1990) Transformation by v-myb correlates with trans-activation of gene expression. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>2591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2598</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2160580</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c47"><label>47.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, Edmondson,D.G. and Roth,S.Y. (1998) Mammalian GCN5 and P&#x0002f;CAF acetyltransferases have homologous amino-terminal domains important for recognition of nucleosomal substrates. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>5659</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5669</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9742083</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c48"><label>48.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Eberharter</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, Lechner,T., Goralik-Schramel,M. and Loidl,P. (1996) Purification and characterization of the cytoplasmic histone acetyltransferase B of maize embryos. <source>FEBS Lett.</source>, <volume>386</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8635608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c49"><label>49.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lusser</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, Eberharter,A., Loidl,A., Goralik-Schramel,M., Horngacher,M., Haas,H. and Loidl,P. (1999) Analysis of the histone acetyltransferase B complex of maize embryos. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>4427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10536152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c50"><label>50.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, Black,R. and Ecker,J.R. (1996) <italic>HOOKLES</italic>S1, an ethylene response gene, is required for differential cell elongation in the Arabidopsis hypocotyl. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8612271</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c51"><label>51.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name>, Belote,J.R., Schiltz,R.L., Yang,X.-J., Moore,P.A., Berger,S.L., Yoshihiro,N. and Allis,C.D. (1998) Cloning of <italic>Drosophila </italic>GCN5: conserved features among metazoan GCN5 family members. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>2948</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2954</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9611240</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c52"><label>52.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Brownell</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name>, Zhou,J., Ranalli,T., Kobayashi,R., Edmondson,D.G., Roth,S.Y. and Allis,C.D. (1996) <italic>Tetrahymena</italic> histone acetyltransferase A: a homolog to yeast Gcn5p linking histone acetylation to gene activation. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>843</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>851</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8601308</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c53"><label>53.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Holstege</surname><given-names>F.C.P.</given-names></name>, Jennings,E.G., Wyrick,J.J., Lee,T.I., Hengartner,C.J., Green,M.R., Golub,T.R., Lander,E.S. and Young,E.S. (1998) Dissecting the regulatory circuitry of a eukaryotic genome. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>717</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>728</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9845373</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c54"><label>54.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, Edmondson,D.G., Evrard,Y.A., Wakamiya,M., Behringer,R.R. and Roth,S.Y. (2000) Loss of gcn5l2 leads to increased apoptosis and mesodermal defects during mouse development. <source>Nature Genet.</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>232</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11017084</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c55"><label>55.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, Yamauchi,J., Kuwata,T., Tamura,T., Yamashita,T., Bae,N., Westphal,H., Ozato,K. and Nakatani,Y. (2000) Distinct but overlapping roles of histone acetylase PCAF and of the closely related PCAF-B&#x0002f;GCN5 in mouse embryogenesis. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>11303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11027331</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gke245c56"><label>56.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bordoli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Netsch,N., L&#x000fc;thi,U., Lutz,W. and Eckner,R. (2001) Plant orthologs of p300&#x0002f;CBP: conservation of a core domain in metazoan p300&#x0002f;CBP acetyltransferase-related proteins. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>597</lpage>.</citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 