 <!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20031101//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?scanned_data?><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">2165589</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A steroid/thyroid hormone receptor superfamily member in Drosophila melanogaster that shares extensive sequence similarity with a mammalian homologue.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Henrich</surname><given-names>V C</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sliter</surname><given-names>T J</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lubahn</surname><given-names>D B</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>MacIntyre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>L I</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Biology, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill 27599-3280.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>1990</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>4143</fpage><lpage>4148</lpage><abstract><p>A gene in Drosophila melanogaster that maps cytologically to 2C1-3 on the distal portion of the X-chromosome encodes a member of the steroid/thyroid hormone receptor superfamily. The gene was isolated from an embryonic cDNA library using an oligonucleotide probe that specifies the consensus amino acid sequence in the DNA-binding domain of several human receptors. The conceptual amino acid sequence of 2C reveals at least four regions of homology that are shared with all identified vertebrate receptors. Region I includes the two cysteine-cysteine zinc fingers that comprise a DNA-binding domain which typifies all members of the superfamily. In addition, three regions (Regions II-IV) in the carboxy-terminal portion of the protein that encode the putative hormone-binding domain of the 2C gene product resemble similar sequences in vertebrate steroid/thyroid hormone receptors. The similarity suggests that this Drosophila receptor possesses many of the regulatory functions attributed to these regions in vertebrate counterparts. A portion of Region II also resembles part of the human c-jun oncoprotein's leucine zipper, which in turn, has been demonstrated to be the heterodimerization site between the jun and fos oncoproteins. The 2C receptor-like protein most resembles the mouse H2RII binding protein, a member of the superfamily which has been implicated in the regulation of major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class I gene expression. These two gene products are 83% identical in the DNA-binding domain and 50% identical in the putative hormone-binding domain, although no ligand has been identified for either protein. The high degree of similarity in the hormone-binding domain between the 2C protein and the H2RII binding protein outside regions II-IV suggests specific functional roles which are not shared by other members of the superfamily.</p><sec><title>Images</title><fig id="F1"><graphic xlink:href="nar00198-0101-a" xlink:role="4145"/></fig></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="nar00198-0099.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="4143"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00198-0100.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="4144"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00198-0101.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="4145"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00198-0102.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="4146"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00198-0103.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="4147"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00198-0104.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="4148"/></supplementary-material></body></article> 