 <!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20031101//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?scanned_data?><?from_PubMed?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">1702199</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mutagenesis of selC, the gene for the selenocysteine-inserting tRNA-species in E. coli: effects on in vivo function.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heider</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;ck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Lehrstuhl f&#x000fc;r Mikrobiologie der Universit&#x000e4;t M&#x000fc;nchen, FRG.</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>1990</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>6761</fpage><lpage>6766</lpage><abstract><p>The selenocysteine-inserting tRNA (tRNA(Sec)) of E. coli differs in a number of structural features from all other elongator tRNA species. To analyse the functional implications of the deviations from the consensus, these positions have been reverted to the canonical configuration. The following results were obtained: (i) inversion of the purine/pyrimidine pair at position 11/24 and change of the purine at position 8 into the universally conserved U had no functional consequence whereas replacements of U9 by G9 and of U14 by A14 decreased the efficiency of selenocysteine insertion as measured by translation of the fdhF message; (ii) deleting one basepair in the aminoacyl acceptor stem, thus creating the canonical 7 bp configuration, inactivated tRNA(Sec); (iii) replacement of the extra arm by that of a serine-inserting tRNA abolished the activity whereas reduction by 1 base or the insertion of three bases partially reduced function; (iv) change of the anticodon to that of a serine inserter abolished the capacity to decode UGA140 whereas the alteration to a cysteine codon permitted 30% read-through. However, the variant with the serine-specific anticodon efficiently inserted selenocysteine into a gene product when the UGA140 of the fdhF mRNA was replaced by a serine codon (UCA). Significantly, none of these changes resulted in the non-specific incorporation of selenocysteine into protein, indicating that the mRNA context also plays a major role in directing insertion. Taken together, the results demonstrate that the 8-basepair acceptor stem and the long extra arm are crucial determinants of tRNA(Sec) which enable decoding of UGA140 in the fdhF message.</p><sec><title>Images</title><fig id="F1"><graphic xlink:href="nar00207-0028-a" xlink:role="6764"/></fig><fig id="F2"><graphic xlink:href="nar00207-0028-b" xlink:role="6764"/></fig></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><supplementary-material content-type="scanned-pages"><graphic xlink:href="nar00207-0025.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="6761"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00207-0026.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="6762"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00207-0027.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="6763"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00207-0028.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="6764"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00207-0029.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="6765"/><graphic xlink:href="nar00207-0030.tif" xlink:title="scanned-page" xlink:role="6766"/></supplementary-material></body></article> 