<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkh194</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh194</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">14744977</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cassette-like variation of restriction enzyme genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> C and relatives</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>Marion H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raleigh</surname><given-names>Elisabeth A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="gkh194fn1">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x8f472b0.0x96a5740">New England Biolabs, Beverly, MA 01915, USA </aff><author-notes><fn id="gkh194fn1"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: &#x0002b;1 978 927 5054; Fax: &#x0002b;1 978 921 1350; Email: <email>raleigh@neb.com</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nar.oupjournals.org/content/vol32/issue2//"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2003</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Oxford University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><abstract><p>A surprising result of comparative bacterial genomics has been the large amount of DNA found to be present in one strain but not in another of the same species. We examine in detail one location where gene content varies extensively, the restriction cluster in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. This region is designated the Immigration Control Region (ICR) for the density and variability of restriction functions found there. To better define the boundaries of this variable locus, we determined the sequence of the region from a restrictionless strain, <italic>E.coli</italic> C. Here we compare the 13.7 kb <italic>E.coli</italic> C sequence spanning the site of the ICR with corresponding sequences from five <italic>E.coli</italic> strains and <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> LT2. To discuss this variation, we adopt the term &#x02018;framework&#x02019; to refer to genes that are stable components of genomes within related lineages, while &#x02018;migratory&#x02019; genes are transient inhabitants of the genome. Strikingly, seven different migratory DNA segments, encoding different sets of genes and gene fragments, alternatively occupy a single well-defined location in the seven strains examined. The flanking framework genes, <italic>yjiS</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic>, display approximately normal patterns of conservation. The patterns observed are consistent with the action of a site-specific recombinase. Since no nearby gene codes for a likely recombinase of known families, such a recombinase must be of a new family or unlinked.</p></abstract></article-meta><notes id="N0x8f472b0.0x96a5800" notes-type="data_link"><p>DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank accession no. AY392450</p></notes></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The Immigration Control Region (ICR) was defined in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c1">1</xref>) as a locus at 98.6 min specifying three different restriction systems within 14 kb of DNA. This cluster includes the <italic>hsdR</italic>, <italic>hsdM</italic> and <italic>hsdS</italic> genes encoding the type I system EcoKI, as well as the methylation-dependent restriction system genes <italic>mcrB</italic>, <italic>mcrC</italic> and <italic>mrr.</italic> Type I restriction genes resident here (linked to <italic>serB</italic> and <italic>thr</italic>) are known to be highly variable in specificity, both within <italic>E.coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c4">4</xref>) and among enteric bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c6">6</xref>). Some strains apparently lack restriction-modification (RM) systems at this locus. <italic>E.coli</italic> C has been a reference &#x02018;restrictionless&#x02019; strain for many years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c8">8</xref>).</p><p>Existing clues to the sequence evolution of the ICR of <italic>E.coli</italic> suggested a model of replaceable cassettes at a single location. These might be similar to the cassettes of integrons, which can be exchanged by means of site-specific recombinases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c9">9</xref>); or to alternative prophages at an attachment site, as with phage 21 and the e14 excisable element (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c10">10</xref>); or they could resemble the DpnI/DpnII exchangeable cassettes found in <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c12">12</xref>), which are exchanged by means of homologous recombination in flanking DNA.</p><p>Three lines of evidence suggested that replaceable cassettes might occupy this location. First, many enteric strains have at least one restriction gene in this genetic location, but the restriction specificities are quite variable. At least 16 different specificities can be identified in 37 isolates of the ECOR collection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c13">13</xref>), a strain set designed to represent the diversity of the <italic>E.coli</italic> species worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c15">15</xref>). This variability is found not only in <italic>E.coli</italic> but also among different genera of enteric bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c6">6</xref>).</p><p>Second, despite the residence of similar function (restriction) at the same genetic location in different strains, the DNA sequences determining that function are often highly divergent. The <italic>hsd</italic> genes have been grouped into four families (IA, IB, IC, ID) based on sequence similarity, functional complementation, and antibody cross-reactivity within but not between families (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c18">18</xref>). To appreciate the level of divergence between families, Sharp <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c19">19</xref>) used divergence within type IA modification subunits (HsdM) of <italic>E.coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> as a clock and suggested that IA and IB families were so divergent that the difference might distinguish bacterial phyla &#x0005b;roughly, comparing purple sulfur bacteria and spirochaetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c20">20</xref>)&#x0005d;. Despite this high level of divergence, members of three of the four families are found at the same location in <italic>E.coli</italic>, genetically linked to the <italic>thr</italic> locus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c4">4</xref>). Analysis of four members of the IA family suggested that lateral transfer of <italic>hsd</italic> sequence has occurred (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c19">19</xref>).</p><p>The third line of evidence suggesting a cassette-swap model is the presence of conserved (or at least hybridizable) sequence flanking the locus in strains with divergent type I systems, by Southern blot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c6">6</xref>). This suggests that these diverged genes occupy the same sequence environment, and that transposition or other site-independent mechanisms did not mediate acquisition.</p><p>The modification-dependent restriction genes flanking the type I systems have been less well-studied, but limited evidence suggests lateral transfer has affected these genes as well. The <italic>mrr</italic> gene of <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> LT2 is relatively divergent from that of <italic>E.coli</italic> K-12 (71&#x00025; DNA identity). Typical homologous genes serving the same function (orthologs) display DNA identity of &#x0223c;84&#x00025; in <italic>E.coli&#x02013;Salmonella</italic> comparisons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c21">21</xref>). The <italic>mcrB</italic> and <italic>mcrC</italic> genes are entirely absent from many <italic>E.coli</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c6">6</xref>).</p><p>In addition to a high frequency of segmental replacement, the region as a whole appears to be subject to higher levels of homologous recombination than is typical of most of the chromosome. Milkman and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c23">23</xref>) designated the region containing the ICR as one of two &#x02018;hypervariable regions&#x02019; in the <italic>E.coli</italic> genome. These regions show signs that homologous recombination of horizontally transferred DNA contributed significantly to the evolutionary history of the genes resident there. The other such region contains the O-antigen gene complex near 45 min (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c25">25</xref>). Taking another approach, Lawrence and Ochman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c26">26</xref>) classify all three restriction systems, <italic>hsd, mcrBC</italic> and <italic>mrr</italic>, as laterally transferred genes using criteria of GC content and codon usage.</p><p>To clarify the boundaries of this putative cassette locus and to gain insight into the mechanisms of variation, we sought to obtain the sequence of the region from a strain thought to lack any &#x02018;cassette&#x02019; at this location. <italic>E.coli</italic> C is such a strain by three criteria. The first is the absence of a classical RM system; it has long been used as a permissive host in the study of type I enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c7">7</xref>), and no restriction locus genetically linked to <italic>thr</italic> is identifiable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c27">27</xref>). The second is the absence of modification-dependent restriction systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c8">8</xref>), two of which flank the type I system in K-12. The third is the absence of hybridizing sequence over much of the region by Southern blot analysis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c6">6</xref>).</p><p>It is convenient at this point to enunciate the idea of &#x02018;framework genes&#x02019; and &#x02018;migratory genes&#x02019;. &#x02018;Framework genes&#x02019; are defined here as genes that remain constant in genomes of close relatives: they remain in the same order with respect to each other and in approximately the same chromosomal location, but may be locally separated by segments that come and go among strains. This idea has had several antecedents: Welch <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c28">28</xref>) used &#x02018;framework&#x02019;, &#x02018;backbone&#x02019; and &#x02018;conserved synteny&#x02019; to refer to such segments. Perna <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c29">29</xref>) used &#x02018;backbone&#x02019;, while others have referred to &#x02018;collinear regions&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c31">31</xref>). We imagine that within a cell lineage, such genes diverge in sequence in concert, or are exchanged by homologous recombination. Such recombination depends on preservation of a high degree of DNA sequence identity &#x0005b;&#x0003e;96&#x00025;; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c32">32</xref>)&#x0005d;. The default assumption is that each copy of such a gene in the lineage is descended from a common ancestor of that gene in the same lineage. Such genes are termed &#x02018;orthologous&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c33">33</xref>).</p><p>In contrast, we propose the term &#x02018;migratory genes&#x02019; to refer to genes in sequence segments that come and go <italic>en bloc</italic> within a species or other taxon. Elsewhere, such segments have been called &#x02018;loops&#x02019; or &#x02018;islands&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c30">30</xref>), or &#x02018;lineage-specific segments&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c29">29</xref>). In principle, these could be transposable elements; genes acquired by &#x02018;illegitimate recombination&#x02019; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c34">34</xref>) in an undirected fashion; or genes associated with prophages or other elements that mediate site-specific recombination at particular locations. Site-specific recombination requires particular short sequences (attachment sites) to be present on both recombining partners, and mediates rearrangement events with precise borders. Rearrangements can include insertion of one molecule into another, deletion between two such sites, or inversion between them. Such attachment sites would presumably occur at loci permissive for DNA acquisition, while insertions that disrupt other genes would be purged from the population by selection. Migratory genes found at the same locus in two cell lineages may be totally unrelated. We show below that these ideas accurately reflect the pattern of sequence variation observed in the vicinity of the ICR.</p><p>We find that the ICR is occupied by a variety of migratory genes in different strains, all flanked precisely by the same framework genes, consistent with acquisition by site-specific recombination. We also find evidence for reshuffling of these migratory genes by homologous recombination.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Strains of <italic>E.coli</italic> and growth conditions</title><p>The wild-type <italic>E.coli</italic> strain C (AC3121 &#x0003d; CGSC 3121) was obtained from the <italic>E.coli</italic> Genetic Stock Center. The wild-type <italic>E.coli</italic> strain W (ATCC 11105) was obtained from the American Type Culture Collection. The K-12 strain ER2683 &#x0005b;<italic>fhuA2 glnV44 e14- rfbD1? relA1? endA1 spoT1? thi-1</italic> &#x00394; <italic>(mcrC-mrr) 114::IS10</italic> &#x00394; <italic>(lacI-lacA) 200/</italic>F&#x02032;<italic>proAB lacI</italic><sup><italic>q</italic></sup> &#x00394;<italic>lacZM15 zzf::miniTn10</italic> (KanR)&#x0005d;, used for transformations, was constructed in this laboratory from an MM294 background strain. All strains were grown in Luria-Bertani medium at 37&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec><title>General DNA methods</title><p>Qiagen kits were used for purification of chromosomal and plasmid DNAs according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. All enzymes were from New England Biolabs. DNA amplification by PCR, restriction endonuclease digestions, DNA ligations and agarose gel electrophoresis were performed according to standard protocols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c35">35</xref>). Transformation of <italic>E.coli</italic> with plasmid DNA was done using electroporation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c36">36</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Size-fractionated genomic DNA library from <italic>E.coli</italic> C</title><p>A size-fractionated <italic>E.coli</italic> C genomic DNA library was prepared by digesting purified chromosomal DNA with EcoRI, followed by electrophoresis on an agarose gel, and elution of DNA running at about 5 kb using a Qiagen gel extraction kit. A library of these fragments was ligated to EcoRI-digested, dephosphorylated pBR322. Following electroporation into ER2683, 10 pools of about 300 colonies each were prepared, and plasmid minipreps were made from each pool. These pools comprised the size-selected library. Glycerol stocks were also prepared from 1 ml of each wash.</p></sec><sec><title>Screening of library for ICR flanking regions by PCR</title><p>We identified a pair of primers that amplify a region in the <italic>yjiY</italic> gene (downstream of <italic>mrr</italic> in <italic>E.coli</italic> K-12) from both K-12 and C genomic DNA. These <italic>yjiY</italic> primers were used to screen each of the 10 plasmid pools of the size-selected <italic>E.coli</italic> C DNA genomic library, and one of the 10 (9) showed the expected 1022 bp PCR product. The strain ER2683 was transformed with the 9 plasmid pool and 136 resulting colonies were patched on to an LB plate with ampicillin. Cells scraped from the patches were combined to make secondary pools of 13 patches each. Plasmid DNA was prepared from each secondary pool, and the <italic>yjiY</italic> PCR repeated. The pool containing patches 27&#x02013;39 was positive. Cells from each of these individual patches were scraped from the plate, individual plasmid preps made, and the <italic>yjiY</italic> PCR again repeated. Colony 38 had a positive PCR and cells from the 38 patch remaining on the plate were scraped off and an overnight culture grown to isolate a stock of this plasmid DNA. The plasmid of colony 38 was designated pMS3. To sequence the ICR flanking region upstream of <italic>mrr</italic> in <italic>E.coli</italic> C, PCR primers in <italic>yjiS</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic> were used to screen the size-selected library. The plasmid pool from plate 8 of the size-selected <italic>E.coli</italic> C library had the correct sized product from the <italic>yjiS</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic> primers. The ER2683 strain was transformed with this prep and 208 resulting colonies were patched on to LB ampicillin. Successive <italic>yjiS-yjiA</italic> PCRs were performed as described above and the plasmid DNA from one final positive colony was designated pMS4.</p></sec><sec><title>Additional PCR fragments</title><p>Because of two closely spaced EcoRI sites in the K-12 sequence (193 bp apart), we expected a corresponding gap between the ends of the pMS3 and pMS4 sequences. Primers were used to amplify a PCR product across this gap, one primer in the Z5950 coding sequence (pMS4) and one primer in <italic>yjiX</italic> (pMS3) from <italic>E.coli</italic> C genomic DNA.</p><p>Genes <italic>hpaC</italic> and <italic>hpaB</italic> are not known from <italic>E.coli</italic> C; <italic>hpaI</italic> is known from C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c37">37</xref>). To join sequence information revealed in this study with information from known <italic>E.coli</italic> C sequence, a PCR product was generated using primers in <italic>hpaC</italic> and <italic>hpaI</italic> with <italic>E.coli</italic> C chromosomal DNA as template; <italic>E.coli</italic> K-12 and <italic>E.coli</italic> W chromosomal DNA were used as negative and positive controls, respectively. A PCR product of about 5.5 kb was generated from these primers from <italic>E.coli</italic> C DNA. As expected, this product was also generated from W DNA and no product was generated from K-12 DNA. The PCR product from C DNA was cloned into the pPCR-Script Amp SK (&#x0002b;) vector (Stratagene). The sequencing of the <italic>hpaC</italic>-<italic>hpaI</italic> PCR product yielded a 5.5 kb sequence containing sequence similar to the <italic>E.coli</italic> W sequence spanning <italic>hpaC</italic> through <italic>hpaI</italic>, including the entirety of <italic>hpaB</italic>, <italic>hpaA</italic> and <italic>hpaX</italic> (GenBank Z37980).</p></sec><sec><title>Sequencing</title><p>The inserts of both pMS3 and pMS4 and the cloned <italic>hpaC</italic>&#x02013;<italic>hpaI</italic> PCR product were sequenced using as templates random insertions generated with the GPS-1 Genome Priming System (New England Biolabs). Sequencing primers were Primers S and N of the GPS kit. The PCR product joining pMS3 to pMS4 was directly sequenced using the primers employed for the original amplification. Sequence was assembled using AutoAssembler (Applied Biosystems).</p></sec><sec><title>Dyad element detection</title><p>Sequence files were created containing 70 bp of sequence from each strain, joining 40 bp to the left of the <italic>yjiS</italic> stop with 30 bp to the right of the <italic>yjiA</italic> stop. The GCG program LINEUP created a consensus sequence. STEMLOOP was then used to predict dyad symmetry elements, with parameters of: minimum stem, 6; minimum bonds/stem, 12; maximum loop 20. The dyad shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f5">5</xref> was the best of seven stems found.</p></sec><sec><title>Other genome sequence files and methods</title><p>Sequence files used were: <italic>E.coli</italic> K-12, complete genome NC&#x0005f;000913.1, nucleotides 4567731&#x02013;4590882 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c38">38</xref>); <italic>E.coli</italic> O157:H7, complete genome NC&#x0005f;002655.2, nucleotides 5463295&#x02013;5481664 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c29">29</xref>); <italic>E.coli</italic> CFT073 complete genome NC&#x0005f;004431, nucleotides 5159888&#x02013;5178596 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c28">28</xref>); <italic>E.coli</italic> W, M15950.1, AF109125.1, M17609.1 and Z37980.2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c41">41</xref>); and <italic>S.typhimurium</italic> LT2, complete genome NC&#x0005f;003197, nucleotides 4774451&#x02013;4791743 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c30">30</xref>). The <italic>E.coli</italic> C sequence files Z47799, AF036583, X81446, x55200, X53666, x81322, x75028 and s56952 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c37">37</xref>) were used to join our sequence to the rest of the <italic>hpc</italic> (<italic>hpa</italic>) operon. Sequences for CFT073 and K1 were kindly provided by Guy Plunkett in advance of publication. Sequence of the pathogenic strain K1 will be published elsewhere. Protein family annotation in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkh194tb1">1</xref> employed the Linkout facility of the Entrez web site at the National Center for Biotechnology Information (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Database/index.html">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Database/index.html</ext-link>), and the Conserved Domain Database there (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c42">42</xref>). For correlation purposes, the genetic and restriction maps of <italic>E.coli</italic> may be consulted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c44">44</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Assembly of the <italic>E.coli</italic> W contig</title><p>GenBank files M15950.1 Penicillin acylase &#x0005b;ECOPAC; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c45">45</xref>)&#x0005d;, AF109125.1 Penicillin amidase precursor regulatory region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c46">46</xref>), M17609.1 Penicillin G acylase, complete &#x0005b;ECOPGA; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c39">39</xref>)&#x0005d; and Z37980.2 &#x0005b;EC4HPADNA; <italic>hpa</italic> genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c40">40</xref>)&#x0005d; combined to form the sequence across the <italic>E.coli</italic> W version of the ICR as far as tsr. The last 21 base pairs of ECOPGA were similar to <italic>yjiS</italic> of K-12. To verify connection of this contig to <italic>yjiR</italic>, primers were designed in <italic>pac</italic> and <italic>yjiR</italic> based on known sequence in W and K-12. End sequencing of this product confirmed linkage of <italic>pac</italic> and <italic>yjiR</italic>. The sequence used in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref> was obtained from a composite of three sequences such that all the sequence was obtained from two sources. The entire region is present in AF109125 (bp 85&#x02013;373). Two corrections to the AF109125 sequence were made based on other available sequences, since this allowed improved alignment in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref>. Discrepancies were: AF109125 contained a three base insertion (&#x02018;TCG&#x02019; bp 198&#x02013;91 of that file) relative to our <italic>yjiS</italic> end sequence; second, AF109125 contained an insertion of G at position 277 of that sequence relative to ECOPAC (no G before position 21). Sequence in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f3">3</xref> is contained in ECOPGA only and was accepted as presented. Linkage to EC4HPADNA rests on a 35 bp overlap between the end of ECOPGA and the end of EC4HPADNA and the consistency of this linkage with the stable framework of the <italic>E.coli</italic> genomes.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> C ICR sequence</title><p>The region of the ICR in the <italic>E.coli</italic> genome, including the genes <italic>yjiS</italic> through <italic>yjiA</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f1">1</xref>), is spanned by an 18 kb EcoRI fragment in K-12 but only by a 5.1 kb EcoRI fragment in C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c6">6</xref>). We cloned and sequenced the 5 kb EcoRI fragment identified by Daniel <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c6">6</xref>) by Southern blot, using a PCR-directed search strategy to identify suitable clones in a size-selected clone library. The adjacent 6.7 kb was obtained by bootstrap PCR and cloning of segments with similarity to the adjoining region in the K-12 genome, also identified by PCR. Sequencing employed a mixture of vector-primed end sequencing, transposon insertion sequencing and gap closure by sequencing of PCR products. This sequence was deposited in GenBank (accession number AY392450).</p></sec><sec><title>Genes present in <italic>E.coli</italic> C</title><p>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkh194tb1">1</xref> lists genes identified in our 13.7 kb segment, inferred from DNA sequence similarity found in GenBank (release 138) using nBLAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c47">47</xref>). Genes are listed in clockwise order with respect to the K-12 sequence, and have been given the name of the best match to another <italic>E.coli</italic> strain. All genes were uninterrupted in frame relative to the database version adopted as a name, except that the start codon and first six amino acids of Z5950 differ between C and the source CFT073.</p><p>As required by the sequencing strategy, one border of this region comprises two framework genes, <italic>yjiR</italic> and <italic>yjiS</italic>. The next three genes are candidate migratory genes: they are not found at all in K-12, but are found in other strains (see below). First is a fragment of an <italic>hsdR</italic> gene similar to a type IB family restriction enzyme, EcoA. EcoA is found genetically in this region in <italic>E.coli</italic> 15T<sup>&#x02013;</sup>. We note that the 565 nucleotides encode an N-terminal fragment of <italic>hsdR</italic> that would not form a functional endonuclease. This sequence also would not have been present on the EcoA DNA probe used by Daniel <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c6">6</xref>). Our result is thus consistent with the observed lack of restriction activity or hybridization. An ORF of unknown function is next. This is also found in <italic>E.coli</italic> CFT073, designated Z5950 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c28">28</xref>); in O157:H7 a frameshift breaks this ORF into two parts, Z5949 and Z5950 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c29">29</xref>). Similarity to K-12 then resumes, with more framework genes of unknown function found to the right of the ICR in K-12: <italic>yjiA</italic>, <italic>yjiX</italic> and <italic>yjiY</italic>.</p><p>At the right end of our <italic>E.coli</italic> C sequence are five more candidate migratory genes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkh194tb1">1</xref>). Again, these are not found in K-12 but are found at this sequence location in another strain, this time in <italic>E.coli</italic> W (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c40">40</xref>). These genes, <italic>hpaC</italic>, <italic>hpaB</italic>, <italic>hpaA</italic>, <italic>hpaX</italic> and <italic>hpaI</italic> (<italic>hpcH</italic>), form the left end of a 10-gene cluster found between <italic>yjiY</italic> and <italic>tsr</italic> in <italic>E.coli</italic> W. The gene cluster enables <italic>E.coli</italic> W to degrade 4-<underline>h</underline>ydroxy<underline>p</underline>henyl<underline>a</underline>cetic acid. <italic>E.coli</italic> C also carries the other genes of this cluster: they were designated <italic>hpc</italic> (<underline>h</underline>omo<underline>p</underline>roto<underline>c</underline>atechuate degradation) by Roper <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c37">37</xref>). Our sequence overlaps that of Roper <italic>et al</italic>., and we were able to construct a contiguous sequence as far as <italic>tsr</italic> by connecting those sequences with ours. This second locus for migratory genes will not be discussed further.</p></sec><sec><title>A coarse-grained comparison: patterns of gene occurrence in the variable region between <italic>yjiS</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic></title><p>We compared our <italic>E.coli</italic> C ICR sequence with sequences around this region of the chromosome from six other strains of enteric bacteria. In addition to the well-studied <italic>E.coli</italic> laboratory strain K-12, these strains include another <italic>E.coli</italic> laboratory strain (W), the <italic>E.coli</italic> pathogens CFT073, O157:H7 and K1, and <italic>S.typhimurium</italic> LT2 (see Materials and Methods for references). For all seven strains, the same framework genes are present in the same order, interrupted by a variable region in the same location as the ICR of <italic>E.coli</italic> K-12 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f1">1</xref>). In all strains, the framework genes <italic>yjiS</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic> constitute the left and right borders, respectively, of the ICR collection of migratory genes.</p><p>Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f2">2</xref> shows the migratory genes contained within the variable region in the seven strains (not to scale). ORFs similar at the DNA level &#x0005b;&#x0003e;65&#x00025; identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c48">48</xref>)&#x0005d; are assumed to be orthologous and given names annotated in the earliest genome sequence. The number of genes present ranges from one (<italic>E.coli</italic> W) to 10 (<italic>E.coli</italic> K-12). In all, 45 ORFs representing 20 different genes are found here. Ten of these can be assigned a function. Collectively, RM genes comprise 21 of the 43 ORFs, and nine of the 10 assignable functions, consistent with the designation &#x02018;ICR&#x02019;. Six of the seven strains have at least one RM gene or gene fragment in this region. The RM systems are highly variable: two of the four type I families are represented, most likely representing five different specificities (see below); modification-dependent enzymes of two unrelated sorts are also present. The remaining gene with assignable function is penicillin acylase, in <italic>E.coli</italic> W. The remaining 10 genes (21 ORFs) are of unknown function.</p><p>Some groups of genes migrate together (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f2">2</xref>). The first group comprises the type IA restriction genes <italic>hsdS, hsdM, hsdR</italic> and <italic>mrr</italic> (orange boxes) found in three strains&#x02014;K-12, <italic>S.typhimurium</italic> and K1. Second are the type IB restriction genes, also <italic>hsdS, hsdM</italic> and <italic>hsdR</italic>, and two ORFs of unknown function, Z5949 and Z5950 (dark blue boxes) which are found in O157:H7, CFT073 and C. Third, <italic>yjiW</italic> (yellow box), a gene of unknown function that may be SOS-regulated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c49">49</xref>), appears in all five of the strains with complete type I systems. Fourth, Z5943 and Z5944 (green boxes) are found together in the three <italic>E.coli</italic> pathogens. The strain-specific genes not found anywhere else in this dataset (white boxes) include: the K-12 genes <italic>yjiT, yjiU, mcrD, mcrC</italic> and <italic>mcrB</italic>; the <italic>Salmonella</italic> ORFs STM4522 (on the left) and STM4528 and 4529 (between <italic>mrr</italic> and y<italic>jiA</italic>); and penicillin acylase &#x0005b;<italic>pac</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c50">50</xref>)&#x0005d;, the sole gene found in place of the ICR region in <italic>E.coli</italic> W.</p></sec><sec><title>Intermediate scale view: DNA similarity patterns surrounding the ICR</title><p>The pattern of gene relationships described above is even more confusing than we had anticipated. To get a sharper sense of gene relationships, we derived PIP indices &#x0005b;percentage of aligned bases identical; as in Florea <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c51">51</xref>)&#x0005d; for DNA segments spanning the ICR and its flanks, from <italic>yjiS</italic> to <italic>yjiY</italic>. <italic>E.coli</italic> C was compared with six of the other strains, K-12 with five, K1 with four, and O157 with CFT073. The results are shown in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkh194tb2">2</xref> (for framework genes) and <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkh194tb3">3</xref> (for migratory genes).</p><p>The levels of DNA identity in the framework genes are generally consistent with expectation (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkh194tb2">2</xref>). In general, <italic>E.coli</italic> genes diverge at up to 5&#x00025; of base pairs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c53">53</xref>) (&#x02265;95&#x00025; identical), while <italic>E.coli&#x02013;Salmonella</italic> divergence is 10&#x02013;20&#x00025; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c53">53</xref>). For <italic>yjiX</italic> and <italic>yjiY,</italic> we observe divergence of up to 2&#x00025; within <italic>E.coli</italic> and 9&#x02013;12&#x00025; between <italic>E.coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic>. Divergence is higher in the framework genes <italic>yjiS</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic>, immediately adjacent to the variable locus: up to 15&#x00025; for <italic>E.coli</italic> comparisons, 13&#x02013;33&#x00025; for <italic>E.coli&#x02013;Salmonella.</italic> In all pairwise comparisons, <italic>yjiS</italic> is least conserved and <italic>yjiX</italic> is most conserved among the four framework genes. This may reflect higher levels of homologous exchange immediately around the variable locus, mediated by selection acting on the genes found there (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c55">55</xref>). Below (next section) we discuss evidence for homologous exchange in the generation of the set of strains under consideration.</p><p>The pattern of sequence variation between similar migratory genes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkh194tb3">3</xref>) is consistent with previous studies. The type IB <italic>hsdRM</italic> genes of O157 and CFT073 are highly similar to each other (98&#x02013;99&#x00025; nucleotide identity) and so highly divergent from the type IA <italic>hsdRM</italic> genes of K-12 that meaningful alignments cannot be made. This divergence is in line with earlier characterization of these families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c56">56</xref>). The <italic>hsdS</italic> genes of the two pathogens show the patchy similarity expected for <italic>hsdS</italic> genes encoding different sequence specificity: conserved regions of the protein can be recognized as segments with 85&#x02013;97&#x00025; DNA identity, while the inferred DNA-binding regions are &#x0003c;50&#x00025; identical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c56">56</xref>). The K-12/<italic>Salmonella</italic> comparison has been made before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c57">57</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>A fine-scale view: borders of the ICR migratory elements</title><p>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref> display nucleotide sequence alignments of the seven strains at the right (<italic>yjiA</italic>) and left (<italic>yjiS</italic>) borders of the ICR. These alignments display sequence differences in different colors: O157:H7 was taken as the reference sequence (black letters) to minimize the amount of color. Differences from this are coded in color hierarchically. Those differences found in K1 or CFT073 are in blue wherever they occur; additional differences found in C are in green; then further differences found in <italic>Salmonella</italic> are in red; then additional differences found in W are in yellow; and remaining differences found in K-12 are in pink.</p><p>Three properties of these border sequences are evident. First, extreme sequence divergence begins abruptly after the stop codon of the flanking framework gene (to the left of the <italic>yjiA</italic> stop codon in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f3">3</xref>; to the right of the <italic>yjiS</italic> stop codon in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref>), visually recognized as a high level of color variation.</p><p>Second, families of sequences can nevertheless be identified, and at the right border these are congruent with families identified by patterns of shared genes seen in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f2">2</xref>. At the right border, O157:H7, CFT073 and <italic>E.coli</italic> C form one family (reference sequence, black), K1 and K-12 form another (blue highlighted changes); while <italic>S.typhimurium</italic> (red) and <italic>E.coli</italic> W (yellow) are each unique (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f3">3</xref>). This is consistent with gene groupings: O157:H7, CFT073 and C all share Z5950 immediately to the left of <italic>yjiA</italic>, K1 and K-12 share <italic>mrr</italic>, W carries <italic>pac</italic>, and <italic>Salmonella</italic> carries STM5428 and STM5429 interposed between <italic>mrr</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic>. Sequence families are so dissimilar that they appear to be unrelated. This suggests that four independent DNA acquisition events may have occurred at this location, immediately adjacent to <italic>yjiA</italic>.</p><p>Third, the family structure observed at the right border is almost totally erased at the left (<italic>yjiS</italic>) border (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref>). As at the right border, sequences associated with four different categories of genes are found adjacent to the border (Z5943, <italic>yjiT</italic>, STM4552 and penicillin acylase), but deletion and homologous recombination have obscured relationships, and two novel sequences generate further variation.</p><p>K1 appears to be a recombinant between strains similar to K-12 and CFT073. Markers flanking the recombination interval are a short deletion and the different <italic>hsd</italic> family genes. The deletion joins the <italic>yjiR</italic> and <italic>yjiS</italic> coding sequences in CFT073 and K1 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref>). (Note that these genes are coded on opposite strands, so no fusion protein will be expressed.) CFT073 and K1 also share similar sequence to the right of the <italic>yjiS</italic> stop codon, the only two strains to do so. These two are thus grouped together at the left border, although they were not grouped at the right border. Inspection of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f2">2</xref> suggests that a recombination event between strains similar to K-12 and CFT073, occurring within <italic>yjiW</italic>, could generate the gene configuration found in K1. The CFT073-like ancestor must have already carried the deletion, since K1 carries this as well.</p><p>This proposed sequence of events in CFT073 and K1 does not account for all the variation at the <italic>yjiS</italic> border, however. Two anomalies are evident in comparing Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref>. First, the pattern of shared genes seen next to <italic>yjiS</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f2">2</xref>) would suggest that O157:H7 should belong with CFT073 and K1, yet O157:H7 carries 57 bp of unique sequence between the <italic>yjiS</italic> stop codon and common sequence to the left (upstream) of Z5943. Identity among the three strains begins abruptly after this 57 bp, 36 bp from the Z5943 start codon. In effect, O157:H7 has suffered a short replacement event, compared with K1 and CFT073.</p><p>The second anomaly concerns <italic>E.coli</italic> C. From Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f2">2</xref>, we might have proposed that a simple deletion, occurring in a strain like one of the pathogens, had joined <italic>yjiS</italic> with the middle of <italic>hsdR</italic>. However, in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref> we see that in <italic>E.coli C</italic>, 47 bp of unique sequence lies between the <italic>yjiS</italic> stop codon and the <italic>hsdR</italic> fragment. This sequence is unlike either that of O157:H7 or that shared by CFT073 and K1. Possibly some still-unknown cassette was acquired at some time to occupy the position of Z5943/4, followed by a deletion event. This brings the number of cassette acquisitions to five; in any case, some event occurred at this border to generate novel sequence.</p><p>In summary, there must have been six different events at the left border, and four different events at the right border. This suggests an active mechanism for generating sequence variation precisely at this locus. This mechanism is such that six of seven strains carry 50&#x02013;60 base pairs of unique intergenic sequence at the <italic>yjiS</italic> border, even when genes immediately to the right of that unique sequence are shared. The border sequence (adjacent to the <italic>yjiS</italic> stop) also appears to form a barrier to sequence rearrangement, since deletion on the left (joining <italic>yjiR</italic> and <italic>yjiS</italic> in K1 and CFT073) and both deletion (in C) and replacement (in O157:H7) on the right do not cross this edge. Features of the right and left border sequences are considered in the Discussion.</p></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic distribution of yjiAXY and adjacent sequences</title><p>We consider below (Discussion) the possibility that site-specific recombination mediates acquisition of elements of the ICR. Recombinases that mediate such events are usually found immediately adjacent to their sites of action. Therefore, the distribution and environment of the contiguous framework genes <italic>yjiA, yjiX</italic> and <italic>yjiY</italic> (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f1">1</xref>) were considered in light of this possibility.</p><p>These framework genes are present in all complete <italic>E.coli</italic>, <italic>Shigella</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> genomes but are absent from more distant enteric species: for example from the two complete <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> genomes, the two complete <italic>Buchnera aphidicola</italic> genomes, or the partially completed <italic>Klebsiella pneumonia</italic> sequences. Nevertheless, strongly conserved homologs of these genes are found in the distant non-enteric relative <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (PA4604, PA4605 and PA4606). They are present in conserved order and orientation, and are &#x0003e;50&#x00025; identical at the amino acid level. The conservation of organization may indicate a functional relationship among these genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c58">58</xref>).</p><p>Interestingly, all five of the sequenced <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> have <italic>yjiA,</italic> but the sequences immediately downstream differ (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkh194tb4">4</xref>); the five ORFs at this location are unrelated. This situation would be expected if the gene cluster acts as a recombinase at an attachment site downstream of <italic>yjiA</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Based on our sequence comparisons, the borders of the ICR are the <italic>yjiS</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic> genes. A variety of migratory genes and gene fragments lie between these genes in the different strains. Between these border genes, the variability of the ICR begins immediately adjacent to their convergent stop codons. The identifiable genes found at the ICR have the common feature that they mediate interaction with external challenges of a sporadic nature: restriction systems (or remnants) to cope with invading DNA, or an enzyme for antibiotic modification (penicillin acylase). It is appropriate that genes with a sporadic distribution should respond to sporadic challenges. Below we consider some mechanistic models for generating this variation.</p><sec><title>Mechanism of segmental replacements at the ICR</title><p>Any mechanism proposed for segmental replacements at the ICR must account for the abrupt transition from similarity to dissimilarity at the borders (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref>). In addition, horizontal transfer must play a role, since divergence among the <italic>hsd</italic> genes of the <italic>E.coli</italic> strains is greater than that between those of K-12 and <italic>S.typhimurium</italic>.</p><p><italic>Site-specific recombinase (cassette) model.</italic> Our preferred model invokes an attachment site for site-specific recombination. It is known that unrelated phages may carry related integrases and can use the same attachment site &#x0005b;e.g. phage 21 and e14; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c59">59</xref>)&#x0005d;. Thus, the inserted sequence can be totally dissimilar except for the integration machinery. Such a model would allow the inserted segments to diverge over long periods, sufficient even to allow divergence of the families of type I restriction enzymes, while conserving the sequences required for recombinase action in the host genome by selection for function of the flanking genes. The precision of the borders is immediately accounted for. Cassettes of genes would be propagated to new hosts only if they retained sequences compatible with recombinase specificity. A pool of genes would then evolve that circulates specifically at this locus.</p><p><italic>Recombinase candidate.</italic> The problem with this model is that for all site-specific mechanisms known to mediate DNA acquisition, the gene for the recombinase is closely associated with the recombining segment &#x0005b;this is not true for XerCD, which mediates resolution of circular dimers at unlinked sites of action; XerCD action is highly regulated and has not been reported to mediate sequence acquisition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c60">60</xref>)&#x0005d;. For phages (or transposon Tn7 in site-specific mode), the gene(s) is (are) contained within the mobile segment, while in the case of integron integrases, the recombinase gene lies immediately outside the mobile segment. In the present example, no integrase/transposase candidate is immediately identifiable by sequence similarity. However, the neighboring gene cluster <italic>yjiAXY</italic> might code for a novel recombinase of episodic distribution. Consistent with this proposal, this cluster is found immediately adjacent to a variable locus in the distantly related genus <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="gkh194tb4">4</xref>). Interestingly, it is missing from several organisms more closely related to <italic>E.coli</italic>, suggesting that the cluster itself, as well as the cassettes adjacent, may be mobile, or at any rate dispensable.</p><p><italic>Possible attachment site.</italic> Dyad symmetry elements (inverted repeats) are often prominent components of the DNA sites at which integrases act, although they can sometimes be difficult to detect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c59">59</xref>). The alignment of sequences obtained by joining the left and right borders of the ICR in the seven strains reveals such an element (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f5">5</xref>), identified using the program STEMLOOP (see Materials and Methods). This joined sequence would be the presumed empty attachment site if these segments were prophage-like or cassette acquisitions as in integrons. A 13 bp dyad symmetry element (with two mismatches) surrounds the joined stop codons, interrupted by 5 bp including the <italic>yjiS</italic> stop. Even though no lambda-integrase-related gene is present, the dyad symmetry could still be important for a novel site-specific recombinase. We note further that the structure of the occupied sites is not that expected from a lambda-like integrase enzyme. Occupied sites should conserve the dyad structure at each border&#x02014;that is, Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f3">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f4">4</xref> should also exhibit the presence of dyads or sequences related to them, especially in any consensus sequence.</p><p><italic>Illegitimate recombination/transposition model.</italic> An alternative model would invoke random insertion events introducing new genes, for example by non-homologous end-joining &#x0005b;possibly stimulated by the action of a restriction enzyme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c61">61</xref>)&#x0005d;, or by transposition. Purifying selection against those insertions in unfavorable locations would eliminate most events. In the present case, the problem is to account for the apparently precise nature of the insertion process.</p><p>Illegitimate recombination has been invoked to explain the tight packing of related and unrelated genes in phage genomes. In a comparison of the genomic sequences of 14 mycobacteriophage, Pedulla <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c62">62</xref>) also find a mosaic structure with segments separated by sharp transitions in sequence similarity. As in our bacterial ICR sequences, they find that most mosaic boundaries in these phage sequences are located at or very near gene boundaries, but of the &#x0003e;500 boundaries found, three disrupted coding sequence. Pedulla <italic>et al</italic>. invoked an earlier suggestion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c63">63</xref>) that such diversity must be generated by a combination of illegitimate and homologous recombination and mutational drift. In their model, recombination can occur virtually anywhere along the phage sequence, but the only phages that survive to be analyzed have undergone recombination events that do not diminish the function of any phage protein on which natural selection acts.</p><p>In the case under study, this seems an unsatisfactory model. In <italic>E.coli</italic> K-12, the entire region can be deleted &#x0005b;Raleigh <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c64">64</xref>) and unpublished observations&#x0005d;, so selective constraints are presumably less than is the case for the streamlined phage genomes. Thus, the insertion locations would be expected to vary somewhat in different events. Moreover, the model does not account for the high frequency of highly divergent restriction genes at this location. At least six different events must have occurred among the seven strains, at least at the left (<italic>yjiS</italic>) border (see Results: A fine scale view).</p><p><italic>Differential deletion model.</italic> Differential deletion from a large original set of &#x02018;migratory genes&#x02019; could in principle account for what we see. Selection for function of the framework genes would be required. This model would require an initial set of 20 different genes. Many of the deletion events would have had to occur in a highly precise fashion to generate the sharp borders observed. Trials on paper (not shown) suggest that 11 different deletion events and (contrary to the model) two small insertion events (of 47 and 57 bp, in <italic>E.coli</italic> C and O157:H7) would be required to generate the observed pattern. Even more genes and events would be required to generate the novel joints of C and O157:H7 by deletion only. Of those 13 events, eight (including both insertions) would involve one of the two borders in an event with a precise endpoint (five on the left and three on the right; not shown). Deletions would have had to bring the type I genes adjacent to <italic>yjiW</italic> in two different ways, with the type IA and type IB systems separately eliminated. This mechanism seems excessively baroque, and does not readily account for any of the properties of the locus.</p></sec><sec><title>RM variation in other taxa</title><p>Variation of RM systems within populations has been a topic of interest for other taxa also. In <italic>Mycoplasma genitalium</italic>, site-specific recombinase action enables reassortment of endogenous Type I specificity domains, such that any cell in the population may express one or two of at least eight possible specificities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c65">65</xref>). Horizontal transfer is not needed for this.</p><p>In <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>, very large numbers of RM sequences are found in each isolate, with around two dozen candidate systems in each strain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c66">66</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c67">67</xref>), scattered around the chromosome. Many of the type II system candidates turn out to be inactive or only partially active (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c68">68</xref>), with non-overlapping sets of four systems active in the two strains examined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c67">67</xref>). Reactivation of inactive alleles by horizontal transfer and homologous recombination has been invoked as a regulatory mechanism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c69">69</xref>). No locus has been described that contains multiple alternative specificities.</p><p>A closer analog of our situation is a variable restriction locus in <italic>Neisseria,</italic> found between two conserved genes, <italic>pheS</italic> and <italic>pheT</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c70">70</xref>). The variable region contains between zero and six genes, six of the nine strains contain RM-related genes, and divergence begins immediately after the start and stop codons of the flanking genes <italic>pheS</italic> and <italic>pheT.</italic> Saunders and Snyder invoke homologous recombination as a mechanism for reassortment of the contents of the variable sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c70">70</xref>), much as we see with K1, an apparent recombinant between CFT073-like and K-12-like ancestors. There as here, however, homologous recombination could not account for the insertion of diverse sequence at precise locations. Neither dyad symmetry element nor candidate recombinase is identifiable in <italic>Neisseria</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Why is there so much variation?</title><p>The nature of selective pressures on restriction enzyme function has been considerably debated (see references in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c71">71</xref>). All models for the evolution of these genes proceed from the diversity observed. Three general models have been proposed: that RM systems protect the host from invading DNA (phages or plasmids); that they enable the host to promote or regulate recombination (a sexual function) or that they have selfish features that promote their own spread. In all cases, there must be horizontal DNA transfer events to provide a selection substrate.</p><p>The site-specific recombinase model could account for the high frequency of restriction loci at this site, while not excluding that other functions, also advantageous when rare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c72">72</xref>), might acquire the ability to circulate here (e.g. the <italic>pac</italic> gene). This could occur when such genes acquire sequence determinants that allow interaction with the putative recombinase.</p></sec><sec><title>Variable loci in enteric bacteria</title><p>Insertion/deletion variation has been extensively discussed in reports on enteric genome sequences, but most discussion has focused on the gene content of the variable islands, not the mechanism of acquisition. Phage-like islands or transposase homologues near island junctions have been noted in some cases, but these are present in only a fraction of examples. Clearly, some mechanisms remain to be discovered.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig id="gkh194f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p> Genetic structure surrounding the ICR in <italic>E.coli.</italic> Conserved framework genes (striped boxes, approximately to scale) encode hypothetical proteins of unknown function, between 98.4 and 98.9 min on the K-12 chromosome. The variable region (dashed line) found between <italic>yjiS</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic> contains distinct gene sets in different strains. A part of this region has been designated the Immigration Control Region (ICR) in <italic>E.coli</italic> K-12.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh194f1"/></fig><fig id="gkh194f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p> Gene content of the ICR in six strains of <italic>E.coli</italic> and in <italic>Salmonella enterica sv typhimurium</italic> LT2. Boxes (not to scale) represent gene coding sequence, even if the gene is truncated. Similarity was assessed at the DNA level; if similarity was &#x0003e;65&#x00025;, genes were judged orthologous, and named according to the earliest genome sequence. Boxes of the same color represent orthologous blocks of genes that appear to be moving together. Orange boxes: type IA restriction genes (<italic>hsdRMS</italic>) and <italic>mrr</italic>. Blue boxes: type IB restriction genes (<italic>hsdRMS</italic>) and two ORFs of unknown function, Z5949 and Z5950; these are fused in C and CFT073 with a 10 amino acid linker relative to the two in O157:H7. Yellow boxes: <italic>yjiW</italic>. Green boxes: unknowns Z5943 and Z5944. White boxes: genes unique in this dataset. These are: <italic>yjiT, yjiU</italic> and <italic>mcrD</italic>, all of unknown function, in K-12; restriction genes <italic>mcrB</italic> and <italic>mcrC</italic>; penicillin acylase (<italic>pac</italic>) in W; and unknowns STM4522, 4528 and 4529 in <italic>S.typhimurium</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh194f2"/></fig><fig id="gkh194f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p> DNA sequence alignments at the right (<italic>yjiA</italic>) border of the ICR. O157:H7 was taken as the reference sequence (black letters) to minimize the amount of color. Differences from this are coded in color hierarchically, and the main goal is to highlight the sudden transition to diversity at the <italic>yjiA</italic> stop codon. Where K1 differs from O157:H7, the K1 allele is blue (even in other strains); additional differences found in C are in green; further differences found in <italic>S.typhimurium</italic> are in red; then differences found in W are in yellow and finally remaining differences in K-12 are in pink.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh194f3"/></fig><fig id="gkh194f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p> DNA sequence alignments at the left (<italic>yjiS</italic>) border of the ICR. O157:H7 was taken as the reference sequence (black letters) to minimize the amount of color. Differences from this are coded in color hierarchically as in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh194f3">3</xref>. The sequence of the <italic>hsdR</italic> fragment found in C is boxed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh194f4"/></fig><fig id="gkh194f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p> Dyad symmetry element in DNA sequence around the proposed empty &#x02018;attachment site&#x02019;. Dyad symmetry elements can serve as binding sites or sites of action for proteins. Conserved sequence to the left of the <italic>yjiS</italic> stop codon was joined with sequence to the right of the <italic>yjiA</italic> stop codon for each strain, and aligned. Stop codons are boxed. The consensus sequence convention is: capital, all sequences identical; lower case: a majority of sequences identical. Mismatches to the consensus are lettered in red. Nucleotides involved in an interrupted dyad symmetry element are marked with a vertical line; mismatches within the dyad with dots.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh194f5"/></fig><table-wrap id="gkh194tb1"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Genes spanning the &#x02018;empty&#x02019; ICR in <italic>E.coli</italic> C</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">Nucleotides</th><th valign="top">Gene</th><th valign="top">Distribution<sup>a</sup></th><th valign="top">Functional information<sup>b</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">5&#x02013;1417<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>yjiR</italic><sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">All strains except <italic>S.typhimurium</italic>. CFT073 and K1 have only a 77 nt fragment from the middle of the gene; W sequence is unfinished<hr/></td><td valign="top">COG1167.1, ARO8. Transcriptional regulator containing a DNA-binding HTH domain and an aminotransferase domain (MocR family)<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">1594&#x02013;1758<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>yjiS</italic><sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">All strains. CFT073 and K1 have only an 86-nt fragment from the 3&#x02032; end of the gene including the stop codon; this fragment is fused to the <italic>yjiR</italic> fragment<hr/></td><td valign="top">COG5457.1. Uncharacterized conserved small protein, function unknown<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">1807&#x02013;2370<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>hsdR</italic> (fragment with upstream sequence)<hr/></td><td valign="top">CFT073 and O157:H7. Fragment includes the 5&#x02032; 565 nt of gene with start codon<hr/></td><td valign="top">Type IB restriction endonuclease fragment. DNA sequence is 98&#x00025; identical with EcoA restriction enzyme of <italic>E.coli</italic> 15T<sup>&#x02013;</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c57">57</xref>)<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">2648&#x02013;4300<hr/></td><td valign="top">Z5950<sup>d</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">CFT073 and O157:H7<hr/></td><td valign="top">pfam03235.8, DUF262. Protein of unknown function<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">4369&#x02013;5223<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>yjiA</italic><sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">All strains<hr/></td><td valign="top">pfam02492, CobW<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">5336&#x02013;5539<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>yjiX</italic><sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">All strains<hr/></td><td valign="top">COG2879.1. Uncharacterized small protein<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">5670&#x02013;7835<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>yjiY</italic><sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">All strains<hr/></td><td valign="top">COG1966.1, CstA. Carbon starvation protein, predicted membrane protein<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">8213&#x02013;8725<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>hpaC</italic><sup>e</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">W and <italic>S.typhimurium</italic><sup>f</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">4-hydroxyphenylacetate (4-HPA) hydroxylase, reductase component<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">8743&#x02013;10305<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>hpaB</italic><sup>e</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">W and <italic>S.typhimurium</italic><sup>f</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">4-hydroxyphenylacetate (4-HPA) hydroxylase, oxygenase component<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">10556&#x02013;11449<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>hpaA</italic><sup>e</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">W and <italic>S.typhimurium</italic><sup>f</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">Transcription regulator<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">11459&#x02013;12835<hr/></td><td valign="top"><italic>hpaX</italic><sup>e</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">W and <italic>S.typhimurium</italic><sup>f</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">Transmembrane facilitator<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">13010&#x02013;13753 (end of sequenced region)</td><td valign="top"><italic>hpaI</italic><sup>e</sup> (also known as <italic>hpcH</italic> in <italic>E.coli</italic> C)</td><td valign="top">W and <italic>S.typhimurium</italic><sup>f</sup></td><td valign="top">2,4-dihydroxy-hept-2-ene-1,7-dioic acid aldolase</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>Distribution among the strains of the set considered in this paper.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup>Information from Conserved Domain Database &#x0005b;see Methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c42">42</xref>)&#x0005d; or Prieto <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c40">40</xref>).</p></fn><fn><p><sup>c</sup>Designation is from <italic>E.coli</italic> K-12 sequence.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>d</sup>Designation is from <italic>E.coli</italic> CFT073 sequence; the Z5950 sequence found in C and CFT073 represents a fusion of the coding sequences designated Z4949 and Z5950 in O157:H7.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>e</sup>Designation from <italic>E.coli</italic> W sequence; part of the 4-HPA degradative gene cluster of 11 genes, completely sequenced in <italic>E.coli</italic> W (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh194c40">40</xref>).</p></fn><fn><p><sup>f</sup>Gene is found elsewhere in the chromosome of <italic>S.typhimurium.</italic></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="gkh194tb2"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Percent nucleotide identity of framework genes around the ICR in the seven strains (<italic>E.coli</italic> and <italic>S.typhimurium</italic> LT2)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">Strain comparison</th><th valign="top">yjiS (165 nt)<sup>a</sup></th><th valign="top">yjiA (854 nt)</th><th valign="top">yjiX (203 nt)</th><th valign="top">yjiY (2166 nt)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K1/CFT073<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">C/0157:H7<hr/></td><td valign="top">97<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">C/CFT073<hr/></td><td valign="top">85<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">C/K1<hr/></td><td valign="top">85<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K-12/O157:H7<hr/></td><td valign="top">93<hr/></td><td valign="top">97<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K-12/K1<hr/></td><td valign="top">87<hr/></td><td valign="top">97<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">CFT073/O157:H7<hr/></td><td valign="top">86<hr/></td><td valign="top">97<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K-12/CFT073<hr/></td><td valign="top">87<hr/></td><td valign="top">96<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">C/K-12<hr/></td><td valign="top">93<hr/></td><td valign="top">96<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">C/W<hr/></td><td valign="top">95<hr/></td><td valign="top">96<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K-12/W<hr/></td><td valign="top">93<hr/></td><td valign="top">95<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K-12/<italic>S.typhimurium</italic><hr/></td><td valign="top">68<hr/></td><td valign="top">87<hr/></td><td valign="top">91<hr/></td><td valign="top">88<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">C/<italic>S.typhimurium</italic><hr/></td><td valign="top">67<hr/></td><td valign="top">86<hr/></td><td valign="top">91<hr/></td><td valign="top">88<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K1/<italic>S.typhimurium</italic></td><td valign="top">75</td><td valign="top">85</td><td valign="top">91</td><td valign="top">88</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>Comparisons with <italic>E.coli</italic> K1 and CFT073 were done using the 87 nt C-terminal fragment of yjiS found in these strains.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="gkh194tb3"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Percent nucleotide identity of migratory genes found in the variable locus between <italic>yjiS</italic> and <italic>yjiA</italic></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">Strain comparison</th><th valign="top">Z5943 (882 nt)</th><th valign="top">Z5944 (1164 nt)</th><th valign="top">yjiW (399 nt)</th><th valign="top">hsdS (1367 nt)</th><th valign="top">hsdM (1588 nt)</th><th valign="top">hsdR (3562 nt)</th><th valign="top">mrr (914 nt)</th><th valign="top">Z5950 (1653 nt)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K1/CFT073<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<hr/></td><td valign="top">97<hr/></td><td valign="top">96<hr/></td><td valign="top">Div<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">Div<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">Div<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">C/0157:H7<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">C/CFT073<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K-12/O157:H7<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">94<hr/></td><td valign="top">Div<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">Div<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">Div<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K-12/K1<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">94<hr/></td><td valign="top">Patchy<sup>d</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">97<hr/></td><td valign="top">97<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">CFT073/O157:H7<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td><td valign="top">100<hr/></td><td valign="top">Patchy<sup>d</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">99<hr/></td><td valign="top">98<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">99<sup>b</sup><hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K-12/CFT073<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">94<hr/></td><td valign="top">Div<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">Div<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">Div<sup>a</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K-12/<italic>S.typhimurium</italic><hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td><td valign="top">79<hr/></td><td valign="top">Patchy<sup>d</sup><hr/></td><td valign="top">89<hr/></td><td valign="top">83<hr/></td><td valign="top">71<hr/></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top">K1/<italic>S.typhimurium</italic></td><td valign="top">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top">81</td><td valign="top">Patchy<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top">89</td><td valign="top">84</td><td valign="top">71</td><td valign="top">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>Div &#x0003d; highly diverged. Comparisons between Type IA and Type IB hsd genes were not possible using this procedure because the genes are too divergent.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup>Comparisons with O157:H7 were done using a segment covering both Z5949 and Z5950; the Z5950 sequence found in C and CFT073 represents a fusion of the coding sequences designated Z4949 and Z5950 in O157:H7.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>c</sup>Comparisons with <italic>E.coli</italic> C were done using the 565-nt N-terminal fragment of hsdR (Type IB) found in this strain.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>d</sup>In comparisons within Type IA or Type IB hsdS genes, the alignment procedure yielded 85&#x02013;96&#x00025; identity within the carboxy conserved region, 40&#x02013;50&#x00025; identity within the carboxy target recognition domain (TRD), 94&#x02013;97&#x00025; identity within the central conserved region, 40&#x02013;50&#x00025; identity within the amino TRD, and 91&#x02013;97&#x00025; identity within the amino conserved region.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="gkh194tb4"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>YjiAXY homologs and ORFs C-terminal to (left of) YjiA in <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> species</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1" width="85%"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">Organism<hr/></th><th valign="top">ORF C-terminal to YjiA homolog and best hit to GenBank database<hr/></th><th colspan="3" valign="top"><italic>E.coli</italic> K-12 homolog and &#x00025; amino acid identity to K-12</th></tr><tr valign="top"><th valign="top">&#x000a0;</th><th valign="top">&#x000a0;</th><th valign="top"><italic>yjiA</italic></th><th valign="top"><italic>yjiX</italic></th><th valign="top"><italic>yjiY</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr valign="top"><td valign="top"><italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> PfO-1<hr/></td><td valign="top">ZP&#x0005f;00086222: Best hit to AAN67866, &#x02018;transcriptional regulator, GntR family&#x02019; of <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic>, 110/214 identical (51&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">ZP&#x0005f;00086223: 171/313 identical (54&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">ZP&#x0005f;00086224: 43/60 identical (71&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">ZP&#x0005f;00086225: 484/708 identical (68&#x00025;)<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top"><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PA01<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAG07991: Best hit to NMB0780, hypothetical protein of <italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic>, 63/117 identical (53&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAG07992: 169/318 identical (53&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAG07993: 45/67 identical (68&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAG07994: 489/708 identical (69&#x00025;)<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top"><italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> KT2440<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAN70211: Best hit to ZP&#x0005f;00103628, &#x02018;methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase domain protein&#x02019; of <italic>Desulfitobacterium hafniense</italic>, 127/468 identical (27&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAN70212: 168/320 identical (52&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAN70213: 46/65 identical (70&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAN70214: 482/681 identical (70&#x00025;)<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top"><italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. tomato str. DC3000<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAO58081: Best hit to AA036475, &#x02018;membrane associated protein&#x02019; of <italic>Clostridium tetani</italic>, 56/187 identical (29&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAO58082: 167/321 identical (52&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAO58083: 46/65 identical (70&#x00025;)<hr/></td><td valign="top">AAO58084: 449/636 identical (70&#x00025;)<hr/></td></tr><tr valign="top"><td valign="top"><italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. syringae B728a</td><td valign="top">ZP&#x0005f;00126198: Best hit to AAO58078, serine hydroxymethyltransferase of <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. tomato str. DC3000, 410/417 identical (98&#x00025;)</td><td valign="top">ZP&#x0005f;00126197: 164/319 identical (51&#x00025;)</td><td valign="top">ZP&#x0005f;00126196: 46/65 identical (70&#x00025;)</td><td valign="top">ZP&#x0005f;00126195: 479/707 identical (67&#x00025;)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><ack><sec><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank Noreen Murray, Rich Roberts, Roger Milkman and Romualdas Vaisvila for extensive discussions and intellectual support during conception of this paper. Guy Plunkett shared sequence of the <italic>E.coli</italic> pathogens in advance of publication. Rob Edwards was sufficiently critical that we re-examined the sequence environment surrounding the proposed attachment site. We thank Don Comb and New England Biolabs for support.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="gkh194c1"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Raleigh</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name> (1992) Organization and function of the <italic>mcrBC</italic> genes of <italic>E.coli</italic> K-12. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1079</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1086</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1316984</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c2"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name> (1964) Genetic control of restriction and modification in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>88</volume>, <fpage>1652</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1660</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14240953</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c3"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Arber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name> and Wauters-Willems,D. (1970) Host specificity of DNA produced by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. XII. The two restriction and modification systems of strain 15T-. <source>Mol. Gen. Genet.</source>, <volume>108</volume>, <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>217</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4920152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c4"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Barcus</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name>, Titheradge,A.J.B. and Murray,N.E. (1995) The diversity of alleles at the <italic>hsd</italic> locus in natural populations of <italic>Escherichia coli.</italic><source>Genetics</source>, <volume>140</volume>, <fpage>1187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1197</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7498762</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c5"><label>5.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bullas</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name>, Colson,C. and Neufeld,B. (1980) Deoxyribonucleic acid restriction and modification systems in <italic>Salmonella</italic>: chromosomally located systems of different serotypes. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>141</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>292</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6243623</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c6"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name>, Fuller-Pace,F.V., Legge,D.M. and Murray,N.E. (1988) Distribution and diversity of hsd genes in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and other enteric bacteria. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>170</volume>, <fpage>1775</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1782</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2832380</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c7"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bertani</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and Weigle,J.J. (1953) Host-controlled variation in bacterial viruses. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13034700</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c8"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Gossen</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name> and Vijg,J. (1988) <italic>E.coli</italic> C: a convenient host strain for rescue of highly methylated DNA. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>9343</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2845371</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c9"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name> and Collis,C.M. (1995) Mobile gene cassettes and integrons: capture and spread of genes by site-specific recombination. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>600</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7783631</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c10"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, Schneider,S.J. and Song,B. (1992) Lambdoid phages as elements of bacterial genomes. <source>Genetica</source>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>267</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1468648</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c11"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lacks</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> and Greenberg,B. (1977) Complementary specificity of restriction endonucleases of <italic>Diplococcus pneumoniae</italic> with respect to DNA methylation. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>114</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20509</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c12"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lacks</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>, Mannarelli,B.M., Springhorn,S.S. and Greenberg,B. (1986) Genetic basis of the complementary <italic>Dpn</italic>I and <italic>Dpn</italic>II restriction systems of <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>: an intercellular cassette mechanism. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>993</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1000</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3019562</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c13"><label>13.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name> (2002) Immigration control of DNA in bacteria: self versus non-self. <source>Microbiology</source>, <volume>148</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11782494</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c14"><label>14.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ochman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name> and Selander,R.K. (1984) Standard reference strains of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> from natural populations. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>157</volume>, <fpage>690</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>693</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6363394</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c15"><label>15.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Milkman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (1973) Electrophoretic variation in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> from natural sources. <source>Science</source>, <volume>182</volume>, <fpage>1024</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1026</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4584002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c16"><label>16.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Barcus</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name> and Murray,N.E. (1995) Barriers to recombination: restriction. <source>Soc. Gen. Microbiol. Symp.</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c17"><label>17.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bickle</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name> and Kr&#x000fc;ger,D.H. (1993) Biology of DNA restriction. <source>Microbiol. Rev.</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>434</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>450</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8336674</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c18"><label>18.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Titheradge</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name>, Ternent,D. and Murray,N.E. (1996) A third family of allelic hsd genes in <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic>: sequence comparisons with related proteins identify conserved regions implicated in restriction of DNA. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>447</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8939428</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c19"><label>19.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name>, Kelleher,J.E., Daniel,A.S., Cowan,G.M. and Murray,N.E. (1992) Roles of selection and recombination in the evolution of type I restriction-modification systems in enterobacteria. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>89</volume>, <fpage>9836</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9840</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1409708</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c20"><label>20.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name>, Woese,C.R. and Overbeek,R. (1994) The winds of (evolutionary) change: breathing new life into microbiology. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>176</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8282683</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c21"><label>21.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Florea,L., Sanderson,K., Clifton,S.W., Parkhill,J., Churcher,C., Dougan,G., Wilson,R.K. and Miller,W. (2000) Comparison of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12 genome with sampled genomes of a <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> and three salmonella enterica serovars, Typhimurium, Typhi and Paratyphi. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>4974</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4986</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11121489</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c22"><label>22.</label><citation citation-type="book"><name><surname>Milkman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> (1999) Gene transfer in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. In Charlebois,R.L. (ed.), <source>Organization of the Prokaryotic Genome</source>. <publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name>, Washington, DC, pp. <fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c23"><label>23.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Milkman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, Jaeger,E. and McBride,R.D. (2003) Molecular evolution of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> chromosome. VI. Two regions of high effective recombination. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>163</volume>, <fpage>475</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>483</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12618387</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c24"><label>24.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> (1993) Evolution of <italic>Salmonella</italic> O antigen variation by interspecific gene transfer on a large scale. <source>Trends Genet.</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8434412</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c25"><label>25.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> and Reeves,P.R. (1994) Presence of different O antigen forms in three isolates of one clone of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>138</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7528154</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c26"><label>26.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name> and Ochman,H. (1998) Molecular archaeology of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> genome. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>9413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9417</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9689094</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c27"><label>27.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>W.B.</given-names></name> (1966) Host specificity of DNA produced by <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: bacterial mutations affecting the restriction and modification of DNA. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5331240</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c28"><label>28.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name>, Burland,V., Plunkett,G.,3rd, Redford,P., Roesch,P., Rasko,D., Buckles,E.L., Liou,S.R., Boutin,A., Hackett,J. <italic>et al</italic>. (2002) Extensive mosaic structure revealed by the complete genome sequence of uropathogenic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>99</volume>, <fpage>17020</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17024</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12471157</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c29"><label>29.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Perna</surname><given-names>N.T.</given-names></name>, Plunkett,G.,3rd, Burland,V., Mau,B., Glasner,J.D., Rose,D.J., Mayhew,G.F., Evans,P.S., Gregor,J., Kirkpatrick,H.A. <italic>et al</italic>. (2001) Genome sequence of enterohaemorrhagic <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>409</volume>, <fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>533</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11206551</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c30"><label>30.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Sanderson,K.E., Spieth,J., Clifton,S.W., Latreille,P., Courtney,L., Porwollik,S., Ali,J., Dante,M., Du,F. <italic>et al</italic>. (2001) Complete genome sequence of <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium LT2. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>413</volume>, <fpage>852</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>856</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11677609</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c31"><label>31.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, Dougan,G., James,K.D., Thomson,N.R., Pickard,D., Wain,J., Churcher,C., Mungall,K.L., Bentley,S.D., Holden,M.T. <italic>et al</italic>. (2001) Complete genome sequence of a multiple drug resistant <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhi CT18. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>413</volume>, <fpage>848</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>852</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11677608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c32"><label>32.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Worth</surname><given-names>L.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, Clark,S., Radman,M. and Modrich,P. (1994) Mismatch repair proteins MutS and MutL inhibit RecA-catalyzed strand transfer between diverged DNAs. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>3238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3241</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8159731</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c33"><label>33.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>E.V.</given-names></name>, Mushegian,A.R. and Rudd,K.E. (1996) Sequencing and analysis of bacterial genomes. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>404</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>416</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8723345</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c34"><label>34.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Rappeley</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name> and Roth,J.R. (1997) Transposition without transposase: a spontaneous mutation in bacteria. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>179</volume>, <fpage>2047</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2052</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9068653</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c35"><label>35.</label><citation citation-type="book"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, Fritsch,E.F. and Maniatis,T. (1989) <source>Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual. 2nd Edn.</source><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name>, Cold Spring Harbor, NY.</citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c36"><label>36.</label><citation citation-type="book"><name><surname>Siedman</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name>, Struhl,K. and Jessen,T. (1997) Introduction of plasmid DNA into cells. In Ausubel,F.M., Kingston,R.B., Moore,D.D., Seidman,J.G., Smith,J.A. and Struhl,K. (eds), <source>Current Protocols in Molecular Biology</source>, pp. <fpage>1.8.1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1.8.10</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c37"><label>37.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Roper</surname><given-names>D.I.</given-names></name>, Fawcett,T. and Cooper,R.A. (1993) The <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> C homoprotocatechuate degradative operon: hpc gene order, direction of transcription and control of expression. <source>Mol. Gen. Genet.</source>, <volume>237</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>250</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8384293</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c38"><label>38.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Blattner</surname><given-names>F.R.</given-names></name>, Plunkett,G., Bloch,C.A., Perna,N.T., Burland,V., Riley,M., Collado-Vides,J., Glasner,J.D., Rode,C.K., Mayhew,G.F. <italic>et al</italic>. (1997) The complete genome sequence of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12. <source>Science</source>, <volume>277</volume>, <fpage>1433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1462</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c39"><label>39.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name>, Kim,Y.C., Park,Y.W., Min,S.Y., Kim,I.S. and Kang,H.S. (1987) Complete nucleotide sequence of the penicillin G acylase gene and the flanking regions and its expression in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. <source>Gene</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3315861</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c40"><label>40.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, Diaz,E. and Garcia,J.L. (1996) Molecular characterization of the 4-hydroxyphenylacetate catabolic pathway of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> W: engineering a mobile aromatic degradative cluster. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>178</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8550403</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c41"><label>41.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Roa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and Garcia,J.L. (1999) New insights into the regulation of the pac gene from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> W ATCC 11105. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source>, <volume>177</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10436917</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c42"><label>42.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Geer</surname><given-names>L.Y.</given-names></name>, Domrachev,M., Lipman,D.J. and Bryant,S.H. (2002) CDART: protein homology by domain architecture. <source>Genome Res.</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1623</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368255</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c43"><label>43.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Rudd</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name> (1998) Linkage map of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12, edition 10: the physical map. <source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>985</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1019</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9729612</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c44"><label>44.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Berlyn</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name> (1998) Linkage map of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12, edition 10: the traditional map. <source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>814</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>984</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9729611</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c45"><label>45.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, Gosset,G., Tenorio,B., Oliver,G. and Bolivar,F. (1986) Characterization of the regulatory region of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> penicillin acylase structural gene. <source>Gene</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3556321</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c46"><label>46.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Radoja</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Francetic,O., Stojicevic,N., Moric,I., Glisin,V. and Konstantinovic,M. (1999) DNA region responsible for transcriptional regulation of the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> penicillin amidase (pac) gene by CRP and PAA. <source>Genet. Anal.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10609760</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c47"><label>47.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name>, Madden,T.L., Sch&#x000e4;ffer,A.A., Zhang,J., Zhang,Z., Miller,W. and Lipman,D.J. (1997) Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>3389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3402</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c48"><label>48.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Mira</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> and Ochman,H. (2002) Gene location and bacterial sequence divergence. <source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1350</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1358</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12140247</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c49"><label>49.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>L.K.</given-names></name>, Harlow,G.R., Gregg-Jolly,L.A. and Mount,D.W. (1994) Identification of high affinity binding sites for LexA which define new DNA damage-inducible genes in <italic>Escherichia coli.</italic><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>241</volume>, <fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>523</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8057377</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c50"><label>50.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, Sizmann,D., Haug,H., Buckel,P. and Bock,A. (1986) Penicillin acylase from <italic>E.coli</italic>: unique gene-protein relation. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>5713</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5727</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3016663</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c51"><label>51.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Florea</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Riemer,C., Schwartz,S., Zhang,Z., Stojanovic,N., Miller,W. and McClelland,M. (2000) Web-based visualization tools for bacterial genome alignments. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>3486</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3496</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10982867</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c52"><label>52.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name>, Whittam,T.S. and Selander,R.K. (1997) Evolutionary genetics of the isocitrate dehydrogenase gene (icd) in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>179</volume>, <fpage>6551</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6559</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9352899</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c53"><label>53.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> and Selander,R.K. (1992) Evolutionary genetics of the proline permease gene (putP) and the control region of the proline utilization operon in populations of Salmonella and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>174</volume>, <fpage>6886</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6895</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1400239</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c54"><label>54.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name>, Nelson,K., Wang,F.S., Whittam,T.S. and Selander,R.K. (1994) Molecular genetic basis of allelic polymorphism in malate dehydrogenase (mdh) in natural populations of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic>. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>1280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1284</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8108402</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c55"><label>55.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bisercic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Feutrier,J.Y. and Reeves,P.R. (1991) Nucleotide sequences of the gnd genes from nine natural isolates of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: evidence of intragenic recombination as a contributing factor in the evolution of the polymorphic gnd locus. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>173</volume>, <fpage>3894</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3900</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2050640</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c56"><label>56.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name> (2000) Type I restriction systems: sophisticated molecular machines (a legacy of Bertani and Weigle). <source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>412</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>434</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10839821</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c57"><label>57.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name>, Daniel,A.S., Cowan,G.M. and Sharp,P.M. (1993) Conservation of motifs within the unusually variable polypeptide sequences of type I restriction and modification enzymes. <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>143</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8412658</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c58"><label>58.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Overbeek</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, Fonstein,M., D&#x02019;Souza,M., Pusch,G.D. and Maltsev,N. (1999) The use of gene clusters to infer functional coupling. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>96</volume>, <fpage>2896</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2901</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10077608</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c59"><label>59.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name> (1992) Chromosomal insertion sites for phages and plasmids. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>174</volume>, <fpage>7495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7499</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1447124</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c60"><label>60.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Barre</surname><given-names>F.X.</given-names></name>, Soballe,B., Michel,B., Aroyo,M., Robertson,M. and Sherratt,D. (2001) Circles: the replication-recombination-chromosome segregation connection. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>8189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11459952</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c61"><label>61.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kusano</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, Sakagami,K., Yokochi,T., Naito,T., Tokinaga,Y., Ueda,E. and Kobayashi,I. (1997) A new type of illegitimate recombination is dependent on restriction and homologous interaction. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>179</volume>, <fpage>5380</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5390</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9286991</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c62"><label>62.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Pedulla</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name>, Ford,M.E., Houtz,J.M., Karthikeyan,T., Wadsworth,C., Lewis,J.A., Jacobs-Sera,D., Falbo,J., Gross,J., Pannunzio,N.R. <italic>et al</italic>. (2003) Origins of highly mosaic mycobacteriophage genomes. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>113</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>182</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12705866</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c63"><label>63.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Juhala</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name>, Ford,M.E., Duda,R.L., Youlton,A., Hatfull,G.F. and Hendrix,R.W. (2000) Genomic sequences of bacteriophages HK97 and HK022: pervasive genetic mosaicism in the lambdoid bacteriophages. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>299</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10860721</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c64"><label>64.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Raleigh</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name>, Trimarchi,R. and Revel,H. (1989) Genetic and physical mapping of the mcrA (rglA) and mcrB (rglB) loci of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> K-12. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>122</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2548920</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c65"><label>65.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Dybvig</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, Sitaraman,R. and French,C.T. (1998) A family of phase-variable restriction enzymes with differing specificities generated by high-frequency gene rearrangements. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>13923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13928</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9811902</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c66"><label>66.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nobusato</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, Uchiyama,I. and Kobayashi,I. (2000) Diversity of restriction-modification gene homologues in <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>. <source>Gene</source>, <volume>259</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11163966</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c67"><label>67.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, Morgan,R.D., Roberts,R.J. and Blaser,M.J. (2000) Identification of type II restriction and modification systems in <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> reveals their substantial diversity among strains. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>9671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9676</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10944229</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c68"><label>68.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, Lin,L.F., Porter,N., Stickel,S., Byrd,D., Posfai,J. and Roberts,R.J. (2000) Functional analysis of putative restriction-modification system genes in the <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> J99 genome. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>3216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3223</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10954588</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c69"><label>69.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Aras</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name>, Small,A.J., Ando,T. and Blaser,M.J. (2002) <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> interstrain restriction-modification diversity prevents genome subversion by chromosomal DNA from competing strains. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>5391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5397</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490707</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c70"><label>70.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name> and Snyder,L.A. (2002) The minimal mobile element. <source>Microbiology</source>, <volume>148</volume>, <fpage>3756</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12480877</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c71"><label>71.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name> (2001) Behavior of restriction-modification systems as selfish mobile elements and their impact on genome evolution. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>3742</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3756</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11557807</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh194c72"><label>72.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name> (1988) Frequency-dependent selection in bacterial populations. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond., B, Biol. Sci.</source>, <volume>319</volume>, <fpage>459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>472</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2905487</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 