<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Respir Res</journal-id><journal-title>Respiratory Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1465-9921</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-993X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1465-9921-5-16</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15450125</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1465-9921-5-16</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Protection of pulmonary epithelial cells from oxidative stress by <italic>hMYH </italic>adenine glycosylase</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>Ted M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kremert@ummhc.org</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rinne</surname><given-names>Mikael L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mrinne@iupui.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>yxu1@iupui.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xian Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>xmchen@iupui.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>Mark R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mkelley@iupui.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics, Herman B Wells Center for Pediatric Research, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, Indiana, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://respiratory-research.com/content/5/1/16"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Kremer et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kremer et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author> Kremer M Ted kremert@ummhc.org </dc:author><dc:title> Protection of pulmonary epithelial cells from oxidative stress by hMYH adenine glycosylase </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Respiratory Research 5(1): 16-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1465-9921(2004)5:1&#x0003c;16&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1465-9921</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Oxygen toxicity is a major cause of lung injury. The base excision repair pathway is one of the most important cellular protection mechanisms that responds to oxidative DNA damage. Lesion-specific DNA repair enzymes include <italic>hOgg1</italic>, <italic>hMYH</italic>, <italic>hNTH </italic>and <italic>hMTH.</italic></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>The above lesion-specific DNA repair enzymes were expressed in human alveolar epithelial cells (A549) using the pSF91.1 retroviral vector. Cells were exposed to a 95% oxygen environment, ionizing radiation (IR), or H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Cell growth analysis was performed under non-toxic conditions. Western blot analysis was performed to verify over-expression and assess endogenous expression under toxic and non-toxic conditions. Statistical analysis was performed using the paired Student's <italic>t </italic>test with significance being accepted for p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Cell killing assays demonstrated cells over-expressing <italic>hMYH </italic>had improved survival to both increased oxygen and IR. Cell growth analysis of A549 cells under non-toxic conditions revealed cells over-expressing <italic>hMYH </italic>also grow at a slower rate. Western blot analysis demonstrated over-expression of each individual gene and did not result in altered endogenous expression of the others. However, it was observed that O<sub>2 </sub>toxicity did lead to a reduced endogenous expression of <italic>hNTH </italic>in A549 cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Increased expression of the DNA glycosylase repair enzyme <italic>hMYH </italic>in A549 cells exposed to O<sub>2 </sub>and IR leads to improvements in cell survival. DNA repair through the base excision repair pathway may provide an alternative way to offset the damaging effects of O<sub>2 </sub>and its metabolites.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Oxidative stress leading to the overproduction of free radicals in the lungs is present in many clinical situations. Such clinical settings include acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), infants of prematurity going on to develop bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD), pathogenesis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), asthma, cystic fibrosis, ischemia-reperfusion injury, drug-induced lung toxicity, cancer and aging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Although the use of oxygen may be clinically indicated in hypoxemic situations, one must consider the potential long-term toxic side effects. For example, we know that oxygen creates cellular damage by a variety of mechanisms. Normal cellular metabolism of oxygen involves the transfer of electrons from NADH to O<sub>2 </sub>molecules to form water (H<sub>2</sub>O). At normal partial pressure, 95% of oxygen molecules (O<sub>2</sub>) are reduced to H<sub>2</sub>O and 5% are partially reduced to toxic byproducts by normal metabolism in the mitochondria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. These metabolites include the superoxide anion (O<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup>), hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>), and hydroxyl radicals (<sup>&#x02022;</sup>OH) all of which make up what are known as Reactive Oxygen Species (ROS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Exposure to conditions of hyperoxia as well as ionizing radiation (IR) leads to increased amounts of these ROS and their damaging effects.</p><p>ROS are known to attack the lipids, proteins, and nucleic acids of cells and tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Lipids, including pulmonary surfactant, react with ROS to produce lipid peroxides, which cause increased membrane permeability, inactivation of surfactant, and inhibition of normal cellular enzyme processes. Proteins reacting with ROS result in decreased protein synthesis due to inhibition of ribosomal translation or destruction of formed proteins. This ultimately leads to inactivation of intracellular enzymes and transport proteins resulting in impaired cellular metabolism and accumulation of cellular waste products. Lastly, ROS cause damage to nucleic acids by leading to modified purine and pyrimidine bases, apurinic (AP) /apyrimidinic sites, and DNA protein cross-links which can lead to single strand breaks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>Several defense mechanisms exist to combat the damaging effects of ROS. Intracellular enzymatic systems include superoxide dismutase which eliminates the superoxide anion, catalase which catalyzes the reduction of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>directly to H<sub>2</sub>O without the production of the hydroxyl radical, and glutathione peroxidase which directly reduces H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>and lipid peroxides. Free radical scavengers, which stop free radical chain reactions by accepting electrons, include &#x003b1;-tocopheral (vitamin E), ascorbic acid (vitamin C), niacin (vitamin B), riboflavin (vitamin B<sub>2</sub>), vitamin A, and ceruloplasmin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. These systems usually provide enough protection against oxygen metabolism under normal conditions, but may become depleted under conditions of increased oxidative stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>The defense mechanism of interest in this paper involves the repair of oxidative damage through the human DNA base excision repair pathway (BER). BER is the most important cellular protection mechanism that removes oxidative DNA damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Damaged bases are excised and replaced in a multi-step process. Lesion-specific DNA glycosylase repair genes initiate this process. After removal of the damaged base, the resulting AP site is cleaved by AP-endonuclease generating a 3'OH and 5'deoxyribose phosphate (dRP). &#x003b2;-polymerase, which possesses dRPase activity, cleaves the dRP residue generating a nucleotide gap and then fills in this single nucleotide gap. The final nick is sealed by DNA ligase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Base excision repair pathways for Oxidative DNA damage. </bold>(A) BER pathway demonstrating repair of 8-oxoG by the repair enzymes <italic>hOgg1 </italic>and <italic>hNTH</italic>. (B) <italic>hOgg1</italic>, <italic>hMYH</italic>, and <italic>hMTH </italic>and their respective repair function.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1465-9921-5-16-1"/></fig><p>The oxidative repair genes that we have analyzed in this study include 8-oxoguanine DNA glycosylase (<italic>hOgg1</italic>), human Mut Y homologue (<italic>hMYH</italic>), human Mut T homologue (<italic>hMTH</italic>), and endonuclease III (<italic>hNTH</italic>) all of which are present in human cells and involved in the protection of DNA from oxidative damage. The repair enzyme <italic>hOgg1 </italic>is a purine oxidation glycosylase that recognizes and excise 8-oxoguanine lesions (GO) paired with cytosine. GO can pair with both cytosine and adenine during DNA replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. If repair of C/GO does not occur, then G:C to T:A transversions may result [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The repair enzyme <italic>hMYH </italic>is an 8-oxoguanine mismatch glycosylase that removes adenines misincorporated opposite 8-oxoG lesions that arise through DNA replication errors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. The repair enzyme <italic>hMTH </italic>hydrolyzes oxidized purine nucleoside triphosphates such as 8-oxo-dGTP, 8-oxo-GTP, 8-oxo-dATP, and 2-hydroxy-dATP, effectively removing them from the nucleotide pool and preventing their incorporation into DNA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Lastly, the repair gene endonuclease III (<italic>hNTH</italic>) is a pyrimidine oxidation and hydration glycosylase that recognizes a wide range of damaged pyrimidines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. <italic>hNTH </italic>has also been shown to have a similar DNA glycosylase/AP lyase activity that can remove 8-oxoG from 8-oxoG/G, 8-oxoG/A, and 8-oxoG/C mispairs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Subsequent steps following <italic>hNTH </italic>are identical to those following <italic>hOgg1 </italic>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>).</p><p>A previous study has shown that over-expression of the DNA repair gene <italic>hOgg1 </italic>leads to reduced hyperoxia-induced DNA damage in human alveolar epithelial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The primary goal of our present study was to compare the protective effects of the four main lesion-specific DNA glycosylase repair genes by individually over-expressing each in lung cells and determining which of these provides the greatest degree of protection under conditions of increased oxidative stress.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Cell Culture</title><p>The human alveolar epithelial cell line A549 (58 year old Caucasian male), was purchased from ATCC Cat No CCL-185. The cells were grown in DMEM (Gibco, Grand Island, NY) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (HyClone, Logan, UT) and penicillin (100 U/ml)/streptomycin (100 &#x003bc;g/ml) (Gibco, Grand Island, NY). Passaging of cells was performed every 3&#x02013;4 days with cells grown to 80% confluency in a 10 cm cell culture dish (Corning Incorporated, Corning, NY). Cells were kept at 37&#x000b0;C in a humidified, 5% CO2 incubator.</p></sec><sec><title>Retroviral Vector Construction</title><p>The retroviral vector pSF91.1, a gift from Dr. C. Baum from the University of Hamburg in Germany, was constructed with an internal ribosome entry site (IRES) upstream to the gene expressing enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p><p>Four DNA repair genes were individually ligated into the retroviral vector pSF91.1.</p><sec><title>hOgg1-6pcDNA3.1</title><p>was initially amplified by PCR by primers to introduce a kozak sequence at the 5' end [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Digestion of this product with EcoRI and SalI was performed and then <italic>hOgg1 </italic>was subcloned into digested plasmid vector pSF91.1, with T4 DNA ligase. DNA sequencing was performed to confirm integrity of the <italic>hOgg1 </italic>gene.</p></sec><sec><title>hMYH/PGEX4T-1 and hMTH/PGEX4T-1</title><p><italic>hMYH </italic>was a gift from Dr. A. McCullough (University of Texas Medical School, Galveston, TX) and <italic>hMTH </italic>was cloned in Dr. Kelley's lab. Plasmid DNA was prepared as above by digestion with EcoRI and SalI and ligated into pSF91.1 as above and sequencing was performed to confirm integrity of the genes.</p></sec><sec><title>PGEX-6PI-hNTH1-wild type</title><p>this gene was a gift from Dr. S. Mitra (University of Texas Medical School, Galveston, TX). Digestion with BamHI and SalI was performed and the <italic>hNTH1-wt </italic>fragment was ligated into the empty plasmid vector PUC18. The <italic>hNTH1-wt </italic>fragment was then excised with both sides flanked by EcoRI restriction sites and ligated into pSF91.1. Proper orientation of the gene was confirmed and sequencing was performed to determine the integrity of the gene.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Retroviral Production and Infection</title><p>DH5&#x003b1; competent cells (Life Technologies, Gaithersburg, MD) with each of the five DNA repair genes were grown in LB-broth with ampicillin (Sigma, St. Louis, MO). Plasmid DNA was prepared and used to transfect phoenix amphotropic cells, from the Nolan Lab (Stanford University Medical Center, San Francisco, CA), grown to ~80% confluency. On the second day sodium butyrate was added to each plate and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 6 hours. Fresh DMEM supplemented with FBS and penicillin/streptomycin was added and the plates were incubated at 33&#x000b0;C. Viral supernatant was collected 24 and 48 hrs later, filtered through a 0.45 &#x003bc;m acrodisc syringe filter (Pall Corporation, Ann Arbor, MI) and frozen at -80&#x000b0;C for later use. Retroviral titers were determined by fluorescent-activated cell sorter (FACS) analysis. Titers of viral supernatant were 8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>to 1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>particles/ml [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p><p>2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>A549 cells were suspended with the viral supernatant and plated in 1 well of a 6-well plate along with polybrene (Sigma, St. Louis, MO). This exposure was performed 6 hours per day for three days. At approximately five days from the beginning of the infection, the infected cells were analyzed using flow cytometry and sorted for EGFP expression.</p></sec><sec><title>Western Analysis</title><p>Cell pellets of sorted cells were resuspended in NuPage buffer (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) and protein concentrations were determined using the DC protein assay (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). 20 ug of protein were loaded into individual lanes of a NuPage Bis-Tris Gel (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). The gel was then transferred to nitrocellulose paper (Osmonics Inc, Gloucester, MA). The membranes were then blocked with 1% blocking solution (Roche Diagnostics, Indianapolis, IN) for 1 hour at room temperature and then incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C with rabbit polyclonal antibodies to <italic>hOgg1 </italic>(Novus Biologicals, Littleton, CO), <italic>hMTH </italic>(Novus Biologicals, Littleton, CO), <italic>hMYH </italic>(Oncogene Research Products, Darmstadt, Germany) and <italic>hNTH </italic>(Proteintech Group Inc, Chicago, IL) all at a dilution of 1:1000 except <italic>hNTH </italic>which was diluted 1:2500. They were then washed 2 times with TBST and 2 times with 0.5% blocking solution, 10 minutes per wash. The membranes were incubated with anti-rabbit secondary antibodies at 1:1000 for 1 hour at room temperature. Lastly, the membranes were washed 4 times with TBST, 15 minutes per wash. The membranes were briefly soaked in BM chemiluminescence blotting substrate (Roche Diagnostics, Indianapolis, IN) and then exposed to high performance autoradiography film (Amersham Biosciences, Buckinghamshire, England). Kodak Digital Science 1D Image Analysis software was utilized to quantify the region of interest (ROI) band mass of individual bands on films where visualized differences were detected.</p></sec><sec><title>Hyperoxic Exposure</title><p>Sorted EGFP positive A549 cells infected with the above DNA repair genes were counted and seeded into 96-well plates at a density of 1000 cells/well, 6 wells per gene. Six hours after seeding, individual plates were placed into an oxygen chamber supplied by Dr. L. Haneline (Wells Center for Research, Indianapolis, IN) located in a 37&#x000b0;C incubator. The oxygen chamber was then infused with 95% O<sub>2 </sub>and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Individual plates were removed after 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours of exposure. Control A549 cells were incubated in a normal 37&#x000b0;C humidified-5% CO<sub>2 </sub>incubator. O<sub>2 </sub>concentrations were monitored with a MAXO<sub>2 </sub>analyzer (Maxtec, Salt Lake City, UT). Four days from the beginning of the exposure, cells were assessed for cell growth/survival using the sulforhodamine B assay (SRB assay).</p></sec><sec><title>Sulforhodamine B Assay</title><p>The SRB assay (Sigma, St. Louis, MO), developed by the National Cancer Institute, provides a sensitive measure of drug-induced cytotoxicity through a colorimetric endpoint that is non-destructive, indefinitely stable, and visible to the naked eye. This assay was used to assess the cell growth/survival of over-expressed cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Cold 10% TCA was used to fix the cells to the plate. After incubation for 1 hour at 4&#x000b0;C, the individual wells were rinsed with water. After air-drying, SRB solution was added to each well and cells were allowed to stain for 20&#x02013;30 minutes. 1% acetic acid wash was used to rinse off unincorporated dye. Incorporated dye was then solubilized in 100 &#x003bc;l per well of 10 mM Tris. Absorbance was measured by a tunable microplate reader (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA) at a wavelength of 565 nm. Background absorbance measured at 690 nm was subtracted from the measurements at 565 nm.</p></sec><sec><title>Irradiation and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>Exposure</title><p>Sorted EGFP positive A549 cells were seeded into 96-well plates at a density of 1000 cells/well. Six hours after seeding, individual plates were then exposed to radiation at doses of 250, 500, 1000, and 1500 Rads or 0.2 mM, 0.4 mM, and 0.6 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>(Sigma, St. Louis, MO). All plates including control plates were then placed into a 37&#x000b0;C humidified-5% CO<sub>2 </sub>incubator. Four days after exposure, cells were fixed and assessed for cell growth/survival by the SRB assay.</p></sec><sec><title>Natural Cell growth</title><p>Sorted EGFP positive A549 cells and wild type cells were seeded individually onto four 96-well plates at 1000 cells/well. All the plates were placed into a 37&#x000b0;C humidified-5% CO<sub>2 </sub>incubator. Every 24 hours for 4 days, 1 plate was removed and the cells were fixed and analyzed by the SRB assay looking at cell growth under non-toxic conditions. Growth curves and exponential growth equations were determined to look at the doubling time (DT) of cells infected with each repair gene of interest compared to vector infected and uninfected wild type cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistics</title><p>All drug exposure experiments were performed at least three times and individual drug doses included 6&#x02013;8 wells for each group of infected cells. Analysis of cell growth and exponential growth equations were determined using Microsoft Excel. All experiments involving drug exposures were normalized to the zero dose. Data are expressed as means &#x000b1; SE. The significance of differences were calculated using the paired Student's <italic>t </italic>test with significance being accepted for p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Retroviral Constructs</title><p>The DNA repair genes <italic>hOgg1</italic>, <italic>hMYH</italic>, <italic>hMTH</italic>, and <italic>hNTH </italic>were ligated into the retroviral vector pSF91.1 (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). This vector, derived from a murine stem cell virus backbone, along with each individual repair gene, was used for transfection of phoenix amphotropic cells. Viral supernatant was then collected and used to stably infect A549 cells. A heterogeneous population of A549 cells expressing EGFP was sorted so all cells used for experiments contained the genes of interest integrated into their DNA (data not shown).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Retroviral vector pSF91.1. </bold>Depiction of the retroviral vector utilized in these experiments demonstrating restriction sites and location of entry of the gene of interest between the LTR and the IRES.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1465-9921-5-16-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Repair Gene Expression</title><p>Western blot analysis was performed on sorted cells in order to verify over-expression of the four genes of interest. <italic>hOgg1</italic>, <italic>hMYH</italic>, <italic>hMTH</italic>, and <italic>hNTH </italic>were all detected at their correct position on western blots (data not shown).</p><p>Western analysis was also utilized to assess whether over-expression of each individual repair gene resulted in altered endogenous expression of the other repair genes under both non-toxic and toxic conditions (24 hrs of 95% O<sub>2 </sub>and 1000 Rad). Cells over-expressing the repair genes <italic>hOgg1</italic>, <italic>hMYH</italic>, <italic>hMTH</italic>, and <italic>hNTH </italic>did not lead to altered expression of the other endogenous repair genes under the above conditions when compared to each other or pSF91.1 vector control cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A,3B,3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). <italic>hOgg1</italic>'s endogenous expression was below the level of detection. The pattern of endogenous expression of <italic>hNTH </italic>was consistent for each condition when comparing cells over-expressing <italic>hOgg1</italic>, <italic>hMYH</italic>, <italic>hMTH</italic>, and pSF91.1. Reduced expression of <italic>hNTH </italic>after exposure to 95% O<sub>2 </sub>was noted.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Western analysis of A549 cells over-expressing individual repair genes and effect on endogenous glycosylase level. </bold>(A) Endogenous expression of hOgg1 was not altered in A549 cells over-expressing any of the other repair genes when analyzed after non-toxic and toxic exposures. <italic>hOgg1 </italic>protein was not detectable for any of the cells under the above conditions when compared to cells over expressing <italic>hOgg1</italic>. (B) and (C) Endogenous expression of hMTH and hMYH respectively also were not altered in A549 cells over-expressing any of the other repair genes when analyzed after non-toxic and toxic exposures. (D) Endogenous expression of hNTH was analyzed under non-toxic and toxic conditions in A549 cells over-expressing the other repair genes. Reduced expression of hNTH was observed equally with all of the other genes after exposure to 95% O<sub>2</sub>. Endogenous expression of all four genes was equivalent under the above conditions in vector control cells; pSF91.1 (data not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1465-9921-5-16-3"/></fig><p>Lastly, we assessed endogenous expression of each individual repair gene in cells infected with pSF91.1 following non-toxic and toxic conditions (24 hrs of 95% O<sub>2 </sub>and 1000 Rad) at 24 and 48 hrs after the onset of exposure. Endogenous <italic>hMYH </italic>and <italic>hMTH </italic>were expressed to the same degree. <italic>hOgg1</italic>'s endogenous expression was below the level of detection using western analysis (results not shown). When analyzing endogenous <italic>hNTH </italic>expression, it was noted that hyperoxia at 24 hrs and 48 hrs resulted in reduced protein expression by 93% and 64% respectively. There also was a small increase in expression of <italic>hNTH </italic>noted after 1000 Rad one day post exposure that was back to baseline by two days post exposure. ROI band mass quantification demonstrated this finding (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). Two or more replicates were performed for each western analysis to determine consistency of the results.</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Western analysis of endogenous <italic>hNTH </italic>repair gene after exposure to O<sub>2 </sub>and IR. </bold>(A) Analysis of <italic>hNTH </italic>expression in A549 vector control cells following O<sub>2 </sub>or IR treatment. The ROI band mass mean intensity was calculated for individual bands and <italic>hNTH </italic>expression was normalized to the corresponding actin loading control. (B) Graph of ROI band mass normalized to the pSF91.1 zero dose.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1465-9921-5-16-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Protection from Hyperoxia and Radiation</title><p>A549 cells expressing <italic>hMYH </italic>demonstrated increased survival after exposure to conditions with elevated levels of oxygen compared to cells expressing only the pSF91.1 vector (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Results were highly significant at all time points except after 12 hours O<sub>2 </sub>where it almost reached a highly significant value. The differences between pSF91.1 and <italic>hMYH </italic>varied from 12% after 12 hours O<sub>2 </sub>exposure to 7% after 72 hours O<sub>2 </sub>exposure. A549 cells expressing <italic>hMYH </italic>also demonstrated increased survival after exposure to all doses of radiation in comparison to pSF91.1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). These results were also highly significant at all doses of radiation except at 250 Rads where it almost reached a highly significant value. The differences between pSF91.1 and <italic>hMYH </italic>varied from 12%&#x02013;14% for all doses of radiation. Also noted in these experiments was that vector control cells demonstrated no significant difference in survival at all doses of O<sub>2 </sub>and radiation in comparison to wild type A549 cells.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Cell survival analysis following O<sub>2</sub>, IR, and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>treatments. </bold>A549 cells over-expressing <italic>hOgg1</italic>, <italic>hMYH</italic>, <italic>hMTH </italic>and <italic>hNTH </italic>following (A) O<sub>2</sub>, (B) IR, and (C) H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Brackets indicate statistical significance at * p &#x0003c; 0.05 and ** p &#x0003c; 0.001 compared to pSF91.1 at each individual dose for 1 representative experiment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1465-9921-5-16-5"/></fig><p>Experiments looking at the effects of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>on cells expressing the repair genes did not demonstrate increased survival for any of these repair genes when compared to vector control cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). This data demonstrates that over-expression of <italic>hMYH </italic>has the ability to improve cellular survival under conditions of hyperoxia and radiation but may not be able to overcome the toxicity of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Growth</title><p>Cell growth under normal conditions was ascertained to determine if over-expression of any of the repair genes caused an alteration in the growth of cells in the absence of oxidative stress. Wild type A549 cells and cells expressing pSF91.1, <italic>hNTH</italic>, <italic>hOgg1</italic>, and <italic>hMTH </italic>appeared to grow at similar rates with doubling times within the same range. A549 cells expressing <italic>hMYH </italic>did show a slower growth rate that resulted in significant differences in cell number by day 3. The calculated doubling time for the cells over expressing <italic>hMYH </italic>is &#x0003e; 3 hrs longer than the cells with the other repair genes and vector alone (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). This slowing of growth may allow for more time to repair DNA damage, ultimately leading to increased cell survival following oxidative stress.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Cell growth curve and associated doubling times (DT). </bold>A549 cells over-expressing <italic>hMYH </italic>grow at a slower rate in comparison to all other cells under non-toxic conditions resulting in a prolongation of the doubling time. Of note, all other over-expressed cells have approximately the same doubling time as wild type A549 cells. Statistical significance noted at ** p &#x0003c; 0.001 compared to pSF91.1 for 1 representative experiment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1465-9921-5-16-6"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Oxidative stress to the lung leads to cellular DNA damage as evidenced by the release of specific gene products known to regulate DNA base excision repair pathways such as p53 and p21 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Alterations in pro-inflammatory mediators, transcription factors, and other related gene products are also observed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. This injury has been shown to be associated with features of both cellular necrosis and apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. The resultant cellular inflammation and death from oxidative stress has a dramatic impact on the outcome of patients in the clinical setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>].</p><p>Most of our current clinical therapy towards oxidative stress in the lung involves both supportive measures and prevention. Research dealing with oxidative lung injury has focused mainly on enhancing antioxidant enzymatic processes and free radical scavengers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. The ability to alter cellular survival by increasing specific DNA repair mechanisms may add another approach to the treatment of oxidant-mediated lung injury.</p><p>Many investigators have used hydrogen peroxide as a substitute for hyperoxia since it is known to be one of the metabolites produced by the metabolism of oxygen. ROS such as H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>and those produced by hyperoxia clearly lead to DNA damage but questions exist as to whether H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>leads to the same deleterious effects upon DNA as hyperoxia. Analysis of our growth curves after exposure to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>in comparison to hyperoxia and IR clearly indicates that cellular protection by oxidative DNA repair genes is specific to the agent used. Because no protection was observed with over-expression of any of the repair genes following exposure to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, we speculate that the damage it causes is dissimilar. It may be that its damage not only involves oxidized bases, but may also include other forms of DNA, lipid, and protein damage that are not corrected by oxidative DNA repair genes. Alternatively, the amount and type of damage evoked by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>could be beyond that which can be corrected by over-expressing these repair genes.</p><p>Another form of stress known to induce damage through the formation of ROS is IR. Radiation induced free radical damage to DNA has substantial overlap with that of oxidative damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. The protection provided by specific oxidative DNA repair genes under conditions of IR, was notable throughout our experiments only with the repair enzyme <italic>hMYH</italic>.</p><p>The primary agent utilized to induce the formation of ROS was an oxygen rich environment. The use of oxygen as a stressor leading to the formation of ROS, offers a distinct advantage over IR and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>by mimicking the clinical situation where constant exposure to hyperoxia leads to cumulative cellular damage which further compromises repair. We determined that survival of A549 cells was also enhanced to a small degree with increased expression of the repair enzyme <italic>hMYH</italic>. This was an unexpected finding as we anticipated the repair gene <italic>hOgg1 </italic>would demonstrate the greatest protection in response to oxidative stress based on previous studies, however these experiments utilized the colony forming assay (CFA) to detect improvements in survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Additionally, the CFA may provide different results compared to the SRB assay, which allows for growth analysis over a shorter window of time. Furthermore, their study did not look at the repair enzyme <italic>hMYH </italic>and its impact on survival. Another study has investigated the repair function of <italic>hMYH </italic>in MYH-deficient murine cells. It was demonstrated that transfection of the MYH-deficient cells with a wild-type MYH expression vector increased the efficiency of A:GO repair [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>].</p><p>An interesting observation noted while doing our experiments lead us to look at individual growth characteristics of cells over-expressing each of the oxidative repair enzymes. Cells over-expressing the repair enzyme <italic>hMYH </italic>clearly grow at a slower rate when compared with the other enzymes. The mechanism behind this is not understood at this point in time. The repair action of <italic>hMYH </italic>is known to remove adenines misincorporated opposite 8-oxoG lesions. This lesion occurs when a C/GO lesion is allowed to replicate before being corrected by <italic>hOgg1</italic>. Repair by <italic>hMYH </italic>is not a final corrective measure. The product of <italic>hMYH </italic>activity is the lesion C/GO, which allows <italic>hOgg1 </italic>to have another opportunity to remove 8-oxoG opposite cytosine. We know that A549 cells possess the <italic>hOgg1 </italic>gene based on a previous study demonstrating the presence of this gene after amplification by genomic PCR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. We also have demonstrated endogenous activity of <italic>hOgg1 </italic>in A549 cells by using an 8-oxoguanine bioactivity assay. Therefore, our explanation of these results is that the slowed growth created by <italic>hMYH </italic>may provide a wider window of opportunity for the repair process to take place, which ultimately grants endogenous <italic>hOgg1 </italic>another opportunity to remove the 8-oxoG lesion created by oxidative stress.</p><p>As noted in the methods section, the SRB assay provides a sensitive measure of drug-induced cytotoxicity that is used to assess cell proliferation/survival. The reduced cell proliferation of A549 cells over-expressing hMYH under non-toxic conditions may likely underestimate the magnitude of the protective effect of this particular repair enzyme. This may in fact make the results even more significant.</p><p>Recent studies have discovered hereditary variations of the glycosylase <italic>hMYH </italic>that may predispose to familial colorectal cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Others have looked for <italic>hMYH </italic>variants in lung cancer patients and have not identified any clear pathogenic biallelic <italic>hMYH </italic>mutations or an over-representation of <italic>hMYH </italic>polymorphisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. The A549 cell line has not demonstrated somatic mutations in <italic>hMYH</italic>, but a single nucleotide polymorphism (SNPs) has been noted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. The impact on function by this SNP is unknown. It would appear that the function of <italic>hMYH </italic>is very important in preventing somatic mutations leading to cancer in the gastrointestinal tract. Although studies to date have not demonstrated this same relationship with lung cancer, we do know that the lungs are subjected to large quantities of ROS under certain conditions as discussed earlier. The formation of mutations from oxidative stress does have other deleterious effects on cells including cellular death by necrosis and apoptosis. Tissue viability is dependent upon mutation correction and replication of the surviving cells to replace those that have died. The ability to enhance cellular survival, after specific oxidative exposures, is evident after increased production of the <italic>hMYH </italic>repair gene in these experiments.</p><p>We additionally wanted to determine the level of endogenous expression of the glycosylase repair genes in the pulmonary epithelial A549 cell line. Others have demonstrated how different stressors lead to alterations in the endogenous production of specific repair genes. For example, it has been shown that endogenous gene expression of <italic>hOgg1 </italic>was elevated following exposure to crocidolite asbestos which is known to cause an increase in 8-oxoG levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]. It has also previously been reported that treatment of A549 cells with sodium dichromate, a pro-oxidant, leads to a reduction of <italic>hOgg1 </italic>protein expression that was not observed with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]. One additional study demonstrated a dose dependent down regulation of <italic>hOgg1 </italic>protein expression in rat lung after exposure to cadmium, a known carcinogen associated with the formation of intracellular ROS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>]. In our experiments we were able to demonstrate that both hyperoxia and IR do not appear to impact the endogenous expression of <italic>hOgg1</italic>, <italic>hMYH</italic>, and <italic>hMTH </italic>at 24 and 48 hours following exposure. It was noted that endogenous <italic>hNTH </italic>was reduced after hyperoxia at 24 and 48 hours after the onset of exposure. One would speculate that this reduction in endogenous <italic>hNTH </italic>secondary to hyperoxia is related to either decreased production or increased destruction in response to O<sub>2 </sub>exposure. Over-expression of this repair enzyme did not result in improvements in survival after O<sub>2 </sub>exposure based on our experiments. It may be that endogenous levels are adequate to correct this specific mutational burden for these experiments.</p><p>Furthermore, no previous studies have determined how cells over-expressing specific repair genes may impact endogenous expression of the other oxidative BER genes under both normal and oxidative stress conditions. We were also able to demonstrate that endogenous expression of glycosylase repair genes were not altered under these conditions secondary to the over-expression of any of these genes. This is an important finding for interpretation of survival data; protection of cells is due to the over-expression of the specific gene and not due to enhancement of other endogenous repair enzyme levels, at least for the genes studied under these conditions.</p><p>Some limitations may exist in using a lung carcinoma cell-line, which likely differs both in proliferative properties as well as in response to oxidative stress in comparison to primary epithelial cells. The enhanced cell growth observed with cell lines may be more reflective of undifferentiated alveolar type II cells which are likely to replace terminally differentiated alveolar type I cells after injury/death due to oxidative stress. This may not be a true reflection of growth under non-toxic conditions when very little cell division is occurring. This is an inherent problem observed when comparing cell lines with primary cells and results need to be interpreted in a way that considers this.</p><p>It is difficult to know how this will translate to pulmonary epithelial cells <italic>in vivo </italic>at this stage. It certainly would appear that the protection observed is modest in degree in this pulmonary epithelial cell line. Further experiments assessing the function of the repair enzyme <italic>hMYH </italic>in this model will be important to perform in order to delineate the findings of slowed growth under normal conditions and improved survivability under conditions of O<sub>2 </sub>and IR. More research looking at the potential for combination therapy, including DNA repair mechanisms in conjunction with other antioxidant defense mechanisms may be another approach to enhancing cell survival, which may lead to better clinical outcomes. Alternatively, cell survival may not be the most important end point for hyperoxia studies. Given that 8-oxoG, if left unrepaired, leads to G:C to T:A transversions, there may be an increase in mutational burden by these cells that isn't reflected in cell survival. Further experiments studying the impact on mutation production is underway. Ultimately, experiments need to be done in animal models to determine the translation to <italic>in vivo </italic>pulmonary cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, we have demonstrated that over-expression of the DNA glycosylase repair enzyme <italic>hMYH </italic>may enhance survival of a pulmonary epithelial cell line after exposure to conditions of IR and hyperoxia. We have also demonstrated that over-expression of <italic>hMYH </italic>leads to a slowing of growth of A549 cells under non-toxic conditions, which may in part play a role in this enhancement of survival by providing a wider window of opportunity for repair of oxidized lesions to occur. Lastly, we demonstrated that over-expression does not lead to altered endogenous expression of these repair genes. As the understanding of DNA repair mechanisms continues to grow and the evolution of gene therapy takes place, more treatment options may be available in the clinical setting to help with many disease processes including the damaging effects of oxygen and its metabolites.</p></sec><sec><title>List of abbreviations</title><p>apurinic, AP; base excision repair, BER; Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium, DMEM; deoxyribose phosphate, dRP; enhanced green fluorescent protein, EGFP; fetal bovine serum, FBS; hydrogen peroxide, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>; ionizing radiation, IR; internal ribosomal entry site, IRES; long terminal repeat, LTR; oxygen, O<sub>2</sub>; Sulforhodamine B, SRB; reactive oxygen species, ROS; region of interest, ROI; Tris-Borate-EDTA, TBE; tris-buffered saline Tween-20, TBST; 8-oxoguanine, GO and 8-oxoG</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>TK conducted the majority of the research experiments, performed the statistical analysis, and drafted the manuscript. MR conducted some of the cell survival experiments and participated in the design of the study. YX and XC helped with production of the lesion specific DNA repair genes. MK conceived of the study, and participated in its design and coordination. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grantsNS38506, ES05865, ES03456, and P30 DK49218 supporting MRK.TK was supported on a T32 pulmonary training grant NIH-NHLBI/T32 (46886). Additional support was from The RileyChildren's Foundation.We would also like to thank Dr. Sankar Mitra for the <italic>hNTH </italic>clones, Dr. Amanda McCullough for the <italic>hMYH </italic>clones, and Dr. Laura Haneline for allowing us to use her oxygen chamber. Lastly, the Pediatric Pulmonary section at Riley Hospital for Children has been an additional provider of support and information throughout this research project.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Significance of glutathione in lung disease and implications for therapy</article-title><source>Am J Med Sci</source><year>1994</year><volume>307</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8141138</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Housset</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Free radicals and respiratory pathology]</article-title><source>C R Seances Soc Biol Fil</source><year>1994</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7736256</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Science review: Redox and oxygen-sensitive transcription factors in the regulation of oxidant-mediated lung injury: role for nuclear factor-kappaB</article-title><source>Crit Care</source><year>2002</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12493069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/cc1839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>W. R., Jr.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemogenomic identification of Ref-1/AP-1 as a therapeutic target for asthma</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>1169</fpage><lpage>1173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12552119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0437889100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repair of oxidative DNA damage: mechanisms and functions</article-title><source>Cell Biochem Biophys</source><year>2001</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11892789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/CBB:35:2:141</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halliwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free radicals, reactive oxygen species and human disease: a critical evaluation with special reference to atherosclerosis</article-title><source>Br J Exp Pathol</source><year>1989</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2557883</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA damage and cell cycle checkpoints in hyperoxic lung injury: braking to facilitate repair</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>L291</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11435201</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dizdaroglu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaruga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Birincioglu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free radical-induced damage to DNA: mechanisms and measurement</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1102</fpage><lpage>1115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12031895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(02)00826-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Olver</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Land</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant/pro-oxidant equilibrium regulates HIF-1alpha and NF-kappa B redox sensitivity. Evidence for inhibition by glutathione oxidation in alveolar epithelial cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>21130</fpage><lpage>21139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10801793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M000737200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michiels</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Raes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Toussaint</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Remacle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of Se-glutathione peroxidase, catalase, and Cu/Zn-SOD for cell survival against oxidative stress</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>1994</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7982629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0891-5849(94)90079-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Morey</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Doetsch</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jinks-Robertson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overlapping specificities of base excision repair, nucleotide excision repair, recombination, and translesion synthesis pathways for DNA base damage in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2929</fpage><lpage>2935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10082560</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excision of deoxyribose phosphate residues by DNA polymerase beta during DNA repair</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1995</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7624801</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chyan</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Maciejewski</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of the amino-terminal 8-kDa domain of DNA polymerase beta as revealed by site-directed mutagenesis. DNA binding and 5'-deoxyribose phosphate lyase activities</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>11121</fpage><lpage>11126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9556598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.273.18.11121</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boldogh</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazra</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complexities of the DNA base excision repair pathway for repair of oxidative DNA damage</article-title><source>Environ Mol Mutagen</source><year>2001</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11746753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/em.1070</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shibutani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grollman</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insertion of specific bases during DNA synthesis past the oxidation-damaged base 8-oxodG</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1991</year><volume>349</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1992344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/349431a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The GO system protects organisms from the mutagenic effect of the spontaneous lesion 8-hydroxyguanine (7,8-dihydro-8-oxoguanine)</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1992</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>6321</fpage><lpage>6325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1328155</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Dizdaroglu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gajewski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Essigmann</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanistic studies of ionizing radiation and oxidative mutagenesis: genetic effects of a single 8-hydroxyguanine (7-hydro-8-oxoguanine) residue inserted at a unique site in a viral genome</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1990</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>7024</fpage><lpage>7032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2223758</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohtsubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Imaiso</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimokawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakabeppu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of human MutY homolog (hMYH) as a repair enzyme for 2-hydroxyadenine in DNA and detection of multiple forms of hMYH located in nuclei and mitochondria</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1355</fpage><lpage>1364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10684930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.6.1355</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slupska</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Luther</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional expression of hMYH, a human homolog of the Escherichia coli MutY protein</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1999</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>6210</fpage><lpage>6213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10498741</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential subcellular localization of human MutY homolog (hMYH) and the functional activity of adenine:8-oxoguanine DNA glycosylase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>3638</fpage><lpage>3644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10471731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/27.18.3638</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakushiji</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakabeppu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The oxidized forms of dATP are substrates for the human MutT homologue, the hMTH1 protein</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>18201</fpage><lpage>18205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10373420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.26.18201</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyabe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of repair enzymes for 5-formyluracil in DNA. Nth, Nei, and MutM proteins of Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>35471</fpage><lpage>35477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10956660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M006125200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazra</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkataraman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kow</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dizdaroglu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of a novel 8-oxoguanine-DNA glycosylase activity in Escherichia coli and identification of the enzyme as endonuclease VIII</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>27762</fpage><lpage>27767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10862773</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name><name><surname>Takao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Escherichia coli Nth and human hNTH1 DNA glycosylases are involved in removal of 8-oxoguanine from 8-oxoguanine/guanine mispairs in DNA</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1975</fpage><lpage>1981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11328882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/29.9.1975</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobune</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>W. J., 2nd</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protection of human lung cells against hyperoxia using the DNA base excision repair genes hOgg1 and Fpg</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200112-130OC</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobune</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retrovirus-mediated expression of the base excision repair proteins, formamidopyrimidine DNA glycosylase or human oxoguanine DNA glycosylase, protects hematopoietic cells from N,N',N"-triethylenethiophosphoramide (thioTEPA)-induced toxicity in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>5116</fpage><lpage>5125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11431349</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Point mutations define a sequence flanking the AUG initiator codon that modulates translation by eukaryotic ribosomes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1986</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3943125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(86)90762-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skehan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Storeng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scudiero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Monks</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vistica</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokesch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New colorimetric cytotoxicity assay for anticancer-drug screening</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1990</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>1112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2359136</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Offer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zurer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Banfalvi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reha'k</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Falcovitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Milyavsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldfinger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p53 modulates base excision repair activity in a cell cycle-specific manner after genotoxic stress</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11196204</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranalli</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Podust</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bambara</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulatory roles of p21 and apurinic/apyrimidinic endonuclease 1 in base excision repair</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>48781</fpage><lpage>48789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11641413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109626200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p53 regulation of DNA excision repair pathways</article-title><source>Mutagenesis</source><year>2002</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11880544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mutage/17.2.149</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrion-Caude</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Besnard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Corroyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of cyclins in epithelial response to oxidants</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>S81</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11734473</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barazzone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Donati</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Piguet</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxygen toxicity in mouse lung: pathways to cell death</article-title><source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9761753</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barazzone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of cell injury and death in hyperoxia: role of cytokines and Bcl-2 family proteins</article-title><source>Am J Respir Cell Mol Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10783120</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazzaz</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Horowitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantell</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hyperoxia in cell culture. A non-apoptotic programmed cell death</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>887</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10668472</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequelae of the adult respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>1994</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8153946</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muzykantov</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delivery of antioxidant enzyme proteins to the lung</article-title><source>Antioxid Redox Signal</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11291598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/152308601750100489</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsan</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superoxide dismutase and pulmonary oxygen toxicity: lessons from transgenic and knockout mice (Review)</article-title><source>Int J Mol Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11115602</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsan</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superoxide dismutase and pulmonary oxygen toxicity</article-title><source>Proc Soc Exp Biol Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>214</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9034127</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glutamine protects mitochondrial structure and function in oxygen toxicity</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>L779</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238020</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henle</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation, prevention, and repair of DNA damage by iron/hydrogen peroxide</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>19095</fpage><lpage>19098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9235895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.31.19095</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beckman</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative decay of DNA</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>19633</fpage><lpage>19636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9289489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.272.32.19633</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaisdell</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Base excision repair processing of radiation-induced clustered DNA lesions</article-title><source>Radiat Prot Dosimetry</source><year>2001</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11763354</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakabeppu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replication-associated repair of adenine:8-oxoguanine mispairs by MYH</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11864576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(02)00686-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shinmura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Somatic mutations and single nucleotide polymorphisms of base excision repair genes involved in the repair of 8-hydroxyguanine in damaged DNA</article-title><source>Cancer Lett</source><year>2001</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11295288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3835(01)00435-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sieber</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinimann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fidalgo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisgaard</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Orntoft</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Aaltonen</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple colorectal adenomas, classic adenomatous polyposis, and germ-line mutations in MYH</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12606733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa025283</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Tassan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheadle</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Houlston</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inherited variants in MYH are unlikely to contribute to the risk of lung carcinoma</article-title><source>Hum Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14579148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00439-003-1033-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ootsuyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirohashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in DNA 8-hydroxyguanine levels, 8-hydroxyguanine repair activity, and hOGG1 and hMTH1 mRNA expression in human lung alveolar epithelial cells induced by crocidolite asbestos</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>2001</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11181447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/carcin/22.2.265</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chipman</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Down-regulation of the DNA-repair endonuclease 8-oxo-guanine DNA glycosylase 1 (hOGG1) by sodium dichromate in cultured human A549 lung carcinoma cells</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11756223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/carcin/23.1.55</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Watkin</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadmium exposure down-regulates 8-oxoguanine DNA glycosylase expression in rat lung and alveolar epithelial cells</article-title><source>Toxicology</source><year>2003</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12499121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0300-483X(02)00579-6</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 