<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.1 20050630//EN" "archivearticle.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkh927</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh927</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520468</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CTD kinase I is involved in RNA polymerase I transcription</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bouchoux</surname><given-names>C&#x000e9;line</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hautbergue</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="gkh927fn2">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grenetier</surname><given-names>Sabrina</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carles</surname><given-names>Christophe</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Riva</surname><given-names>Michel</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Goguel</surname><given-names>Val&#x000e9;rie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="gkh927fn1">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0xa100c00.0x9909918">Service de Biochimie et G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique Mol&#x000e9;culaire, CEA&#x0002f;Saclay, 91191 Gif&#x0002f;Yvette, France </aff><author-notes><fn id="gkh927fn1"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: &#x0002b;33 1 6908 9921; Fax: &#x0002b;33 1 6908 4712; Email: <email>vgoguel@cea.fr</email></p></fn><fn id="gkh927fn2"><label>a</label><p>Present address: Guillaume Hautbergue, Department of Biology and Biotechnology, The University of Sheffield, Firth Court, Western Bank, Sheffield S10 2TN, UK</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>32</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>5851</fpage><lpage>5860</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nar.oupjournals.org/content/vol32/issue19//"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Oxford University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><abstract><p>RNA polymerase II carboxy terminal domain (CTD) kinases are key elements in the control of mRNA synthesis. Yeast CTD kinase I (CTDK-I), is a non-essential complex involved in the regulation of mRNA synthesis at the level of transcription elongation, pre-mRNA 3&#x02032; formation and nuclear export. Here, we report that CTDK-I is also involved in ribosomal RNA synthesis. We show that CTDK-I is localized in part in the nucleolus. In its absence, nucleolar structure and RNA polymerase I transcription are affected. <italic>In vitro</italic> experiments show an impairment of the Pol I transcription machinery. Remarkably, RNA polymerase I co-precipitates from cellular extracts with Ctk1, the kinase subunit of the CTDK-I complex. <italic>In vitro</italic> analysis further demonstrates a direct interaction between RNA polymerase I and Ctk1. The results suggest that CTDK-I might participate in the regulation of distinct nuclear transcriptional machineries, thus playing a role in the adaptation of the global transcriptional response to growth signalling.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Eukaryotic cells contain three nuclear RNA polymerases (Pol I, II and III) that can be distinguished by their polypeptide composition, gene specificity and sub-cellular localization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c1">1</xref>). Pol I is localized in the nucleolus where it transcribes the 35S rDNA to generate the precursor transcript of the mature 25, 18 and 5.8S rRNA species. Pol I transcription accounts for &#x0223c;60% of the total transcription activity of exponentially growing yeast cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c2">2</xref>). Specific initiation requires four general initiation factors: the upstream activating factor complex (UAF), the TATA binding protein (TBP), the core factor complex (CF) and Rrn3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c3">3</xref>). Assembled onto the 35S rDNA promoter, UAF, TBP and CF form a pre-initiation complex that recruits the Pol I&#x02013;Rrn3 complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c6">6</xref>), the only form of Pol I competent for initiation. Phosphorylation of Pol I is necessary for its interaction with Rrn3, suggesting that one way to regulate rDNA transcription is at the level of Pol I&#x02013;Rrn3 complex formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c7">7</xref>). Strong functional and structural homologies can be drawn from yeast to mammals, and in both systems, rRNA synthesis rate is under the control of growth signalling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c10">10</xref>).</p><p>Pol II produces mRNA precursors, and the majority of the snRNA implicated in splicing. A key element of transcription by Pol II is the carboxy terminal domain (CTD) of its largest subunit, Rpb1. The CTD is an essential domain specific to Pol II, composed of numerous repeats of the consensus heptapeptide YSPTSPS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c11">11</xref>). This domain involved in the major steps of mRNA synthesis, is present under two distinct forms: a highly phosphorylated form (IIo) and a poorly phosphorylated form (IIa) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c12">12</xref>). Only the Pol IIA is recruited to the promoter to participate in the formation of the pre-initiation complex, while it needs to be converted to the Pol IIO form in order to enter transcription elongation. A transcription cycle thus involves the cyclical phosphorylation and dephosphorylation of the CTD. In addition, the phosphorylation pattern of the Pol II CTD changes during the transcription process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c13">13</xref>), and varies in response to growth conditions and environmental stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c14">14</xref>).</p><p>Four CTD kinases have been described in the yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, all of them being cyclin-dependent kinases: Kin28, Srb10, Bur1 and Ctk1. Kin28 is required for transcription of most class II genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c15">15</xref>). Like its human counterpart, Cdk7, it is an essential subunit of the general transcription factor TFIIH. Its activity is required for transcription initiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c16">16</xref>), and for recruitment of capping enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c17">17</xref>). Srb10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c18">18</xref>) is structurally related to mammalian Cdk8. This non-essential kinase phosphorylates the CTD prior to the formation of the pre-initiation complex, thus preventing its formation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c16">16</xref>). <italic>BUR1&#x0002f;SGV1</italic> encodes an essential CTD kinase that might be implicated in elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c20">20</xref>). The non-essential CTD kinase I complex (CTDK-I) comprises three specific subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c21">21</xref>): Ctk1, the catalytic subunit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c22">22</xref>), Ctk2, the cyclin subunit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c23">23</xref>), and Ctk3 a co-cyclin factor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c24">24</xref>). Deletion of the <italic>CTK1</italic> gene results in defects in the pattern of the CTD phosphorylation, and correlated defects in transcriptional induction of sets of genes, suggesting a role for CTDK-I in response to nutrient depletion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c25">25</xref>). Several studies have implicated CTDK-I in the control of transcription elongation: (i) CTDK-I can modulate the elongation efficiency of Pol II in HeLa extracts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c26">26</xref>), (ii) <italic>ctk</italic> mutants are synthetic lethal with mutants in various genes implicated in elongation control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c28">28</xref>) and (iii), a recent study has revealed that Ctk1 might be the major kinase involved in CTD phosphorylation during elongation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c29">29</xref>). Ctk1 has also been connected to 3&#x02032; end processing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c31">31</xref>), splicing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c32">32</xref>), histone methylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c33">33</xref>), DNA damage-induced transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c34">34</xref>) and nuclear export of mRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c35">35</xref>). In human, the closest characterized kinase to Ctk1 is Cdk9, the catalytic subunit of the positive elongation factor P-TEFb in metazoans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c36">36</xref>). P-TEFb&#x0002f;Cdk9 is a key cellular factor that supports Tat <italic>trans</italic>-activation and HIV replication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c37">37</xref>).</p><p>In higher eukaryotes, CTD kinases have been implicated in phosphorylation of additional substrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c38">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c42">42</xref>). Similarly, in yeast, both Kin28 and Srb10 have been shown to phosphorylate substrates other than the CTD. However, these substrates are all implicated in Pol II transcription. Kin28 phosphorylates subunits of Mediator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c44">44</xref>), while Srb10 phosphorylates subunits of TFIID (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c43">43</xref>) and several Pol II specific transcription factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c48">48</xref>).</p><p>In this report, we show that, in addition to its role as a Pol II CTD kinase, CTDK-I is implicated in Pol I transcription.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Yeast strains</title><p>The yeast strains used in this study were derived from W303-1B (MAT&#x003b1; ade2-1 can1-100 his3-11,15 leu2-3,112 trp1-1 ura3-1) and grown in either YPD or SD medium supplemented with casamino-acids and appropriate nutrients (SD-casa). The CTK tagged-strains were constructed by fusion of sequences encoding several epitope-tags (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c49">49</xref>) at the 3&#x02032; end of the CTK coding sequence: CTK1&#x02013;HA (3-HA::<italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> HIS5), CTK1&#x02013;Myc (13-Myc::<italic>S.pombe</italic> HIS5) and CTK2&#x02013;Myc (13-Myc::<italic>Escherichia coli</italic> KanR). &#x00394;<italic>ctk</italic>1 and &#x00394;<italic>ctk</italic>3 null mutants are described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c23">23</xref>). The isogenic &#x00394;<italic>pdr</italic>13 strain (pdr13::<italic>S.pombe</italic> HIS5) was constructed using the pFA6a-His3MX6 plasmid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c49">49</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Ctk1&#x02013;Myc purification</title><p>Wild-type and CTK1&#x02013;Myc strains were grown in 12 l of YPD to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 2, and pelleted by centrifugation. Fifty gram of cells were typically obtained and resuspended in 50 ml of buffer B [25 mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT, 20% glycerol (v&#x0002f;v) with 1 mM phenylmethylsulphonyl fluoride (PMSF) and complete protease inhibitors mixture (Roche)] containing 130 mM potassium acetate (B130). Cell suspensions were frozen at &#x02212;70&#x000b0;C and disrupted in an Eaton press. After ultracentrifugation at 100&#x02009;000 <italic>g</italic> for 1 h in a 45 Ti rotor (Beckman), crude extract was loaded on a SP-Sepharose column (10 &#x000d7; 2.5 cm, Amersham Biosciences) equilibrated in buffer B130 at a flow rate of 2 ml&#x0002f;min. Elution of bound proteins was performed by a 300 ml linear gradient of potassium acetate (0.13&#x02013;1.2 M) in buffer B. Fractions (5 ml) containing Ctk1 were pooled, dialysed for 14 h against 2 l of buffer B100 (0.1 M potassium acetate), and loaded at a flow rate of 1 ml&#x0002f;min on a Poros 10 HQ column (0.8 ml, Perkin Elmer) equilibrated in B100. Ctk1 was eluted with a 13.4 ml linear gradient of potassium acetate (0.1&#x02013;1M) in buffer B. Fractions (0.8 ml) were analysed by SDS&#x02013;PAGE and western blot.</p></sec><sec><title>Purification of Ctk1&#x02013;HA&#x0002f;Pol I complexes</title><p>Wild-type and CTK1&#x02013;HA strains were submitted to the purification procedure described above except for the second chromatography step. The pooled solution obtained from SP-Sepharose chromatography was dialysed for 14 h against 2 l of buffer B containing 0.3 M potassium acetate and loaded at a flow rate of 0.5 ml&#x0002f;min on a MonoQ column (1 ml, Amersham Biosciences) equilibrated in buffer B300. Ctk1 was eluted with a 12 ml linear gradient of potassium acetate (0.3&#x02013;1.6 M) in buffer B. Fractions (0.3 ml) containing Ctk1 were pooled and further loaded on an immuno-affinity column. Protein G-Sepharose (200 &#x003bc;l, Amersham Biosciences) crosslinked to HA-12CA5 antibodies (0.03 mg&#x0002f;ml) was packed in micro-tips and equilibrated with buffer B1000. Proteins were loaded by gravity flow, recycling the flow through eight times. After intensive washing with buffer B1000, the resin was re-equilibrated in buffer B130. Three successive elutions were performed in batch by adding 300 &#x003bc;l of buffer B130 containing 0.1 mg&#x0002f;ml of a synthetic haemagglutinin (HA) peptide. Elutions were pooled and analysed by SDS&#x02013;PAGE and western blot with anti-HA, anti-Pol I and anti-Rrn3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c50">50</xref>) antibodies.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> co-immunoprecipitation</title><p>Pol I, Pol I&#x00394; and Pol I<sup>&#x0002a;</sup> were purified from yeast cells as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c51">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c53">53</xref>) and analysed by SDS&#x02013;PAGE and silver staining. Expression of recombinant HA&#x02013;Ctk1, HA&#x02013;Ctk2 and HA&#x02013;Ctk3 was performed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c24">24</xref>) in <italic>E.Coli Rosetta (DE3)</italic> strain (Novagen). Immunoprecipitation experiments were performed with 5 &#x003bc;g of purified Pol I, and different combinations of bacterial extracts each expressing a single recombinant protein, with 30 &#x003bc;l of Protein G-Sepharose (Amersham Biosciences) coupled with 5 &#x003bc;l of a serum directed against A190 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c54">54</xref>), as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c24">24</xref>). Proteins were eluted with Laemmli buffer and separated by SDS&#x02013;PAGE prior to western immunoblotting.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunofluorescence microscopy</title><p>Ten millilitre of cells grown in YPD at an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.5 were fixed by the addition of formaldehyde to a final concentration of 3.7%. Cells were further incubated for 10 min at room temperature, centrifuged and resuspended in KP&#x02013;Sorbitol buffer (50 mM potassium phosphate, pH 6.5, 0.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.2 M Sorbitol). Spheroplasts were prepared by incubation at 37&#x000b0;C for 30 min with zymolyase 100T (0.2 mg&#x0002f;ml, ICN). Cells were washed [once with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) buffer containing 1% fish gelatine (Teleostan gelatin, Sigma), twice with PBS buffer with 0.1% Triton X-100 (Fluka) and once more with PBS buffer], prior to incubation with the primary antibody in PBS buffer for 1 h at room temperature. Antibodies used were: 10 &#x003bc;g&#x0002f;ml of purified monoclonal anti-Myc 9E10 (Babco), rabbit polyclonal serum anti-A190 at 1:100 dilution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c54">54</xref>) and monoclonal anti-Nop1 Mab66 at 1:150 dilution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c55">55</xref>). Cells were washed, resuspended in PBS buffer containing either anti-mouse Alexa 594 IgG or anti-rabbit Alexa 488 IgG (1:100 dilution, Molecular Probes) for 1 h at room temperature. After washing, cells were incubated with 0.5 &#x003bc;g&#x0002f;ml 4&#x02032;,6&#x02032;-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, Sigma) in 0.5 ml of PBS buffer for 2 min. Cells were washed once with PBS buffer and observed with a Leica microscope.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vivo</italic> RNA labelling</title><p>Ten millilitre of yeast cells were grown in SD-casa at an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.5. Cell labelling was conducted for 30 min at 30&#x000b0;C with 150 &#x003bc;Ci of <sup>3</sup>H-Uracil (Amersham Biosciences). After centrifugation, cells were washed with water prior to freezing in liquid nitrogen. Total RNA was extracted by hot acid&#x02013;phenol treatment as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c56">56</xref>). RNA was quantified, and 5 &#x003bc;g was separated by electrophoresis on an 8% acrylamide gel containing 7 M urea in TBE. The gel was stained with ethidium bromide, dried and submitted to autoradiography.</p></sec><sec><title>Primer extension analyses</title><p>Ten millilitre of yeast cells were grown in SD-casa at an OD<sub>600</sub> of 1 and 2, respectively. Total RNA was extracted by hot acid&#x02013;phenol treatment as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c56">56</xref>). RNA was quantified by OD<sub>260</sub> measurements, and 3 &#x003bc;g was analysed by primer extension [as in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c57">57</xref>)] with 0.2 pmol of end-labelled 35S and 25S oligonucleotides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c58">58</xref>), plus 5 pmol of cold 25S oligonucleotide. Extension products were separated by electrophoresis on an 8% acrylamide gel containing 7 M urea in TBE. The gel was dried, submitted to autoradiography and analysed with a PhosphorImager (Molecular Dynamics).</p></sec><sec><title>Chromatin immunoprecipitation</title><p>Wild-type and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> strains were grown in SD-casa medium to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 2. Cross-link, cell lysis, chromatin preparation, cross-link reversal and immunoprecipitation were performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c60">60</xref>). Immunoprecipitation was realized with protein A-Sepharose (Sigma) coupled with polyclonal anti-A190 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c54">54</xref>). Immuno-precipitated and total DNA were analysed by real-time PCR with SYBR Green (Applied Biosystems) using two sets of primer amplifying a 122 bp fragment specific of the 35S rDNA promoter region (<italic>GTGTGAGGAAAAGTAGTTGGGAGGTA</italic>, <italic>GACGAGGCCATTTACAAAAACATAAC</italic>), and a 236 bp fragment specific of the 5S rDNA (<italic>GACGAGGCCATTTACAAAAACATAAC</italic>, <italic>CATGTCTGGACCCTGCCCTCATA</italic>). For each experiment, triplicates of three dilutions were analysed; and five independent experiments were performed. The occupancy level was defined as the ratio of immunoprecipitated DNA over total DNA.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription assays</title><p>Purification of PA600 fractions from cells grown in YPD to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 2 was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c61">61</xref>). Specific transcription assays were performed [as in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c61">61</xref>)] with 40 ng of YepSIRT template (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c62">62</xref>). Pol I from PA600 extracts (15 &#x003bc;g) was analysed by western immunoblotting with polyclonal antibodies raised against Pol I.</p></sec><sec><title>Immobilized templates assays</title><p>DNA templates containing [YepSIRT, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c62">62</xref>)], or not containing (&#x00394;prom, O. Gadal, unpublished data) the 35S rDNA promoter were amplified by PCR using oligonucleotides 5&#x02032;pSIRT (<italic>CCGCTTCCGCTTCCGCAGT</italic>) and biotinylated-3&#x02032;pSIRT (biotin&#x02013;<italic>CAACCCATCTTTGCAACGA</italic>). After purification, PCR fragments were bound to streptavidin-linked magnetic beads (Dynabeads M280 Streptavidin, Dynal) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. The DNA bound-beads were extensively washed and pre-incubated in recruitment buffer (20 mM HEPES, pH 7.8, 350 mM potassium acetate, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 50 &#x003bc;M EDTA, 2.5 mM DTT, 200 &#x003bc;M ATP, 1 mg&#x0002f;ml BSA). Protein complexes were assembled on immobilized DNA templates by incubation in recruitment buffer of 10 &#x003bc;g of PA600 fractions derived from wild-type and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells. Beads were washed, and bound proteins were eluted after enzymatic digestion (EcoRI) to release the templates. Elution fractions were analysed by western blot with anti-Pol I antibodies. Direct recording of the chemiluminescence corresponding to A49, A43, AC40 and A34.5 subunits was performed using a CCD camera, and quantification was achieved using the FluorChem software (Alpha Innotech).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>The Ctk1 kinase interacts with Pol I</title><p>To isolate components interacting with CTDK-I, the Ctk1 kinase subunit was purified from yeast cells under mild salt conditions. After two subsequent ion exchange chromatography columns (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>A), Ctk1&#x02013;Myc was eluted from the Poros 10 HQ column in two well separated peaks, a major and a minor one (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>B, upper panel). Strikingly, western blot analysis with anti-Pol II antibodies revealed the presence of subunits common to the three nuclear polymerases in the same fractions (data not shown). Further analyses specifically identified the different subunits composing the Pol I enzyme in the minor elution peak of Ctk1 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>B, lower panel). We did not succeed in immuno-affinity efficient purification of the Ctk1&#x02013;Myc protein, probably due to a low accessibility of the Myc epitope. We therefore turned to the purification of Ctk1&#x02013;HA (see Materials and Methods). After the second ion exchange chromatography column, fractions that contained the minor elution peak of Ctk1 were pooled and subjected to HA immuno-affinity purification. A control experiment was also conducted with extracts derived from a wild-type strain. Proteins eluted with HA peptide were analysed by western blot probed with anti-HA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>C, left panel) and anti-Pol I antibodies (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>C, right upper panel). We observed the presence of Pol I in the fractions derived from the tagged-strain, showing an <italic>in vivo</italic> interaction between the Ctk1 kinase and Pol I.</p><p>Although only the Pol I&#x02013;Rrn3 complex is competent for transcription initiation, the majority of Pol I is not associated with Rrn3 during exponential growth. To get an insight into the form of Pol I that was associated with Ctk1, we analysed the eluates of the HA affinity columns by western blotting with antibodies directed against Rrn3. We observed that Rrn3 and Ctk1 co-purify (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>C, right lower panel). It is thus possible that the Pol I co-purified with Ctk1, or at least a substantial fraction, may be the Pol I&#x02013;Rrn3 form of the enzyme.</p><p>To investigate a direct interaction between Ctk1 and Pol I, we performed <italic>in vitro</italic> co-immunoprecipitation experiments. Three different forms of Pol I were purified from yeast cell and analysed by SDS&#x02013;PAGE and silver staining (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>D). Pol I&#x00394; is a form of Pol I lacking three subunits: A14, ABC23 and A43 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c53">53</xref>), while Pol I<sup>&#x0002a;</sup> is devoid of A34.5 and A49 subunits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c52">52</xref>). HA-tagged versions of the different Ctk subunits were expressed in <italic>E.coli</italic> cells from the <italic>T7</italic> promoter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c24">24</xref>), and the bacterial extracts were preincubated independently with each type of polymerase prior to Pol I immunoprecipitation with anti-A190 polyclonal antibodies. When Pol I was incubated with the three distinct Ctk subunits, its precipitation resulted in efficient co-precipitation of the CTDK-I complex (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>E, lane 3). Similarly, after incubation with Ctk1 alone, Pol I precipitation resulted in efficient co-precipitation of the kinase subunit (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>E, lane 2). In contrast, when Pol I was incubated with the Ctk2 and Ctk3 subunits together, neither Ctk2 nor Ctk3 was recovered after Pol I precipitation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f1">1</xref>E, lane 4). Specific co-precipitation of Pol I and Ctk1 was also observed with the Pol I&#x00394; and Pol I<sup>&#x0002a;</sup> preparations (data not shown).</p><p>We conclude that Pol I interacts with the CTDK-I complex as well as with the Ctk1 subunit alone. This interaction does not require the integrity of the Pol I as it does not require the presence of either A14, A34.5, A43, A49 or ABC23 subunit. Furthermore, Pol I does not interact with the Ctk2 cyclin and the Ctk3 co-cyclin subunits, showing that a direct interaction between the CTDK-I complex and Pol I is mediated by the kinase subunit.</p></sec><sec><title>Sub-cellular localization of the CTDK-I complex</title><p>The observation that Ctk1 interacts with a nucleolar component prompted us to study CTDK-I sub-cellular localization. For this purpose, we have epitope-tagged each of its three subunits (see Materials and Methods). The cellular localization of Ctk1&#x02013;Myc was analysed by immunofluorescence microscopy using monoclonal anti-Myc antibodies. As expected, we observed a nuclear localization in cells grown to early exponential phase (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f2">2</xref>A). Myc staining appeared to overflow the DAPI staining that preferentially reveals the nucleoplasmic DNA, suggesting that Ctk1 might be partly localized in the nucleolar compartment. To confirm the presence of Ctk1 in the nucleolus, we next used polyclonal antibodies raised against the largest subunit of Pol I, A190. These antibodies allow the specific staining of the nucleolus that appears as a crescent-shaped structure making extensive contacts with the nuclear envelope (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f2">2</xref>, A190). When both anti-Myc and anti-A190 antibodies were combined, we observed some Myc staining overlapping the Pol I staining (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f2">2</xref>B). Similar results were obtained when we analysed staining derived from Ctk2&#x02013;Myc (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f2">2</xref>C) and HA&#x02013;Ctk3 (data not shown) proteins. As a control, we analysed an RPB3-HA strain where the Pol II Rpb3 subunit is tagged at its C-terminus with three HA epitopes (C.B., unpublished data). Unlike that observed with Ctk proteins, Rpb3 staining was restricted to the nucleoplasmic compartment, showing no overlap with A190 staining (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f2">2</xref>D).</p><p>We conclude that the three subunits composing the CTDK-I complex, co-localize in the nucleoplasm as well as in the nucleolus. This is consistent with the fact that <italic>in vivo</italic>, a subpopulation of Ctk1 interacts with Pol I, and suggests that CTDK-I might play a role that is distinct from its function in Pol II transcription.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> strains display defects in nucleolar structure</title><p>In an attempt to determine whether CTDK-I plays a role in the nucleolar compartment, we analysed the nucleolus structure in <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> cells by immunofluorescence microscopy. Deletion of either <italic>CTK</italic> gene generates a slow growth at 30&#x000b0;C and no growth at 15&#x000b0;C. As previously observed, <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> cells grown in rich medium to early exponential phase, were much larger than wild-type cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c21">21</xref>). Remarkably, antibodies against A190 did not reveal in <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells the characteristic crescent shape of the nucleolus observed in wild-type cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f3">3</xref>A). On the contrary, we observed a more diffuse signal overlapping part of the DAPI staining. A similar result was obtained with the <italic>&#x00394;ctk3</italic> strain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f3">3</xref>A). To confirm these observations, experiments were repeated using antibodies directed against Nop1, a nucleolar protein involved in rRNA maturation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c63">63</xref>). Again, instead of the crescent-shaped nucleoli seen in wild-type cells, isogenic <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells exhibited a more diffuse Nop1 staining (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f3">3</xref>B). Because CTDK-I is involved in Pol II transcription, we were interested to also analyse nucleoli in a Pol II mutant strain. We used a mutant in Rpb3, the third-largest subunit of Pol II. At 30&#x000b0;C, <italic>rpb3-2</italic> is a slow growth mutant that exhibits defects in Pol II transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c64">64</xref>). Microscopy analysis of <italic>rpb3-2</italic> cells using antibodies against A190 revealed nucleoli similar to that observed in wild-type cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f3">3</xref>A).</p><p>In conclusion, <italic>ctk</italic> null mutations lead to the disruption of the nucleolar structure during early exponential growth, as evidenced by the delocalization of both Pol I and Nop1, two specific components of the nucleolus. It is interesting to note that such defects are not observed in several other mutants affected for Pol II transcription (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f3">3</xref>A, and data not shown). Because Pol I transcription plays an essential role in organizing nucleolar structure and localization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c65">65</xref>), the results suggest that this process might be affected in <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Pol I transcription in <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells</title><p>To get an insight into rRNA synthesis in <italic>ctk</italic> mutants, we realized pulse experiments in early log phase cells grown in SD-casa medium. Similar amounts of rRNA species were analysed, as determined by ethidium bromide staining (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f4">4</xref>A, lower panel). Auto-radiography revealed a decrease of 25S, 18S and 5.8S rRNA synthesis in the null <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> and <italic>&#x00394;ctk3</italic> mutant strains, as compared to the isogenic wild-type strain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f4">4</xref>A, upper panel, and data not shown). A similar result was observed with an inactive mutant of the Ctk1 kinase (G.Hautbergue, unpublished data) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f4">4</xref>A, <italic>ctk1-mut</italic>), suggesting a substantial defect in rRNA synthesis in the absence of the Ctk1 kinase activity.</p><p>Next, we performed primer extension experiments. Because mutant <italic>ctk</italic> cells exhibit a reduced growth rate (170 min) compared to wild-type cells (90 min), we also analysed <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> isogenic cells as control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c66">66</xref>). Pdr13 encodes a member of the Hsp70 family that is implicated in pleiotropic drug resistance. <italic>PDR13</italic> is required for normal growth, and <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> cells display a reduced growth rate similar to that of <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> cells, both in YPD and SD-casa media (data not shown). Cells were grown to log phase in SD-casa medium (OD 1 and 2). After extraction, similar amounts of RNA were analysed by primer extension with two distinct primers allowing specific extension of the mature 25S rRNA, and the 35S rRNA precursor. Gel analysis by auto-radiography (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f4">4</xref>B) and with a PhosphorImager (data not shown), revealed similar levels of primer extension products corresponding to the mature 25S rRNA species for all strains, at OD 1 as well as 2. Levels of products corresponding to the 35S rRNA precursor were also similar in wild-type and <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> cells, whereas in contrast, they were significantly lower when RNA was extracted from <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f4">4</xref>B and C). These results indicate a substantial defect in rRNA synthesis in the absence of the Ctk1 kinase activity. This defect cannot be only the consequence of the reduced growth rate of <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> cells as it is not observed in the slow-growing control <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> strain.</p><p>To get further insight into Pol I transcription in <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells, we investigated Pol I recruitment at 35S rDNA promoters by chromatin immunoprecipitation experiments. After cross-link and sonication of yeast cells, Pol I was immunoprecipitated with anti-A190 antibodies, from wild-type and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells grown in SD-casa to mid-log phase (OD 2). After reversal of cross-links, Pol I immunoprecipitation efficiency was analysed by western blot with anti-A190 antibodies. Similar amounts of enzyme were recovered for the wild-type and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> strains (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f4">4</xref>D). Total and co-precipitated DNA were analysed by real-time PCR with two pairs of primers. The first pair allowed amplification of a specific fragment corresponding to the 35S rDNA promoter region (35S), whereas the second pair generated a fragment corresponding to the adjacent 5S region transcribed by Pol III (non-specific). While similar low levels of non-specific fragment were amplified in both extracts (data not shown), we observed a 2-fold decrease in the abundance of the 35S PCR fragment in <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells compared to wild-type cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f4">4</xref>E, left panel). Thus, the enrichment ratio 35S&#x0002f;non-specific was lower in <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> compared to wild-type extracts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f4">4</xref>E, right panel). Similar results were observed with <italic>&#x00394;ctk2</italic> cells (data not shown), indicating that during mid-log phase, formation of the Pol I initiation complex at 35S promoters is less efficient in <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> cells as compared to wild type. This data is consistent with the rRNA synthesis defect observed in the absence of the Ctk1 kinase.</p></sec><sec><title>Pol I specific <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription is impaired in the absence of Ctk1</title><p>To confirm that the defect in rRNA synthesis observed <italic>in vivo</italic> was at the level of Pol I transcription machinery, we next investigated Pol I specific transcription in extracts from <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells. PA600 fraction containing the complete Pol I transcription apparatus, i.e. the Pol I and the general transcription factors required for Pol I specific transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c61">61</xref>), was purified from wild-type, <italic>&#x00394;pdr13,</italic> and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells. Western blot analysis did not reveal any Pol II or Pol III specific subunit in the PA600 fraction, showing that the major polymerase form present in this fraction is the Pol I (data not shown). We first assessed Pol I catalytic activity by performing non-specific transcription assays with poly (dA-dT) as template. With such a template, RNA synthesis does not rely upon general transcription factors. We observed similar results with wild-type, <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> extracts (data not shown). Pol I levels and subunit composition, as analysed by western immunoblotting, were similar in all PA600 extracts (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f5">5</xref>A, and data not shown). Altogether, the data show that the catalytic activity of the Pol I enzyme is not affected in either <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> or <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells. For specific <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription assays, we used the YepSIRT plasmid that carries an rDNA unit containing a large deletion of the sequence transcribed by Pol I (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c62">62</xref>). Transcription of this mini-gene in wild-type, <italic>&#x00394;pdr13,</italic> and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> PA600 fractions, was analysed by electrophoresis on a urea&#x02013;polyacrylamide gel. Autoradiography revealed a specific RNA for both the wild-type and <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> extracts, whereas in contrast, no specific transcript was detected for the <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> extract (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f5">5</xref>B), unless blots were overexposed (data not shown). The same result was observed with a linearized template (data not shown), suggesting that the <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> PA600 defect does not take place at the level of transcription termination. To determine whether specific transcription impairment was due to the presence of an inhibitor, wild-type and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> mutant, extracts were mixed prior to incubation with YepSIRT. We observed an efficient specific transcription (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f5">5</xref>C), showing that the defective <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> extract does not contain any inhibitor of transcription. Despite the fact that the Pol I enzyme from <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cell extract is catalytically active, <italic>in vitro</italic> Pol I specific transcription is dramatically deficient.</p><p>We next analysed <italic>in vitro</italic> Pol I binding to the DNA template. Mini-genes from the YepSIRT and &#x00394;prom (identical to the YepSIRT construct except that the 35S promoter has been deleted; O. Gadal, unpublished data) plasmids were amplified by PCR with a downstream oligonucleotide that was biotinylated. After purification, PCR products were bound to magnetic beads coupled with streptavidin. PA600 fractions derived from wild-type and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells were incubated with the immobilized templates in the same conditions as specific transcription assays, except that UTP, GTP and CTP were omitted (see Materials and Methods). Bound proteins were eluted after release of the templates by enzymatic digestion, and analysed by western blot with anti-Pol I antibodies (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f5">5</xref>D, and data not shown). Quantification was performed from A49, A43, AC40 and A34.5 subunits. We observed that Pol I from wild-type and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> fractions was similarly bound to the mini-gene in the absence of promoter sequences (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f5">5</xref>D and E, &#x00394;prom). This is due to the high affinity of RNA polymerases for non-specific DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c67">67</xref>). However, in the presence of promoter sequences, we observed an increase in Pol I binding only in the case of wild-type extract (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="gkh927f5">5</xref>D and E, pSIRT). Although Pol I from <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> extract exhibits the same non-specific DNA binding properties than wild-type Pol I, no promoter-dependent binding is observed. This result is consistent with specific <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription data.</p><p>We conclude that the reduction in rRNA synthesis observed <italic>in vivo</italic> is due to an impairment of the Pol I transcription machinery.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Altogether, our results reveal that CTDK-I, previously described as a class II factor, is also involved in the Pol I transcription process: (i) <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> cells exhibit defects in nucleolar structure. Such defects are not observed with several other Pol II transcription mutants. (ii) <italic>In vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> defects in Pol I transcription are observed in the absence of Ctk1, but not in the case of a slow-growth mutant control, and (iii) Ctk1 is present in the nucleolus and interacts directly and specifically with Pol I.</p><p>In yeast, substrates other than the CTD have been described for the CTD kinases Kin28 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c44">44</xref>) and Srb10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c43">43</xref>). All these substrates are class II transcription factors, in agreement with the fact that so far, the function of CTD kinases has been restricted to mRNA synthesis. CTDK-I being involved in rRNA synthesis raises the question of whether the Pol I might be a new substrate of the Ctk1 kinase. Although we do not rule out this possibility, several lines of evidence suggest that it might not be the case: (i) most cyclin-dependent kinases can associate with several cyclins either sequentially, or in diverse cellular compartments, and cyclins often dictate their kinase specificity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c68">68</xref>). Indeed, physical interaction between a cyclin subunit and its kinase substrate has been reported in both yeast and mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c69">69</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c71">71</xref>), whereas neither the Ctk2 cyclin nor the Ctk3 co-cyclin subunit display a detectable interaction with Pol I. (ii) A stable interaction is generally not observed between a kinase and its substrate. Interestingly, during the Ctk1 purification process, we never evidenced any interaction between Ctk1 and its known substrate, namely the CTD, consistent with the fact that Ctk1 has never been identified as a component of either the Pol II holoenzyme or the Pol II elongator complex. In contrast, co-immunoprecipitation experiments demonstrate physical interaction between Ctk1 and Pol I.</p><p>It has been suggested that some nucleolar proteins are not specifically targeted to the nucleolus, but rather are retained in this compartment as a consequence of their functional interactions with other components (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c72">72</xref>). We suggest that Pol I might be the docking site of the Ctk1 kinase, thus targeting CTDK-I to a nucleolar substrate. Such hypothesis is reminiscent of the recruitment of the CTD phosphatase Fcp1 that has a docking site distinct from its CTD substrate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c73">73</xref>).</p><p>We have tried to rescue <italic>in vitro</italic> Pol I transcription from <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> mutant extract by the addition of purified CTDK-I. Although CTDK-I could efficiently phosphorylate a recombinant CTD, its addition did not rescue specific transcription in <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> extract (data not shown). Several reasons can account for this negative result (e.g. it is possible that a cofactor required for Ctk1 function in the Pol I transcription process is not co-purified with Ctk1) that is in agreement with previous data showing that only CF, UAF&#x02013;TBP, and Pol I&#x02013;Rrn3 are required for efficient <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c57">57</xref>). It is thus possible that Ctk1 is not active <italic>in vitro</italic> for Pol I transcription. Although Ctk1 is not essential <italic>in vivo</italic> for Pol I transcription, prior phosphorylation of its substrate <italic>in vivo</italic> would be required to observe efficient transcription <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p><p>Altogether our data suggest that Ctk1 might be involved in Pol I transcription during the initiation step, the major step of Pol I transcription regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c74">74</xref>). <italic>In vitro</italic> experiments indicate that Pol I binding to the 35S promoter is defective in the absence of Ctk1, and Pol I occupancy at the 35S promoter is decreased in <italic>&#x00394;ctk</italic> cells as observed by chromatin immunoprecipitation experiments. Furthermore, in yeast exponential cells most Pol I is not associated with Rrn3, and similarly, most Pol I is not associated with the Ctk1 kinase. Because the fraction of cellular Ctk1 that co-purifies with Pol I also co-purifies with Rrn3, it is possible that <italic>in vivo</italic>, Ctk1 is associated with Pol I&#x02013;Rrn3 the only form of enzyme competent for transcription initiation.</p><p>Several lines of evidence indicate that at the level of Pol II transcription, CTDK-I function is growth-related. (i) The stability of the activating subunit, the Ctk2 cyclin, is correlated to cell density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c23">23</xref>), (ii) <italic>CTK1</italic> deletion affects the pattern of CTD phosphorylation, a pattern shown to be regulated in response to environmental signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c25">25</xref>), and (iii) <italic>ctk</italic> mutants exhibit defects in the transcriptional induction of various classes of genes in response to growth conditions [(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c25">25</xref>) V.G., unpublished data], indicating that CTDK-I functions in a gene-specific fashion in response to growth conditions. It is possible that CTDK-I may play a regulatory role related to environmental signals in both Pol II and Pol I transcription processes, consistent with the fact that this kinase is not essential to cell viability.</p><p>Interestingly, Fath <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c75">75</xref>) recently reported that dephosphorylation of Pol I by the CTD phosphatase Fcp1 is required for efficient rRNA synthesis. It thus appears that enzymes involved in CTD phosphorylation&#x0002f;dephosphorylation are also implicated in Pol I transcription in yeast. In higher eukaryotes, several components previously described as class II specific factors, have also revealed to be involved in rDNA transcription (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c76">76</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c77">77</xref>). For example, in mouse, the class II general transcription initiation factor TFIIH has been shown to be an integral component of the Pol I holoenzyme required for <italic>in vitro</italic> rRNA synthesis, providing a link between Pol I transcription and transcription-coupled repair of active ribosomal genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c78">78</xref>). Given the strong functional similarities between gene expression in yeast and mammals, it is likely that similar to CTDK-I, CTD kinases will be implicated in mammals in the control of other transcription systems, a means for eukaryotic cells to coordinate the control of mRNA and rRNA synthesis in response to changes in the environment or in the cell growth rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="gkh927c79">79</xref>). An attractive possibility is that CTDK-I links distinct nuclear machineries, thus participating in the global transcriptional response to environmental signals.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig id="gkh927f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p> Ctk1 interacts with Pol I <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic>. (A and B) Ctk1&#x02013;Myc purification. (<bold>A</bold>) Fractionation scheme used to purify Ctk1&#x02013;Myc from yeast exponential cells by ion exchange chromatographies. (<bold>B</bold>) The different fractions recovered were analysed by western blot with anti-Myc antibodies (upper panel), and polyclonal antibodies raised against Pol I (lower panel). I and FT indicate input and flow through samples, respectively. (<bold>C</bold>) Ctk1&#x02013;HA immunopurification. After the second chromatography, fractions that contained the minor elution peak of Ctk1&#x02013;HA from CTK1&#x02013;HA cell extract, and identical fractions from wild-type (Ctk1) cell extract, were pooled and subjected to HA immuno-affinity purification. Eluates were analysed by western blot with anti-HA (left panel), anti-Pol I (right upper panel) and anti-Rrn3 (right lower panel) antibodies. (D and E) <italic>In vitro</italic> co-immunoprecipitation experiments. (<bold>D</bold>) Pol I, Pol I&#x00394; and Pol I<sup>&#x0002a;</sup> purified from yeast cell were analysed by silver staining. A43<sup>&#x0002a;</sup> corresponds to a degraded form of the A43 subunit. (<bold>E</bold>) Pol I was incubated with different combinations of recombinant Ctk proteins each tagged with 2 HA epitopes (HA-rCtk). Immunoprecipitation was performed with polyclonal antibodies against the largest subunit of Pol I, A190. Western blot analysis with anti-Pol I (upper panel) and anti-HA (lower panel) antibodies. Asterisk indicates a band corresponding to immunoglobulin heavy chains.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh927f1"/></fig><fig id="gkh927f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p> Immunolocalization of the Ctk proteins. Indirect immunofluorescence was performed with: (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) CTK1&#x02013;Myc, (<bold>C</bold>) CTK2&#x02013;Myc and (<bold>D</bold>) RPB3-HA early exponential cells. DNA was stained with DAPI (A), while Ctk1 (A and B), Ctk2 (C) and Rpb3 (D) were detected with mouse monoclonal anti-Myc (A, B and C) or anti-HA (D) antibodies, and A190 (B, C and D) was detected using a rabbit antibody. Three distinct representative nuclei are shown in each case.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh927f2"/></fig><fig id="gkh927f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p> Immunofluorescence microscopy analysis of the nucleolus. Wild-type (WT), <italic>&#x00394;ctk1, &#x00394;ctk3</italic> and <italic>rpb3-2</italic> early exponential cells were analysed with either anti-A190 (<bold>A</bold>) or anti-Nop1 (<bold>B</bold>) antibodies, and DAPI staining. Three distinct representative nuclei are shown in each case.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh927f3"/></fig><fig id="gkh927f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p> (A, B and C) <italic>In vivo</italic> transcription analyses. (<bold>A</bold>) Wild-type (WT), <italic>&#x00394;ctk1, &#x00394;ctk3</italic> and <italic>ctk1-mut</italic> isogenic cells, were cultivated in SD-casa to early log phase, prior to incubation with <sup>3</sup>H-Uracil for 30 min. After extraction, total RNA was separated by electrophoresis on urea&#x02013;polyacrylamide gels prior to auto-radiography (upper panel) or ethidium bromide staining (lower panel). (<bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold>) Wild-type (WT), <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> isogenic cells, were cultivated in SD-casa to an OD of either 1 or 2. After extraction, total RNA was analysed by primer extension with two oligonucleotides specific for the 35 and 25S rRNA species, respectively. Products were separated by electrophoresis on urea&#x02013;polyacrylamide gels prior to auto-radiography (B), and 35S products analysed with a PhosphorImager (C). Grey, black and white boxes correspond to 35S amounts in WT, <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> cells, respectively. Results correspond to three independent experiments. (D and E) rDNA chromatin immunoprecipitation. After cross-link, cell lysis and sonication, wild-type (WT) and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> extracts from cells grown in SD-casa to an OD of 2 were immunoprecipitated with anti-A190 antibodies. (<bold>D</bold>) Recovered proteins were analysed by western immunoblotting with anti-A190 antibodies. (<bold>E</bold>) Total and immuno-precipitated DNA were analysed by real-time PCR. Fragment corresponding to the 35S rDNA promoter (left panel), and enrichment of the 35S rDNA promoter compared to a non-specific 5S fragment (right panel). Grey and white boxes correspond to WT and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> extracts, respectively. Results correspond to five independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh927f4"/></fig><fig id="gkh927f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><italic>In vitro</italic> analyses. (A, B and C) Transcription assay. (<bold>A</bold>) Pol I from wild-type (WT) and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> PA600 fractions were analysed by western blot with anti-Pol I antibodies. (<bold>B</bold>) Specific <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription of a mini rDNA transcription unit was carried out with PA600 fractions purified from wild-type (WT), <italic>&#x00394;pdr13</italic> and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> strains. (<bold>C</bold>) Specific <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription with different combinations of wild-type (WT) and <italic>&#x00394;ctk1</italic> PA600 fractions. (D and E) <italic>In vitro</italic> binding of Pol I to the 35S rDNA promoter. (<bold>D</bold>) After incubation with immobilized templates containing (pSIRT), or not (&#x00394;prom), the 35S rDNA promoter, bound proteins were eluted from released templates and analysed by western immunoblot with anti-Pol I antibodies. (<bold>E</bold>) Quantification of three independent experiments. Grey boxes, &#x00394;prom template; white boxes, pSIRT template.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkh927f5"/></fig></sec><ack><sec><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We are grateful to S. Ch&#x000e9;din, G. Peyroche and A. Sentenac for critical reading of the manuscript. C.B. was supported by the Fondation pour la Recherche Medicale (FDT20030926549). G.H. was supported by the Association pour la Recherche contre le Cancer. V.G. was supported by the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="gkh927c1"><label>1.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Sentenac</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> (1985) Eukaryotic RNA polymerases. <source>CRC Crit. Rev. Biochem.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3893883</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c2"><label>2.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name> (1999) The economics of ribosome biosynthesis in yeast. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>440</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10542411</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c3"><label>3.</label><citation citation-type="book"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (1998) Transcription factors used by <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> RNA polymerase I and the mechanism of initiation. In Paule,M.R. (ed.), <source>Transcription of Ribosomal RNA Genes by Eukaryotic RNA Polymerase I</source>. <publisher-name>Springer Verlag</publisher-name>, Berlin, Germany, pp. <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>172</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c4"><label>4.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Keys</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name>, Lee,B.S., Dodd,J.A., Nguyen,T.T., Vu,L., Fantino,E., Burson,L.M., Nogi,Y. and Nomura,M. (1996) Multiprotein transcription factor UAF interacts with the upstream element of the yeast RNA polymerase I promoter and forms a stable preinitiation complex. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>903</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8846924</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c5"><label>5.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Aprikian</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, Moorefield,B. and Reeder,R.H. (2001) New model for the yeast RNA polymerase I transcription cycle. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>4847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4855</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11438642</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c6"><label>6.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bordi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Cioci,F. and Camilloni,G. (2001) <italic>In vivo</italic> binding and hierarchy of assembly of the yeast RNA polymerase I transcription factors. <source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>760</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11251085</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c7"><label>7.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Fath</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Milkereit,P., Peyroche,G., Riva,M., Carles,C. and Tschochner,H. (2001) Differential roles of phosphorylation in the formation of transcriptional active RNA polymerase I. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>14334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11717393</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c8"><label>8.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name>, Peterson,C.L., Wickham,J.Q., Miller,L.M., Clarke,E.M., Crowell,J.A. and Sergere,J.C. (1995) Characterization of the components of reconstituted <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> RNA polymerase I transcription complexes. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>6205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7890756</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c9"><label>9.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name>, Peterson,C.L., Brainard,A.V. and Riggs,D.L. (1996) Regulation of the RNA polymerase I and III transcription systems in response to growth conditions. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>271</volume>, <fpage>22189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8703032</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c10"><label>10.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Stefanovsky</surname><given-names>V.Y.</given-names></name>, Pelletier,G., Hannan,R., Gagnon-Kugler,T., Rothblum,L.I. and Moss,T. (2001) An immediate response of ribosomal transcription to growth factor stimulation in mammals is mediated by ERK phosphorylation of UBF. <source>Mol. Cell</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1063</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1073</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11741541</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c11"><label>11.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Corden</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name> (1990) Tails of RNA polymerase II. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>387</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2251729</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c12"><label>12.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Dahmus</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name> (1996) Reversible phosphorylation of the C-terminal domain of RNA polymerase II. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>271</volume>, <fpage>19009</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19012</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8759772</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c13"><label>13.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Komarnitsky</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, Cho,E.J. and Buratowski,S. (2000) Different phosphorylated forms of RNA polymerase II and associated mRNA processing factors during transcription. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>2452</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2460</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11018013</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c14"><label>14.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Patturajan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Schulte,R.J., Sefton,B.M., Berezney,R., Vincent,M., Bensaude,O., Warren,S.L. and Corden,J.L. (1998) Growth-related changes in phosphorylation of yeast RNA polymerase II. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>273</volume>, <fpage>4689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4694</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9468530</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c15"><label>15.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Holstege</surname><given-names>F.C.</given-names></name>, Jennings,E.G., Wyrick,J.J., Lee,T.I., Hengartner,C.J., Green,M.R., Golub,T.R., Lander,E.S. and Young,R.A. (1998) Dissecting the regulatory circuitry of a eukaryotic genome. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>717</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>728</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9845373</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c16"><label>16.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hengartner</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name>, Myer,V.E., Liao,S., Wilson,C.J., Koh,S.S. and Young,R.A. (1998) Temporal regulation of RNA polymerase II by Srb10 and Kin28 cyclin-dependent kinases. <source>Mol. Cell</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9702190</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c17"><label>17.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name>, Cho,E.J., Keogh,M.C., Moore,C.L., Greenleaf,A.L. and Buratowski,S. (2000) Kin28, the TFIIH-associated carboxy-terminal domain kinase, facilitates the recruitment of mRNA processing machinery to RNA polymerase II. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10594013</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c18"><label>18.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>-M., Zhang,J., Jeffery,D.A., Koleske,A.J., Thompson,C.M., Chao,D.M., Viljoen,M., van Vuuren,H.J.J. and Young,R.A. (1995) A kinase-cyclin pair in the RNA polymerase II holoenzyme. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>374</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7877695</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c19"><label>19.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Udupa,R., Yao,S., Hartzog,G. and Prelich,G. (2001) Phosphorylation of the RNA polymerase II carboxy-terminal domain by the Bur1 cyclin-dependent kinase. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>4089</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4096</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11390638</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c20"><label>20.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Keogh</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name>, Podolny,V. and Buratowski,S. (2003) Bur1 kinase is required for efficient transcription elongation by RNA polymerase II. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>7005</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7018</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12972617</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c21"><label>21.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Sterner</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name>, Moon Lee,J., Hardin,S.E. and Greenleaf,A.L. (1995) The yeast carboxyl-terminal repeat domain kinase CTDK-I is a divergent cyclin-cyclin-dependent kinase complex. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>5716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5724</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7565723</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c22"><label>22.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name> and Greenleaf,A.L. (1991) CTD kinase large subunit is encoded by <italic>CTK1</italic>, a gene required for normal growth of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>Gene Expr.</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1820212</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c23"><label>23.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hautbergue</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and Goguel,V. (1999) The yeast C-type cyclin Ctk2p is phosphorylated and rapidly degraded by the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>2527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2534</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10082518</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c24"><label>24.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hautbergue</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name> and Goguel,V. (2001) Activation of the cyclin-dependent kinase CTDK-I requires the heterodimerization of two unstable subunits. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>8005</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8013</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c25"><label>25.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Patturajan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Conrad,N.K., Bregman,D.B. and Corden,J.L. (1999) Yeast carboxyl-terminal domain kinase I positively and negatively regulates RNA polymerase II carboxyl-terminal domain phosphorylation. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>274</volume>, <fpage>27823</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27828</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10488128</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c26"><label>26.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name> and Greenleaf,A.L. (1997) Modulation of RNA polymerase II elongation efficiency by C-terminal heptapeptide repeat domain kinase I. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>272</volume>, <fpage>10990</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10993</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9110987</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c27"><label>27.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Jona</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, Wittschieben,B.O., Svejstrup,J.Q. and Gileadi,O. (2001) Involvement of yeast carboxy-terminal domain kinase I (CTDK-I) in transcription elongation <italic>in vivo</italic>. <source>Gene</source>, <volume>267</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11311553</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c28"><label>28.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name> and Hartzog,G.A. (2001) Genetic interactions of Spt4-Spt5 and TFIIS with the RNA polymerase II CTD and CTD modifying enzymes in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>159</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>497</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11606527</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c29"><label>29.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name>, Kobor,M.S., Kim,M., Greenblatt,J. and Buratowski,S. (2001) Opposing effects of Ctk1 kinase and Fcp1 phosphatase at Ser 2 of the RNA polymerase II C-terminal domain. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>3319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3329</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751637</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c30"><label>30.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Skaar</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name> and Greenleaf,A.L. (2002) The RNA polymerase II CTD kinase CTDK-I affects pre-mRNA 3&#x02032; cleavage&#x0002f;polyadenylation through the processing component Pti1p. <source>Mol. Cell</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1439</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12504017</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c31"><label>31.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name>, Kim,M. and Buratowski,S. (2004) Phosphorylation of serine 2 within the RNA polymerase II C-terminal domain couples transcription and 3&#x02032; end processing. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c32"><label>32.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name> and Greenleaf,A.L. (2000) The splicing factor, Prp40, binds the phosphorylated carboxyl-terminal domain of RNA polymerase II. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>275</volume>, <fpage>39935</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39943</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10978320</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c33"><label>33.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, Hall,H., Kizer,K.O., Shibata,Y., Hall,M.C., Borchers,C.H. and Strahl,B.D. (2003) Phosphorylation of RNA polymerase II CTD regulates H3 methylation in yeast. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>654</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>663</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12629047</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c34"><label>34.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ostapenko</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> and Solomon,M.J. (2003) Budding yeast CTDK-I is required for DNA damage-induced transcription. <source>Eukaryot. Cell</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>274</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>283</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12684377</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c35"><label>35.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hurt</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, Luo,M.J., Rother,S., Reed,R. and Strasser,K. (2004) Cotranscriptional recruitment of the serine-arginine-rich (SR)-like proteins Gbp2 and Hrb1 to nascent mRNA via the TREX complex. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>101</volume>, <fpage>1858</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1862</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14769921</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c36"><label>36.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>N.F.</given-names></name> and Price,D.H. (1995) Purification of P-TEFb, a transcription factor required for the transition into productive elongation. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>12335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12338</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7759473</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c37"><label>37.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name> (2000) P-TEFb, a cyclin-dependent kinase controlling elongation by RNA polymerase II. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>2629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2634</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10733565</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c38"><label>38.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Serizawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, Makela,T.P., Conaway,J.W., Conaway,R.C., Weinberg,R.A. and Young,R.A. (1995) Association of Cdk-activating kinase subunits with transcription factor TFIIH. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>374</volume>, <fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>282</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7885450</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c39"><label>39.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Shiekhattar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, Mermelstein,F., Fisher,R.P., Drapkin,R., Dynlacht,B., Wessling,H.C., Morgan,D.O. and Reinberg,D. (1995) Cdk-activating kinase complex is a component of human transcription factor TFIIH. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>374</volume>, <fpage>283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7533895</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c40"><label>40.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, Fisher,R.P., Bailey,P. and Levine,A.J. (1997) The CDK7-cycH-p36 complex of transcription factor IIH phosphorylates p53, enhancing its sequence-specific DNA binding activity <italic>in vitro</italic>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>5923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5934</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9315650</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c41"><label>41.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Akoulitchev</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Chuikov,S. and Reinberg,D. (2000) TFIIH is negatively regulated by cdk8-containing mediator complexes. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>407</volume>, <fpage>102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10993082</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c42"><label>42.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name> and Sharp,P.A. (2001) Positive transcription elongation factor B phosphorylates hSPT5 and RNA polymerase II carboxyl-terminal domain independently of cyclin-dependent kinase-activating kinase. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>276</volume>, <fpage>12317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12323</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11145967</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c43"><label>43.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Guidi</surname><given-names>B.W.</given-names></name>, Bjornsdottir,G., Hopkins,D.C., Lacomis,L., Erdjument-Bromage,H., Tempst,P. and Myers,L.C. (2004) Mutual targeting of mediator and the TFIIH kinase Kin28. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>279</volume>, <fpage>29114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15126497</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c44"><label>44.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, Kung,C., Fishburn,J., Ansari,A.Z., Shokat,K.M. and Hahn,S. (2004) Two cyclin-dependent kinases promote RNA polymerase II transcription and formation of the scaffold complex. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1735</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14749387</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c45"><label>45.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hirst</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Kobor,M.S., Kuriakose,N., Greenblatt,J. and Sadowski,I. (1999) GAL4 is regulated by the RNA polymerase II holoenzyme-associated cyclin-dependent protein kinase SRB10&#x0002f;CDK8. <source>Mol. Cell</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>678</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10360183</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c46"><label>46.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, Huddleston,M.J., Zhang,X., Young,R.A., Annan,R.S., Carr,S.A. and Deshaies,R.J. (2001) Negative regulation of Gcn4 and Msn2 transcription factors by Srb10 cyclin-dependent kinase. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1092</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11331604</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c47"><label>47.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, Kuchin,S., Hong,S.P., Townley,R., Vyas,V.K. and Carlson,M. (2001) Interaction of the Srb10 kinase with Sip4, a transcriptional activator of gluconeogenic genes in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>5790</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5796</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11486018</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c48"><label>48.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, Goto,S., Lund,K., Hung,W. and Sadowski,I. (2003) Srb10&#x0002f;Cdk8 regulates yeast filamentous growth by phosphorylating the transcription factor Ste12. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>421</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12520306</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c49"><label>49.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Longtine</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, McKenzie,A., Demarini,D.J., Shah,N.G., Wach,A., Brachat,A., Philippsen,P. and Pringle,J.R. (1998) Additional modules for versatile and economical PCR-based gene deletion and modification in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>Yeast</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>953</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>961</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9717241</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c50"><label>50.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Milkereit</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> and Tschochner,H. (1998) A specialized form of RNA polymerase I, essential for initiation and growth-dependent regulation of rRNA synthesis, is disrupted during transcription. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>3692</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3703</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9649439</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c51"><label>51.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Buhler</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, Sentenac,A. and Fromageot,P. (1974) Isolation, structure, and general properties of yeast ribonucleic acid polymerase A (or I). <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>249</volume>, <fpage>5963</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5970</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4606699</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c52"><label>52.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Huet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, Buhler,J.M., Sentenac,A. and Fromageot,P. (1975) Dissociation of two polypeptide chains from yeast RNA polymerase A. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>3034</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3038</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1103135</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c53"><label>53.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Smid</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, Riva,M., Bouet,F., Sentenac,A. and Carles,C. (1995) The association of three subunits with yeast RNA polymerase is stabilized by A14. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>13534</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13540</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7768955</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c54"><label>54.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Buhler</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name>, Huet,J., Davies,K.E., Sentenac,A. and Fromageot,P. (1980) Immunological studies of yeast nuclear RNA polymerases at the subunit level. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>255</volume>, <fpage>9949</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9954</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7000767</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c55"><label>55.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Aris</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name> and Blobel,G. (1988) Identification and characterization of a yeast nucleolar protein that is similar to a rat liver nucleolar protein. <source>J. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3292539</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c56"><label>56.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name>, Brown,T.A. and Trumpower,B.L. (1990) A rapid and simple method for preparation of RNA from <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>3091</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3092</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2190191</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c57"><label>57.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Keener</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, Josaitis,C.A., Dodd,J.A. and Nomura,M. (1998) Reconstitution of yeast RNA polymerase I transcription <italic>in vitro</italic> from purified components. TATA-binding protein is not required for basal transcription. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>273</volume>, <fpage>33795</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33802</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9837969</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c58"><label>58.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Iben</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Tschochner,H., Bier,M., Hoogstraten,D., Hozak,P., Egly,J.M. and Grummt,I. (2002) TFIIH plays an essential role in RNA polymerase I transcription. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015980</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c59"><label>59.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuras</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> and Struhl,K. (1999) Binding of TBP to promoters <italic>in vivo</italic> is stimulated by activators and requires Pol II holoenzyme. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>399</volume>, <fpage>609</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>613</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10376605</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c60"><label>60.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Kuras</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, Borggrefe,T. and Kornberg,R.D. (2003) Association of the Mediator complex with enhancers of active genes. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>13887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13891</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14623974</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c61"><label>61.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Milkereit</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, Schultz,P. and Tschochner,H. (1997) Resolution of RNA polymerase I into dimers and monomers and their function in transcription. <source>Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>378</volume>, <fpage>1433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1443</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9461342</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c62"><label>62.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Musters</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, Knol,J., Maas,P., Dekker,A.F., van Heerikhuizen,H. and Planta,R.J. (1989) Linker scanning of the yeast RNA polymerase I promoter. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>9661</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9678</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2690005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c63"><label>63.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Tollervey</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, Lehtonen,H., Carmo-Fonseca,M. and Hurt,E.C. (1991) The small nucleolar RNP protein NOP1 (fibrillarin) is required for pre-rRNA processing in yeast. <source>EMBO J.</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>583</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1825809</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c64"><label>64.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, Linask,K.L., Ebright,R.H. and Woychik,N.A. (2000) Activation mutants in yeast RNA polymerase II subunit RPB3 provide evidence for a structurally conserved surface required for activation in eukaryotes and bacteria. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10673505</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c65"><label>65.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Oakes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, Nogi,Y., Clark,M.W. and Nomura,M. (1993) Structural alterations of the nucleolus in mutants of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> defective in RNA polymerase I. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>2441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2455</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8455621</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c66"><label>66.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hallstrom</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name>, Katzmann,D.J., Torres,R.J., Sharp,W.J. and Moye-Rowley,W.S. (1998) Regulation of transcription factor Pdr1p function by an Hsp70 protein in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1155</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9488429</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c67"><label>67.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name>, Takagi,T., Moore,C.R. and Buratowski,S. (1997) mRNA capping enzyme is recruited to the transcription complex by phosphorylation of the RNA polymerase II carboxy-terminal domain. <source>Genes Dev.</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>3319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3326</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9407025</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c68"><label>68.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name> and Cross,F.R. (2001) Cyclin specificity: how many wheels do you need on a unicycle? <source>J. Cell Sci.</source>, <volume>114</volume>, <fpage>1811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1820</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11329367</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c69"><label>69.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Ewen</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name>, Sluss,H.K., Sherr,C.J., Matsushime,H., Kato,J. and Livingston,D.M. (1993) Functional interactions of the retinoblastoma protein with mammalian D-type cyclins. <source>Cell</source>, <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>497</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8343202</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c70"><label>70.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Schulman</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name>, Lindstrom,D.L. and Harlow,E. (1998) Substrate recruitment to cyclin-dependent kinase 2 by a multipurpose docking site on cyclin A. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>10453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10458</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9724724</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c71"><label>71.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name>, Mahrenholz,A.M. and Roach,P.J. (1999) Substrate targeting of the yeast cyclin-dependent kinase Pho85p by the cyclin Pcl10p. <source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>7020</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7030</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10490639</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c72"><label>72.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Dundr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> and Misteli,T. (2002) Nucleolomics: an inventory of the nucleolus. <source>Mol. Cell</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11804579</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c73"><label>73.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name>, Wang,B.Q., Burton,Z.F. and Dahmus,M.E. (1995) The activity of COOH-terminal domain phosphatase is regulated by a docking site on RNA polymerase II and by the general transcription factors IIF and IIB. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>270</volume>, <fpage>14962</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14969</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7797476</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c74"><label>74.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Reeder</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name> (1999) Regulation of RNA polymerase I transcription in yeast and vertebrates. <source>Prog. Nucleic Acid Res. Mol. Biol.</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>327</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9932458</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c75"><label>75.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Fath</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, Kobor,M.S., Philippi,A., Greenblatt,J. and Tschochner,H. (2004) Dephosphorylation of RNA polymerase I by Fcp1p is required for efficient rRNA synthesis. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>, <volume>279</volume>, <fpage>25251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25259</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15073185</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c76"><label>76.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Bradsher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, Auriol,J., Proietti de Santis,L., Iben,S., Vonesch,J.L., Grummt,I. and Egly,J.M. (2002) CSB is a component of RNA Pol I transcription. <source>Mol. Cell</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>819</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>829</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12419226</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c77"><label>77.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name>, Tuan,J., Scalia,P., Bui,T. and Comai,L. (2002) The cell cycle regulatory factor TAF1 stimulates ribosomal DNA transcription by binding to the activator UBF. <source>Curr. Biol.</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>2142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2146</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12498690</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c78"><label>78.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoogstraten</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, Nigg,A.L., Heath,H., Mullenders,L.H., van Driel,R., Hoeijmakers,J.H., Vermeulen,W. and Houtsmuller,A.B. (2002) Rapid switching of TFIIH between RNA polymerase I and II transcription and DNA repair <italic>in vivo</italic>. <source>Mol. Cell</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12453423</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="gkh927c79"><label>79.</label><citation citation-type="journal"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> (1999) Regulation of ribosome biosynthesis in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>: diversity and common principles. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>, <volume>181</volume>, <fpage>6857</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6864</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10559149</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article> 